[1]当时招募新兵的差役都穿蓝制服。

[2]阿伐尔人又称阿巴尔人，为匈奴族的一支，曾于七八世纪时侵入欧洲，后为查理曼大帝逐走；自第十世纪后即不见史乘。伏尔泰仅以之为寓言材料，读者幸勿以史实绳之。

[3]荷兰在宗教革命时代为新教徒的大本营，当然反对教皇。

[4]再浸礼派为基督教中的一小派，认为婴儿受洗完全无效，必于成人后再行洗礼。该派起源于十六世纪，正当日耳曼若干地区发生农民革命的时期。

[5]弗洛冷为一种货币名称，十三世纪起由翡冷翠政府发行，原为金币。以后各国皆有仿制，并改铸为银币，法、荷、奥诸国均有。

[6]至十九世纪中叶为止，放血为欧洲最普遍的一种治疗方法，其作用略如吾国民间之“放痧”。

[7]二十四磅炮即发射二十四磅重的炮弹的炮。

[8]此液质指人身内部的各种液体，如血、淋巴等等。

[9]影射一七五五年十一月七日的里斯本地震。

[10]最后两句指亚当与夏娃偷食禁果之事。

[11]科印勃勒大学为葡萄牙有名的大学。一七五六年六月二十日，葡萄牙确曾举办此种“功德大会”。

[12]教徒受洗时有教父教母各一人，干妈为教徒对教母的称谓。

[13]十六七世纪时，异教裁判所执行火刑时，犯人装束确如作者所述。

[14]一七五五年十二月二十一日葡萄牙再度地震。

[15]希伯来族自所罗门王薨后，分为犹太与以色列两国，公元前六世纪为巴比伦王尼布甲尼撒二世征服，大批希伯来人被移往巴比伦为奴。西方所谓希伯来人、以色列人、犹太人皆指同一民族。

[16]加利利人为异教徒对基督徒之称谓，因伊萨加为犹太人，居内贡为基督徒。

[17]异教裁判所的法官均系高级的教士兼的。

[18]比斯多为西班牙的一种金币。

[19]南美之巴拉圭于十七世纪时为西班牙属国，西王腓列伯三世授权耶稣会教士统治，直至一七六七年此神权政治方始告终。

[20]希腊古雕塑中有许多维纳斯像，均系杰作。后人均以掘得该像之所在地，或获得该像之诸侯之名名之。梅迭西斯为文艺复兴期统治翡冷翠的大族。

[21]玛德会又名耶路撒冷的圣·约翰会，为基督旧教中的一个宗派，纯属军事性质的教会团体；创于十一世纪，以地中海的玛德岛为根据地。

[22]半黑人指皮肤黝黑、近于紫铜色的人。

[23]阿特拉斯为北非大山脉，主山在摩洛哥境内。

[24]影射西班牙的加洛·勃罗斯几（一七〇五至一七八二），他被封为贵族，执掌朝政，煊赫一时。

[25]影射一六九五至一六九六年间的战事。伏尔泰当时正为其所著的《俄国史》搜集材料。

[26]今南美阿根廷的城市布宜诺斯艾利斯。——编者注。

[27]伊巴拉等五个名字，乃一七五八年九月谋刺葡萄牙王凶犯之名，作者借作总督封邑之名。

[28]此系隐指亚伯拉罕在基拉尔地方伪称妻子为妹的故事，详见《旧约·创世记》第二十章。

[29]伏尔泰曾为其所著《风俗论》（一七五八年）搜集有关巴拉圭耶稣会士的材料；一七五四至一七五八年间，作者又将此项题材写成重要文字多篇。本章所述，伏尔泰大抵皆有考据。

[30]图库曼为今阿根廷的一个省份。

[31]圣·伊涅斯（一四九一至一五五六），又名圣·伊涅斯·特·雷育拉，为耶稣会的创办人。

[32]十八世纪时，耶稣会于法国索纳州德雷甫城办一刊物，名《见闻录》，抨击当时反宗教的哲学思想。

[33]此系印第安族的一支，戴大木耳环，故被称为大耳人。

[34]相传南美洲有一遍地黄金的国土，叫作黄金国，位于亚马逊河及俄利诺科河之间，居屋皆以白银为顶，国王遍体皆饰黄金。自马可·波罗以来即有此传说，哥伦布及以后之西班牙、葡萄牙殖民冒险家，均曾寻访。十八世纪后期，一般人对此神奇的国土犹抱幻想。伏尔泰本章所述，均采自各旅行家之游记，其中事实与幻想，杂然并列。

[35]开颜为南美洲东北角上一小岛，属法国。

[36]据专家考证，此名影射范·杜仑（Van Düren）；范为荷兰出版商，伏尔泰谓其在版税上舞弊，损害伏尔泰权益。

[37]索星尼派为十六世纪时神学家索星所创，否认三位一体及耶稣为神之说。

[38]马尼教为公元三世纪时波斯人马奈斯所创，是一种二元论的宗教，言原人为善神所造，其性善；今人为恶神所造，其性恶，唯认识真理后方能解脱罪恶；并称世界上的光明与黑暗是永远斗争不已的。

[39]此处所谓疱疮，原是羊特有的病症。

[40]此系指忏悔证书。今日旧教徒结婚之前，教会尚限令双方缴纳忏悔证书。街坊上的熟客即暗指教士。

[41]外国纸牌中普通最大的王牌为A，读如爱司（As）。

[42]笛卡儿的哲学系统以生来自具之观念为意识之内容，此生来自具之观念即名为“先天观念”。

[43]此段故事系隐指法国有名的女演员勒戈佛滦（一六九二至一七三〇）事，生前声名藉盛，死后教堂拒绝为之举行葬礼，卒埋于巴黎蒲高涅街路角，塞纳河畔。

[44]弗莱隆（一七一九至一七七六）为法国政论家，终身与百科全书派为敌，攻击伏尔泰尤为激烈。

[45]法老是一种纸牌的赌博。

[46]莫利尼派为耶稣会中的一支，十六世纪时由耶稣会神学家莫利尼创立，以调和人的自由与神的恩宠为主要学说。

[47]此系作者影射达眠安事件：一七五七年一月五日，一个精神不健全的乡下人，名叫达眠安，以小刀刺伤路易十五，卒被凌迟处死。

[48]一五九四年十二月，亨利四世被约翰·夏丹行刺；又于一六一〇年五月，被拉伐伊阿克行刺，重伤身死。以上各案均与十六七世纪的宗教斗争有关。

[49]一七五七年达眠安处死以前，备受酷刑；拿过凶器的手被火焚烧，又浇以沸油及熔化的铅。

[50]影射一七五七年三月英国海军提督平格被杀事，因平格于一七五六年与法国舰队作战败绩。

[51]丹阿德会为旧教中的一派，十六世纪时由丹阿多主教创立。

[52]佛尼市游艇有名于世，舟子之善歌亦有名于世。

[53]佛尼市共和城邦的政府首长，自七世纪末至十八世纪末均称Doge，原义为公爵，但易与普通的公爵相混，故暂译作“执政”。

[54]拉丁诗人维琪尔（公元前七〇至前一九年）著有未完成的史诗《埃奈伊特》，叙述荷马史诗中的英雄定居意大利的故事，以埃奈伊为主角。全书完成的有十二卷。

[55]意大利诗人塔索（一五四四至一五九五）著有史诗《耶路撒冷之解放》。诗人阿利渥斯托（一四七四至一五三三）著有长诗《狂怒的洛朗》。

[56]拉丁诗人荷拉斯（公元前六五至前八年）与当时皇帝奥古斯德为友，尤受政治家曼塞纳之知遇；荷拉斯曾于有名的献词中，言人各有愿望理想，己之理想则为抒情诗人。

[57]西塞罗（公元前一〇六至前四三年）为罗马共和时代之政论家、演说家。

[58]赛纳克（公元前四至公元六五年）为罗马时代哲学家，遗著除哲学论文外，尚有讽刺文集。

[59]《创世记》第一章有“神说：要有光；就有光”等等之语，故基督教素来认为上帝是用言语创造世界的。摩西相传为《创世记》的作者；今人考证，则谓《创世记》系犹太人于公元六世纪时得之于巴比伦传说。弥尔敦诗中《失乐园》则谓弥赛亚（意为神之子）以金圆规画出世界，使有边际，不致浩瀚无涯。

[60]魔鬼虽从基督教观念中来，塔索写之仍用异教徒笔法，与古代拉丁诗人同；不若弥尔敦之形容魔鬼，高踞于地狱之中，横卧于火湖之上，半沉半浮，身遭缧绁。以纯粹古典趣味之伏尔泰观之，弥尔敦与塔索之描写，自有雅俗之分。魔鬼有许多名字，吕西番其一也。

[61]阿利渥斯托在《狂怒的洛朗》（在意大利文则为《狂怒的奥朗多》）中曾谓弗列查（Friza）之王有一兵器（火枪），举世莫敌。弥尔敦于《失乐园》中称魔鬼发明枪炮以攻天堂。

[62]此为伏尔泰误忆。《失乐园》第十卷中仅言罪恶与死在地狱中等候，一知撒旦诱致亚当与夏娃堕落一事成功，即结伴同贺，并未提及结婚。撒旦返地狱，自夸功绩，上帝罚之忽为蛇形，手下诸魔亦变为蛇，并非罪恶所生产。

[63]《失乐园》第十一卷，天使弥盖尔示亚当以将来世界，有病院中各种呻吟痛苦之状。

[64]十七世纪时服役法国的波兰骑兵叫作波拉葛。

[65]自中古时代起，欧洲的外科手术大多操于理发匠之手；法国直至一七四三年，路易十五始下诏将外科医生与理发匠二业完全分离。

[66]先天谐和（又译“预定调和”）为德国哲学家莱布尼兹（一六四六至一七一六）解释宇宙之学说；本书中常常提到天下事尽善尽美的话，亦系莱布尼兹之说。奇妙的物质为笛卡儿解释万物动力的学说，谓宇宙间到处皆有一种液质推动万物。

[67]一阿尔邦等于五十亩，每亩等于一百方尺。

[68]以上均系古希伯来族的王，见《圣经》。

[69]以上均为自利提亚起至罗马帝国为止的国王、将军及皇帝。

译者序　完美的童话

直到译完这本书的结尾，我才发现原来《长腿叔叔》是一部出其不意的作品，这样令人惊喜的结局完美得像一出童话，或许，它本身就是一部成人童话吧！

这本书的作者简·韦伯斯特（1876—1916）之所以能够写出这样一本感情丰富而又诙谐有趣的书，不知道是不是部分得益于家族的遗传——她是美国知名作家马克·吐温的侄孙女，《长腿叔叔》是她最广为人知的一部作品。

简·韦伯斯特对慈善事业的参与构筑了这部小说的框架，作者在对穷苦人民的访视中，坚定了逆境中成长的孩子能成就大事业的信念，也正是这种信念激发了《长腿叔叔》的问世，也正因为亲眼看到了这样的生活，有过感同身受的体验，作者才能将孤独、骄傲、勤奋的小孤儿茱迪的各种微妙的心理刻画得淋漓尽致。

小茱迪活泼、俏皮、倔强的个性在给长腿叔叔的信中无时无刻不表现出来，她的任性、骄傲、刻苦、知足也在笔墨间随意流洒，我们在她身上读到了小女生特有的虚荣，也读到了足以克服虚荣的隐忍，然后顺其自然地随着她走进爱情，或许她的爱情和任何我们知晓的爱情一样盲目得可爱。

小茱迪和长腿叔叔似乎具有“过度幽默”的特质，这着实让死板的人们有点吃不消，让无关痛痒的人们好气又好笑。因为在这个世界上，说真话是需要天真和勇气的！所以，小茱迪这个人物才会显得鲜明生动、可爱真实，就像笑容甜美的邻家女孩，让人忍不住要去宠爱她。

小茱迪这样一个可爱的小姑娘，在这本书的字里行间都充分地展现出她的智慧和灵气。一一列举并且解释这些闪光点实在是很困难。那么就这样吧，请你们沿着我翻译时走过的同一道路走下去——先到孤儿院去看看她，感受一下孤儿院公式化的冷漠，小茱迪的零乱不安与繁忙，然后随着她睁大眼睛满怀好奇地走进校园，和她一起努力地从生活、书本中汲取知识，亲眼看着她茁壮地成长，看着她渐渐摆脱孤儿院给她带来的忧伤、自卑、压抑，乐观地面对一切挫折，成为一个善良的人吧。

忧郁星期三

每个月的第一个礼拜三都糟糕透顶——是满怀恐惧地等待，鼓足勇气地承受，而后再急急忙忙地忘掉的一天。每层楼的地板都得一尘不染，每把椅子都必须整洁无瑕，每张床都要铺得一丝不皱。要给九十七个四处乱爬的小孤儿梳洗干净，套上刚刚浆洗过的花格布衬衫，一个个地提醒他们注意自己的仪态，还要教他们学会不管理事什么时候问话，要回答“是的，先生”或“不，先生”。

这个时候真是令人痛苦。可怜的杰瑞莎·艾伯特作为最年长的孤儿，这一天对她来说就更倒霉了。像往常一样，这个特殊的星期三总算挨到了尾声，杰瑞莎终于从厨房逃了出来，她刚在这里为客人们做了三明治，又跑到楼上去完成她的日常任务。她负责的是第六室，那里有十一个四岁到七岁不等的小不点儿，放了十一张排成一行的小床，杰瑞莎好不容易才把他们集合起来，帮他们整理好皱巴巴的上衣，擦了擦鼻涕，让他们心甘情愿地排成整齐的队伍，而后领着他们去餐室，吃面包，喝牛奶，还有李子布丁，享受半个小时的快乐时光。

做完这些后，她跌坐在靠窗台的椅子上，将涨得生疼的太阳穴抵住冰冷的玻璃。她从早上五点钟开始就手脚不停地忙，还时不时地被神经质的女监事责骂、催促，私底下的李佩特太太可并不会一直保持她面对理事及女宾时平静、庄重的样子。杰瑞莎的目光越过一片上了冻的开阔草地，越过孤儿院高高的铁栏杆，落在远处起伏的山峦、山间散落着的农庄，以及光秃秃的树丛中露出的村庄尖屋顶上。

这一天结束了——就她所知，相当顺利。理事和巡查委员会成员照例巡视了孤儿院，读完了报告，喝完了茶，现在正急匆匆地赶回家享受令人欢欣的炉火，至少要到下个月才能想起他们照管的这些折磨人的小鬼。杰瑞莎探着身子，好奇并带着一丝憧憬地望着那成队的马车、小汽车驶出孤儿院的大门。她幻想自己跟随着一辆又一辆车，去了那些沿着山腰星罗棋布的大房子前。她看到自己穿着皮大衣，戴着插了羽毛的天鹅绒帽子，靠在椅子后背上漫不经心地对车夫说：“回家。”然而到了门槛上，家的画面便模糊不清了。

杰瑞莎喜欢幻想——李佩特太太告诉她说，幻想，要是不小心的话会惹麻烦——但是不管她的想象力有多么丰富，都无法带领她跨过门廊，走进那些她想去的屋子里。可怜的、富有冒险精神的小杰瑞莎，在她有生的十七年间，从未跨入一扇平常的家门，她根本就想象不出那些没有孤儿烦扰的人怎样生活。

杰——瑞——莎　艾——伯——特

办公室有人找

照我看

你还是快点为妙！

汤米·迪伦参加了唱诗班，从楼梯到走廊他一路都在唱歌，靠近第六室的时候，他的歌声越发嘹亮起来。杰瑞莎从窗口收回了目光，不得不再次面对生活的烦恼。

“谁找我？”她打断了汤米的歌唱，急切地问。

办公室里的李佩特太太

我想她快疯啦

阿——门！

汤米拖长了声音唱着，他的语调并没有恶意。甚至连心肠最硬的小孤儿也会对犯了错被叫到办公室的姐姐满怀同情，因为她得到办公室去面对招人讨厌的老太太。汤米还是蛮喜欢杰瑞莎的，虽然她有时使劲儿地拽着他的胳膊，或是差点要把他的鼻子给擦下来。

杰瑞莎没有再说话，走了，只是额头多了两条皱纹。她想知道哪里出问题了，是三明治不够薄吗？是果仁饼里有壳吗？还是哪位女宾发现苏茜·霍森的长袜上有个洞呢？是不是——哦，糟糕！——第六室那些天真无邪的小宝贝跟理事顶嘴了？

低矮的长廊上灯还没有亮，她下楼的时候，最后一位理事站在那儿，正准备离开，他站在通向院外的门口，杰瑞莎对他只有个一闪即逝的印象——他很高。他正朝着一辆停在弯道上的汽车挥手，车子启动开过来时，耀眼的光芒把他的影子投在了室内的墙壁上。影子奇形怪状的：拉长的四肢沿着地板奔跑，蹿上了走廊墙壁，就像人们常常说的“长腿叔叔”——那是一种摇摇晃晃的大蜘蛛。

杰瑞莎紧锁的眉头顿时松开了，发出了一阵欢快的笑声。她性格开朗，一点点小事都能把她逗乐。谁能从哪个理事的难堪之中找到点乐子，自然是意外的惊喜啦！她继续往办公室走去，这个小小的插曲让她非常开心，面对着李佩特太太时也是笑逐颜开。出乎意料的是，杰瑞莎发现李佩特太太也相当和蔼，即便她没有笑容。她的表情愉快得像在接待来访的客人。

“坐下，杰瑞莎，我有话要对你说。”

杰瑞莎坐在了离她最近的椅子上，屏住了呼吸等待着。一辆汽车从窗外闪过，李佩特太太的目光跟在它后头。

“你注意到刚刚走的这位先生了吗？”

“我看到了他的背影。”

“他是我们最富有的理事之一，给救济院捐赠了大笔的款项来支持我们。我没有权利说出他的名字，他特别要求不要说出他的名字。”

杰瑞莎的眼睛微微睁大，她不习惯被召到办公室里来和监事谈论理事们的古怪脾气。

“这位先生一直很关注我们的几个男孩子。你记得查理·本顿和亨利·弗瑞兹吧？他们两个都是——这位，呃……理事先生送去大学的，他们两个人都很用功，都以良好的成绩回报了这位先生的慷慨资助。别的回报这位先生并不想要。迄今为止，他的善心仅限于男孩子，我从来没能让他对这里的女孩子有一点点的兴趣，不管是多么值得的姑娘。我可以告诉你，他不喜欢女孩子。”

“是的。太太。”杰瑞莎讷讷地回答，因为此时，这样的回答似乎是李佩特太太希望听到的。

“今天在例会上，有人提到了你的前途问题。”

李佩特太太略微停顿了片刻，而后又慢条斯理地说了下去，这让她的听众的神经骤然紧绷了起来。

“你也知道，通常，孩子们十六岁以后就不能留在这里了，但你是个例外。你十四岁就完成我们的课程，成绩不错——但也不尽然，得说你的操行并非一向优良——我们才让你继续在村里的中学读书。如今你就要毕业了，当然，院里不能再负担你的费用。即便如此，你也比大部分孩子多读了两年书。”

李佩特太太全然不提在这两年里，杰瑞莎为了自己的食宿卖力地工作。救济院一直是第一位的，她的学习排在第二位，一旦遇到像今天这样的日子，杰瑞莎就得被留下来打扫卫生。

“我刚才说了，有人提出你的前途问题，讨论了你的表现——一场彻底的讨论。”

李佩特太太用谴责的目光望着这个“被告席上的小囚犯”，而“犯人”也配合地露出有罪的神情。因为这种表情是李佩特太太希望看到的，并不是因为她自己记起了自己有什么让人侧目的污点记录。

“自然，像你这种情况，通常安排一个工作就可以了。但是你在学校的时候有些学科学得很不错，英文甚至可以说非常优秀。普里查德小姐是我们巡查委员会的委员，也是学校理事会的成员，她曾经和你的语文老师谈过话，她说了一大通你的好话。她还大声地朗读了你写的一篇作文，叫作《忧郁星期三》。”

这下杰瑞莎可真的知罪了。

“你嘲笑这个为你做了这么多事情的救济院，这让我感觉你丝毫不知道感恩。要是你没有这么幽默的话，我怀疑会不会有人原谅你。然而，幸运的是，那位先生，刚刚走掉的那位理事先生表现出了极大的幽默感，就因为那篇无礼的作文，他决定送你去上大学。”

“上大学？”杰瑞莎瞪大了双眼。

李佩特太太点了点头。

“他留下来和我谈了条件，条件不同寻常。我觉得这位先生相当古怪。他认为你很有天分，他想把你培养成作家。”

“作家？”杰瑞莎的脑袋一下就蒙了，只能重复李佩特太太的话。

“这只是他的愿望，能否成功将来自然会知道的。他会给你提供充裕的零花钱，对一个从来没管过钱的女孩子来说，几乎是过于慷慨了。不过他把事情的细节都计划好了，我感觉似乎不能再提建议了。今年夏天你还是在这里，普里查德小姐慷慨地答应帮你添置衣服。至于你的膳食费以及学费，直接由那位先生付给校方。大学的四年里，你每个月会有三十五美元的零用钱，这足以使你和其他学生的情况相当。这位先生的私人秘书每个月会把钱寄给你，而你每个月收到钱以后要写信给他。并不是要你感谢他给的零用钱，他不在乎你提不提这个，而是让你写一封信说说你的学习进展，以及生活细节，就好像你的父母还在世，你会给他们写的信一样。收信人的名字叫约翰·史密斯，信件由他的秘书转交。这并不是他的真名，他宁愿不让人知道他的真名。对你而言，他永远就是约翰·史密斯。他让你写信，是因为他认为没什么能比写信更能培养人的文学表达能力，既然你没有家人可以通信，他希望你用给家人写信的方式来给他写信。同样地，他也希望能知道你的进展。他不会回你的信，也不会特别挑剔你的来信。他不喜欢写信，也不希望写信成为你的负担。如果有什么紧急问题，有必要回复你的话——譬如你被开除，我相信这种事是不会发生的——你可以和他的秘书格利兹先生联系。对你这一方，这些信件则是绝对的义务，这是史密斯先生对你唯一的要求。因此，你必须把信当成要按时支付的账单一样准时寄出。我希望你的语气能一直保持恭敬，这能反映出你所受到的教育。你必须牢牢记住，你的信是写给约翰·格里尔之家的一位理事。”

杰瑞莎的眼神急切地找寻门在哪里，她已经兴奋得晕头转向了，这会儿，她只希望从李佩特太太的老生常谈中逃开，而后想一想。她起身，试探着退了一步，李佩特太太用手势示意她留下来——这可是一个难得的演说机会。

“我相信，对于这从天而降的好运气你一定是心存感激吧？像你这种情况的女孩子很少有这种见世面的机会，你必须永远地记住——”

“我——是的，太太，谢谢您。我想，要是没有其他事的话，我得去补弗雷德的裤子了。”

门在她身后关上了。李佩特太太盯着门咽下了一肚子被打断的唠叨。她才刚刚说到兴头呢。

序言

爱情是什么？爱情是两性间一种难以名状而又魅力无限的情结。它有时是健康的，有时是病态的；有时在皆大欢喜中让你获得大满足，有时在刻骨铭心的悲痛中铸成人生的大痛苦。试想一下：你一片痴情爱上一位异性，这段经历消耗你好几个年头的生命，到头来却发现自己付出的爱像水一样白白流失。她（或他）受某种陈腐观念的束缚，不敢接受你虔诚奉献的玫瑰，或者根本就麻木不仁，不珍惜你情感的价值，这时你心里是怎样的滋味？你会不会痛心疾首，像《瞎子吃下许多苍蝇》的作者那样，用刻薄的语言来诅咒你的爱人？如果你这样做了，先不论你的认识是否有失偏颇，你已经有了自己的关于“爱情是什么”的答案了。

不错，人类最复杂的情感莫过于爱情了！难怪世世代代的文人骚客总要围绕这个主题喋喋不休，再三宣称它是文学永恒的主题。他们不断描绘爱情的情状，不惜引用自己的隐私说事，无奈仍揭不开爱情的谜底。但在这种徒劳的探索中，人类的文学宝库却增添了许多闪光的诗篇，如马韦尔的《致害羞的情人》，彭斯的《一朵红红的玫瑰》，爱伦·坡的《安娜贝尔·莉》，普拉斯的《对手》，等等。

2000年，上海一家出版社出版过我编译的英美爱情诗歌选集。现我以那个本子为基础，增添必要的篇什，以加强这一类别的作品在文学史意义上的系统性。不敢说英美两国最优秀的爱情诗篇在这里已一览无余，但窥豹之用一定还是有的。至于书名，就叫作《永不凋谢的紫罗兰》吧，因为紫罗兰是一种神秘而优雅的爱情之花，据说还是维纳斯女神的眼泪幻化而成的。

译文会有诸多不如意处，好在原文也一同印出，方便读者直接通过原文欣赏诗歌的美，并对我的译文提出指正。

陈才宇　2017年元月
于杭州寓所

2　瞎子吃下许多苍蝇

无名氏

恋爱的人们，请你们千万小心，
别让情欲使你变得过分痴情。
眼睛所见的一切不要太迷恋——
参孙力大无穷，所罗门是圣人，
只因过于轻信，都曾上当受骗。
明眼人懂得眼见为实的道理。
请记住：瞎子吃下许多苍蝇。

我是说，女人尽管一个个长得端正，
但不能太信任：她们的许诺缺乏真诚。
她们美丽的外表可用脂粉化妆，
她们的忠诚只能维持一百个晚上。
因为她们明里多情，暗中无义，
她们无不是天生的杨花水性。
请记住：瞎子吃下许多苍蝇。

男人如把女人的感情过于当真，
那他到头来一定会自食其果。
因为女人见异思迁，说翻脸就翻脸，
闪光的并非都是金子——男人啊，请小心！
女人的阴毒隐藏在迷人的伪装里，
你别想轻而易举就将它戳穿。
请记住：瞎子吃下许多苍蝇。

尽管整个世界都在忙个不停，
千方百计让女人变得忠贞守信。
但这办不到，这有违她们的天性，
要让她们无二心，除非乾坤颠倒。
她们只会笑不会爱——这一点最肯定，
想要她们靠得住，只是痴心妄想。
请记住：瞎子吃下许多苍蝇。

女人天生有三件护身法宝：
首先，她们最善于作假弄巧，
其次，欺骗是她们的拿手好戏，
再次，她们有的是花招和诡计。
她们要哭就哭，其实别有用心，
只要她们愿意，眼泪就在眼里，
请记住：瞎子吃下许多苍蝇。

说实话，即使这黑咕隆咚的世界，
全都变成光滑而白净的羊皮纸，
即使那无边无际的大海洋，
全变成黑得不能再黑的墨水，
每根树枝变成笔，人人成作家，
也写不完女人的虚伪和阴险。
请记住：瞎子吃下许多苍蝇。

11　林中仙女答牧羊人[1]

劳利[2]

如果世界与爱情天真无邪，
如果牧羊人说话至诚殷切，
这些赏心乐事也许会使我动情，
诱使我跟你一道生活，做你的爱人。

但当河水泛滥，岩石就变得冰凉，
时光将羊群从田野赶回羊栏。
这时夜莺也将沉默无语，
万物都抱怨即临的忧虑。

百花凋谢，草木繁茂的田野
被暴戾的冬天摧残得苍凉萧瑟，
一张甜蜜的嘴，一颗刻毒的心，
那便是想象的春光，悲伤的秋天。

你的礼服，你的鞋，你的玫瑰床，
你的花束，你的绿裳，你的凤冠，
一旦过于成熟，在恶劣的季节里——
便很快枯萎，很快破损，很快被弃。

你麦草与常春藤织成的腰带，
你珊瑚的襻扣，琥珀的饰纽，
这一切都很难使我动情，
诱使我来到你身边，做你的爱人。

但如果爱情不衰亡，青春能持久，
如果欢乐既无尽期又无图谋，
那这些赏心乐事也许能使我动情，
诱使我与你一道生活，做你的爱人。

[1]此诗为应和马洛的《痴情的牧羊人致爱人》（见后文第17首）而作，意在讽刺牧歌式的田园生活的非现实性。

[2]瓦尔特·劳利（Walter Raleigh，1554—1618），政治活动家、军事统帅、航海家、音乐家和历史学家，同时又是诗人。出生于名门望族，在牛津大学就读不到一年便弃学从军。一生从事航海和殖民活动。1603年，因叛国罪被囚禁于伦敦塔。1616年获释，赴圭亚那寻找金矿。1618年10月被处死。著有《世界史》（1614）。

13　他的狄安娜[1]

格雷维尔[2]

别理会顾影自怜的少年，
丘比特不会向他们射出金箭。
别理会悲悲戚戚的可怜虫，
爱情已在眼前，他们还躺着做梦；
丘比特是个草泽之神，
不会强制人跟他的权杖亲吻。

丘比特的神箭有如命运，
善与恶全由他一手裁定；
惩罚出自他那张神弓，
奖掖追随着他的行踪。
哪个傻瓜不明白这道理？
爱情有他自己喜欢的法律！

我的歌要将狄安娜礼赞，
每逢圣节我都把她的戒指戴上，
每棵树上我都写下她的芳名，
每天我都要把它读上几遍。
丘比特的敌手出现在哪里，
哪里就能见到种种奇迹。

如果狄安娜向我索回戒指，
我就在树上抹掉她的名字。
如果猜忌弄脏了珍贵的东西，
那一年一度就不必举行祭礼。
许多人赛跑，夺魁只有一人，
只有傻瓜才让布谷鸟陷入窘困。

感化的力量就是爱情的价值，
这也正是爱情所应有的权益。
爱不仅仅属于那班贵人达官，
牧羊人一样能爱得披肝沥胆。
不错，美丽的仙女可敬可亲，
但没有爱情，对我不值一文。

[1]此诗创作于1600年，原文Cynthia又可译成“铿提亚”，传说勒托在得罗斯岛的铿托斯山上生下阿波罗和阿耳忒弥斯（即狄安娜），这个名字由此而来。

[2]伏尔克·格雷维尔（Fulke Greville，1554—1628），诗人、散文家。毕业于剑桥大学基督学院，做过宫廷官员，1621年封爵。与锡德尼私交甚笃，著有《锡德尼爵士的一生》。诗歌代表作是《玛斯塔佛》。

17　痴情的牧羊人致爱人

马洛[1]

来吧，跟我一起生活，做我的爱人，
天地间的欢乐我们都去追寻，
溪谷、山丘、田野、树林与高山，
无处不是其乐融融的地方。

我们将一块儿坐在岩石上，
看同伴放牧成群的绵羊，
浅水河湾流水声儿淙淙，
歌喉甜润的鸟儿情歌唱得融融。

你的床我要用玫瑰来制造，
再饰以一千束芬芳的花草。
无数朵鲜花织成你的凤冠，
爱神木的叶子装点你的衣裳。

你的礼服用的是最好的羊毛，
那羊毛我们取自可爱的羊羔。
你御寒的鞋子里衬舒适，
那扣结用的是最纯的黄金。

麦草与常春藤的蓓蕾织成你的腰带，
那上面有珊瑚的襻扣，琥珀的饰纽：
如果这些赏心乐事能使你动情，
来吧，与我一道生活，做我的爱人。

每一个五月之晨都充满欢愉，
牧童们将为你载歌载舞：
如果这些赏心乐事能使你动心，
来吧，与我一道生活，做我的爱人。

[1]克利斯朵夫·马洛（Christopher Marlowe，1564—1593），戏剧家、诗人。毕业于剑桥大学，号称“大学才子”。代表作是诗剧《浮士德博士的悲剧》。马洛的诗以气势雄伟、比拟大胆、富于夸张著称。但生活中，他是爱惹是生非的人：1589年，曾参与一次街头的斗殴；1592年，曾因图谋制造假币被荷兰政府驱逐出境。1593年，在小酒店因付账与人发生争执，被人刺死。

28　歌

多恩[1]

去吧，逮住划过天空的流星，
让曼德拉草根怀孕生子，[2]
告诉我：过去的岁月何处栖身？
是谁劈开了魔鬼的脚趾？[3]
教教我：如何去听美人鱼的歌？
如何避免忌妒招致的恶果？
再寻一寻
怎样的风
有助于加强一个人的真诚。

如果你天生一双神奇的眼睛，
看得见别人看不见的一切，
就骑马走上一万夜一万天，
直到岁月在你头上下满霜雪。
当你回来时，你可以如实叙说
你在旅途中经历的奇异事件。
你还可以
对天发誓
说自己从未见过德貌双全的女子。

如有这样的女子，我很想知晓，
你千里迢迢的旅行可谓美满；
但你不必写信，我也不会去寻找，
即便她与我同住在一个街坊。
即便你见到她时，她确实真诚，
那感情一直延续至你写信的一天；
但她一定，
一定有变
不等我到达，已背叛了多个男人。

[1]约翰·多恩（John Donne，1572—1631），玄学派诗人，生于伦敦的一个天主教家庭，父亲是一个富有的商人。就读于牛津和剑桥，因是天主教徒而未能获得学位。做过掌玺大臣埃格顿的秘书，后改信国教，出任伦敦圣保罗教堂的教长。著有《歌与短歌》《世界的剖析》《灵魂的历程》和《神圣的十四行诗》等。

[2]曼德拉草的根部状如人形，民间医学中将它作为保胎药。

[3]据说魔鬼的脚趾是分叉的。

32　离别赠言：莫悲伤

多恩

有德之士逝世时都很安祥，
他对灵魂轻轻地说一声“走”，
这时朋友们都围在他的身旁，
有的说他断气了，有的说没有。

让我们压低嗓门，保持安静，
不必泪流如注，不必哀号叹息，
跟庸俗之徒谈论我们的爱情，
那是对我们的幸福的亵渎。

大地的晃动带来恐慌和灾害，
人们总要测算，把原因探寻，
但宇宙的震颤比这强大千万倍，
人们却无知无觉，毫发未损。

感官即为凡夫俗子的灵台，
他们的爱情接受不了离别，
因为他们一旦与情人分开，
即意味着爱情根基的丧失。

但我们的爱何等的纯洁清明，
连我们自己也说不出所以然，
我们内在的精神始终相互信任，
并不在乎眼、嘴和手的离场。

我们两个灵魂已融合成一体，
尽管我必须离开，这让人难受，
但分离只是灵魂的一种扬厉，
就像金子经锤打变成金箔一轴。

如果说二归二，两个灵魂不相同，
那也好比刚硬的圆规的两只脚，
你的灵魂是固定的一只，不移不动，
只有另一只转动时，它才转起来。

虽然这只脚占据着圆的中心，
一旦另一只脚远远外出漫游，
它总是侧着身子，朝着它倾听，
只有游子回家，它才重新抬头。

你我的联系就这样相依相辅，
我像圆规另一只脚在外打转，
你的坚定使我画的圆规范有度，
最后助我从终点回到起点。

43　致亡妻

弥尔顿[1]

我仿佛看见我圣洁的妻子离开坟墓，[2]
苍白而昏沉，来到我身边，犹如
朱庇特之子从死神处夺回阿尔刻斯提斯，
交还给她那喜不自胜的丈夫。[3]
我的妻子已洗去产褥的污浊，
行过洁身礼，按古法获得救赎，
我还相信，当我们不再受约束，
在天堂重逢时，她也是那般圣洁：
身披白袍而至，纯洁如她的心灵。
脸上蒙着纱巾，在我的幻觉中，
浑身闪耀着爱，闪耀着美和善，
喜气洋溢的样子，更无人能比。
正当她想要拥抱我时，我醒了，
她遁去，我的白天又回到暗夜。

[1]约翰·弥尔顿（John Milton，1608—1674），诗人。生于伦敦的一个清教徒家庭，毕业于剑桥大学基督学院。年轻时积极参加政治斗争，撰文参与宗教论战，担任克伦威尔革命政府的拉丁文秘书。因辛劳过度导致双目失明。王政复辟后遭到迫害，逆境中从事诗歌创作，凭非凡的毅力写出史诗《失乐园》《复乐园》和《力士参孙》等诗篇。此外还写出一些十四行诗和抒情诗。田园挽歌《利瑟达斯》为悼念溺水而亡的同学爱德华·金而作，是悼词诗中最优秀的作品之一。

[2]弥尔顿的第二任妻子凯瑟琳·伍德考克亡于1658年。弥尔顿失明于1651年。

[3]据希腊神话，赫拉克勒斯曾赴地府救出阿尔刻斯提斯，把她送还给她的丈夫阿德墨托斯。欧里庇得斯根据这一题材写过悲剧《阿尔刻斯提斯》。

47　致害羞的情人

马韦尔[1]

只要我们有足够的时间和空间，
夫人，你的羞怯不是过失。
我们可以坐下来慢慢思索，
决定如何行走，如何消度长夜。
你将在恒河边寻找红宝石，
我则随汉姆河的潮水叹息。
我可以在大洪水前十年，
就开始与你说爱谈情，
你呢，只要你乐意这样做，
等到犹太人皈依基督后答应我。
我的平淡的爱可以慢慢生长，
比帝国还广阔，进展更缓慢。
一百年可用来把你的双眼赞美，
欣赏你额头上的神韵与光彩。
两百年爱慕你的每一只乳房，
另外用三万年专注其他地方。
每一部位我都要欣赏至少一世纪，
最后那个世纪才向你披露心迹。
夫人，你确实值得我这样去爱慕，
我自己也不愿让爱流于轻浮。
但是，我私下里经常听人说，
长翅膀的时间马车总匆匆驶过；
看那边，在我们前方不远处，
就是一片永恒的大沙漠。
你的美在那时再难寻觅，
你那座大理石砌成的坟墓
听不见我的歌：只有一群蛆虫
将你长期坚守的贞操享用。
你刻意维护的尊严将归于尘土，
我的一切欲念也将化为灰烬。
坟墓是一座美好的私人宅第，
我相信，无人在那里拥抱亲昵。
因此，趁青春的光华像晨露，
仍然在你的肌肤上留驻，
趁那颗早已以情相许的心，
正向外喷吐熊熊的火焰，
让我们嬉戏行乐，尽兴尽情，
学一学多情多义的猛禽，
宁可由自己一口吞咽时光，
而不要在蚕食中自甘悲凉。
让我们将自身的全部气力，
连同一切美妙聚集在一起，
然后猛一用劲，将生活的铁栏
彻底打开，放出我们的欢畅：
这样，我们虽不能把青春留住，
但将促使它为我们消度。

[1]安德鲁·马韦尔（Andrew Marvell，1621—1678），诗人。毕业于剑桥大学的三一学院。1657年继弥尔顿就任国会的拉丁文秘书。王政复辟时期曾援助过弥尔顿，使他免遭牢狱之灾。生前写过许多诗，但一直被读者忽视，直到20世纪初，即他死后200多年，他的诗才得到读者的高度评价。主要作品有《致害羞的情人》、《花园》及讽刺诗《对画家的最后指示》。

51　我的玛丽[1]

柯伯[2]

自从我们的天空布满乌云，
时间已过去将近二十年；
哎呀，但愿这是最后的不幸！
我的玛丽！

你的精神越来越恍惚，我发现，
你的身体也日渐虚弱，
都是倒霉的我连累了你，
我的玛丽！

你的缝衣针曾经闪闪发光，
为了我，你始终没有闲着，
如今这针锈了，不再闪光了；
我的玛丽！

为了我，你一如既往，
乐意继续为我缝衣，
但你的视力已经不济，
我的玛丽！

你是个出色的家庭主妇，
你手中的线具有一种魔力，
能把我的心紧紧缠起，
我的玛丽！

你说话有点口齿不清，
听起来好像是梦中发声；
但我觉得你的声音最迷人，
我的玛丽！

你的白发曾经一片金黄，
在我眼里，这白发更其可爱，
胜过拂晓时的那万道金光，
我的玛丽！

如果对你的白发熟视无睹，
天底下还有何物值得我关注？
没有你，太阳为我徒劳升起，
我的玛丽！

你的手已经软弱无力，
我的身体也一样在衰竭，
但我们手拉手，永远亲密！
我的玛丽！

当我握住你的手，总觉得
自己比天底下任何人都富有，
吝啬鬼手捧金币，难有这般感受，
我的玛丽！

你很虚弱，每移动一步，
都得有另一双手搀扶，
但你仍有爱心，永朝永夕，
我的玛丽！

你仍有爱心，尽管疾病缠身，
凭这爱心，冬天你不觉得冷，
在我眼里，你永远可爱可亲，
我的玛丽！

哦！通过长期的观察、留意，
我知道：只要我显得忧悒，
你脸上的微笑就被忧伤代替，
我的玛丽！

我还知道：如果我的未来
重新陷入过去的厄运之中，
你疲惫的心一定会破碎，
我的玛丽！

[1]此诗表达诗人对玛丽的感恩之情。其时玛丽照顾诗人的生活已达20年，她自己却患了中风。诗中表达的温柔情感“几乎到了令人痛苦的程度”（丁尼生语）。

[2]威廉·柯伯（William Cowper，1731—1800），诗人。出生于赫里福德的一个牧师家庭，6岁丧母，童年时生活不幸。毕业于一所私立学校，后来精神失常，几度想自杀，被送进精神病院治疗。治愈出院后寄住牧师摩莱·安温家。安温两年后去世，其妻玛丽继续无微不至地照顾他。在玛丽的鼓励下开始诗歌创作，主要作品有《约翰·吉尔宾》《任务》《亚德利的橡树》等。

59　孤独的刈禾女

华兹华斯[1]

看，那边有个高原姑娘，
独自一人在田野里刈禾！
她一边挥镰，一边歌唱，
停下吧，要么悄悄走过！
刈禾，打捆，全凭她一人，
口中的歌凄婉深沉。
听吧，这悠扬的乐音
传遍深邃的山谷。

在阿拉伯的沙漠上，
荫凉处出没的夜莺，
也未曾为疲惫的旅商
把它的歌儿唱得这般动听；
在遥远的群岛希伯里斯，
春天的布谷声声长啼，
那歌声能打破大海的宁静，
也未曾唱得这般扣人心弦。

她唱的是什么，谁能让我晓知？
莫非这哀怨的曲调在倾诉
那古老而悲伤的往事
和那古代战争的痛苦？
也许那是一支普通的歌谣，
它的主题今天无人不晓？
或者那是以往的，可能再现的，
自然的悲哀、痛苦和损失？

不管唱的是什么主题，
姑娘的歌似乎永远唱不完；
我见她一边干活儿一边唱歌，
弯着腰伏在镰刀上——
我伫立着，凝神谛听；
后来我登上了山巅，
这支歌曲虽已无闻，
心头却缭绕着它的余韵。

[1]威廉·华兹华斯（William Wordsworth，1770—1850），浪漫主义诗人。毕业于剑桥大学，年轻时向往法国大革命，还曾经加入过激进派的组织。后来认为大革命的行为过分，才冷却了革命热情。脱离“革命”后回到家乡，专心一致从事诗歌写作。1798年与柯勒律治合出诗集《抒情歌谣集》，并在序言中提出浪漫主义诗歌理论。著名长诗《序曲》具有自传性质。1843年获“桂冠诗人”的称号。

65　她在美中行走

拜伦[1]

她在美中行走，像黑夜
晴朗无云，满天星斗闪耀，
黑暗和光明中美好的一切
都融入她的容颜和双眸；
那光辉如此柔和清冽，
俗丽的白昼得不到造化的关照。

增一毫太稠，减一丝太稀，
非凡的美均会遭到损伤，
因为它荡漾于每一根青丝，
在她的脸上温柔地闪光；
祥和的情思在那里显示，
它的栖息地何等洁净、漂亮！

还有她的双颊，她的额上，
那么温润，那么宁静，那么动人，
以致微笑洋溢，神采飞扬，
说明她享受着美好的人生，
更有那一腔宁静的思想，
那一颗天真无邪的爱心！

[1]乔治·高顿·拜伦（George Gordon Byron，1788—1824），浪漫主义诗人。10岁时即承袭男爵爵位。毕业于剑桥大学。读书时就出版诗集《懒散的时刻》（1807），评论界没有给予好评，伤害了他的自尊心，遂写出一首言辞激烈的讽刺诗《英格兰吟游诗人和苏格兰评论家》予以回击，将当代的文化名人逐一挖苦、贬损。1812年，长诗《恰尔德·哈罗尔德游记》前两章出版，获得好评，随即自封为“诗歌王国的拿破仑”。后又写出长诗《唐璜》。1824年前往希腊，参与那里的民族解放运动。在一次军事行动中患热病去世。

83　我已故的公爵夫人——费拉拉[1]

勃朗宁

墙上挂着我已故的公爵夫人像，
画像栩栩如生，堪称绝世珍品。
佛拉·潘多夫的画笔忙活一天
才大功告成，让她在此立身。
阁下要不要坐下仔细看看？
我特意提及潘多夫，这是因为：
你这样的陌生人见了画中面容，
见了这无比深情而热烈的眼神，
都会转身对着我，（我现在
为你揭去画像上盖的布帷）
他们只要有胆量，一定会问：
画家怎么画得出这般眼神？
是的，并非你第一个这样相问。
先生，公爵夫人脸上那块红晕
并非单单为她的丈夫而生。
也许潘多夫就碰巧说过这话：
“披风将夫人的手盖住太多；
红晕向颈部褪去，隐隐约约；
那不是我们的颜料所能复制。”
她知道，这样的话出于礼节，
但也足以使她变得春风得意。
她这人——我怎么说她好呢？——
太爱听好话，太容易动感情；
见什么爱什么，眼珠转个不停。
先生，她就这个样！喜欢佩戴
我送的饰物，喜欢落日的余晖，
好事的傻瓜为她在园中折取
一支樱桃，或者让她骑白骡
绕园子走走——所有这一切
她都赞不绝口，至少闹个红脸。
她感谢人——这很好！但这感谢——
我不知她怎么谢，只是觉得
她把我给她的九百年的门第
等同别人的礼物。这点小过失
谁愿意追究？即便你口才甚好，
（我没口才）也犯不着跟她计较，
阐明你的意志，说，“我厌恶
你的这点那点；这是你的疏忽，
那是你的越轨。”——即便她愿意
从中吸取教训，不跟你争辩，
不为自己找借口，但即便如此，
我也觉得有失身份，不屑为之。
噢，先生，她爱笑，这没疑问，
只要我走过她身边；但对别人
她也笑脸相迎！后来我只好下禁令，
她的笑从此消失。如今她栩栩如生，
挂在这上面。请阁下起来，我们
还要下楼会见几个朋友。我重申：
伯爵——您的主人出名的慷慨大方，
关于嫁妆，我提的要求也颇正当，
他一定不会轻易予以拒绝；不过，
正如我当初所说，他漂亮的女儿
才是我追求的目标。先生，来吧，
我们一块下楼。看看这座雕像，
海神在驯海马，不愧为稀世珍宝，
这是京城的克劳斯用铜为我铸造。

[1]此诗是一首戏剧独白诗，独白者为费拉拉公爵艾尔逢索（生于1533年），他25岁那年娶了佛罗伦萨公爵之女为妻，当时她才14岁。婚后第三年，公爵夫人去世，死因存疑。而后艾尔逢索公爵预备再娶，女方是奥地利的一位伯爵小姐。伯爵派来一位使者与公爵谈论这桩婚姻。公爵领使者观看他已故夫人的画像，此诗即为公爵在画像前对使者的“独白”。

85　忆

勃朗特

地下冷啊，身上还盖着厚厚积雪，
远离人世，你就在这阴冷的墓里！
隔绝一切的时间之河终将你隔绝，
唯一的爱人啊，我何曾忘了爱你？

如今我孤身一人，我的思念怎能
不盘旋在这北部海岸和连绵高山，
怎能不栖息于石楠和蕨草的莽丛，
以求与你高贵的心灵永远相伴？

地下冷啊，十五个寒冬腊月过去，
那些褐色的山岗都已融化成春天，
经过这么多年的变迁和凄凉悲苦，
我这灵魂依然记着你，依然坚贞！

青春的恋人啊，即便我把你忘记，
那也情有可原：世俗之潮卷我前行，
别的欲求与希望将我团团围起，
你因此被遮蔽，但我不能待你不公。

迟来的阳光已照不见我的天堂，
明天的晨曦也不再为我闪光，
我一生的幸福都寄寓在你身上，
我一生的幸福就在你的坟场！

但是，当金色梦中的日子消逝，
甚至连绝望也失去毁灭的力量，
这时，我得学会对生存的珍惜，
勉力维持，让生存滋养于无欢。

我得遏制青春的灵魂对你的思慕，
擦干从无用的激情流下的泪滴，
你的坟墓，其实就是我的坟墓，
但我仍得拒绝，不急于登程归去。

我甚至不敢让灵魂从此萎靡，
不敢沉溺于记忆的大悲和大喜；
如我在神圣的苦恼中陶醉自己，
那我如何直面这空洞的人世？

93　伊堤罗斯[1]

斯文本

燕子，我的姐姐，哟，姐姐燕子，
你的心怎么会这般春意盎然？
一千个夏天已消逝，已作古。
你发现春天有什么值得追随？
什么事值得你用心来歌唱？
夏季过去，你要飞往何处？

哟，燕子，姐姐，疾飞的燕子，
春天过后，你为何要飞往南方？
温暖的南方就那么值得你思慕？
是不是那里没有往昔的痛苦？
你在那里唱歌不会失调走腔？
你是否先于我忘记了过去？

姐姐，我的姐姐，可亲的燕子，
太阳离你遥远，南方隔之千里。
但我在这里照样活得称心：
我把歌唱向高空，唱向天际，
从茶色的身躯，小小的喉舌，
向黑夜的心献出火样的情。

哟，燕子，姐姐，善变的燕子，
瞧瞧我夜莺吧，这一整个春天，
一整个春天，我自始至终
披一袭露珠闪烁的夜光衣
不息地歌唱，领着时光和鸟儿飞行，
追寻着太阳，直到它显出真身。

姐姐，我的姐姐，噢，轻柔的燕子，
即便万物都在春天的客厅欢宴，
你凭什么也那么兴高采烈？
不管你飞往哪里，我都不会追随你，
直到生命遗弃我，死神把我叨念，
直到你记起我，我忘却一切。

燕子，我的姐姐，爱唱歌的燕子，
我不知道你怎么还有心思歌吟。
你有一颗心吗？事情都过去了？
夏天是你的主人，值得你追随，
拥有美足的春天是你的爱人，
你对这位爱人有什么要说？

哟，燕子，姐姐，疾飞的燕子，
我的心是一堆熔化的余烬，
我头上是一片汹涌的海洋。
如果我犯健忘，只有你依然铭记，
如果你不忘过去，是我忘了干净，
那时你可留下，让我飞离远方。

迷途的姐姐啊，善变的燕子，
由于心性相异，你我各奔东西。
你的心轻浮，树叶般飘忽不定；
我的心始终徘徊在海港天际，
流连于伊堤罗斯被害的凶地，
纪念着达利斯之宴和色雷斯海滨。

哟，燕子，姐姐，疾飞的燕子，
不要再歌唱了，我恳求你。
屋顶和门楣都湿了，你没看见？
塔楼内结满了蛛网，你不记得？
被杀的小身体，那花一般的脸，
即便你忘了，我铭记在心！

姐姐啊姐姐，那是你的头生子！
他的手拉着你，他的脚跟着你，
孩子的鲜血仍在那里呼喊：
谁还记得我啊？谁把我忘了？
忘了他的是你哟，夏日的燕子！
若要我忘记，那该是世界末日。

[1]此诗为戏剧独白诗，独白者是夜莺菲罗墨拉。据希腊神话，色雷斯国王奸污了王后普洛克涅的妹妹菲罗墨拉，为了掩饰罪行，色雷斯国王将菲罗墨拉囚禁于塔楼，并割去她的舌头。普洛克涅了解事情真相后替妹妹报仇：亲手杀死她与国王所生的儿子伊堤罗斯。色雷斯国王随后追杀两姐妹。两姐妹在逃命途中被神变形：普洛克涅变成了一只燕子，菲罗墨拉成了一只夜莺。

103　丽达与天鹅

叶芝[1]

猛地一扑：一对巨翼降落少女头顶，
使她踉踉跄跄站立不稳，黑色的蹼
抚弄她的大腿，鹅喙衔住她的脖颈，
那天鹅的胸脯已紧紧压住她的胸脯。

她那双因惊恐而僵硬的手怎能从
松开的腿间推开白羽赋予的荣耀？
她的身体倒在雪白的灯心草丛中，
怎会感觉不到那不可思议的心跳？

股间的一阵震颤，居然由此导致
城墙的倒塌，楼宇被烈火焚毁，以及
阿伽门农的死亡[2]。她如此被霸占，
被来自空中的鲁莽的血所挟制，
当那冷漠的鹅喙终于放开她时，
她是否拥有了他的知识和力量？

[1]威廉·巴特勒·叶芝（William Butler Yeats，1865—1939），爱尔兰诗人。生于都柏林的一个艺术家家庭。父亲和兄弟杰克·叶芝都是画家。早年也曾学习绘画，但后来弃艺术而专志于文学。一生中不断尝试新的诗风，唯美主义、象征主义、现代主义中都留下过他的足迹，尤以象征主义诗歌的创作著称于世。一生共写过11部诗歌、26个剧本、9部散文集和一些哲学、文论的著作。艾略特曾把他称为“我们时代最伟大的诗人”。1923年因“始终富于灵感的诗歌”获诺贝尔文学奖。

[2]据希腊神话，变作天鹅的主神宙斯与丽达的这一次结合，生下了美人海伦。特洛伊王子帕里斯诱拐了海伦，导致特洛伊战争。城墙的倒塌，楼宇被烈火焚毁，阿伽门农的死亡，指的都是这次战争的结果。

108　一天傍晚，我走出家门

奥登[1]

一天傍晚，我走出家门，
沿着布里斯托大街前行，
人行道两旁鳞次栉比，
是一片片成熟的麦田。

在河水满溢的岸边，
铁路桥的桥墩下面，
我听见一个恋人在歌吟：
“我的爱没有终点。

“我爱你，亲爱的，我爱你，
直到中国与非洲接壤，
直到河水跃上山顶，
大马哈鱼在街上歌唱。

“我爱你，直到海洋被折起，
悬挂空中被太阳晒干，
直到七颗星成了鹅鸭，
在空中鸣叫着飞翔。

“直到岁月兔子般奔跑，
因为我把你拥在怀中，
你是千古不朽的一朵花，
你是我人世间的初恋。”

但城里所有的大钟
都气呼呼地开口申诉：
“哟，别让时间欺骗你，
也别妄想把时间征服。

“正义如今已赤身裸体，
在噩梦的洞窟幽囚，
时间在黑暗中监视，
你一亲吻，它就咳嗽。

“生活是一片混沌，
流失于病痛和焦虑，
时间有自己的幻想，
今天和明天，不分早迟。

“令人震惊的鹅毛大雪
飘向青翠的群山幽谷；
时间打断交织的舞蹈
和潜水者优雅的鞠礼。

“把你的双手伸入水中，
让水浸过你的手腕，
然后朝水盆仔细看看，
为你的所失而迷惶。

“冰川叩击你的食品柜，
沙漠在你的床上哀叹，
茶杯上显现一道裂痕，
是指向死亡的小巷。

“乞丐在那里博彩，
巨人施魔法将杰克迷惑，
纯洁的少年成了暴徒，
吉尔下山，已体无完肤。[2]

“哟，看看吧，看看镜子，
留意你自己的不幸；
虽然你不能赐福予人，
但生活仍是一种幸福。

“哟，站住吧，站在窗口边，
让伤心的泪夺眶而出；
你的那颗心已经扭曲，
就该去爱扭曲的邻居。”

天色已经很晚，很晚，
情人们都已散去；
时钟闭上了嘴巴，
但河水仍流淌不止。

[1]温斯坦·休·奥登（Wynstan Hugh Auden，1907—1973），诗人。出生于英国约克郡的一个医生家庭，15岁开始写诗，在牛津大学就读时，已有许多爱好诗歌的青年追随他，人称“奥登派”。一度信仰过马克思主义，与德国法西斯作过勇敢的斗争，并同情中国的抗日战争。1939年定居美国，皈依基督教，世界观从此发生变化。1946年加入美国国籍。曾任教于美国多所大学。诗集有《短诗集》《长诗集》。

[2]杰克和吉尔，是童谣中两个上山取水的孩子，民间故事中也通常用这两个名字代替“小伙子”和“姑娘”。

109　临产时致爱人

布莱斯特里特[1]

世间万事万物都有终期，
我们的幸福总伴随着痛苦。
亲近的友人，紧密的结合，
逃不脱命定的生离死别。
昔日的判决无挽回的可能，
死亡寻常事，无人能永生。
亲爱的，死神何时将我追寻，
你何时注定失去你的亲朋，
我们不得而知，但爱有嘱咐，
要我将这首离别诗献给你，
以便绑定你我的结一旦消除，
不复存在的死者也有其依附。
如果我半途而夭，天年未尽，
主会将我的余寿转赐予你。
你清楚，我有诸多的缺陷，
让它们随我一道埋入坟茔。
如果我也有些许优点和美德，
让它们在你的记忆里长驻。
当你不再为离世的人伤情，
请你仍爱着曾经相拥过的人。
你若续弦，以补偿你的所失，
请你照料好我留下的孩子。
如果你爱自己，对我也有爱，
千万别让他们受后母伤害。
如果你有机会读到这首诗，
请叹息几声，光耀我的坟墓，
为你的爱人吻一吻这片纸，
她用咸泪向你作最后辞别。

[1]安妮·布莱斯特里特（Anne Bradstreet，1612—1672），诗人。出生于英格兰，父亲是马萨诸塞湾侨居地总督，16岁嫁给西蒙·布莱斯特里特（另一侨居地总督）。1620年随父亲和丈夫移居伊普斯威奇，后又定居于北安多弗。生有8个孩子，于繁忙的家务间隙从事诗歌创作。1650年出版第一部诗集《最近出现于美洲的第十个缪斯》。著有长诗《新老英格兰的对话》《四王朝》等。最为人称颂的是晚年写的一些审察内心和新英格兰的短诗。

111　一切献给爱

爱默生[1]

一切献给爱，
让心作为主宰；
朋友、亲戚、岁月，
财产、名望，
规划、信誉、诗才——
什么都别拒绝。

爱是一位明主，
就让它君临天下吧！
唯她马首是瞻，
永远怀着希望。
爱无须张开翅膀，
她只要怀着默默的期待，
就能越升越高，
直上云霄。

爱是一位神，
认识自己的行程
以及通向天堂的门。
爱与卑贱无缘，
她需要大无畏，
无猜忌的胸怀，
不屈不挠的精神。
她只肯回报这种人——
当他们返回时，
意志更坚定，
勇气继续上升。

为爱抛弃一切吧！
但听我再说一句，
这将对你大有好处：
在你不懈的努力中再加一把劲儿，
就能使你如意称心，
今天，明天，乃至永远，
自由自在，一如
你所向往的阿拉伯人。

与少女一道生活吧！
但是，一旦惊惶
和猜忌的阴影
掠过她年轻的心扉，
欢乐离你而去，
那就别管她，任她远走高飞。
你用不着扯住她的衣襟，
更不必保留那枝从她的夏日王冠上摘下，
已经褪色的玫瑰。

尽管你爱她就像爱你自己，
甚至把她当作更圣洁的自我，
尽管她的分享使白昼显得暗淡，
使一切生命失去光辉，
但你仍应欣然领悟：
只要假神一走，
真神就在后头。

[1]莱尔夫·华尔多·爱默生（Ralph Waldo Emerson，1803—1882），思想家，文学家，诗人。生于波士顿，毕业于哈佛大学。本科毕业后入神学院深造。先后担任过教师和牧师。1832年赴欧洲游历，接受康德的哲学。回国后主编评论季刊《日规》，创立超验主义哲学体系。他认为，自然现象都是某种精神现象的象征，只要你能感悟，就能掌握真理。他的哲学思想成了美国浪漫主义文学的哲学基础。他自己也写诗，他的诗体现一种智性的、哲理的、玄奥的思考。主要作品有《论文集》《代表人物》《英国人的性格》等。诗集有《诗选》。

114　乌鸦

爱伦·坡

一个阴沉沉的午夜，
案前一大堆奇书古籍
记载着被人遗忘的传说，
我苦苦思索，又累又困；
当我打起盹儿，几乎睡着时，
突然响起一记拍打声，
好像有人正在敲门——
在敲我的卧室的门。
我对自己说，“有客人来了，
客人在敲我的房门；
一定如此，没有别的解释。”

噢，这事我记得清楚，
那是阴沉萧瑟的腊月，
行将熄灭的每一块炭火
都鬼魂般在室内穿梭。
我渴望天色早点放明；
我徒劳地翻阅手中书卷，
那里没有消愁的良方——
消释我失去丽诺的忧愁——
丽诺，最美最可爱的少女，
为她起名的是天使——
人间从此没有这名字。

每一幅紫色的丝绸窗帘
都发出悲哀莫名的簌簌声，
令我毛骨悚然——使我内心
充满从未有过的疯狂和恐惧。
此刻，为了止住心跳，
我站在那里，重复着说：
“一定是什么人来找我，
求我允许他进入房门；
对了，没有别的解释。”

我的灵魂顿时变得坚强；
我不想再迟疑观望，
我于是说：“先生或夫人，
我真心请求你的原谅；
刚才我正在打瞌睡，
而你又拍打得太轻，
我是说刚才你敲得太轻——
我的房门你敲得太轻，
以致我不敢肯定门外有人。”
说完我便将房门洞开：
门外一片黑暗，一无所有。

我凝视黑暗的深处，
久久站在那里沉思
我恐惧，疑虑，做着梦，
做着常人从不敢做的梦；
但静寂没有被打破，
黑暗中没有任何人影，
只有一个声音在响，
那是一声“丽诺！”的低语，
低语出自我自己，回声
传来，也是低声的“丽诺！”
仅此而已，没有别的。

我返身回到室内，
灵魂整个儿都在燃烧，
很快又听见一记拍打声，
那声音比刚才还响。
我说：“这回清楚了，
有东西在敲我的窗棂；
让我看看究竟是什么，
让我揭开这个谜——
让我的心先静一静，
马上揭开这个谜；
肯定是风，没有别的。”

我于是打开百叶窗，
一只来自神圣古代的乌鸦
拍打着翅膀，摇着尾巴，
昂首阔步进入我的房间。
他没有向我致敬行礼，
没有迟疑，没有停下脚步，
他的神气就像这里的主人，
他在房门上方停息下来——
就停息在房门上方
那一尊雅典娜的塑像上——
那样蹲着，毫不含糊。

这只黑如乌木的鸟
凭着他天生的庄严仪表
哄着我悲伤的心窍，
让我转悲为喜。
我说：“你真够胆大，
就不怕我把你的羽毛拔下！
你这阴森可怕的古代乌鸦，
来处黑暗的彼岸；
告诉我，在普路同的冥府，
你可有尊姓大名？”
乌鸦回答：“永不再。”

丑陋的大鸟听得懂人话，
这让我无比惊讶，
尽管他的回答语焉不详，
好像还有点不恰当。
但我们不能不承认：
活在世上的芸芸众生，
没有谁能像我这样福星高照，
能亲眼见到房门上有鸟来到——
有鸟或兽光顾门庭，
栖息在房门口的塑像之上，
那鸟就叫“永不再。”

在这宁静的塑像上，
乌鸦独自停息，只说
一句话，他的灵魂
似乎凭这句话而倾诉。
他没有再说什么，
也不再拍打翅膀，
直到我禁不住自语喃喃：
“别的朋友已经飞走，
明天一早他也会离开，
就像希望弃我而去那样。”
乌鸦开口说：“永不再。”

他打破沉默的回答十分贴切，
我不由得大吃一惊。
我于是说：“毫无疑问，
这就是他能说的全部；
他从某位不幸的主人学得
这一句，但无情的灾难
追随他的主人，越追越紧，
直到他的歌负载起——
直到他希望的安魂曲
负载起忧郁的重荷，
这重荷就是“永不再。”

但乌鸦继续在哄我，
想让我由苦恼转为欢笑，
我索性将一把靠背椅
推到他跟前，推到塑像下方；
我往天鹅绒上一坐，
打算将自己的幻想
一一梳理，并揣摩
这只不祥古鸟的来历——
我想知道这只丑陋的、
不祥的、阴森可怕的古鸟
为何总是叫着“永不再。”

我就这样坐着，思忖着，
对这只鸟不发一言，
此刻，乌鸦眼睛中的火
已经点燃我的心灵深处；
我就这样坐着，揣测着，
我的头轻轻地靠住
座椅上的天鹅绒衬套，
任凭灯光轻慢的照耀。
这紫罗兰色的天鹅绒衬套，
这灯光轻慢的照耀，
她都不再拥有，永不再！

然后我觉得空气变稠密了，
无形的香炉由天使摇晃着，
散发出浓香，绒绒的地板上
响着天使的脚步，丁丁有声。
“可怜人啊，”我呼喊起来，
“上帝眷顾你，派天使
送来安息——安息和忘忧神水，
好让你不再思念你的丽诺！
喝下吧，喝下这忘忧神水，
忘了你已经失去的丽诺！”
乌鸦说：“永不再。”

“先知啊，恶魔啊，”我对他说，
“不论是鸟是鬼，你首先是先知！
不管你出于魔王的派遣，
还是狂风将你吹来此地，
你孑然一身，浑身是胆，
来到这被魔法控制的荒土——
来到这充满恐怖的家园——
我恳求你，求你如实相告：
在基列[1]，是否真有灵药？
告诉我，告诉我，我求你了！”
乌鸦说：“永不再。”

“先知啊，恶魔啊，”我对他说，
“不论是鸟是鬼，你首先是先知！
凭着我们头顶的苍天——
凭着你和我都崇拜的上帝——
告诉我这痛不欲生的灵魂：
在那遥远的伊甸园，
我是否能拥抱神圣的少女，
那位天使称为丽诺的姑娘？”
乌鸦说：“永不再。”

“你这鸟或魔鬼，”我尖叫着跳起，
“凭这句话我们分手吧！
回到你暴风雨的居所，
回到黑暗的普路同海岸！
你的黑羽毛，一根也别留下，
免得它见证你说过的谎话！
别将我的寂寞打破！——
离开我房门上的塑像！
别用你的嘴啄我的心，
请你离开我的家门！”
乌鸦说：“永不再。”

乌鸦没有动一动身子，
他始终停在那里，停在那里，
就在苍白的雅典娜的塑像上，
就在我的卧室的门上；
他的眼睛显现的神情，
就像魔鬼正在做梦，
灯光在他身上晃动，
地板上映出他的影子；
我的灵魂飘浮在地板上，
无法摆脱那影子，无法
往上升起——永不再！

[1]基列，《圣经》地名，在约旦河东岸，那里出产止痛灵药。

124　艾尔莎·维德曼

马斯特斯[1]

我是来自德国的一个农家女，
碧眼，红润的脸，快活又健壮。
我一开始就在格林家做工。
夏季的一天，她出了家门，
他溜进厨房，把我紧紧
抱在怀里，吻我的脖子；
我扭头抵抗。我们似乎
谁也不知发生了什么事。
我为未知的未来而啼哭，
我哭啊哭，直到秘密开始显露。
一天，格林太太说她理解我，
要为我排忧解难，
他们无子女，可以将孩子收养。
（为求安静，他送给她一个农庄。）
从此她躲在家里，传话出去，
好像事情都发生在她身上。
一切顺利，孩子生下——他们对我很好。
后来我嫁给格斯·维德曼，许多年过去。
但是——政治集会时，汉密尔顿·格林夸夸其谈，
我身边的人却发现我在啼哭——
事情不是这样的。
不是的！我只想说：
那是我的儿子！
那是我的儿子！

[1]爱德加·李·马斯特斯（Edgar Lee Masters，1868—1950），诗人，小说家。出生于堪萨斯州，做过律师。1898年出版诗集《诗编》。1915年出版《斯蓬河诗集》，一举成名。这部诗集用事主独白的形式描述埋葬在米德韦斯特公墓的200多位死者的生平行迹，语言直白、通俗、幽默。晚年的代表诗作有《走向深渊》《饥饿的岩石》等。著有小说《市场里的孩子》《芝加哥故事》等。有自传《跨过斯蓬河》。

140　致罗斯姨妈

金斯堡[1]

罗斯姨妈——现在——但愿我能见到你
那张枯瘦的脸和露出暴牙的笑和风湿病的
痛苦——以及那只又长又黑又重的鞋子
就为你瘦骨嶙峋的左腿
一瘸一拐走过纽瓦克铺有地毯的长廊
走过那台黑色的大钢琴
那间娱乐室
是聚会的场所
我用尖锐的高音（歇斯底里）
唱出西班牙共和派的歌[2]
委员会的成员都在听
你一瘸一拐在娱乐室里行走
一边收钱——
亲爱的姨妈，山姆大叔是一个口袋里藏着
一把布手枪的陌生人
亚伯拉罕·林肯旅团[3]中
一个高大年轻的秃头。

——你长长的脸带着忧伤
性挫折使你泪流满面
（何其压抑的抽泣和瘦削的臀部
掩埋在奥斯本·泰勒斯的枕头底下）
——有一回我赤身裸体站在马桶座圈上
你用卡洛明搽我的大腿
以消除我的皮疹——我那柔软的
令人羞耻的黑色卷须刚长出
当你知道我已经变为一个男人
你隐秘的内心不知怎么想——
我对一个无知的女孩所行的家丑叉开双腿
立于盥洗室单薄的座垫上——纽瓦克博物馆。
罗斯姨妈
希特勒死了，希特勒已经在永恒之中；希特勒已经跟
帖木儿和艾米丽·勃朗特[4]在一起

我看见你还在行走，从奥斯本梯田出发的一个幽灵
沿着黑暗的长廊来到大门口
身子微微晃动脸上挤出笑容
身穿一件印花的
绸衣
迎接我那做诗人的父亲来纽瓦克做客
——看见你来到起居室
用你的跛足跳舞
拍手祝贺他的书
被莱佛莱特[5]所接受
希特勒死了，莱佛莱特倒闭了
《早年的阁楼》和《永恒的分分秒秒》已成绝版
哈莱叔叔卖掉了他最后一双丝袜
克莱从舞蹈学校辍学
老祖母像一尊起皱的雕像坐在
养老院对着新生的婴儿眨眼睛。

我最后一次见到你是在医院里
瘦骨嶙峋脸色苍白如一具骷髅
青筋暴起失去知觉的一个老女孩
戴着氧气面罩
西班牙的战争早就结束了
罗斯姨妈。

[1]艾伦·金斯堡（Allen Ginsberg，1926—1997），诗人。生于新泽西州，毕业于哥伦比亚大学。1956年出版诗集《嚎叫》，一举成名。他被称为“垮掉的一代的代言人”（a voice of the Beat Generation）。出版商弗林费蒂因出版这部“淫秽的作品”，还受到过审判。金斯堡喜欢游历，到过古巴、印度、日本、中国、俄国，宣传他反权威、反主流文化的思想。另有诗集《祈祷及其他》《空镜子》《现实三明治》等。1973年出版的诗集《美国的堕落》获国家图书奖。

[2]西班牙内战发生于1937—1939年间，交战双方是共和派与佛朗哥的法西斯主义者。

[3]林肯旅团是美国支援西班牙反法西斯战争的志愿军。

[4]帖木儿（1336—1405），帖木儿帝国的创建者；艾米丽·勃朗特（1818—1848），英国女作家，《呼啸山庄》的作者。

[5]莱佛莱特，出版公司名。

145　郁金香

普拉斯

郁金香太容易激动，这里是冬天。
看，一切多么白净，多么安静，多么像一片雪地。
一个人静静地躺着，我得学会让自己保持心灵的安宁，
阳光落在白色的墙上，落在床上，落在我的手掌上。
我微不足道；没有理由大叫大喊。
我已经把我的名字和日用的衣物交给护士，
已经把我的历史交给麻醉师，身体交给医生。

他们把我的头放在枕头和被头之间，
就像眼珠子嵌进不能闭合的白色眼睑。
愚蠢的瞳孔，不得不接纳一切。
护士来回走动，他们并不令人讨厌，
他们戴着白帽，行走时就像着陆的海鸥，
他们用双手做事，动作一致，
因此很难说清究竟有多少人。

在他们看来，我的身体是一块卵石，他们抚慰它
就像水抚慰卵石，因为水得从上面轻轻流过，
他们用闪亮的针让我麻痹，使我睡着。
既然失去了自我，我厌恶那多余的东西——
那暂时专属于我的皮革箱像一个黑色的药盒，
我的丈夫和孩子在全家的合影里微笑；
这微笑扎进我的皮肤，变成了钩子。

我已经让货物滑落，一条航行了三十年的
小货船固执地挂着我的名字和地址。
它们已经为我抹去爱的种种联系。
光着身子，惊恐地躺在塑制的推车上，
我望见我的茶具、衣柜、书籍都在下沉，
从视野中消失，水从我的头颅流过。
我现在成了修女，变得无比的纯洁。

我不需要鲜花，只需要这样躺着，
手掌向上摊开，手上一无所有。
何等的自由啊，你无法想象这自由——
这安宁，巨大得足以让你晕眩，一无所求，
连一纸姓名标签、几件小玩意儿都不需要。
死人最后都这结局；我想象得到：
人们从此噤声，就像面对一块圣餐面包。

首先，郁金香太艳丽，它们伤害了我。
即便是折纸，我仍能听见郁金香轻微的呼吸，
透过白色的襁褓，像一个可怕的婴儿。
那殷红在跟我的伤口说话，在传递信息。
狡猾的花啊：尽管我被压着，总觉得它们飘在空中，
以它们的快嘴和颜色搅扰我的安宁，
其中有几支还领着送葬者绕行在我身边。

我本无人围观，如今被人盯着看。
郁金香对着我，对着身后的窗户，
阳光每天一次在那里慢慢扩展，慢慢淡去，
我看见自己平卧着，模样可笑，一个剪纸的影
徘徊在太阳的眼睛和郁金香的眼睛之间，
我没有脸，想抹去自己。
鲜艳的郁金香吞食我的氧气。

它们到来以前，空气显得异常的安静，
来回自若，一阵一阵，一点也不凌乱。
这以后郁金香就将它挤压成一个喧哗的声音。
空气开始东拐西弯，像河水
围着一个下沉的破水泵横冲直撞。
它们聚集起我的注意力，自己不作为，
便能尽情玩耍、休息，真是幸福的事。

墙壁也好像正在为自己取暖。
郁金香本应该像危险的动物那样躲在栅栏背后；
它们正在开放，像张着嘴的非洲大猫，
我知道我的心：它一张一合开出
红彤彤的花冠完全出于对我的爱。
我尝到的水是温的，海水般的咸，
来自与健康一样遥远的国度。

2. The Blind Eateth Many a Fly

——Anonym

Look well about, ye that lovers be;
Let not your lustes lead you to dotage.
Be not enamored on all things that ye see——
Samson the fort and Solomon the sage,
Deceived were, for all their great corage.
Men deem it right, that they see with eye——
Beware, therefore: the blind eateth many a fly.

I mean, of women, for all their cheeres quaint,
Trust them not too much——their troth is but geason.
The fairest outward well can they paint;
Their steadfastness endureth but a season,
For they feign friendliness and worken treason.
And for they are changeable naturally,
Beware, therefore: the blind eateth many a fly.

What wight alive trusteth on their cheers,
Shall have at last his guerdon and his meed,
For women can shave nearer than razors or shears.
All is not gold that shineth——men, take heed.
Their gall is hid under a sugared weed.
It is full quaint their fantasy to espy.
Beware, therefore: the blind eateth many a fly.

Though all the world do its busy cure
To make women stand in stableness,
It will not be, it is against nature:
The world is done when they lack doubleness,
For they can laugh and love not——this is express.
To trust on them, it is but fantasy.
Beware, therefore: the blind eateth many a fly.

Women of kinde have conditions three:
The first is they be full of deceit;
To spin also is theire property;
And women have a wonderful conceit.
For they can weep oft, and all is a sleight,
And ever when they list, the tear is in the eye.
Beware, therefore: the blind eateth many a fly.

In sooth to say, though all the earth so wan
Were parchment smooth, white, and scribable,
And the great sea that called is the ocean
Were turned into ink blacker than sable,
Every stick a pen, each man a scrivener able,
Not could they then write woman's treachery.
Beware, therefore: the blind eateth many a fly.

13. Of His Cynthia

——F. Greville

Away with these self-loving lads,
Whom Cupid's arrow never glads.
Away, poor souls that sigh and weep,
In love of them that lie and sleep;
For Cupid is a meadow god,
And forceth none to kiss the rod.

God Cupid's shaft, like destiny,
Doth either good or ill decree;
Desert is born out of his bow,
Reward upon his feet doth go.
What fools are they that have not known
That love likes no laws but his own?

My songs they be of Cynthia's praise,
I wear her rings on holy-days,
On every tree I write her name,
And every day I read the same.
Where Honor Cupid's rival is,
There miracles are seen of his.

If Cynthia crave her ring of me,
I blot her name out of the tree.
If doubt do darken things held clear,
Then well fare nothing once a year.
For many run, but one must win;
Fools only hedge the cuckoo in.

The worth that worthiness should move
Is lore, which is the due of love.
And love as well the sllepherd can
As can the mighty nobleman.
Sweet nymph, 'tis true you worthy be,
Yet without love, nought worth to me.

29. The Good-Morrow

——John Donne

I wonder by my troth what thou, and I
Did, till we loved? Were we not weaned till then,
But sucked on country pleasures, childishly?
Or snorted we in the seven sleepers' den?
'Twas so; but this, all pleasures fancies be.
If ever any beauty I did see,
Which I desired and got, 'twas but a dream of thee.

And now good-morrow to our waking souls,
Which watch not one another out of fear;
For love all love of other sights controls
And makes one little room an everywhere.
Let sea-discoverers to new worlds have gone,
Let maps to others, worlds on worlds have shown:
Let us possess one world; each hath one, and is one.

My face in thine eye, thine in mine appears,
And true plain hearts do in the faces rest;
Where can we find two better hemispheres,
Without sharp North, without declining West?
Whatever dies was not mixed equally;
If our two loves be one, or, thou and I
Love so alike that none do slacken, none can die.

30. The Sun Rising

——John Donne

Busy old fool, unruly Sun,
Why dost thou thus,
Through windows, and through curtains call on us?
Must to thy motions lovers' seasons run?
Saucy pedantic wretch, go chide
Late school-boys, and sour' prentices,
Go tell court-huntsmen that the King will ride,
Call country ants to harvest offices;
Love, all alike, no season knows, nor clime,
Nor hours, days, months, which are the rags of time.

Thy beams, so reverend, and strong
Why shouldst thou think?
I could eclipse and cloud them with a wink,
But that I would not lose her sight so long:
If her eyes have not blinded thine,
Look, and tomorrow late, tell me,
Whether both the Indias of spice and mine.
Be where thou left'st them, or lie here with me.
Ask for those kings whom thou saw'st yesterday,
And thou shalt hear,“All here in one bed lay.”

She is all States, and all Princes, I;
Nothing else is.
Princes do but play us; compar'd to this,
All honour's mimic; all wealth alchemy.
Thou Sun art half as happy as we,
In that the world's contracted thus;
Thine age asks ease, and since thy duties be
To warm the world, that's done in warming us.
Shine here to us, and thou art every where;
This bed thy centre is, these walls, thy sphere.

32. A Valediction: Forbidding Mourning

——John Donne

As virtuous men pass mildly away,
And whisper to their souls to go,
Whilst some of their friends do say
The breath goes now, and some say, No;

So let us melt, and make no noise,
No tear-floods, nor sigh-tempests move,
'Twere profanation of our joys
To tell the laity our love.

Moving of th' earth brings harm and fears,
Men reckon what it did and meant;
But trepidation of the spheres,
Though greater far, is innocent.

Dull sublunary lovers' love
(Whose soul is sense) cannot admit
Absence, because it doth remove
Those things which elemented it.

But we, by a love so much refined
That our selves know not what it is,
Inter-assurèd of the mind,
Care less, eyes, lips, and hand to miss.

Our two souls therefore, which are one,
Though I must go, endure not yet
A breach, but an expansion,
Like gold to airy thinness beat.

If they be two, they are two so
As stiff twin compasses are two;
Thy soul, the fixed foot, makes no show
To move, but does, if th' other do.

And though it the center sit,
Yet when the other far doth roam,
It leans and hearkens after it,
And grow erect, as that comes home.

Such wilt thou be to me, Who must
Like th' other foot, obliquely run;
Thy firmness makes my circle just,
And makes me end where I begun.

37. I Loved a Lass, a Fair One

——G. Wither

I loved a lass, a fair one,
As fair as e'er was seen;
She was indeed a rare one,
Another Sheba Queen:
But, fool as then I was,
I thought she loved me too:
But now, alas! she's left me,
Falero, lero, loo!

Her hair like gold did glister,
Each eye was like a star,
She did surpass her sister,
Which pass'd all others far;
She would me honey call,
She'd——O she'd kiss me too!
But now, alas! she's left me,
Falero, lero, loo!

Many a merry meeting
My love and I have had;
She was my only sweeting,
She made my heart full glad;
The tears stood in her eyes
Like to the morning dew:
But now, alas! she's left me,
Falero, lero, loo!

Her cheeks were like the cherry,
Her skin was white as snow;
When she was blithe and merry
She angel-like did show;
Her waist exceeding small,
The fives did fit her shoe:
But now, alas! she's left me,
Falero, lero, loo!

In summer time or winter
She had her heart's desire;
I still did scorn to stint her
From sugar sack, or fire;
The world went round about,
No cares we ever knew:
But now, alas! she's left me,
Falero, lero, loo!

To maidens' vows and swearing
Henceforth no credit give;
You may give them the hearing
But never them believe;
They are as false as fair,
Unconstant, frail, untrue:
For mine, alas! hath left me,
Falero, lero, loo!

47. To His Coy Mistress

——A. Marvell

Had we but world enough, and time,
This coyness, Lady, were no crime.
We would sit down and think which way
To walk and pass our long love's day.
Thou by the Indian Ganges' side
Shouldst rubies find: I by the tide
Of Humber would complain. I would
Love you ten years before the Flood,
And you should, if you please, refuse
Till the conversion of the Jews.
My vegetable love should grow
Vaster than empires, and more slow;
An hundred years should go to praise
Thine eyes and on thy forehead gaze;
Two hundred to adore each breast;
But thirty thousand to the rest;
An age at least to every part,
And the last age should show your heart;
For, Lady, you deserve this state,
Nor would I love at lower rate.
But at my back I always hear
Time's winged chariot hurrying near;
And yonder all before us lie
Deserts of vast eternity.
Thy beauty shall no more be found,
Nor, in thy marble vault, shall sound
My echoing song: then worms shall try
That long preserved virginity,
And your quaint honour turn to dust,
And into ashes all my lust:
The grave's a fine and private place,
But none, I think, do there embrace.
Now therefore, while the youthful hue
Sits on thy skin like morning dew,
And while thy willing soul transpires
At every pore with instant fires,
Now let us sport us while we may,
And now, like amorous birds of prey,
Rather at once our time devour
Than languish in his slow-chapped power.
Let us roll all our strength and all
Our sweetness up into one ball,
And tear our pleasures with rough strife
Thorough the iron gates of life:
Thus, though we cannot make our sun
Stand still, yet we will make him run.

51. To Mary

——W. Cowper

The twentieth year is well-nigh past,
Since first our sky was overcast;
Ah would that this might be the last!
My Mary!

Thy spirits have a fainter flow,
I see thee daily weaker grow——
'Twas my distress that brought thee low,
My Mary!

Thy needles, once a shining store,
For my sake restless heretofore,
Now rust disus'd, and shine no more,
My Mary!

For though thou gladly wouldst fulfil
The same kind office for me still,
Thy sight now seconds not thy will,
My Mary!

But well thou play'dst the housewife's part,
And all thy threads with magic art
Have wound themselves about this heart,
My Mary!

Thy indistinct expressions seem
Like language utter'd in a dream;
Yet me they charm, whate'er the theme,
My Mary!

Thy silver locks, once auburn bright,
Are still more lovely in my sight
Than golden beams of orient light,
My Mary!

For could I view nor them nor thee,
What sight worth seeing could I see?
The sun would rise in vain for me,
My Mary!

Partakers of thy sad decline,
Thy hands their little force resign;
Yet, gently prest, press gently mine,
My Mary!

And then I feel that still I hold
A richer store ten thousandfold
Than misers fancy in their gold,
My Mary!

Such feebleness of limbs thou prov'st,
That now at every step thou mov'st
Upheld by two; yet still thou lov'st,
My Mary!

And still to love, though prest with ill,
In wintry age to feel no chill,
With me is to be lovely still,
My Mary!

But ah! by constant heed I know,
How oft the sadness that I show
Transforms thy smiles to looks of woe,
My Mary!

And should my future lot be cast
With much resemblance of the past,
Thy worn-out heart will break at last.
My Mary!

54. Sweet Afton

——R. Burns

Flow gently, sweet Afton! among thy green braes,
Flow gently, I'll sing thee a song in thy praise;
My Mary's asleep by thy murmuring stream,
Flow gently, sweet Afton, disturb not her dream.

Thou stock-dove whose echo resounds thro' the glen,
Ye wild whistling blackbirds in yon thorny den,
Thou green crested lapwing, thy screaming forbear,
I charge you, disturb not my slumbering Fair.

How lofty, sweet Afton, thy neighbouring hills,
Far marked with the courses of clear, winding rills;
There daily I wander as noon rises high,
My flocks and my Mary's sweet cot in my eye.

How pleasant thy banks and green valleys below,
Where, wild in the woodlands, the primroses blow;
There oft, as mild ev'ning weeps ove the lea,
The sweet-scented birk shades my Mary and me.

Thy crystal stream, Afton, how lovely it glides,
And winds by the cot where my Mary resides;
How wanton thy water her snowy feet lave,
As, gathering sweet flowerets, she stems thy clear wave.

Flow gently, sweet Afton, among thy green braes,
Flow gently, sweet river, the theme of my lays;
My Mary's asleep by thy murmuring stream,
Flow gently, sweet Afton, disturb not her dream.

59. The Solitary Reaper

——W. Wordsworth

Behold her, single in the field.
Yon solitary Highland Lass!
Reaping and singing by herself;
Stop here, or gently pass!
Alone she cuts and binds the grain,
And sings a melancholy strain;
O listen! for the Vale profound
Is overflowing with the sound.

No Nightingale did ever chaunt
More welcome notes to weary bands
Of travelers in some shady haunt,
Among Arabian sands;
A voice so thriling ne'er was heard
In springtime from he Cuckoo bird,
Breaking the silence of the seas
Among the farthest Hebrides.

Will no one tell me what she sings?——
Perhaps the plaintive numbers flow
For old, unhappy, far-off things,
And battles long ago;
Or is it some more humble lay,
Familiar matter of today?
Some natural sorrow, loss, or pain.
That has been, and may be again?

Whate'er the theme, the Maiden sang
As if her song could have no ending;
I saw her singing at her work,
And o'er the sickle bending——
I listened, motionless and still;
And, as I mounted up the hill,
The music in my heart I bore,
Long after it was heard no more.

62. An Hour with Thee

——Sir W. Scott

An hour with thee! When earliest day
Dapples with gold the eastern grey,
Oh, what can frame my mind to bear
The toil and turmoil, cark and care,
New griefs, which coming hours unfold,
And sad remembrance of the old?
One hour with thee.

One hour with thee! When burning June
Waves his red flag at pitch of noon;
What shall repay the faithful swain,
His labour on the sultry plain;
And, more than cave or sheltering bough,
Cool feverish blood and throbbing brow?
One hour with thee.

One hour with thee! When sun is set,
Oh, what can teach me to forget
The thankless labours of the day;
The hopes, the wishes, flung away;
The increasing wants, and lessening gains,
The master's pride, who scorns my pains?
One hour with thee.

64. Freedom and Love

——T. Campbell

How delicious is the winning
Of a kiss at love's beginning,
When two mutual hearts are sighing
For the knot there's no untying!

Yet remember, 'midst your wooing
Love has bliss, but Love has ruing;
Other smiles may make you fickle,
Tears for other charms may trickle.

Love he comes and Love he tarries.
Just as fate or fancy carries;
Longest stays, when sorest chidden;
Laughs and flies, when press'd and bidden.

Bind the sea to slumber stilly,
Bind its odour to the lily,
Bind the aspen ne'er to quiver,
Then bind Love to last for ever.

Love's a fire that needs renewal
Of fresh beauty for its fuel:
Love's wing moults when caged and captured,
Only free, he soars enlraptured.

Can you keep the bee from ranging,
Or the ringdove's neck from changing?
No! Nor fetter'd Love from dying
In the knot there's no untying.

67. When We Two Parted

——G. G. Byron

When we two parted
In silence and tears,
Half broken-hearted,
To sever for years,
Pale grew thy cheek and cold,
Colder thy kiss;
Truly that hour foretold
Sorrow to this!

The dew of the morning
Sunk chill on my brow;
It felt like the warning
Of what I feel now.
Thy vows are all broken,
And light is thy fame:
I hear thy name spoken
And share in its shame.

They name thee before me,
A knell to mine ear;
A shudder comes o'er me——
Why wert thou so dear?
They know not I knew thee
Who knew thee too well:
Long, long shall I rue thee
Too deeply to tell.

In secret we met:
In silence I grieve
That thy heart could forget,
Thy spirit deceive.
If I should meet thee
After long years,
How should I greet thee?——
With silence and tears.

71. First Love

——J. Clare

I ne'er was struck before that hour
With love so sudden and so sweet,
Her face it bloomed like a sweet flower
And stole my heart away complete.
My face turned pale as deadly pale.
My legs refused to walk away,
And when she looked, what could I ail?
My life and all seemed turned to clay.

And then my blood rushed to my face
And took my eyesight quite away,
The trees and bushes round the place
Seemed midnight at noonday.
I could not see a single thing,
Words from my eyes did start——
They spoke as chords do from the string,
And blood burnt round my heart.

Are flowers the winter's choice?
Is love's bed always snow?
She seemed to hear my silent voice,
Not love's appeals to know.
I never saw so sweet a face
As that I stood before.
My heart has left its dwelling-place
And can return no more.

79. The Splendor Falls

——A. Tennyson

The splendor falls on castle walls
And snowy summits old in story;
The long light shakes across the lakes,
And the wild cataract leaps in glory.
Blow, bugle, blow, set the wild echoes flying,
Blow, bugle; answer, echoes, dying, dying, dying.

O, hark, O, hear! how thin and clear,
And thinner, clearer, farther going!
O, sweet and far from cliff and scar,
The horns of Elfland faintly blowing!
Blow, let us hear the purple glens replying,
Blow, bugle; answer, echoes, dying, dying, dying.

O love they die in yon rich sky,
They faint on hill or field or river;
Our echoes roll from soul to soul,
And grow for ever and for ever.
Blow, bugle, blow, set the wild echoes flying,
And answer, echoes, answer, dying, dying, dying.

83. My Last Duchess-Ferrara

——R. Browning

Tht's my last Duchess painted on the wall,
Looking as if she were alive. I call
That piece a wonder, now: Fra Pandolf's hands
Worked busily a day, and there she stands.
Will't please you sit and look at her? I said
“Fra Pandolf?”by design, for never read
Strangers like you that pictured countenance,
The depth and passion of its earnest glance,
But to myself they turned (since none puts by
The curtain I have drawn for you, but I)
And seemed as they would ask me, if they durst.
How such a glance came there; so, not the first
Are you to turn and ask thus. Sir, 'twas not
Her husband's presence only, called that spot
Of joy into the Duchess' cheek: perhaps
Fra Pandolf chanced to say“Her mantle laps
Over my lady's wrist too much,”or“Paint
Must never hope to reproduce the faint
Half-flush that dies along her throat:”such stuff
Was courtesy, she thought, and cause enough
For calling up that spot of joy. She had
A heart——how shall I say? too soon made glad.
Too easily impressed; she liked whate'er
She looked on, and her looks went everywhere.
Sir, 'twas all one! My favor at her breast,
The drooping of the daylight in the West,
The bough of cherries some officious fool
Broke in the orchard for her, the white mule
She rode with round the terrace——all and each
Would draw from her alike the approving speech,
Or blush, at least. She thanked men——good! but thanked
Somehow——I know not how, as if she ranked
My gift of a nine-hundred-years-old name
With anybody's gift. Who'd stoop to blame
This sort of trifling? Even had you skil
In speech—— (which I have not)——to make your will
Quite clear to such an one, and say,“Just this
Or that in you disgusts me; here you miss,
Or there exceed the mark——”and if she let
Herself be lessoned so, nor plainly set
Her wits to yours, forsooth, and made excuse,
——E'en then would be some stooping; and I choose
Never to stoop. Oh sir, she smiled, no doubt,
Whene'er I passed her, but who passed without
Much the same smile? This grew; I gave command;
Then all smiles stopped together. There she stands
As if alive. Will't please you rise? We'll meet
The company below, then. I repeat,
The Count your master's known munificence
Is ample warrant that no just pretense
Of mine for dowry will be disallowed;
Though his fair daughter's self, as I avowed
At starting, is my object. Nay, we'll go
Together down, sir. Notice Neptune, though,
Taming a sea-horse, thought a rarity,
Which Claus of Innsbruck cast in bronze for me!

85. Remembrance

——E. Brontё

Cold in the earth——and the deep snow piled above thee,
Far, far removed, cold in the dreary grave!
Have I forgot, my only Love, to love thee,
Severed at last by Time's all-severing wave?

Now, when alone, do my thoughts no longer hover
Over the mountains, on that northern shore,
Resting their wings where heath and fern-leaves cover
Thy noble heart for ever, ever more?

Cold in the earth——and fifteen wild Decembers
From those brown hills, have melted into spring:
Faithful, indeed, is the spirit that remembers
After such years of change and suffering!

Sweet Love of youth, forgive, if l forget thee,
While the world's tide is bearing me along;
Other desires and other hopes beset me,
Hopes which obscure, but cannot do thee wrong!

No later light has lightened up my heaven,
No second morn has ever shone for me;
All my life's bliss from thy dear life was given,
All my life's bliss is in the grave with thee.

But when the days of golden dreams had perished,
And even Despair was powerless to destroy,
Then did I learn how existence could be cherished,
Strengthened, and fed, without the aid of joy.

Then did I check the tears of useless passion——
Weaned my young soul from yearning after thine;
Sternly denied its burning wish to hasten
Down to that tomb already more than mine.

And, even yet, I dare not let it languish,
Dare not indulge in memory's rapturous pain;
Once drinking deep of that divinest anguish,
How could I seek the empty world again?

93. Itylus

——A. C. Swinburne

Swallow, my sister, O sister swallow,
How can thine heart be full of the spring?
A thousand summers are over and dead.
What hast thou found in the spring to follow?
What hast thou found in thine heart to sing?
What wilt thou do when the summer is shed?

O swallow, sister, O fair swift swallow,
Why wilt thou fly after spring to the south,
The soft south whither thine heart is set?
Shall not the grief of the old time follow?
Shall not the song thereof cleave to thy mouth?
Hast thou forgotten ere I forget?

Sister, my sister, O fleet sweet swallow,
Thy way is long to the sun and the south;
But I, fulfilled of my heart's desire,
Shedding my song upon height, upon hollow,
From tawny body and sweet small mouth
Feed the heart of the night with fire.

I the nightingale all spring through,
O swallow, sister, O changing swallow,
All spring through till the spring be done,
Clothed with the light of the night on the dew,
Sing, while the hours and the wild birds follow,
Take flight and follow and find the sun.

Sister, my sister, O soft light swallow,
Though all things feast in the spring's guest-chamber,
How hast thou heart to be glad thereof yet?
For where thou fliest I shall not follow,
Till life forget and death remember,
Till thou remember and I forget.

Swallow, my sister, O singing swallow,
I know not how thou hast heart to sing.
Hast thou the heart? is it all passed over?
Thy lord the summer is good to follow,
And fair the feet of thy lover the spring;
But what wilt thou say to the spring thy lover?

O swallow, sister, O fleeting swallow,
My heart in me is a molten ember
And over my head the waves have met.
But thou wouldst tarry, or I would follow,
Could I forget or thou remember,
Couldst thou remember and I forget.

O sweet stray sister, O shifting swallow,
The heart's division divideth us.
Thy heart is light as a leaf of a tree;
But mine goes forth among sea-gulls hollow
To the place of the slaying of Itylus,
The feast of Daulis, the Thracian sea.

O swallow, sister, O rapid swallow,
I pray thee sing not a little space.
Are not the roofs and the lintels wet?
The woven web that was plain to follow,
The small slain body, the flower-like face,
Can I remember if thou forget?

O sister, sister, thy first-begotten!
The hands that cling and the feet that follow,
The voice of the child's blood crying yet,
Who hath remembered me? who hath forgotten?
Thou hast forgotten, O summer swallow,
But the world shall end when I forget.

97. The Ruined Maid

——T. Hardy

“O 'Melia, my dear, this does everything crown!
Who could have supposed I should meet you in Town?
And whence such fair garments, such prosperi-ty?”
“O didn't you know I'd been ruined?”said she.

“You left us in tatters, without shoes or socks,
Tired of digging potatoes, and spudding up docks;
And now you've gay bracelets and bright feathers three!”
“Yes: that's how we dress when we're ruined,”said she.

“At home in the barton’you said‘thee’and‘thou,’
And‘thik oon,’and‘theäs oon,’and‘t’other’; but now
Your talking quite fits ’ee for high compa-ny!”
“Some polish is gained with one's ruin”said she.

“Your hands were like paws then, your face blue and bleak
But now I'm bewitched by your delicate cheek,
And your little gloves fit as on any la-dy!”
“We never do work when we're ruined,”said she.

“You used to call home-life a hag-ridden dream,
And you'd sigh, and you'd sock; but at present you seem
To know not of megrims' or melancho-ly!”
“True. One's pretty lively when ruined,”said she.

“I wish I had feathers, a fine sweeping gown,
And a delicate face, and could strut about Town!”
“My dear-a raw coutry girl, such as you be,
Cannot quite expect that. You ain't ruined,”said she.

108. As I Walked Out One Evening

——W. H. Auden

As I walked out one evening,
Walking down Bristol Street,
The crowds upon the pavement
Were fields of harvest wheat.

And down by the brimming river
I heard a lover sing
Under an arch of the railway:
“Love has no ending.

“I'll love you, dear, I'll love you
Till China and Africa meet,
And the river jumps over the mountain
And the salmon sing in the street,

“I'll love you till the ocean
Is folded and hung up to dry
And the seven stars go squawking
Like geese about the sky.

“The years shall run like rabbits,
For in my arms I hold
The Flower of the Ages,
And the first love of the world.”

But all the clocks in the city
Began to whirr and chime:
“O let not Time deceive you,
You cannot conquer Time.

“In the burrows of the Nightmare
Where Justice naked is,
Time watches from the shadow
And coughs when you would kiss.

“In headaches and in worry
Vaguely life leaks away,
And Time will have his fancy
Tomrrow or Today.

“Into many a green valley
Drifts the appalling snow;
Time breaks the threaded dances
And the diver's brilliant bow.

“O plunge your hands in water,
Plunge them in up to the wrist;
Stare, stare in the basin
And wonder what you've missed.

“The glacier knocks in the cupboard,
The desert sighs in the bed,
And the crack in the teacup opens
A lane to the land of the dead.

“Where the beggars raffle the banknote
And the Giant is enchanting to Jack,
And the Lily-white Boy is a Roarer,
And Jill goes down on her back.

“O look, look in the mirror,
O look in your distress;
Life remains a blessing
Although you cannot bless.

“O stand, stand at the window
As the tears scald and start;
You shall love your crooked neighbor
With your crooked heart.”

It was late, late in the evening,
The lovers they were gone;
The clocks had ceased their chiming,
And the deep river ran on.

109. Before the Birth of One of Her Childen

——A. Bradstreet

All things within this fading world hath end,
Adversity doth still our joys attend;
No ties so strong, no friends so dear and sweet,
But with death's parting blow is sure to meet.
The sentence past is most irrevocable,
A common thing, yet oh, inevitable.
How soon, my Dear, death may my steps attend.
How soon't may be thy lot to lose thy friend,
We both are ignorant, yet love bids me.
These farewell lines to recommend to thee,
That when that knot's untied that made us one,
I may seem thine, who in effect am none.
And if I see not half my days that's due,
What nature would, God grant to yours and you;
The many faults that well you know I have
Let be interred in my oblivious grave;
If any worth or virtue were in me,
Let that live freshly in thy memory
And when thou feel'st no grief, as I no harms,
Yet love thy dead, who long lay in thine arms.
And when thy loss shall be repaid with gains
Look to my little babes, my dear remains.
And if thou love thyself, or loved'st me,
These O protect from step-dame's injury.
And if chance to thine eyes shall bring this verse,
With some sad sighs honour my absent hearse;
And kiss this paper for thy love's dear sake,
Who with salt tears this last farewell did take.

124. Elsa Wertman

——E. L. Masters

I was a peasant girl from Germany,
Blue-eyed, rosy, happy and strong.
And the first place I worked was at Thomas Greene's.
On a summer's day when she was away
He stole into the kitchen and took me
Right in his arms and kissed me on my throat,
I turning my head. Then neither of us
Seemed to know what happened.
And I cried for what would become of me.
And cried and cried as my secret began to show.
One day Mrs. Greene said she understood,
And would make no trouble for me,
And, being childless, would adopt it.
(He had given her a farm to be still.)
So she hid in the house and sent out rumors,
As if it were going to happen to her.
And all went well and the child was born——They were so kind to me.
Later I married Gus Wertman, and years passed.
But——at political rallies when sitters-by thought I was crying
At the eloquence of Hamilton Greene——
That was not it.
No! I wanted to say:
That's my son!
That's my son!

神童

她走进起居室，一只手里拿着的放乐谱的书包啪嗒啪嗒地撞着她穿着冬季厚长袜的腿，另一只手抱着教科书，让她觉得好累。她站了一会儿倾听着音乐室里传出的声音。那是轻轻的一串钢琴和弦和一把小提琴的调音声。这时候比尔德巴赫先生用他那厚重、喉音很重的声音朝她喊道：

“是你吗，小蜜蜂？”

她把无指手套揪下来时，看到自己的手指都因为这天早上练习赋格曲的动作而变形了。“是的，”她回答道，“是鹅呀。”

“应该说‘是我’，”那声音纠正道，“稍候片刻啊。”

她可以听到拉甫柯维奇先生在讲话——他的每一个字都是带着柔滑、让人听不清的嗡嗡声说出来的。这声音，她寻思，跟比尔德巴赫先生的相比，倒几乎更像是女人的呢。她安不下心，无法集中注意力，于是便摸了摸她的地理课本和Le Voyage de Monsieur Perichon[5]，接着又把它们放到桌子上来。她在沙发上坐下，开始把乐谱从书包里取出来。她再一次看了看自己的手——从关节那里延伸出去的微微颤抖的肌腱以及扭曲、污损的指甲盖底下那酸疼的指尖。看到这些，过去几个月以来开始折磨她的畏惧感变得更加强烈了。

她不出声地嘟哝了几个词儿来鼓励自己。好好上课——好好上课——就跟过去一样。她双唇闭上了，因为她听到了比尔德巴赫先生走在音乐室地板上那重重的脚步声和推开门时所发出的吱嘎声。

片刻之间，她有了一种奇特的感觉，似乎她一生这十五年里，大部分的时间都一直是在盯看，盯看寂静中——这寂静仅仅为小提琴一根弦压低的、不带感情的拨动声所打破——突出在门背后的那张脸和那对肩膀。那就是比尔德巴赫先生。她的老师，比尔德巴赫先生。宽边眼镜后面是一双锐利的眼睛；稀薄的浅色头发下面是一张窄窄的尖脸；厚嘴唇松松地合拢着，下唇因为有牙齿咬着显得是粉红色的而且还闪着光；两边太阳穴上分叉的血管很明显是在一蹦一跳，连在房间的那头都能看得清清楚楚。

“你是不是来得早了点？”他问道，朝壁炉架上的座钟瞥了一眼，那上面一个月以来都是指着十二点差五分。“约瑟夫在这儿。我们把一首小奏鸣曲过上一遍，这是他的一个熟人写的。”

“很好，”她说，尽量想挤出一个笑容，“我听着好了。”她几乎能见到自己的手指无力地沉入到一片模糊不清的钢琴黑白键之中。她只觉得非常疲倦——只觉得要是他再对着她看，那她的手真的会颤抖起来的。

他有点犹豫不决地站在房间中央。牙齿朝他那发亮、肿胀的嘴唇使劲咬下去。“饿了吧，小蜜蜂？”他问道，“这儿有些安娜烤的苹果派，还有牛奶。”

“我待会儿再吃好了，”她说，“谢谢了。”

“等你很好地上完一堂课之后——对不对？”他的笑容似乎还没抵达嘴角就已消隐不见了。

他身后的音乐室里发出了点什么声音，拉甫柯维奇推开另外的那半扇门，站在他的身边。

“是弗朗西斯吧？”他说，一边微笑着，“到现在曲子练得怎么样啦？”

拉甫柯维奇先生总让小姑娘有手足无措和自己身体过于臃肿的感觉，虽说他并没有这个意思。他是那么小的一个小个子，在不捏着小提琴的时候总显得无精打采。他的眉毛在他那张平板的犹太人的脸上弯得高高的，像是在提一个问题，可是那眼帘却倦怠与漫不经心地耷拉着。今天他似乎有点心神不宁。她看着他走进房间来，没有什么明显的目的，静止的手指捏住顶端贴有珠母的琴弓，让上面白色的马鬃慢慢地在一块白垩般的松香上蹭擦。今天他的眼睛成了两道闪闪发亮的缝隙，从领口垂下的那块亚麻布方巾使得底下的阴影变得更加深了。

“我猜你现在练得挺像样了吧。”拉甫柯维奇先生笑着说，虽然她还没有回答他方才的问题。

她把眼光对着比尔德巴赫先生。他身子转了开去。他那厚实的肩膀推得门大开着，让后半晌的斜阳穿过音乐室的窗户把一束束黄色的光线投射到灰尘很多的起居室里。透过老师的背影，她能看到那架低矮的长长的钢琴、窗子以及勃拉姆斯的胸像。

“不，”她对拉甫柯维奇说，“我练得很不好。”她那细细的手指在翻动乐谱的纸页。“我也不明白是怎么一回事。”她说，一面在注视着比尔德巴赫先生那俯伛着的肌肉发达的背，那背显得有点僵硬，说明他在谛听。

拉甫柯维奇先生微笑了，“我琢磨，有时候一个人——”

钢琴那儿响起了一个粗粝的和弦。“你看咱们是不是接着进行下去？”比尔德巴赫先生问道。

“马上就来，”拉甫柯维奇先生说，在朝门走去之前最后擦了一下松香。她能看见他从钢琴顶上拿起了他的小提琴。他看到了她的眼光，又把乐器松垂下来，“你看到海密的照片了吗？”

她的手指在书包硬硬的尖角处紧紧地握拢起来，“什么照片？”

“海密的一张照片在《音乐信使》上登出来了。杂志就在那边的桌子上。照片就登在封里顶端。”

小奏鸣曲开始响起来了。不好听却很简单。没什么内容却有它自己那种直起直落的风格。她拿到那本杂志翻了开来。

海密在这儿哪——在左上角。他托着小提琴，手指勾起在弦上正准备拨弦。他穿着他那条深色哔叽灯笼裤，膝下那儿的摁纽扣得整整齐齐的，上身穿的是一件卷领运动衫。这张照片拍得一点儿也不好。虽然是张侧影，但他眼睛却扭向拍摄者，手指的动作看上去像是会拨错弦似的。他好像因为身体要朝拍摄器材转过来而感到很别扭。他更瘦了——他的肚子现在不鼓出来了——不过六个月以来他的模样没起多大变化。

海密·伊斯雷尔斯基，才华横溢的年轻小提琴家，工作时摄于他老师位于河滨大道的音乐室。年轻的大师伊斯雷尔斯基即将庆祝其十五诞辰，已接受邀请演奏《贝多芬协奏曲》，合作的乐队是——

这天早上，在她从六点钟一直练到八点钟之后，她爸爸硬让她坐到餐桌上来和一家人共进早餐。她讨厌早餐：吃下去以后总让她觉得不舒服。她宁愿先啥也不吃，用给她买午餐的那两角钱买四条巧克力，在上课时慢慢地含着吃——用手绢作掩护把掰开的小块送进嘴里，银纸窸窣一响就赶紧一动不动。可是这天早晨她爸爸都把整只荷包蛋放到她碟子里了，她知道要是它破了——黏糊糊的蛋黄溢到了蛋白上——那她一定会哭出来的。而事情果然这样发生了。她现在又有了同样的感觉。她把杂志轻轻放回到桌子上，然后闭上眼睛。

音乐室里，那音乐好像是在死乞白赖却又笨嘴拙舌地想求得什么不该有的东西似的。过了一会儿，她的思想从海密、协奏曲和照片那里退了回来——又再次兜绕到音乐课这上头来。她在沙发上挪动位置，直到能很清楚地看到音乐室的内部——那两人在怎样演奏，在怎样看着钢琴前摆着的乐谱，很贪婪地非要把上面隐含的一切全都抽吸出来。

她忘不了几分钟前比尔德巴赫先生盯看她时脸上的那副表情。她覆盖在瘦骨嶙峋膝盖上的那两只手仍然在不自觉地随着赋格曲的旋律而扭动。她真的很疲倦了。她有一种盘旋着不断往下沉的感觉，每当她练习过头时，夜晚入睡前的那一刻便总会有这样的感觉。就像是疲倦得半做梦半醒着，在嗡嗡声中给带进了梦境的旋转空间里去。

一位神童[6]——一位神童，一位神童。那些音节会以德语的厚重发音，一个一个地滚出来，激荡着她的耳鼓，然后变成一串耳语。随着那一张张脸的盘旋，肿胀变形，缩小成灰色的水滴——那是比尔德巴赫先生、比尔德巴赫太太、海密、拉甫柯维奇先生的脸。伴随着喉音重重的“神童”那两个字，那些脸一遍又一遍地旋转。在一圈旋转着的脸中比尔德巴赫先生的脸变得越来越大，他的脸也最起劲——其他的那些脸都围绕着在转。

乐句在疯狂地奏响，吱吱嘎嘎，像是在拉锯。她练过的那些音符一个压在另一个的身上，就像一大把玻璃球从楼梯上滚下来。巴赫、德彪西、普罗科菲耶夫、勃拉姆斯——怪异地附和着她疲惫的身体和嗡嗡飞旋着的圆圈的节拍。

有时候——在练琴不超过三小时或是未在中学上课的时候——做的梦还不至于这么乱。音乐声会清清楚楚地在她的头脑里翱翔，急遽、清晰的记忆的小片段会重新出现——清晰得跟那幅稚气十足的图画《童真岁月》一样，那画是在她和海密联合举办音乐会后海密送给她的。

一位神童——一位神童。这是她十二岁时第一次上比尔德巴赫先生这儿来时，他这样称呼她的。年纪大一些的学生也都跟着用这个词儿。

不过他当面倒不用这个词儿叫她。“小蜜蜂——”（她有一个很普通的美国小名，不过他从来不用，除非是她犯了很大的错误。）“小蜜蜂，”他会这么说，“我知道这必定是很痛苦的。任何时候脑袋里都这么昏昏沉沉。可怜的小蜜蜂——”

比尔德巴赫的父亲以前是荷兰的一位小提琴家。他的母亲来自布拉格。他出生在美国，年轻的时候是在德国度过的。有多少次，她希望自己出生和长大的地方不是再平凡不过的辛辛那提[7]。“干酪”在德语里是怎么说的？比尔德巴赫先生，“我不明白你的意思”在德语里是怎么说的？

那是她来到音乐室的第一天。她凭记忆把整个的第二首《匈牙利狂想曲》[8]全弹了出来。这时候，房间里暮色朦胧。老师的脸从钢琴上俯伛下来。

“现在咱们重新开始，”那第一天他那么说，“这是——演奏音乐——不光是耍弄聪明。如果说一个十二岁女孩的手指一秒钟里能摁下多少个键盘——那是一点意思都没有的。”

他用粗粗短短的手指敲击自己宽阔的胸部与脑门，“这儿还有这儿。你年纪足够大了应该能明白这一点了。”他点燃一支香烟，轻轻地把第一口吐出的烟雾喷在她头顶的上空。“得用功——用功——再用功。咱们就从这些巴赫的创意曲和这些舒曼的小曲子开始。”他那双手又在动了——这一回是把灯的电线拉到她身后好让光打到乐谱上，“我让你看看我希望你怎么练习。现在你给我仔细听着。”

她在钢琴前几乎坐了三个小时，简直是累坏了。他那低沉的嗓音嗡嗡响着，仿佛在她的脑子里迷失了很长一段时间。她真想伸出手去触摸在乐段上点点戳戳的他那肌肉收紧的手指，想去摸摸那只闪闪发光的带状金戒指和他那壮实多毛的手背。

她星期二放学后与星期六下午上钢琴课。星期六上完课后，她经常留下来吃晚饭，住上一夜，第二天早上再坐电车回家。比尔德巴赫太太以自己那种安详、几乎有点憨傻的方式喜欢她。太太跟先生颇不相像。她很安静、肥胖，也很迟钝。只要她不是在厨房里烧大伙儿都爱吃的丰富菜肴，她好像什么时间都是躺在二楼他们的床上，或是读杂志，或是微笑着不知瞪向什么。他们在德国结婚时她是一位抒情歌曲的歌唱家。她现在不唱了（她说是嗓子出了毛病）。有时老师冲着厨房喊，让她听听某个学生弹得怎么样，她总是微笑着说“好”[9]，真的是非常“好”。弗朗西斯十三岁时，有一天她忽然想到，比尔德巴赫夫妇没有小孩嘛。这事儿似乎挺古怪的。有一回她跟比尔德巴赫太太一起待在厨房里，老师从音乐室跨着大步子走进来，让某个学生的恶劣表现气得不轻。他妻子一直站在炉火前用勺子搅动锅子里的汤，直到他伸出手去按在她的肩膀上。这时她把身子转了过来——仍然很平和地站着——让他用双臂围拢她，把他那张尖瘦的脸埋在她颈窝神经麻木的白皙肉褶子里。他们那样地站着一动不动。接着他的脸猛地往后一扳，肚子里的怒火就这样悄然熄灭，这以后他又回到音乐室去了。

在她师从比尔德巴赫先生再没有时间和中学同学来往以后，海密便成了跟她年龄相仿的唯一朋友。他是拉甫柯维奇先生的学生，在她上课的晚上会跟着老师一起到比尔德巴赫先生这儿来。他们会听两位老师演奏。他们自己也常常参加到室内乐合奏中来——奏莫扎特或是布洛克[10]的奏鸣曲。

一位神童——一位神童。

海密是一位神童。他和她都是，当时都是。

海密从四岁起就开始拉琴了。他不必去学校上学。拉甫柯维奇的弟弟是个跛子，他当老师，在下午教海密地理、欧洲历史和法语动词变位。十三岁时海密在技巧上就已经能与辛辛那提任何一位小提琴家相匹敌了——大家都这么说。不过拉小提琴一定比弹钢琴容易一些。她知道必定是这样的。

海密身上似乎总有一股灯芯绒裤子和他所吃的东西还有松香的气味。生活中有一半的时候，他的手腕处那一圈总是脏的，从他运动衫底下露出来的衬衫袖口也总是又脏又破。他拉琴时她老是看他的手——只有在关节处才是瘦瘦的，剪得短短的指甲四周挤满了一小块一小块的硬肉，拉弓时手腕上还会显露出婴儿般的肉褶皱纹。

在睡梦中和她清醒时一样，她只能朦朦胧胧地记得音乐会的情景。直到好几个月之后，她才理会到对她来说这次音乐会是不成功的。的确，报纸上对海密的称赞超过了对她的称赞。可是他的身材比她矮得多呀。他们在舞台上并排站立时他只能够到她的肩膀。这在大家的心理上就不一样，她知道的。另外，他们合奏的那支奏鸣曲也有关系。那首布洛克的作品。

“不，不——我觉得那不合适，”在提到让布洛克的曲子作压轴节目时比尔德巴赫先生说，“不如用约翰·鲍威尔[11]的那首——《弗吉尼亚奏鸣曲》。”

她当时不理解，她、拉甫柯维奇和海密同样愿意选择布洛克的曲子，但比尔德巴赫先生最后还是让步了。后来，评论文章说她缺乏演奏这种类型音乐的气质，说她的演奏单薄和缺乏感情，这时，她觉得自己上当了。

“那首老而又老的东西，”比尔德巴赫先生说，一边把甩得啪啪响的报纸塞给她，“你弹并不合适，小蜜蜂。这样就把一切都送给了海密们、鬼才们[12]以及冥冥苍天。”

一位神童。不管报纸上是怎么说的，反正老师过去是这么称呼自己的。

为什么海密在音乐会上的表现会比她好出这么多呢？在学校里，有时，在她理应集中精力看一个同学在黑板上演算一道几何题时，这个问题会像把刀子似的扭绞着她的心。她躺在床上会为了它而受到熬煎，甚至在她本该把思想集中在钢琴上的时候，她也会去想那件事。这还不仅仅是选了布洛克的曲子和她不是犹太人的问题——不完全是。也不是因为海密不用上学和那么早就开始练琴的问题。那么是——

有一回她认为她知道了。

“那就弹幻想曲与赋格吧。”一年前的一个晚上，比尔德巴赫提出这样的建议——这以前，他和拉甫柯维奇先生一起翻阅了许多乐谱。

她弹奏时，觉得巴赫的这首曲子对她来说挺合适的。她用眼角瞟了一下，能看到比尔德巴赫先生脸上有一种安详、愉悦的表情，看到当乐句精彩处得以顺利通过时他的双手也戏剧性地从椅子扶手上升起与落下，表示出了满意的意思。曲子弹完后，她从钢琴旁站立起来，把口水咽下去，以松开仿佛是乐曲对她咽喉与胸口处所做的挤压。可是——

“弗朗西斯——”拉甫柯维奇先生这时突然说道，盯看着她，薄薄的嘴唇扭曲着，他那细巧的眼帘几乎完全遮挡住了眼睛，“你知道巴赫有多少个孩子吗？”

她完全弄糊涂了，把身子转过来对着他，“好些个吧。二十多个吧。”

“那么，显然——”他那苍白的脸上浮现出浅笑的淡淡印痕。“他便不可能是那么冷冰冰的了——对吧。”

比尔德巴赫先生不大高兴，他那喉音重得很神气的德语词里带上了些发小孩子脾气的腔调。拉甫柯维奇扬起了他的眉头。她自然很容易觉察出他的心思，但是她让自己显出一脸茫然与幼稚的表情，并不是在装假，而是因为这正是比尔德巴赫先生希望她显现出来的表情。

不过这样的事情无关紧要。至少是没有多大关系，因为她是会长大的。比尔德巴赫先生明白这一点，连拉甫柯维奇先生那么说也并不是有意的。

在那些梦里，比尔德巴赫先生的脸显现出来，一点点缩小，占据着旋转的圈子的中心。两片嘴唇软软地嘟起着，太阳穴处的血管连续不断地跳动着。

可是有时候，在她入睡之前，那样清晰的记忆也会出现。例如，她把袜子脚跟处的一个破洞往底下拉拉，好让它藏在鞋子里。“小蜜蜂，小蜜蜂！”老师边说边把比尔德巴赫太太放针线活的筐子拿进来，告诉她应该怎么补，千万别挤缩成为一团鼓鼓囊囊的东西。

现在到了她从初中毕业的时候了。

“那么你穿什么衣服呢？”星期天早晨吃饭时她正告诉他们她的同学们在怎样练习步入大礼堂，比尔德巴赫太太插嘴问道。

“我表姐去年穿过的一件晚礼服呀。”

“啊——小蜜蜂！”比尔德巴赫先生说，一边将捧在粗重双手里温热的咖啡杯拨转过来，抬起头用边上全是皱纹的带着笑意的眼睛看着她，“我敢说我知道小蜜蜂需要的是什么——”

他一定要按自己的意思办。不管她怎么解释自己真的什么都不需要，他还是不相信。

“就这样干吧，安娜。”他说，一边把餐巾往桌子当中推，踩着碎步走到房间的另一端，扭动着大腿，厚边框眼镜后面的那对眼球在翻转。

下一个星期六的下午，她上完课之后，他带她去到闹市区的百货商店。女店员把一匹匹料子打开，他粗粗的手指在薄如蝉翼的罗纱和嗖嗖发响的塔夫绸上滑过。他歪斜着脑袋，把各种颜色的料子举到她脸旁去比比，终于挑中了粉红色。皮鞋，他也没有忘记。最让他中意的是一双小羊皮的平底轻便鞋。在她看来这有点儿像是老太太的鞋子，鞋背上的红十字花襻又给人一种慈善施舍的感觉。不过这实际上也没有多大关系。当比尔德巴赫太太开始裁剪长裙并且用别针在她身上做样子时，他中断授课站在一边，建议臀部和颈部周围要添加一些褶子，肩部上得有一只别致的玫瑰花结。钢琴课呢，那一个阶段也进行得非常顺利。新衣服呀、毕业典礼呀，这样的事情再多点也是不会影响正课的。

至关紧要的还是按要求把音乐弹奏好，把自己身上肯定存在的素质发掘出来，练习，练习，弹奏得使比尔德巴赫先生脸上的那种永不餍足的表情可以少一些。得让自己的音乐里拥有一些迈拉·赫斯和耶胡蒂·梅纽因[13]的气质——哪怕是海密那样的也好呀！可是四个月前她这儿开始出现了什么样的情况呢？她手底下蹦出来的一个个声音都是油腻腻的，又死又木。是青春期反应吧，她想。有些孩子一开始很有希望——可是练着练着，就像她一样，会为了不丁点儿大的事情哭起来，试着把事情理顺——以合乎自己的心意呢——人却变得心力交瘁——于是奇怪的情况开始出现了。不过这绝对不能是她！她跟海密是一样的。她必须得是这样。她——

那种禀赋过去肯定是存在的。你不会莫名其妙把它丢失的吧。一位神童……一位神童……他过去是这么说她的，还用很自信、很深沉的德国喉音。在梦中，那喉音就比平时更深沉更自信了。当时，他那张脸俯伛在她的头上，期待的乐句加入到嗡嗡响的喉音里，盘旋着一遍又一遍发出这样的声音——一位神童、一位神童……这个下午比尔德巴赫先生并未像平时那样把拉甫柯维奇先生送到门口。他一动不动地坐在钢琴前，轻轻摁单独的一个乐音。弗朗西斯一边听着，一边看着小提琴老师把围巾往苍白的喉咙上缠绕。

“海密那幅照片挺好的，”她说，一边拿起她的乐谱，“两个月之前我收到他的一封信——告诉我他听了施纳贝尔和胡贝尔曼[14]的演出以及卡内基音乐厅的情况，还谈到在俄罗斯茶室吃到什么东西呢。”

为了拖延片刻再回到音乐室，她一直等到拉甫柯维奇先生真的要走了，又在他开门时伫候在他的身后。外面霜冻的冷空气直逼室内。天一点点黑下来了，空中弥漫着冬天傍晚时分的那种昏黄的光线。当支在枢纽上的门转回来时，房屋似乎比她所熟稔的更黑暗也更阒寂了。

她回到音乐室时，比尔德巴赫先生从钢琴旁站起来，默不作声地瞧着她在琴键前坐下。

“嗯，小蜜蜂，”他说，“今天下午咱们要从头开始。从零开始。把前几个月的事全都忘了。”

他那模样仿佛是想在一部电影里扮演一个角色似的。他那厚实的身体以脚尖与脚跟为支点前后晃动，双手对搓，甚至还泛出了一个心满意足、很电影格式的笑容。但突然之间他把这温文尔雅的态度全收敛起了。他那厚重的肩膀垂了下来，他开始翻动她带来的那叠乐谱。“巴赫吗——不，不，还不到时候，”他喃喃自语道，“贝多芬呢？对了，就弹作品第二十六号《变奏奏鸣曲》吧。”

钢琴的一个个键把她缠住了——那些僵僵的、白森森的、死样活气的琴键。

“等一等。”他说。他站在钢琴的凹弯部位，肘部支在琴上，眼睛看着她，“今天我对你有些要求。现在，这首奏鸣曲——这是你练琴以来所弹的第一首贝多芬奏鸣曲。每一个音符都在你的能力之内——技术上说是这样——除了乐谱你没有别的依据。此刻你有的仅仅是乐谱。这是你唯一必须考虑的。”

他翻动她的乐谱直到找到了那一页。接着他把教师坐的椅子拖到房间中央，让它转了个身，在上面落了座，两条腿跨出在椅背的前面。

她知道，不知出于什么原因，他采取这种姿势一般总对她的演奏产生良好的效果。不过今天她觉得自己会用眼角去瞟他，因而受到干扰。他的背僵僵地斜翘着，他的腿看得出在紧绷着。他面前那本大厚书似乎在椅背上很容易会失去平衡。“咱们现在开始吧。”他说，眼光很专横地朝她这个方向投射过来。

她双手在琴键上空摸索了片刻，接着便按了下去。最初的几个音符声音太大，接下去的乐句却是干巴巴的。

他的手警告地从乐谱上举了起来，“等等！先想一想你在弹的是什么曲子。开首处标的指示词是什么？”

“呃——行板。”

“很好。那就别拖拖拉拉地弹成柔板。而且要深深地摁每一个键。别那样浅浅地碰一下就算。那可是一种优美、深沉的行板——”

她又试了一下。她的手似乎跟她心中的音乐合不到一块儿。

“听我说，”他打断了她，“在全部变奏曲里起主导作用的是哪一段？”

“是挽歌。”她回答道。

“那就得对它有所准备。这是一段行板——不过可不是你方才弹出的那种沙龙货色。开始时很轻，是轻奏，要在琶音即将出现之前让它一点点响起来。要弹得很温暖很有戏剧性。可是到这儿呢——在标了‘柔和地’之处便得让对立的主题唱响。这你都是知道的。我们以前都学过这方面的一切的。现在弹吧。就像贝多芬写下时那样感觉它。去感受那种悲剧性和压抑感。”

她无法抑制自己不去看他的那双手。它们似乎只是暂时性地停留在那本乐谱上，一等她开始就会举起来让她停止，他戒指的闪闪金光会喝令她停下。“比尔德巴赫先生——如果我——如果你让我弹完第一段变奏，当中不打断我，没准我可以弹得好一些的。”

“我不会打断你的。”他说。

她那张苍白的脸在琴键前凑得过于近了。她弹完了第一段，在他点头表示同意之后开始弹第二段。倒没有出现什么差错让她卡壳弹不下去，不过还没等她把感受到的情绪输进去，乐句便自行在她手指底下出现了。

她弹完后，老师从乐谱上抬起眼来，丝毫不客气地开始说了：“我几乎没听到右手部的那些很和谐的补白音嘛。另外，顺便说一下，这个部分照说是应该加大力度的，以发展从第一部分那里得到的预示内涵。不过，你就接着往下弹吧。”

她想一开始先以受压抑的怨恨开始，然后进入到深沉、膨胀的忧伤中去。她的心告诉她应该这样做。可是她那双手却像软乎乎的通心粉似的粘在琴键上，她无法想象这曲子竟会是这样的。

当最后一个音符停止颤动后，他阖上乐谱，不慌不忙地离开椅子站立起来。他在把下颚往左右移动——从他张开的嘴唇里她能瞥见通往他咽喉深处的粉红色的健康通道和那两排结实的被烟熏黄的牙齿。他把那份贝多芬乐谱小心翼翼地放在她别的那些乐谱的顶端，双肘再一次支在光滑的黑色琴盖上。“不行。”他简单地说了一句，一边对着她看。

她的嘴唇开始颤动了，“我没有办法。我——”

突然之间，他强使自己的嘴唇扭出一个笑容。“听我说，小蜜蜂，”他开始用一种新的、做作的声音说道，“你仍然在弹那首《快乐的铁匠》吧，是不是啊？我告诉过你不要丢生，得列入常备演奏节目。”

“是的，”她说，“我是时不时都会复习的。”

他的声调是他用来对孩子说话的那一种，“那是咱们一块儿工作后最早弹的曲子之一——记得吧。你原来弹得那么使劲儿——就好像自己真的是铁匠的女儿似的。你看，小蜜蜂，我是那么了解你——就跟你是我自己的女儿一样。我了解你有什么样的能力——我听到过你把那么多曲子弹得那么美。你过去总是——”

他在慌乱中停了下来，从快被他捏烂的烟蒂里吸了口烟。烟从他粉红色的嘴唇里懒洋洋地飘出来，像灰雾似的缭绕在她平直的头发和幼儿般光滑的前额的四周。

“要把它弹得欢快而单纯。”他说，一边把她身后的灯拧亮，并且从钢琴边上退了开去。

有几分钟，他就站在灯光打出的明亮圈子里。接着，他毛毛草草地往地板上蹲下去，“还得生气勃勃哟。”

她的眼睛无法不一个劲儿地盯看他，看着他用一只脚蹲着，另一只脚伸直在前面以求平衡，他结实的大腿肌肉在裤料底下紧紧地绷着，背挺得笔直，双肘使劲地支撑在膝盖上。“你只想当前的事，”他又用肉鼓鼓的双手做出强调的意思，“集中想那个铁匠——整天在太阳底下干活。工作很单纯也不受到干扰。”

她无法低下头去看钢琴。光线使他伸出的手背上面的纤毛毕露，使他的镜片闪闪发光。

“把这所有的一切都表现出来，”他催促道，“开始吧！”

她只觉得自己的骨髓已全被抽空，身上连一滴血都没有剩下。怦怦跳了一个下午的心脏忽然之间竟像是停止跳动了。她看到那颗心变灰而且变得软疲疲的，边缘处都抽缩了，跟只牡蛎似的。

他的脸似乎在她面前的空间里抖动，随着太阳穴上血管的跳动那张脸逼得更近了。她要退缩，只得低头去看钢琴。她的双唇像果冻似的抖动着，一阵无声的眼泪涌上来使得白色的琴键变得模糊，成了一条水汪汪的线。“我做不到，”她悄声地说，“我不知道为什么，可就是做不到——再也没法做到了。”

他绷紧的身体松懈了下来，他用手扶着腰，使自己站起来。她抱起自己的乐谱，匆匆地从他身边走出来。

她的大衣。还有无指手套和橡胶套鞋。教科书和她生日那天他送的书包。把属于她的东西都从这个静静的房间拿走。而且要快——赶在他张口说话之前。

在她穿过门厅时她看到的又是他的那双手——从他身上伸出来，他的身子懒洋洋、毫无目的地靠在音乐室的门上。门关得太用力了一些。她拖着书和书包跌跌撞撞地走下石头台阶，却转错了方向，她急匆匆地顺着街往下走，在那里，喧闹声、自行车、别的孩子在做的游戏，全都乱成了一团。

赛马骑师

赛马骑师来到餐厅门口，过了一会儿又往边上挪了挪，接着便背靠墙，一动不动地站着。房间里人很挤，因为这是赛马季的第三天，城里所有的旅馆都人满为患。在餐厅里，八月玫瑰的花束把花瓣散落在白色亚麻桌布上，从隔壁的酒吧间涌来一波波热烘烘、醉气冲天的喧闹声。赛马骑师背靠墙等着，一边用眯紧的、眼皮像绉纱的眼睛仔细打量房间。他的眼光上上下下搜索，终于发现在他对角线角落里的一张桌子，那里坐着三个人。在赛马骑师用眼睛找人的时候，他抬起下巴，把头往后边一侧仰去，他那侏儒般的身体变得僵直了，双手也发僵了，以至于手指像爪子似的朝里弯曲。他僵僵地靠在餐厅墙上，就这样地守望着和等候着。

那天晚上他穿的是一套中国绿绸子衣服，剪裁合身，大小跟儿童穿的套服简直没什么差别。衬衫是黄色的，领带上有一个个多种粉色的斜道。他没戴帽子，湿湿的头发往前梳，很不自然地贴在了脑门上。他板着脸，那张脸看不出有多大年纪，反正是灰灰的。他瘪陷的太阳穴发暗，嘴巴扭出了一种冷笑的神情。过了一会儿，他知道他打量着的那三个人里有一个看到他了。不过骑师没跟那人点头，他仅仅是把下巴抬得更高一些，把僵直的手的大拇指勾在外衣兜里。

角落里的那三个人，一个是教练员，一个是管下赌注的经纪人，剩下的那个是阔佬。教练员叫西尔维斯特，是个大个儿，骨架松松垮垮的，酒糟鼻，蓝眼珠，眼神迟缓。经纪人叫西蒙斯。那阔佬是一匹叫塞尔策的赛马的主人，那天下午骑师骑的正是这匹马。那三个人喝兑苏打的威士忌，一个穿白色外衣的侍者刚上完晚餐的头一道菜。

最先看见骑师的是西尔维斯特。他赶紧把目光移开，放下威士忌酒杯，神经兮兮地用大拇指揉揉他那红鼻子的尖端。“是比切·巴洛，”他说，“站在房间那头。一个劲儿地对着我们瞅呢。”

“哦，那骑师呀，”阔佬说了。他是面对墙坐的，他把脑袋转过来一半看看后面，“请他过来好了。”

“天哪，别呀。”西尔维斯特说。

“他疯了。”西蒙斯说。经纪人的声音平平板板的，没有曲折起伏。他有一张天生是赌徒的脸，经过精心调整，把表情置于恐惧与贪欲永恒相持的状态之中。

“全都因为在迈阿密出的那件事。”西蒙斯说。

“什么事儿？”阔佬问。

西尔维斯特的眼光越过房间朝骑师瞥了一眼，用红红的、肉感的舌头舔了舔嘴角。“一件意外事故。一个小伙子在跑道上受了伤，摔断了一条腿和胯骨。他是比切的铁哥们儿，是个爱尔兰小伙儿。骑术也不赖。”他说。

“那真倒霉。”阔佬说。

“可不是吗。他们特别要好，”西尔维斯特说，“在比切的旅馆房间里总能见到他。他们不是打扑克便是一块儿躺在地板上读体育版。”

“是啊，那样的事儿是常有的。”那阔佬说。

西蒙斯用刀子去切他的牛排。他把叉子尖垂直对着碟子，一面小心翼翼地用刀面把蘑菇拨成一堆。“他疯了，”他重复地说，“他让我起鸡皮疙瘩。”

餐厅所有的桌子都坐满了。房间中央宴会长桌前有一伙人在开酒会，八月的青白色飞蛾想方设法飞了进来，在明亮的烛火四周扑舞。两个年轻姑娘穿着长裤和印有校名的运动夹克，手挽着手穿过房间走进酒吧。从外面大街上传来节日喧腾的回声。

“他们说，八月的萨拉托加[15]是全世界人均最富有的地方。”西尔维斯特把脸转向阔佬，“你看怎么样？”

“我可说不上来。”阔佬说，“非常有可能吧。”

西蒙斯很细致地用食指尖揩拭他那张油腻腻的嘴巴，“好莱坞怎么样？还有华尔街呢——”

“等等，”西尔维斯特说，“他决定上这边来了。”

骑师已经离开墙，正走近在角落里的那张餐桌。他装模作样地跨着僵僵的步子，每走一步大腿都要伸出去划半个圆圈，脚后跟踩下来时则是对地板上的红丝绒地毯狠咬上一口。在半路上他蹭到宴会桌边一位穿白缎子礼服的胖夫人的肘弯，他退后一步，显得过于有礼貌地鞠了一躬，眼睛几乎是全闭上的。他穿过房间后便拉过一把椅子，在桌子角边上坐了下来，夹在西尔维斯特和阔佬之间，既不点头也不打招呼，那张板着的灰脸连一点儿变化都没有。

“吃过晚饭啦？”西尔维斯特问道。

“有些人也许会这样说。”骑师的声音高亢、刻薄，也很清晰。

西尔维斯特把刀与叉小心翼翼地放在了自己的盘子上。阔佬挪动了一下位置，让自己在椅子上的身体朝侧边转过去一些，双腿交叉了起来。他穿的是斜纹布马裤和不上鞋油的皮靴，上身是一件又脏又旧的棕色夹克——这可是赛马季里他的制服，虽然从来没人见到他曾经骑在马背上。西蒙还是继续闷头吃他的晚餐。

“想喝杯矿泉水吗？”西尔维斯特问，“还是来点儿别的什么？”

骑师没有回答。他从口袋里掏出一只金烟盒，啪地打开。里面有几支香烟和一把小小的金折刀。他用刀把一支烟切成两半。他点燃烟后，举起手来叫住一个正从桌边走过的侍者，“一杯肯塔基的波旁威士忌，劳驾。”

“嗨，听我说，孩子。”西尔维斯特说。

“别叫我孩子。”

“好好儿的。你知道你做什么都得按规矩嘛。”

骑师把左边的嘴角一扭，做出一副很生硬的不屑的表情。他眼睛垂下来扫了一眼摊开在桌子上的饭菜，但旋即又重新抬起眼光。在阔佬面前的是一份奶汁烤鱼，配菜有欧芹。西尔维斯特要的是本笃式炒蛋，配菜有芦笋、黄油拌鲜玉米，外带一小碟潮滋滋的黑橄榄。骑师身前桌子角上有一盘炸薯条。他再没有朝食物瞧上一眼，而是让自己那双憔悴的眼睛老是盯着摆在桌子中央的那束开得正盛的浅紫色玫瑰。“我想你们是不会记得一个叫麦圭尔的人的吧。”他说。

“嗨，听我说。”西尔维斯特说。

侍者端来了威士忌，骑师坐着，用他那双结实、起老茧的小手抚弄着那只玻璃杯。他手腕上戴着条金手链，在桌子边上碰出轻轻的丁丁声。在把杯子在手掌里转了几圈后，骑师一仰脖，两口就把威士忌吞了下去。他砰地放下杯子。“不，我猜你们的记性不会那么好，是不会记得这么久远、这么琐碎的事儿的。”他说。

“那是自然，比切，”西尔维斯特回答道，“你为什么有这样的反应？今儿个听到那孩子的什么消息了吗？”

“我收到一封信，”骑师说，“咱们方才扯到的那位，星期三拆了石膏。一条腿比另外的一条短了两英寸。整个事情就是这样。”

西尔维斯特用舌头发出了嗒嗒声，摇了摇头，“我很理解你的感情。”

“你理解？”骑师在看着桌子上的饭菜。他的眼光从奶汁烤鱼转移到玉米，最后又落在了那盘炸薯条上。他的脸绷得紧紧的，重新迅速地把眼光抬起来。有一朵玫瑰败落了，他捡起一片花瓣，用大拇指和食指将它碾烂，放进嘴里。

“唉，这类的事儿总断不了会出现的。”阔佬说。

教练和经纪人都吃完了，但是他们盘子前面的盛菜碟子里还有些吃剩的东西。阔佬把油腻腻的手指浸进他的水杯，用餐巾将手指擦干净。

“那么，”骑师说，“有谁要我把什么菜传过去吗？或者是你们还想再要添点儿什么。再来一大块牛排，先生们，或是——”

“拜托了，”西尔维斯特说，“得好好儿过日子嘛。你干吗不上楼去呢？”

“是啊，我干吗不去呢？”骑师说。

他那拘谨的声音升高了一个调，里面还带上些歇斯底里的尖厉呜咽。

“我干吗不上楼，回到我该死的房间，转上几圈，写上几封信，上床睡觉，像个好孩子那样呢？为什么我不仅仅——”他把坐着的椅子往后一推，站了起来。“哦，去，”他说，“去你们的。我想去喝上一杯。”

“我只能说你这是在自寻末路，”西尔维斯特说，“你明白这会对你起什么作用。你知道得很清楚的嘛。”

骑师穿过餐厅，进入酒吧间。他要了一杯曼哈顿，西尔维斯特看到他脚后跟靠得紧紧地站着，身子笔挺，像只玩具锡兵，小手指翘起在鸡尾酒杯的外缘，慢慢地啜饮杯中之物。

“他疯了，”西蒙斯说。“正如我方才说的那样。”

西尔维斯特把脸转向阔佬，“如果他吃下去一块羊排，过一个钟点你还能在他肚子上看出这块肉的形状。他再也没法子通过出汗把东西消化掉了。他的重量是一百一十二磅半。我们离开迈阿密后他又重了三磅。”

“骑师是不应该喝酒的。”阔佬说。

“食物再不能像以前那样满足他了，他没法通过出汗把它们消化掉。如果他吃下去一块羊排，你可以看到它从他肚子里往外戳，它就是下不去。”

骑师喝完了他的曼哈顿。他吞下了酒，又用大拇指捻碎杯子底上的那颗樱桃，然后把杯子从身边推开。两个穿着印有校名的夹克的姑娘站在他的左边，在酒吧台的另一端，有两个贩票的黄牛党在争论世界上哪座山峰最高。每一个人都有他的伙伴，那天晚上再没有另外一个人是单独喝酒的。骑师拿出一张崭新的五十元大钞付账，找回的钱连数都不数。

他走回到餐厅，来到三个人坐着的桌子旁边，不过他没有坐下。“不，我不会那么主观，认定你们的记性覆盖面那么大，什么全都记得。”他说。他个子那么小，以至于桌面都几乎跟他的腰带一般儿高，他用那双瘦而结实的手去抓桌角时连腰都不用弯。“不，你们在餐厅里狼吞虎咽，忙不过来。你们未免太——”

“说实在的，”西尔维斯特恳求地说，“你必须表现得像样一些呀。”

“像样！像样！”骑师灰扑扑的脸在颤抖，接着他又强装出一副邪恶、冰冷的笑容。他晃动桌子，使得盘碟发出了格拉格拉声，一时之间看来他真要把桌子掀了呢。但突然他停下了。他的手朝靠他最近的盘子伸过去，不慌不忙地抓起几根炸薯条，塞进嘴里。他慢慢地嚼着，接着他扭过头去，把一嘴纸浆般的东西啐到了光滑的红地毯上。“浪荡公子。”他说，他的声音又细又碎。他把这几个字搁在嘴里好好回味，仿佛它很有滋味，是件能满足他的要求的什么东西似的。“你们这些浪荡公子哥儿。”他又说了一遍，接着便转过身子，跨着僵僵的步子，大摇大摆地走出餐厅。

西尔维斯特把一只松松垮垮的方肩膀耸了耸。阔佬把泼在桌布上的水抹擦了几下，他们没有说话，一直等到侍者过来清理桌子。

席林斯基夫人与芬兰国王

赖德学院音乐系能聘到席林斯基夫人全靠系头儿布洛克先生办事有方。学院认为自己还是够幸运的，不管作为一位作曲家还是作为一位教师，夫人都是声名远扬。布洛克先生还真卖力气，亲自帮席林斯基夫人寻摸到一处带花园的小楼，那地方上学院很近便，而且就在他自己住的公寓的隔壁。

在席林斯基夫人来到之前，整个西桥没有一个人认识她。布洛克先生在音乐刊物上见到过她的照片，有一回还就布克斯特胡德[16]手稿真实性的问题与她通过信。另外，在她来音乐系工作的事情定下来之后，他们之间就实际问题交换过几封电报与书信。她的书法清晰工整，信里唯一异乎寻常之处，是偶尔会不经意地提到布洛克先生全无所知的一些人与事，比如“里斯本的那只黄猫”或是“可怜的海因利希”。这样的疏忽，布洛克寻思，必定是与她和家人想尽方法离开欧洲时所遇到的种种混乱有关吧。

布洛克先生是个性格比较温和的人，多年讲授莫扎特小步舞曲，解释何为减七度何为小三和弦，已经赋予他一种事事留意的职业性的耐心。大多数的事情，他都独自悄悄处理掉。他厌恶学院式的废话和各式各样的委员会。多年前，音乐系决定同仁们集体去萨尔茨堡[17]过暑假，布洛克先生在最后一刻溜开独自一人去了秘鲁。他自己也是有几样怪癖的，所以很能容忍别人的特立独行。的确，他还挺珍爱那些可笑可乐的人与事的呢。在面临某些严肃与僵持的局面时，他时常会在心里觉得痒痒的却又不敢笑，这就使得他那张温顺的长脸板得更僵了，也使得他的灰眼睛变得更亮了。

秋季开学前的一个星期，布洛克先生上西桥火车站去迎接席林斯基夫人。他一下子就认出她来了。她是个高高的、身板很直的妇人，脸色苍白，有些憔悴。她的眼睛暗淡无光，那头乱蓬蓬的黑发从额上直直地往后梳。那双大手倒是长得挺细巧，只是脏兮兮的。总的来说，她身上有某种高贵、捉摸不定的气质，这使布洛克先生往后退了片刻，不安地站立着，无意间解开了自己的衬衫袖扣。尽管她穿的衣服不伦不类——下面是条黑色长裙，上面是件破旧的皮夹克——她却朦朦胧胧给人一种优雅的感觉。和席林斯基夫人在一起的是三个孩子，六岁到十岁的男孩，全都是金黄头发，黑眼睛，十分漂亮。另外还有一位妇女，是个老太太，后来才知道这是他们的芬兰女佣。

这就是他在车站见到的那群人。他们唯一的行李是两大纸箱手稿，其他的随身物品在斯普林菲尔德换车时留在车站上忘记拿了。这样的事是会发生在任何一个人身上的。在布洛克先生把他们全塞进一辆出租汽车时，他以为最困难的一步总算走完了，可是席林斯基夫人却突然想挤过他的膝盖爬到车门外面去。

“我的上帝！”她说，“我没拿我的——你们是怎么说来着的？——我的嘀㗳—嘀㗳—嘀㗳——”

“你的表？”布洛克先生问道。

“哦，不是的！”她强烈地否认，“你知道吧，我的嘀㗳—嘀㗳—嘀㗳——”她挥动起她的食指，从一边移到另一边，像只钟摆那样。

“嘀㗳—嘀㗳，”布洛克先生说，将双手摁在自己的脑门上，还闭上眼睛，“你的意思会不会是指一只节拍器？”

“对呀！对呀！我想我准是在换乘火车时将它丢失了。”

布洛克先生费尽力气地安抚她。他甚至一冲动豪侠气十足地说，他明天就去弄一架来给她。不过与此同时他无法不暗自承认，她全部行李全都丢个精光，却单单为一个节拍器如此激动，这里头未免有些蹊跷。

席林斯基一大家子搬进了隔壁的那座房子，从表面上看一切都很正常。那几个男孩也的确孩子气十足。他们的名字是西格蒙德、鲍里斯和萨米。他们总是黏在一起，走起路来总是排成单行鱼贯而行，领头的一般都是西格蒙德。他们自己人之间说话时让人听起来像是在用一种由俄语、法语、芬兰语、德语和英语混合而成的发音极其怪异的家庭世界语。遇到有外人在场时，他们便很奇怪地保持沉默。使得布洛克先生感到不安的并不是席林斯基家人所做的或是说的单独的哪一件事，而仅仅是一些芝麻绿豆大的琐事。最后他明白了，他下意识受到干扰的是席林斯基家的孩子们在屋子里的一些做法，比方说吧，他们走动时永远也不会去踩地毯；他们排着纵队在光秃秃的地板上走，如果房间里铺有地毯，他们就站在门口不进来。另外的一件事情是，都过去好几个星期了，而席林斯基夫人却似乎一点也没有安顿下来的意思，连一张桌子几张床都不想往房子里添加。不管是白天还是黑夜，大门都是敞开着的，很快，这座房子便有了一种废弃多年的老房子的奇特、荒凉的模样。

学院倒是大可因为拥有了席林斯基夫人而感到心满意足的。她在教学上有那么一股子狠劲。倘若有某个玛丽·欧文斯或是伯纳丁·史密斯没能完成她布置的斯卡拉蒂[18]的颤音作业，那是会引起她的深深愤慨的。她让学院里她的工作室掌握有四架钢琴，让四个晕头转向的学生联手弹奏巴赫的赋格曲。系里她那一头所发出的喧嚣声真是够大的，可是席林斯基夫人头脑里似乎没有一根神经，如果音乐理想确实是仅仅靠了意志与努力便能完成的话，那么赖德学院便没有什么好发愁了。晚上的时间席林斯基夫人总是用来写她的第十二交响曲。她像是永远都不睡觉的，布洛克先生不论何时从他的起居室朝外张望，总能看到她工作室的灯光永远都是亮着的。不，并非因为任何专业上的考虑才使布洛克先生如此疑团重重的。

到了十月下旬，他才第一次觉察到有什么地方肯定不对头。那天，他和席林斯基夫人一起吃了午餐，心情不错，因为她非常详细地给他描述了一九二八年她参加的一次非洲野外观兽旅行的全过程。下午晚一些时候，她路过他的办公室，在门口那儿神情有些恍惚地停了下来。

布洛克先生从办公桌上抬起头，问道：“你有什么需要吗？”

“不，谢谢你。”席林斯基夫人说。她的声音低沉，很美，也很忧郁，“我只不过是在琢磨。你记得那架节拍器的吧。你说我会不会没准留给那法国人了？”

“谁？”布洛克先生问。

“哦，我跟他结过婚的那个法国人呀。”她回答道。

“法国人呀。”布洛克先生如释重负。他努力去想象席林斯基夫人的丈夫是怎样的一个人，可是他的脑子不听使唤。他自言自语地说：“孩子们的父亲。”

“哦，不是的，”席林斯基夫人斩钉截铁地说，“是萨米的父亲。”

布洛克先生有一种迅速产生的预感。他最深沉的本能警告他千万别再说什么了。可是，他对秩序的尊重、他的良心，迫使他提出了问题，“那么另外两个的父亲呢？”

席林斯基夫人把一只手放到脑袋后面去，把她那剪得短短的头发往上托了托。她脸上出现了一种迷惘的神情，有几分钟她并没有回答。接着她轻声说道：“鲍里斯的是个吹短笛的波兰人。”

“那么西格蒙德呢？”他问。布洛克先生的眼光越过他自己那张井然有序的办公桌，上面有一叠改好的作业、三支削尖的铅笔和一只雕刻成大象形状的象牙镇纸。当他把眼光抬起来看席林斯基夫人时，只见她显然是在苦苦思索。她目光扫过房间的几个角落，眼眉下垂，下巴在左右移动。她终于说道：“我们这是在讨论西格蒙德的父亲？”

“哦，不，”布洛克先生说，“没有这样做的必要。”

席林斯基夫人用一种既有尊严也很决断的声音说：“他是我同一个国家的人。”

其实是什么国家的人对布洛克先生来说根本是无所谓的。他可没有什么偏见，谁想结上十七次婚生出个中国孩子来那也不干他什么事。可是和席林斯基夫人的这次谈话里却有点儿什么让他感到不安。突然之间他明白了。那几个孩子一点儿也不像席林斯基夫人，可是哥仨呢却长得一模一样，既然他们各自有不同的父亲，布洛克先生不由得觉得这样的相似未免有点奇怪。

可是席林斯基夫人认为这个话题已经结束了。她拉上她那件皮夹克的拉链，转身走了。

“那正是我丢失的地方，”她说，迅速地点了点头，“落在[19]那个法国人那里了。”

在音乐系，一切都进行得很顺利。布洛克先生不需要处理什么太挠头的事情，例如去年那位竖琴教师的事件，她最后竟跟一个汽车修理工人私奔了。现在只有一个问题让他有点儿心烦，那就是怎么去理解席林斯基夫人。他说不好自己跟她的关系里有什么不对头的地方，为什么自己的感情如此混乱不清。首先，整个世界她很少有地方不曾去过，她一开口便怪不自然地显露出自己经历丰富，哪怕是地角天边都能跟她扯得上一点关系。她会一连好几天连嘴都不张，双手插在夹克口袋里在过道上游走，脸上一副莫测高深的样子。可是突然之间又会揪住布洛克先生上衣的纽扣眼，发表起情绪激昂的长篇独白来，眼睛里充满感情、炯炯发光，声音因为渴望而变得热情充沛。她要不就是什么事儿都跟你讲，要不就是连一个字都不讲。不过，没有例外的，凡是她提到的每一个片段，都有点怪异，似乎是经过了折射。如果她说带萨米去理发店了，她给你的印象是出了国，仿佛她告诉你某天下午她在巴格达。布洛克先生简直都有点丈二和尚摸不到头脑的感觉。

他是非常突然地知道真相的，这真相使一切都变得非常清晰，至少是使局势显得很明朗。布洛克先生早早儿便回到家中，在他起居室小小的炉架上生起了火。他觉得很舒服，心想今天晚上一定会过得不错。他光穿着袜子坐在炉火前，一本威廉·布莱克的集子已经放在了身边桌子上，他给自己斟了半玻璃杯的杏仁白兰地。十点钟，他正在炉火前很惬意地打瞌睡，脑子里满是马勒云山雾罩的乐句和虚无缥缈思绪的半成品。这时候，突然之间，从这样微妙的恍惚状态里，四个字浮现在他脑子里：“芬兰国王。”这几个字他似乎很熟悉，但头几分钟他还无法确定它们来自何方。但紧接着他一下子就把线索摸清了。那天下午他正步行穿过校园，席林斯基夫人叫住了他，开始不知所云地胡扯起来，对那些话他也就是这耳朵进那耳朵出罢了。他心里在想的是他的对位课[20]班上同学交上来的那摞卡农作业。现在，那几个字，她声调上的抑扬顿挫，异常清晰地重新出现在他的脑海里。席林斯基夫人是这样开始她的讲述的：“有一天，就在我站在一家点心店[21]前面的时候，芬兰国王正好乘了一辆雪橇经过。”

布洛克先生在椅子里猛地坐直身子，放下他手中的那杯白兰地。那个女人是个病态说谎者嘛。她在教室之外所讲的几乎每一个字都是假的。倘若她通宵工作，她会远兜远转地设法告诉你昨天晚上她去看电影了。如果她是在“老酒店”吃的午餐，她肯定会提到她午饭是在家里跟孩子们一起吃的。这个女人根本就是一个病态说谎者，这便是一切疑窦的真正答案。

布洛克先生压响了他一个个手指关节，从椅子里站立起来。他的头一个反应是火冒三丈。日复一日，席林斯基夫人竟然如此厚颜无耻地坐在他的办公室里，把她那些弥天大谎往他头上堆积！布洛克先生真是气不打一处来。他在房间里踱过来走过去，接着又进入他的简便厨房给自己弄了一份沙丁鱼三明治。

一个小时之后，他在炉火前坐下来时，他的气愤已经转化成了一种学者式和思辨式的质疑。他告诉自己，他必须不从个人意气出发对待整个事件，而是应该像一位医生审察一个病人那样地看待席林斯基夫人。她的谎言倒并没有什么欺诈性。她并没有蓄意要骗取什么，她也从未用所说的那些不真实故事获取什么好处。让人恼火的正是这一点。事情的后面说不定根本就没有什么动机。

布洛克先生把剩下的白兰地全都喝了。慢慢地，快到午夜时，他脑子里出现了更进一步的想法。席林斯基夫人说谎的原因既很痛苦也很平凡。她一生都在工作——弹钢琴、教课、创作那些美丽而卷帙浩繁的十二部交响乐。白天黑夜，她都在呕心沥血地投入工作，根本就剩不下什么精力来对付别的事情。她也是一个人，这个方面有所缺失，她只好尽力设法来加以弥补。如果她在图书馆桌子上辛勤工作了一个通宵，以后她宣称这段时间她都用在打牌上了，那就好像她是两件事情都做了似的。通过这些谎言，她觉得自己生活得很充实。谎言使得她工作之余剩下的渺小的生存状态整整丰富了一倍，而且还使她个人生活里的那些小块的破布头变成了五色斑斓的丝绸。

布洛克先生凝视着炉火，他心目中出现了席林斯基夫人的那张脸——一张严峻的脸，上面的眼睛暗暗的，显得很疲惫，那张嘴细细巧巧，显得训练有素。他意识到自己胸膛里升起了一丝温暖的感觉，并且还有一种怜悯、保护感和异常理解的情怀。一时之间，他竟陷入在一种可爱的思想混乱的状态之中。

这以后他刷了牙，穿上他的睡裤。他必须从实际出发。这又能说明什么问题呢？那个法国人、那个吹短笛的波兰人、巴格达？还有那些孩子，西格蒙德、鲍里斯和萨米——他们是谁？他们果真是她的孩子吗，或者仅仅是她从什么地方捡来的呢？布洛克先生把他的眼镜擦干净，放在床头柜上。他必须和她达成一个清晰明白的认识。否则，系里会出现一种局面，那肯定会惹出问题来的。现在是两点钟。他朝自己窗外瞥了一眼，看到席林斯基夫人工作室的灯光仍然亮着。布洛克先生上了床，在黑暗里扭出了几个鬼脸，肚子里还不大清楚自己第二天会对她怎么说。

八点钟，布洛克先生就来到了自己的办公室。他伛起了背在办公桌后面坐下，等待捕捉从走廊上走过来的席林斯基夫人。他不用等候多久，一听到她的脚步声他便喊出了她的名字。

席林斯基夫人在门口站停了下来。她看上去有些迷惘和疲倦，“你好吗？我昨天晚上休息得可好了。”

“能不能请你坐下，”布洛克先生说，“我有几句话想跟你谈谈。”

席林斯基夫人把皮包往边上一放，倦怠地倚靠在他对面的圈手椅里。“怎么啦？”她问道。

“昨天我穿过校园的时候你跟我说话了，”他慢吞吞地说道，“如果我没有记错的话，我相信你说的是一家点心店和芬兰国王这样的事儿。对不对？”

席林斯基夫人把头扭向一侧，似在追忆什么，眼睛盯看着窗框的一角。

“关于一家点心店的什么事儿。”他重复了一遍。

她那张疲惫的脸变得容光焕发了。“哦，当然对的，”她起劲地说道，“我告诉了你，那回我怎样站在这家店铺的门前，正好芬兰国王——”

“席林斯基夫人！”布洛克先生喊出声来，“芬兰是根本没有国王的。”

席林斯基夫人看上去一副茫然不知所措的样子。然后，过了半刻，她才开口重新说话，“那时我正站在布扎尼点心店的橱窗前，我看完蛋糕转过身子，突然看到芬兰国王——”

“席林斯基夫人，我刚跟你说过，世界上是没有芬兰国王的。”

“在赫尔辛福尔斯[22]。”她又一次不顾一切地说道，他再一次让她讲到国王，但是再往下便打断她不让她说了。

“芬兰是一个民主国家，”他说，“你是不可能见到芬兰国王的。因此，你方才说的不是真的，是全然不真实的。”

席林斯基夫人当时脸上的表情是布洛克先生今后再也忘不掉的。在她的眼睛里，有惊讶、沮丧以及一种被逼入死角的恐惧。她那神情，就跟一个人亲眼见到自己的整个内心世界分崩离析变得粉碎时一样。

“这很糟糕。”布洛克说，心中感觉到真正的同情。

可是席林斯基夫人振作起来了。她抬起下巴，冷冷地说：“我可是一个芬兰人哟。”

“这个问题我并未触及。”布洛克先生回答道。在重新想了一想之后，他承认，这个问题他方才也不是完全没有涉及。

“我出生在芬兰，我是一个芬兰公民。”

“这当然非常可能。”布洛克先生的声音也一点点在提高。

“战争时期，”她激昂慷慨地往下说，“我骑了一辆摩托车，担任通信员。”

“你的爱国热情跟这件事没有什么关系。”

“就因为我正要取出第一份文件——”

“席林斯基夫人！”布洛克先生说。他双手紧紧抓住办公桌的边缘，“那件事跟别的没有什么关系。问题是在于，你认为，你坚持说，你见到了——你说你见到了——”不过他说不下去了。她那张脸阻止了他。她的脸变得死一般的苍白，嘴巴周围都已经发暗了。她的眼睛睁得非常大，既绝望，却又很骄傲。布洛克先生突然觉得自己是个杀人犯。乱成一团的混合感情——理解、后悔、不可理喻的爱——使得他用双手去遮住自己的脸。他无法说话，一直到他心中激动的情绪逐渐安定下来，这时候，他用非常微弱的声音说道：“是的。自然是的。芬兰国王。他当时好吗？”

一个小时之后，布洛克先生坐着，朝他办公室窗子外面看去。沿着西桥路的街，树几乎都是光秃秃的了，学院的一幢幢灰色建筑有一种安详、忧郁的神态。在他懒洋洋地打量着熟悉的景色时，他注意到德雷克家的那条老阿莱德尔种犬在街上蹒蹒跚跚地行走。这景象他过去看到都有一百遍了，为什么他还会觉得奇怪呢？接着他不无惊悚地发现，那条老狗是在倒退着跑。布洛克盯看着那条阿莱德尔犬直到它越出了视线，接着便回到他的工作上来，对位课刚交上来的卡农作业还有待他来批改呢。

旅居者

这天早晨，似睡非睡的疆域似乎是在罗马那样的地方：这里有叮咚作响的喷泉，狭窄的街道时不时会拱起脊背，这是个炫耀金彩的城市，鲜花烂漫，连石头都因年代久远变得轮廓柔和。有时候，在这样半清醒的状态下，他会重访巴黎，或是又见战后德国的瓦砾堆，要不就是在瑞士滑雪，住高山客舍。有时候，却又是在佐治亚的休耕地上迎接狩猎日的晨曦。今天早晨，这个没有时间性的梦境则是在罗马。

约翰·费里斯在纽约的一家旅馆里醒来。他有一种预感：某件不愉快的事情正等待着他——是什么，他不知道。这种感觉暂时被早晨的生活需要掩盖了下去，但是即使在他穿好衣服下楼去的时候依然滞留不去。这是秋季无云的一天，一片片淡淡的阳光穿过粉彩色的摩天高楼斜落下来。费里斯走进旅馆隔壁的一家药房，在靠橱窗玻璃最后的那个火车座里坐下，俯瞰下面的人行道。他要了一份美式早餐，外加煎泥肠鸡蛋。

费里斯是从巴黎回国参加他父亲的葬礼的，葬礼一星期前在佐治亚州他老家的小城举行。死亡的震惊使他明白地察觉到自己已经青春不再。他的发线不断往后退缩，如今已变得光秃的鬓角上脉管的跳动显露得很清晰，尽管人不胖，他肚子却开始鼓起来了。费里斯一直很爱他的父亲，两人之间的关系曾一度非常融洽——可是岁月多多少少冲淡了这样的亲情。这次丧父，估计会在很长的一段时间内，使他难以预料地心情抑郁。他已经尽量多滞留了一些日子，好在家里多陪陪母亲和几个弟弟。他搭乘的去巴黎的飞机明天早上走。

费里斯掏出他的地址本，想查一个电话号码。他逐渐专心地翻动起一页又一页的纸。纽约的人名与地址，欧洲的一些首都，南方老家那个州为数不多的字迹变淡的资料。发黄的印刷体，写得趴手趴脚，像是喝醉酒似的。贝蒂·威尔斯：偶然邂逅的爱侣，如今嫁人了。查理·威廉斯：在旭特根森林受了伤，后来没有消息了。老好人威廉斯——不知道还活着不？唐·格林：电视界的一位名人，现在正走财运吧。亨利·格林：战后落魄了，听说住进了一家疗养院。科姬·霍尔：听说她已不在人世了。大大咧咧、嘻嘻哈哈的科姬——真没想到这傻丫头好好儿的怎么就没了呢。在把地址簿合上时，费里斯有了一种不安全、人世无常，几乎是恐惧的感觉。

就在此时他的身体像给电击中似的忽然猛抽了一下。他正盯看着橱窗外面，就在此时，他的前妻伊丽莎白竟从他面前经过，就在离他很近的人行道上慢慢地走了过去。他说不清楚，为什么她走开后自己的心会起了一阵强烈的颤动，也不懂怎么接下来心中又会有那样一种轻率与优雅的感情。

费里斯急忙付了账冲出去来到人行道上。伊丽莎白站在街角等着过第五大道。他朝她赶过去想要叫她，可是绿灯亮了，还不等他赶上，伊丽莎白已经穿过马路了。费里斯接着又跟上去。到了马路对面他原本可以很容易就赶上她的，可是他发现自己却一点一点地落在了后面，他自己也不明白这是怎么回事。她的淡棕色头发很随便地鬈着，在看着她的时候费里斯回想起他父亲有一回说过伊丽莎白的走路姿势“很有风度”。她在下一个街角又拐弯了，费里斯仍然跟着，虽然到此时他要追上她的意愿已经消失了。费里斯在思量见到伊丽莎白为什么会引起自己身体上如此异常的反应，手心为什么会发潮，心跳又为什么会加快。

费里斯已经有八年没见到他的前妻了。他知道很久以前她又结婚了，而且还生有不止一个孩子。近几年来他很少想到她。可是最初，刚离婚那阵，那份失落感几乎要把他摧垮。可是，时间使痛苦渐渐消失，他重新去爱，接着又再一次去爱。燕妮，现在，他在爱着的是燕妮。当然，他对前妻的爱早已是过去的事了。那么，为什么还会出现身体上的把持不住和精神上的动摇呢？他只知道他的阴暗心理与这个晴朗澄澈的秋日很不协调。费里斯猛地扭转身子，迈开大步，几乎像奔跑一样地急忙回到旅馆。

费里斯给自己倒了一杯酒，虽然时间还不到十一点钟。他像个精疲力竭的人那样瘫倒在一把圈椅里，手里紧握着那只盛有兑好水的波旁酒的玻璃杯。他面前还有整整一天，因为去巴黎的飞机明天早上才开。他检查了一下还有什么事情必须要做：把行李交到法航办事处，跟老板共进午餐，买一双皮鞋和一件大衣。那么还有什么事——是不是还有别的什么事情呢？费里斯把酒喝完，接着便打开电话簿。

他要打电话给前妻决定得很草率。电话用的是那位丈夫巴莱的名字。他不等自己来得及作思想斗争便匆匆拨通电话。他和伊丽莎白圣诞节时交换过贺卡，他在收到她的结婚宣告时曾寄去一套雕刻艺术品。不打电话是没什么理由嘛。可是在他等待着、聆听着那一头的铃声时，他却为疑虑烦扰着。

接电话的是伊丽莎白，她那熟悉的声音对他来说又是一次新的震撼。他把自己的名字报了两遍，不过在想起他是谁之后，从她的声音里听她还是很高兴的。他解释道自己在此地只待一天。她说，她和丈夫早就买好票今晚要去观剧，不过——她不知道他可愿意过来吃一顿早一些开的晚餐。费里斯说承蒙邀请他感到不胜荣幸。

他一边在办着一件件要做的事，时不时仍然会考虑有没有忘掉哪件务必要办的事。费里斯晚半晌时洗了个澡，换了衣服，做这些事时经常会想起燕妮，明天晚上他就可以和她在一起了。“燕妮，”他会这么说，“我在纽约的时候很凑巧碰见了我的前妻。还和她一起用了晚餐。自然，还有她的丈夫。这么多年之后又见到她，真有点不可思议呢。”

伊丽莎白住在东五十街，费里斯坐在出租汽车里往城市僻静些的方向驶去，在车子驶过十字路口时他总要抬起头去看看迟迟不肯落下的斜阳，不过等他到达目的地时已经进入秋季的迟暮时分了。她住的是一幢楼前有雨棚和看门人的住宅，她的那套公寓是在七层。

“请进，费里斯先生。”

本来是准备见到伊丽莎白甚至是那位想象不出来的丈夫的，可是费里斯却见到了一个脸上长有雀斑的红头发孩子，因而不免吃了一惊。他知道她有了孩子，可是下意识中不知怎么的总是难以接受。惊讶使得他笨拙地往后退了退。

“这就是我们的公寓，”那孩子很有礼貌地说，“你不是费里斯先生吗？我是比利。进来呀。”

穿过走廊来到起居室，在这儿那位丈夫又让费里斯吃了一惊。这是又一个感情上没有为费里斯接受的人。巴莱是个动作迟缓红头发的男人，一举一动有点装腔作势。他站起身，伸出手向费里斯表示欢迎。

“我是比尔·巴莱。很高兴能见到你。伊丽莎白这就出来。她马上就要打扮好了。”

最后面的那几个字又在他脑海里敲击出一组顺畅的变奏，令他忆起那些年月里的事。俏丽的伊丽莎白，浴前那一丝不挂的绯色躯体。衣服没有完全穿好的伊丽莎白，侧坐在梳妆台镜前，用刷子梳理那头细细的栗色发丝。这里面，处处都有她甜蜜、随和的亲切感以及肉体的温香软玉感。这样预先未曾料到的回忆使费里斯一下子回不过神来，他好不容易才强迫自己去应对比尔·巴莱投来的目光。

“比利，你能不能去把厨房桌子上的饮料托盘端过来？”

孩子立即便按照吩咐的去做了。他走开后，费里斯没话找话地说：“你们的孩子真好啊。”

“我们也是这么想的。”

孩子不在时费里斯再没说出一个字。孩子终于回来了，端着一个托盘，上面有几只玻璃杯和一只马提尼鸡尾酒的调酒器。在酒的帮助下他们好不容易才聊了起来：他们提到了俄国，还说到纽约的人工增雨，还扯起曼哈顿与巴黎公寓状况的孰优孰劣。

“费里斯先生明天要坐飞机横越整片大洋呢。”巴莱对那小男孩说，孩子正斜靠在他的椅子扶手上，静静的，很乖的样子。“我猜你准是很想钻进他的箱包偷搭飞机的吧。”

比利把父亲挺差劲的逗笑顶了回去。“我可是要当一名新闻记者，像费里斯先生那样正正经经搭乘飞机的。”接着他又加强语气地说，“那就是我长大以后想当的。”

巴莱说：“我还以为你想当医生的呢。”

“我是的，”比利说，“我两样都想当。我还想当一名造原子弹的科学家呢。”

伊丽莎白走进来了，手里抱着一个女娃娃。

“哦，约翰！”她说。她把娃娃放在那位父亲的膝上，“见到你真好。你能够来我太高兴了。”

那个女娃娃很庄重地坐在父亲的腿上。她穿了一条水粉色中国绉纱裙子，裙腰处围有玫瑰花状的饰品，淡金色的柔软鬈发用颜色般配的丝带拢在了后面。她的皮肤让夏日的阳光晒得黑黝黝的，棕色的眼睛里闪烁出金光与笑意。在她把手举上去要抓父亲的角边眼镜时，他干脆把眼镜摘下，让她透过镜片看了一会儿。“咱们的老糖球怎么样啊？”他说。

伊丽莎白看上去非常漂亮，也许比他过去理解的更加漂亮。她直直、洁净的头发在闪亮。她的脸显得比以前更柔和了，泛出了圣洁的光。那是一种因家庭氛围才得以产生的圣母般可爱的光芒。

“你几乎一点都没有变化嘛，”伊丽莎白说，“不过时间都过了那么久了呀。”

“八年了。”在双方进一步交谈时，他不禁局促不安地用手去摸摸自己正在变得稀薄的头发。

费里斯突然觉得自己成了一个旁观者——巴莱一家人中的一个闯入者。他为什么要来呢？他在受苦。他自己的生活似乎过得如此孤单，活像一根脆弱的支柱，几乎没能撑起岁月的残骸中的任何东西。他觉得在这家人的房间里连一分钟也待不下去了。

他对着手表瞥了一眼，“你们不是要去剧院吗？”

“真是不好意思，”伊丽莎白说，“不过这事一个多月以前就已经定下来了。不过，约翰，你不久后肯定还会回国的吧。你没打算做移民吧，是不是？”

“移民，”费里斯重复地说道，“这个词儿我可不爱听。”

“那还有什么好听点的词儿吗？”她问道。

他想了几分钟，“也许叫旅居者还差不多吧。”

费里斯又朝他的手表瞥了一眼，伊丽莎白又再一次道歉，“要是我们能够早些知道——”

“我在这地方只待一天。我回来自己也没有料到。你明白吧，爸爸上星期去世了。”

“费里斯老爸不在啦？”

“是的，在约翰斯·霍普金斯医院。他生病后在那里住了都快一年了。葬礼是在佐治亚州老家举行的。”

“哦，我听了真难过。我一直都是很喜欢费里斯老爸的。”

那个小男孩从椅子后面钻出来，以便能正眼看他母亲的脸。他问道：“谁死啦？”

费里斯没有注意到孩子的忧虑，他在想他自己父亲的死亡。他眼前又出现了直直地躺在棺材里丝绸垫巾上的遗体。尸体被怪异地上了胭脂，而他如此熟悉的那双手被交叉地摆放在一层殡丧用的玫瑰花的上面，显得特别巨大。记忆的画面消失了，费里斯被伊丽莎白安详的声音唤回到现实中来。

“是费里斯先生的父亲，比利。一个非常好的人。你不认识他的。”

“不过你干吗叫他费里斯老爸呀？”

巴莱和伊丽莎白交换了一个窘促的眼色。挺身出来回答孩子的问题的是巴莱。“很久以前，”他说，“你母亲和费里斯先生结过婚，那时还没有你呢——是很久很久以前的事了。”

“跟费里斯先生？”

小男孩瞪眼看着费里斯，一副大惑不解、无法相信的样子。而回看这样瞪视的费里斯先生的眼睛，也是同样有点难以置信似的。难道他真的曾经直呼这个陌生女人为伊丽莎白吗，在晚上亲热的时候甚至还叫她“小奶油鸭子”吗？他们真的共同生活过大约一千个日日夜夜吗？而——最终——又经历了婚姻爱情破灭所致的痛苦，那种突如其来的孤独感（嫉妒呀、酗酒呀还有金钱纠葛）。

巴莱对两个孩子说：“该轮到谁吃晚饭啦？随我来吧。”

“可是，爹爹！妈妈跟费里斯先生——我——”

比利那双紧盯不放的眼睛——困惑不解中带有一丝敌意的闪光——使费里斯想起了另外一个孩子的眼光。那是燕妮的年轻的儿子——一个七岁的男孩，他有一张阴森森的小脸，那双膝盖也像是随时要使坏，费里斯总想躲开他但往往会忘记。

“结完婚很快就分开了！”巴莱将比利轻轻地朝门口推，“现在就说再见吧，儿子。”

“再见，费里斯先生。”比利老大不高兴地加了一句，“我原来以为可以留下来吃蛋糕的呢。”

“你待会儿还可以再来的嘛，”伊丽莎白说，“快跟爹爹走，吃你的晚饭去。”

现在房间里只剩下费里斯和伊丽莎白了。一开始，好几分钟都没有人说话，气氛有些尴尬。费里斯请求允许他再给自己斟一杯酒，伊丽莎白便把鸡尾酒调酒器移到桌子靠他的这一边。他看了看那架三角钢琴，注意到书架上的那摞乐谱。

“你现在还弹得跟原先一样漂亮吗？”

“我仍然很喜欢弹的。”

“请奏几曲吧，伊丽莎白。”

伊丽莎白很痛快地站起身来。只要有人请，她就会应邀弹奏，这一直是她脾气中最随和的一面。她从来不推诿退缩，不会光说几句抱歉的话把事情打发过去。此刻她向钢琴走去时还多了几分如释重负的感觉呢。

她先弹一首巴赫的前奏曲与赋格。那首前奏曲欢快多彩，犹如晨室里的一面多棱镜。赋格的第一声部是一个纯正、孤独的宣告，它由第二声部变化着花样重复了一遍，然后又在一个很繁复的框架内被第三次重复，多音部多层次圣洁的音乐从容不迫、很辉煌地流淌而出。主题由两个副主题交织着，又装饰以无数精妙的乐音——它们有时起着主导作用，接着又潜隐到背景里去，它具有一种孤独者不惧怕汇入整体的高尚精神。快到结尾时，音乐语言密集，一鼓作气地使占统治地位的第一主题最后得以有辉煌的再现，几个和弦则宣告了赋格的终止。费里斯把头靠在椅子背上，闭上了眼睛。在曲终后的寂静中，一个清晰高亢的声音从走廊尽头的房间里传来。

“爹爹，妈妈和费里斯先生怎么能——”房门关上了。

钢琴又响起来了——这又是什么曲子呢？说不清曲名是什么，调子却很熟悉，这清澈的曲调曾长期潜伏在他的心中。现在它在向他叙述着另外的一段时间，另外的一个地方——这可是伊丽莎白过去经常弹的曲子。这精巧的曲调唤醒了一片荒原似的记忆。费里斯迷失在对过去的渴念、冲突与矛盾的争斗之中。奇怪的是，这段成为混乱无序状态催化剂的音乐，本身竟是如此的圣洁与明净。但是如歌的乐句被女仆的出现打断了。

“巴莱太太，晚饭已经在餐桌上摆好了。”

即使费里斯已在餐桌旁主人与主妇的中间坐下来时，那没有奏完的音乐仍然影响着他的情绪。他都有几分微醺了。

“世事无常[23]，”他说，“一首没有唱完的歌，再没有什么比这更能让人体会到世事无常了。或者是一本旧地址本，它也能起到这样的作用。”

“地址本？”巴莱重复了一句。但是他打住了，他不想多打听，便很有礼貌地不追问了。

“你仍然是往昔的那个大男孩呢，强尼。”伊丽莎白说，口气里带着当初那种温柔的痕迹。

那天晚上他们吃的是一顿南方的晚餐，那些菜都是他一向爱吃的。餐桌上有炸鸡和玉米布丁，还有厚厚地裹了一层糖釉的甜薯。吃饭的时候，如果沉默的时间稍长一些，伊丽莎白就会设法让交谈活跃起来。现在该由费里斯来谈谈燕妮的情况了。

“我是去年秋天才认识燕妮的——也就是此刻的这个季节——是在意大利。她是一位歌唱家，订了合同在罗马演出。我估计不久之后我们就要结婚了。”

这些话听起来那么像真的，是那么的自然，连费里斯自己起先都不敢相信那是编出来的了。实际上他和燕妮一年来根本没有提到过婚嫁的事情。其实她仍然是有夫之妇——她的丈夫是巴黎的一个白俄钱商，他们分开住已有五年。可是现在再要纠正为时已晚。伊丽莎白已经在向他表示祝贺了：“知道你这样好我真高兴。祝贺你了，强尼。”

他想尽量多讲些真话来加以弥补，“罗马的秋天美极了。气温宜人，鲜花灿烂。”他接着还说，“燕妮有一个小男孩，六岁。会讲三种语言，真是个聪明的小家伙。我们有时候一起去土伊勒里宫[24]去玩。”

他又扯了个谎。他倒是带那男孩到花园里去过一次的。那个脸色蜡黄的外国男孩穿了露出两条细腿的短裤，在水泥水池子里玩他的小船，还骑了小马。孩子还想去看木偶剧。可是时间来不及了，因为费里斯有一个约会要去斯克赖伯饭店。他答应孩子改天下午再去看布袋木偶。他带瓦伦丁只去过一次土伊勒里宫。

房间里起了一些骚动。女仆端来了带白霜的蛋糕，上面插着粉红色的蜡烛。孩子们穿着睡衣进来了。费里斯仍然不明白是怎么回事。

“生日快乐，约翰，”伊丽莎白说，“快吹蜡烛吧。”

费里斯认出了蛋糕上自己的生日日期。烛火还很顽强，好不容易才吹灭，空气里飘着蜡燃烧的气味。费里斯都三十八岁了。他太阳穴上的血管颜色加深了，脉搏跳得更快了。

“到时候了，你们该动身去剧院了。”

费里斯为生日晚餐谢过了伊丽莎白，也说了告别时该说的那些话。全家人都聚在门口目送他离开。

一弯细细的月牙儿高悬在参差不齐、黑乎乎的摩天楼上空。街上刮着风，很冷。费里斯急匆匆地走到第三大街叫住了一辆出租车。他盯看着这座夜间的城市，怀着一种离别甚至是永远告别的细腻的专注心情。他很孤独。他都迫不及待期望着上飞机和航行了。

第二天他从空中俯瞰这座城市，它在阳光中闪闪发亮，像是玩具似的，精巧细致。接着美国被抛在身后，下面只有大西洋和远方的欧洲海岸了。大海泛出了牛奶般的灰白色，在云层下面显得很宁静。费里斯一整天几乎都在打瞌睡。天快黑下来时他又想起伊丽莎白和头天晚上的做客了。他怀着渴望、淡淡的嫉妒和难以解释的遗憾想念着置身于一家人之中的伊丽莎白。他在苦苦回忆曾如此感动过他的那首曲子，那段未能终奏的曲调。他唯一能记起来的只有结尾处的和弦与些许不相干的乐音了，主要旋律本身已经逃离了他。不过他倒还记得伊丽莎白弹奏的赋格的第一声部——只是讽刺性地颠倒了前后次序而且用的还是小调。在大洋上空飞行时，他已经不再为漂流与孤寂的焦虑所困扰，他平静地想到了父亲的死。用晚餐的时候飞机已经来到法兰西的岸边了。

半夜时分，费里斯坐在一辆出租车里穿越巴黎。那是个多云的夜晚，协和广场灯光的上空缭绕着一层轻雾。半夜还营业的小酒吧射出的灯光在潮湿的人行道上闪烁。如同往常一样，在经过一次越洋飞行后两片大陆的差别总让人感到突兀。早上在纽约，半夜却来到巴黎。费里斯眼前闪过了生活的无序与混乱：一个又一个城市的更迭，短暂爱情的嬗变，还有时间，那岁月邪恶的滑奏[25]，时间永远都是在起着变化。

“快！快！”他惊恐地喊道，“你快些呀。”[26]

瓦伦丁为他开了门。这小男孩穿了条睡裤和一件快穿不下的红睡袍。他的灰眼睛显得很没精打采，在费里斯从过道进入套间时，那双眼睛才眨动了几下。

“我在等妈妈呢。”[27]

燕妮如今在一家夜总会唱歌。她还得过一小时才能回到家中。瓦伦丁继续去画他的画，他蹲着用蜡笔在铺在地上的一张纸上画画。费里斯低下头去看了看——画的是一个在弹班卓琴的乐师，旁边的一只气球形状的圆圈里写了些说明词，还画了几根波浪状的杠杠。

“咱们以后一定再去土伊勒里宫啊。”

孩子抬起头来看看他，费里斯将他拉到自己膝前来。突然，他想起伊丽莎白未能弹完的曲子的旋律了。他并未苦思苦想，记忆的沉重负担却自己卸了下来——这一回带来的仅仅是承认与突然的惊喜。

“约翰先生，”那孩子说，“你见到他了吗？”

费里斯弄糊涂了，他还以为说的是另外的那个孩子呢——那个长了雀斑的、全家宠爱的男孩。“见到谁呀，瓦伦丁？”他问。

“在佐治亚你死了的爸爸。”孩子补充了一句，“他没事了吧？”

费里斯急切地快声说道：“咱们以后一定要经常去土伊勒里宫。让你骑上小马，咱们直接去看布袋木偶。咱们好好儿地看木偶剧，再也不慌慌张张离开了。”

“约翰先生，”瓦伦丁说，“布袋木偶戏现在已经不演了。”

又是恐惧，又是不得不承认虚度年华和死亡。瓦伦丁，很懂事又很自信的样子，仍然靠在他的臂弯里。他的面颊挨蹭到那张柔嫩的小脸，感觉到了细细的眼睫毛的抚触。他怀着内心的绝望感将孩子搂得更紧一些——仿佛跟他的爱同样变化多端的一种情绪是能够主宰时代的脉搏似的。

家庭困境

星期四那天，马丁·麦道斯早早地就离开了办公室，以便搭乘第一班特快公共汽车回家。他步出办公楼时，淡紫色的暮霭正在化雪的街道上逐渐变浓，等公共汽车驶离市中心的终点站时，城里的灯光已是一片通明了。星期四下午女佣休息，马丁希望能尽早回家，因为这一年来他妻子的情况，嗯——不大好。这个星期四他疲倦得很，生怕有哪个老乘客会选中他跟他没完没了地聊天，因此，一直到公共汽车过了乔治·华盛顿桥，他都把头埋在打开的报纸里。每回车子一驶上西九公路，马丁总觉得一半的路程已经过去，便深深地往肺里吸气，即使这时是冬天，刮进烟气弥漫的车子里来的冷风只不过是绸带般一窄条一窄条的，他也相信他现在吸进去的是乡间的新鲜空气了。要是在往日，到这时候，他就会松弛神经，开始美滋滋地想到他的家了。可是这一年来，离家越近，他越是感到紧张，他几乎不期望旅途结束了。今天晚上，马丁让他的脸紧挨车窗，凝望着荒芜的田野和掠过去的村镇的孤零零的灯火。天边升起了月亮，给黑沉沉的大地和潮滋滋的晚雪一衬，显得惨白惨白的。在马丁眼里，今晚的乡野也似乎格外苍茫，格外凄凉。在拉响车铃通知司机有人要下车的前几分钟，他从帽架上取下帽子，把叠好的报纸塞进他的大衣口袋。

他住的那幢房子离公共汽车站还有一段路，离河很近可又不紧挨河边。从他起居室的窗口可以越过街道和对面的小花园，瞥见赫德逊河。他的房子是现代风格的，在狭窄的小花园里，显得又白又新，有点刺眼。夏天的时候，花园里的草柔嫩、鲜亮，马丁精心栽种了一个小花圃，还在玫瑰花后面搭了一个木格架。可是在寒冷、休耕的季节里，花园里很荒凉，他的房子也显得光秃秃的。现在，这所小房子每个房间的灯光都亮着，马丁在大门前的小道上急急地走着，快来到台阶的时候，他停下步子，把一辆手推车推到小道外面去。

两个孩子在起居室里玩得很专心，一开始连他开门进来都没有察觉。马丁停住步子，望着他这两个太平无事的、可爱的孩子。他们打开了写字桌最底下的一个抽屉，把装饰圣诞树的小道具都拿了出来。安弟居然设法插上了圣诞树小电灯的插头，那些红红绿绿的小灯泡蜿蜒延伸在起居室的地毯上，一亮一暗，发出了一种不合时令的节日气氛。这当儿，他正努力地把亮着的灯线往马丽纳的木马的背上拉去呢。马丽纳正坐在地上，把小天使的一只翅膀拽下来。孩子一看见他，发出一声尖叫，表示欢迎。马丁把胖嘟嘟的小女孩一下子抱起来，放在自己肩膀上，安弟扑了过来，抱住了他爸爸的腿。

“爸爸，爸爸，爸爸！”

马丁小心翼翼地把小姑娘放下来，又抱起安弟，把他像钟摆似的晃了几下。接着他把圣诞树的灯线收了起来。

“干吗把这些东西都拿出来呀？来帮我把它塞回到抽屉里去。你可不能去动那个电灯插座。我不是告诉过你的吗。这可不是开玩笑的事儿，安弟。”

那个六岁的男孩点点头，一面关上书桌的抽屉。马丁摸了摸他那头柔软的金发，他的手温柔地停留在孩子细细的后脖颈上。

“吃过晚饭了吗，小老乡。”

“不好吃。烤面包是辣的。”

小女孩在地毯上绊了一跤，她先是吓了一跳，愣住了，紧接着就号啕大哭起来。马丁把她抱在怀里，带她到后面的厨房去。

“你瞧，爸爸，”安弟说，“烤面包——”

艾米莉光是把孩子们的晚饭放在瓷砖面的餐桌上，连桌布都不铺。桌子上有两只盘子，里面有麦乳精和鸡蛋的残渣，还有两只盛牛奶的银壶。另外还有一只盘子，放的是夹肉桂酱的烤面包，除去给小牙齿咬掉一口之外，别的一点也没动。马丁闻了闻咬过的那块，又试探性地咬了一小口。他马上把烤面包全倒进了垃圾桶，“咳——呸——这算是什么玩意儿！”

原来艾米莉是误把盛辣椒面的罐头当作肉桂粉罐头了。

“我像给火烧了似的，”安弟说，“我喝了口水，跑到门外，张大嘴巴。马丽纳统统没吃。”

“一口没吃，”马丁纠正他说。他手足无措地站着，眼光从厨房这面墙扫到那面墙，不知该怎么办才好。“好吧，我看那只好算了吧，”他终于这样说，“妈妈这会儿在哪儿呢？”

“她在楼上你们的屋子里。”

马丁让孩子们待在厨房里，独自上楼去找他的妻子。他来到房门口，站了一会儿，好把怒气往下压压。他没有敲门，进屋后马上把身后的门关上。

艾米莉坐在这个舒适的房间窗前的一把摇椅里。她在从一只玻璃杯里喝着什么东西，一见他进来，赶紧把杯子藏在摇椅后面的地上。她的表情里有几分慌乱和内疚的神态，为了掩饰这种神态，她故意做出一副轻松活泼的样子。

“噢，马蒂，你倒已经回来啦？时间过得真快。我正要下楼去——”她蹒蹒跚跚地歪倒在他身上，她的吻里冒出了一股刺鼻的雪利酒味儿。见到他站在那里毫无反应，她便退后了一步，神经质地吃吃地笑了起来。

“你这是怎么啦？站在那儿，就跟理发店前面旋转的花柱子似的。你有什么毛病没有？”

“我有毛病？”马丁弯下腰去，从摇椅后面的地上捡起那只玻璃杯，“我真希望你能明白我多么不喜欢——这对我们全家又是多么不好。”

艾米莉用一种假惺惺、轻飘飘的腔调说话了，这种腔调他太熟悉了。遇到这种场合她常常会冒出一股淡淡的英国口音，没准是从哪个她所崇拜的女明星那里学来的。“我半点儿也不明白你指的是什么事儿。也许你是指我倒了几滴雪利酒的玻璃杯吧。我才喝了一指高——顶多两指。可这又有什么不对呢，我倒要请问？我挺好的嘛。一点事儿也没有嘛。”

“好不好谁都能看得出来。”

艾米莉往浴室走时小心翼翼地保持着平衡。她拧开水龙头，用双手接住水往自己的脸上泼，接着又用浴巾的一只角按按脸，把水擦干。她面容秀美娟丽，显得很年轻，没有一点瑕疵。

“我正要下楼去准备晚饭。”她步履不稳地走着，全靠扶住了门框才没有跌倒。

“我来弄晚饭吧。你待在这儿。我会把饭端上来的。”

“那可不行。有谁听说过这样的事吗？”

“求求你了。”马丁说。

“你别拦住我。我什么事也没有。我正要下楼——”

“你听我说呀。”

“你让你奶奶听你的好了。”

她跌跌撞撞地朝门口走去，可是马丁抓住了她的胳膊，“我不愿让孩子看见你这副模样。你清醒些好不好。”

“模样！”艾米莉猛地把胳膊挣脱开。她因为发火声调变高了。“哼，就因为我下午喝了两口雪利酒，你就硬说我像酒鬼！哼，我连一滴威士忌都没碰。你也不是不知道，我从来不在酒吧间里狂饮。这你总该没什么好说的了吧。我在正正经经吃晚饭的时候连杯鸡尾酒也不喝。我只不过偶尔喝一杯雪利酒。我倒要问，这又有什么见不得人的？模样！”

马丁搜索枯肠，想找出几句话使他的妻子安静下来。“咱们俩单独在楼上安安静静地吃一顿。你乖乖地坐着，做个好姑娘。”他说。艾米莉在床沿上坐了下来，他打开门，急急忙忙地退了出去，“我一分钟就回来。”

他在楼下手忙脚乱地准备晚餐，一边又跟往常那样，陷入了沉思，又在琢磨他们家的麻烦是怎么开始的了。他自己倒是一向喜欢喝上一两杯好酒的。以前住在亚拉巴马州的时候，他们总是用很长时间啜饮一杯烈酒或鸡尾酒的，他们把这看作一件很自然的事。若干年来，他们总是在晚饭前喝上一两杯——顶多三杯，临睡前再慢慢地啜饮一杯。在节假日的前夕，他们有时也会放量饮酒，说不定还会有点醉醺醺。可是杯中之物对他来说从未构成一个问题，仅仅是意味着一笔令人不快的开支，在家中食指日繁的情况下有点负担不起罢了。是在他的公司把他调到纽约来之后，马丁才明确地认识到他的妻子饮酒过量了。他注意到，在大白天，她也不断地酗酒。

承认有这个问题存在之后，他便试着来分析根源。从亚拉巴马搬到纽约来有点打乱了她的生活习惯；她原来是习惯于南方小镇那种懒洋洋的温暖气氛的，是习惯于在家庭、亲戚、儿时的朋友的圈子里活动的，遇到北方比较严峻、比较冷酷的社会风气，她感到不能适应。在她看来，带领子女和料理家务是顶繁重不过的工作。她怀念巴黎城[28]，在这儿大城市的市郊小镇上没交到什么朋友。她只是翻翻杂志，看看侦探小说，别的什么书也不读。没有酒精的调剂，她的内心像是缺了什么似的。艾米莉暴露出自己的不能节制，这就使他暗暗地改变了对妻子的最初印象。有时候，他们之间会产生一种无法解释的怨恨，会因为酒精这个导火线引来一场不适宜的勃然大怒。他发现艾米莉身上隐藏着一种粗俗的性格，这与她那自然淳真的天性是格格不入的。为了喝酒，她扯谎，用莫名其妙的花招来哄骗他。

接着，又出了一件事故。大约一年前，他晚上下班回家，只听见孩子的卧室里发出一阵阵尖叫声。他发现艾米莉手里抱着刚洗完澡的光赤赤、湿漉漉的婴儿。孩子从她怀里掉下来过，那极其脆嫩的头颅撞击在桌子边上，有一缕血迹粘在孩子柔软的发丝上面。艾米莉在抽抽搭搭地啜泣，她喝醉了。马丁把当时觉得无比珍贵的受伤的婴儿抱在怀里，他面前升起了一幅阴森可怖的前景。

第二天，马丽纳看上去倒没什么事。艾米莉发誓以后滴酒不沾了，这以后的几个星期里，她是清醒的、冷静的，却又是萎靡不振的。接着，慢慢地，她又开始了——她倒不喝威士忌与杜松子酒——而是大量地喝啤酒、雪利酒或是各种各样古里古怪的酒。有一次他打开一只帽盒，发现里面都是薄荷酒的空瓶。马丁找到一个可靠的女佣，她把家务事料理得挺好。这个弗尔吉也是从亚拉巴马州来的，马丁没敢告诉艾米莉纽约用人的工资一般是多少。艾米莉现在喝酒完全是偷偷摸摸的了，总是在他回家之前就停住不喝。喝酒的反应一般也是几乎察觉不出——只不过动作有点迟缓，眼皮有点沉滞。不像话的时候，像这次做出辣椒烤面包这样的事，倒也不多，弗尔吉若是在，马丁倒可以不用担心。不过，他的生活中总是永远潜伏着一种焦虑感，总有一种不定什么时候会出现灾祸的预感在威胁着他。

“马丽纳！”马丁喊道，回想起那个事故，他就感到害怕，他需要见到女儿好让自己安心。女孩后来再没受到什么伤害，但是当父亲的却越来越疼爱她了，现在，她和哥哥一起走进厨房。马丁继续准备晚饭。他打开了一个做汤菜的罐头，又往煎锅里放下去两块排骨。接着他在餐桌边坐下来，把他的小马丽纳抱在膝头上，让她“骑马马”。安弟一边看着他们，一边把手指伸进嘴去摇晃那颗活动已有一个星期的牙齿。

“见了糖就不要命的安弟！”马丁说，“那颗牙还没掉吗？走近点，让爸爸好好瞧瞧。”

“我有一根绳子，可以用来拔牙。”那孩子从兜里掏出一根乱成一团的线，“弗尔吉说，把它系在牙齿上，另一头拴在门把上，使劲一关门，牙就会掉了。”

马丁摸出一块干净的手帕，隔着手帕仔细地摸了摸那颗松动的牙齿。“这颗牙今天晚上就会从咱们安弟的嘴里掉下来的。不然，咱们家可要长出一棵牙齿树来了。”他说。

“什么树？”

“牙齿树呀，”马丁说，“你咬什么东西，一不当心，就会把那颗牙齿咽到肚子里去。牙齿在倒霉的安弟肚子里生根长大，变成一棵牙齿树，上面挂满了又尖又怪的小牙齿。”

“我不信，爸爸，”安弟说。可是他却用十分肮脏的大拇指和食指去紧紧捏住那颗牙齿，“从来没有那种树的。我根本没见过。”

“你应该说根本没有那种树，我从来没见到过。”

马丁身子突然发僵，艾米莉从楼上走下来了。他听着她那不稳地探索着的脚步声，不由得惊惧地搂住他的儿子。等艾米莉走进房间，他从她的动作和阴郁的脸色看出她又倒过雪利酒瓶了。她使劲地拉开一个个抽屉，拿餐具，铺餐桌。

“模样！”她大着舌头含混不清地说道，“你这样跟我说话。别以为我能忘得了。你说的每一句恶毒的谎言我都是记住的。别一厢情愿以为我会忘记。”

“艾米莉！”他恳求道，“孩子们——”

“孩子们——一点儿不错！别以为我没看穿你的阴谋诡计。在楼下这儿收买我的孩子的心，让他们不喜欢我。别以为我看不透，不明白。”

“艾米莉！我求求你——请你回到楼上去。”

“好让你唆使我的孩子——我亲生的孩子——”两颗大大的泪珠迅速地顺着她的脸颊流了下来，“想唆使我的宝贝儿子，我的小安弟，来反对他的亲妈妈。”

艾米莉带着酒醉后的冲动，对着吓呆的男孩跪了下来。她双手支在孩子肩膀上以平衡自己的身体。“听我说，我的好安弟，你不会听你爸爸跟你说的那些胡说八道的吧？你不会相信的，是吧？告诉我，安弟，我没下楼那会儿你爸爸跟你说什么来着？”那孩子不知该怎么办，就用眼光去探索他爸爸的脸。“告诉我，妈妈想知道呢。”

“说那棵牙齿树。”

“什么？”

男孩重复了那三个字，接着，艾米莉又用不可言状的恐怖语气，把那三个字念了一遍。“牙齿树！”她身子晃了晃，又重新抓紧了孩子的肩膀。“我真不知道你们说的是什么。不过，听着，安弟，妈妈没什么不对头，不是吗？”眼泪像泉水似的从她脸上淌下来，安弟往后退缩，想离她远一些，因为他感到害怕。艾米莉抓住桌子边，支撑着站了起来。

“瞧！你已经做到让孩子不喜欢我了。”

马丽纳哭起来了，马丁把她搂在自己怀里。

“行啊，你可以疼你的女儿。你打一开始就有偏心眼。这我也不管，不过你至少不要来影响我的乖儿子。”

安弟一点点挨近他的父亲，碰碰他的腿。“爸爸，”他哭声哭气地喊道。

马丁把两个孩子送到楼梯口，“安弟，你带马丽纳先上楼，爸爸一会儿就来。”

“那么妈妈呢？”男孩悄悄地问。

“妈妈一会儿就会好的。别担心。”

艾米莉趴在餐桌上啜泣，她的脸埋在臂弯里。马丁盛来一碗汤，放在她的面前。她那刺耳的抽泣声让他心烦，她感情这样冲动，先不说原因是什么，倒勾起了他的一丝柔情。他不由自主地伸出手去按在她的黑头发上。“坐起来，把这碗汤喝了吧。”她仰起头来看他，那张脸变得纯洁了，像是在恳求什么。孩子的退缩或是马丁的抚摸使她情绪上有了改变。

“马——丁，”她抽噎地说，“我真不好意思。”

“把汤喝了吧。”

她听从了他的话，一边抽噎，一边一口一口地喝着。喝完第二碗之后，她顺从地让马丁领着回到自己的卧室去。她现在很柔顺，能够控制住自己的感情了。他替她把睡衣放在床上，正准备走开，这时一阵新的悲哀、新的醉意又袭上了艾米莉的心头。

“他扭了开去。我的安弟瞧瞧我，把头扭开去了。”

不耐烦与疲倦使他的声音变僵硬了，可他还是小心翼翼地说：“你忘了安弟还不过是一个小小孩——他是弄不清楚这场闹剧是怎么一回事的。”

“我方才胡闹了吗？噢，马丁，我是在孩子们的面前胡闹了吗？”

她那惊恐的面容使他既感到可怜又感到可笑，虽然这种感情是违反他的意愿的，“别往心里去了。穿上睡衣上床睡吧。”

“我的孩子不要我了。安弟瞅瞅他的妈妈，把脸扭了开去。孩子们——”

她又被酒后间歇性忧郁症控制住了。马丁一边走出房间一边说道：“看在上帝的分上快睡吧。孩子们明天一早就会忘掉的。”

他说这句话的时候连自己都不大相信。这个不愉快的场面会那么容易从记忆中抹掉吗——还是会根深蒂固地隐藏在潜意识里到多年之后又浮上来起腐蚀作用呢？马丁也不清楚，但是这后一种可能使他的心沉了下去。他想到了艾米莉，预计到第二天早晨她醒来之后又会出现的羞辱感：支离破碎的印象，什么都记不清，一片黑暗混沌，然而又会泛出几个清晰的景象。她会给纽约的办公室打去两个——甚至是三四个电话。马丁也预见到自己会羞愧难当，他唯恐办公室里别的人会察觉出什么迹象。他感到她的女秘书很久以前就已发现他的苦恼了，而且暗暗地在怜悯自己。他一时之间憎恨和不满起自己的命运来了。他恨他的妻子。

他一走进孩子们的卧室马上把身后的门关上，这个晚上他还是第一次获得安全感。马丽纳朝地板上倒下去，又自己爬起来，嘴巴里喊道：“爸爸，瞧我呀，”说完又倒下去，再爬起来，一遍又一遍玩这种跌倒与叫人的游戏。安弟坐在小椅子里，还在摇晃那颗牙齿。马丁往澡盆里放水，在洗脸盆里洗了手，然后把男孩叫到浴室里来。

“咱们再来瞧瞧那颗牙齿。”马丁坐在马桶上，把安弟挟在双膝之间。孩子张大嘴，马丁捏住那颗牙齿。一晃，使劲一拧，那颗有珍珠光泽的乳齿就给拔下来了。安弟的脸上在同时间里露出了恐惧、诧异以及喜悦种种表情。他积了一口吐沫，吐在洗脸盆里，“瞧，爸爸！有血。马丽纳！”

马丁喜欢替他的孩子洗澡，他难以言喻地喜欢他们赤条条站在水里时那柔嫩、光滑的身体。艾米莉说他偏心眼，其实这种指责是不公正的。在马丁给他儿子那细瘦的小男孩的身子抹肥皂的时候，他觉得爱儿子已经到了极点，再进一步都是不可能的了。不过他也承认他对两个孩子的感情质地上是有所不同的。他对女儿的爱更加严肃，带着怜悯的成分，有一种接近痛苦的温存感。他给小男孩起了各种各样亲昵的外号，这些都是平日奇思怪想的结果——对小女孩，他始终只叫她马丽纳，但是他吐出这几个字时，他的声音本身就是一种温存的抚触。马丁用浴巾把小娃娃胖嘟嘟的肚子上的水擦干。孩子洗过澡后，小脸蛋像花瓣一样鲜嫩，也一样招人疼爱。

“我要把牙齿放在我的枕头底下。明天早上我会拿到一枚两毛五的硬币的。”

“怎么会呢？”

“你怎么不知道，爸爸。强尼上回那颗牙就拿到了两毛五。”

“是谁放在那儿的呢？”马丁问，“我一向以为是仙女在半夜放的。而且我小时候大家拿到的都只是一毛钱。”

“在幼儿园里大家都说是两毛五。”

“到底是谁放的呢？”

“是孩子们的爸爸妈妈。”安弟说，“就是你！”

马丁把马丽纳的被子用别针别好。女儿已经睡着了。她的呼吸很浅，几乎让人觉不出来。马丁弯下身去吻了吻她的前额，又吻了吻她睡梦中摊开在脑袋两侧的两只手掌。

“晚安，安弟老弟。”

回答他的仅仅是一声充满睡意的哼哼。过了一会儿，马丁摸出他的零钱，在孩子枕下塞进去一枚两毛五的硬币。他给房间里留了一盏过夜用的小灯。

马丁在厨房里东摸摸西弄弄，想给自己做一顿拖迟了的晚餐。这时，他忽然想到孩子们一回也没有提到他们的母亲，也没有提到他们肯定不能理解的那次争吵。他们都为当前发生的小事吸引住了——牙齿啦、洗澡啦、硬币啦——飞逝的儿童时代里充满了许多这样微不足道的小插曲，就像一条水流很急的浅滩里回旋着许多落叶，而成年人的那些莫测高深的谜倒搁浅在河滩上，被遗忘了。马丁感谢上帝这样的巧妙安排。

可是他自己的愤怒，暂时被压下去隐藏起来的愤怒，却又涌上心头了。他的青春被一个废物般的酗酒女人糟蹋掉了，连他的男子汉凌云气概也无形中受到了损害。还有那两个孩子，等他们混沌不懂事的阶段过去——一两年之后，情况又将如何呢？他双肘支撑在桌子上，胡乱地吃着，一点也没尝出食物的滋味。真相总是掩盖不住的——要不了多久，办公室里和镇上就会有各种流言蜚语了。人家会说他的妻子是个不检点的女人，不检点。于是，他和孩子们的前途肯定会越来越暗淡，越来越不好过了。

马丁推开椅子，气鼓鼓地大步走进起居室。他拿起一本书，他的眼睛顺着一行行字往下滑，可是他脑子里却映现出一幅幅悲惨的图景：他看见自己的孩子淹死在河里，人们在大街上对着他妻子的脊背点点戳戳。到他去歇息时，这沉郁、巨大的愤怒像一大团铁块压在他的心头，他拖着沉重的脚步爬上楼去。

卧室里一片漆黑，只有浴室半开的门里漏进来一道灯光。马丁轻轻地脱掉衣服。逐渐逐渐地，不知怎么的，他情绪上起了一些变化。他的妻子睡着了，她那安静的呼吸声在房间里轻轻地响着。她那双高跟鞋连同两只随手一扔的长袜在默默地向他发出哀诉。她的内衣乱七八糟地搭在椅子上。马丁拾起了她的紧身褡和柔滑的丝乳罩，拿在手里，呆呆地站了好一会儿。这个晚上第一回，他细细地端详着他的妻子。他的眼光停留在她那秀美的前额上，那两道细眉稍稍弯起的地方。这样的前额已经传给了马丽纳，还有那微微翘起的细巧的鼻子。至于他的儿子，高高的颧骨和尖下巴颏是从妈妈那儿来的。她胸脯高高的，腰肢很细，曲线很美。在马丁凝视着他平静地熟睡了的妻子时，他那股积了好久的怨气不知不觉地消失了。一切责怪她、埋怨她的想法都跑到远远的地方去了。马丁熄掉浴室的灯，打开窗户。他小心翼翼地上床，留神着不去吵醒艾米莉。他凭借着月光又看了他妻子一眼。他的手向身边的身体伸过去，在他深情而又复杂的爱里，既混杂着哀伤，也存在着欲念。

树，石，云

那天早上下着雨，天色仍然很昏暗。男孩来到街车咖啡馆[29]时该派送的报纸都快送完了，他想进去喝一杯咖啡。那是个通宵营业的咖啡馆，老板是个刻薄小气的人，名叫利奥。从阴冷、空旷的街上进来，这咖啡馆倒显得友好而明亮了。柜台旁有两个大兵、三个棉纺厂里来的纺纱工，角落里还弯身坐着一个人，鼻子和半张脸都埋在了一只盛啤酒的大玻璃缸子里。男孩头戴一顶飞行员用的那种款式的头盔。他走进咖啡馆时松开了下巴底下的扣子，将右边的耳罩翻到他粉红色小耳朵的上面。他喝咖啡时经常会有人友好地跟他聊上几句。可是今天早上利奥都没正眼看他一眼，其他的人也没在聊天。他付了钱正要离开咖啡馆，这时有个声音叫住了他。

“小子！嗨，小子！”

他转过身子，在角落里的那个人勾起手指并朝他点点头。这人已经把脸从啤酒缸子里伸了出来，似乎一下子变得非常快乐。那人身量高高的，脸色苍白，鼻子很大，头发是淡褪的橙红色。

“嗨，小子！”

男孩朝他走去。他是个大约十二岁、没长够个儿的男孩，因为经常背沉重的报纸口袋，一只肩膀总挺得比另一只略高一些。他的脸扁扁的，长有雀斑，他的眼睛是小孩子通常会有的那种圆眼睛。“怎么啦，先生？”

那人将一只手按住报童的双肩，接着又捏住孩子的下巴颏，把他的脸缓慢地从一边扭到另一边。男孩不安地往后退缩。

“嗨！这算啥个名堂嘛？”

男孩的声音很尖，咖啡馆里突然变得格外安静。

那人慢条斯理地说：“我爱你。”

所有在柜台边上的人都大笑起来。男孩怒目圆睁往边上退缩，不知道该怎么办才好。他把目光投向柜台上方去看利奥，利奥只是带着漠然、疲惫的冷笑回看他。孩子倒也想一笑置之。可是那个人很认真而且很忧郁。

“我可没有想耍弄你的意思，小子，”他说，“坐下来陪我喝杯啤酒嘛。我有些事情要解释。”

报童用眼角余光小心翼翼地去询问柜台上的那些人，想知道自己应该怎么办。可是他们都已重新低下了头，自顾自地喝啤酒吃早餐，一点儿也不注意他。利奥往柜台上放了一杯咖啡和一小缸奶油。

“他是张小牌。”利奥说。

报童悄悄地坐到高脚凳上去。在翻起的耳罩下，他那只耳朵很小也很红。那人很清醒地对他点了点头。“这很重要。”他说。接着他把手伸到后面裤兜去摸出一样东西，放在手心里举起给男孩看。

“你认真好好看看。”他说。

男孩瞪大眼睛，可是也没觉得有什么值得细看的。那人捏在他脏兮兮大手掌里的是一张照片。里面是张女人的脸，可是已经模糊了，只有她戴的帽子和穿的衣服显得很清楚。

“看到了吧？”那人问道。

男孩点点头，那人又往掌心里放了另外一张照片。那个女的穿了游泳衣站在沙滩上。游泳衣使她的肚子显得很大，那正是会惹人注意的主要之处。

“好好看过了吧？”他把身子靠过来，终于问道，“你见到过她没有？”

男孩坐着一动不动，眼睛斜斜地瞥向那个人，“我一点印象都没有。”

“很好。”那人对着照片吹了口气，把它们放回到兜里去，“是我原来的老婆。”

“死啦？”男孩问。

那人慢慢地摇了摇头。他噘起了嘴，仿佛是要吹口哨，不过仅仅是拖长了声音说：“不噢——我会解释的。”

那人面前柜台上的啤酒是盛在一只棕色大玻璃缸子里的。他不把缸子端起来喝，却是低下头，让脸悬在缸子上空，在那里停留了一阵子。接着他用双手托住缸底，翘起一点点，啜饮起来。

“总有一个晚上，你会把你那只大鼻子浸在缸子里睡过去淹死的，”利奥说，“大名鼎鼎的流浪爷们儿让啤酒憋死。这倒算得上是一种绝妙死法呢。”

报童试着给利奥递眼色。他趁那人没在看的时候做了个怪脸，用嘴不发声地问道：“醉了吧？”可是利奥仅仅是扬了扬眉毛，旋即便转过身在铁烤架上放了几片粉红色的咸肉。那人把啤酒缸从面前推开，坐直身子，在柜台上对握起自己那双松松散散有点走形的手来。在看着报童的时候他的脸很忧郁。他眼睛倒是不眨，可是时不时，他的眼帘会自然而然无力地垂下来，盖住他那双灰绿色的眼睛。天快亮了，男孩把报袋的分量从一个肩膀转移到另一个肩膀。

“我此刻在讲的是爱情问题，”那人说，“对我来说那是一门科学。”

男孩的半个屁股已经从高脚凳上滑下。可是那人举起了一根食指，他身上自有一种气势，吸引住了男孩，使得他无法走开。

“十二年前我娶了照片里的那个女人。她当我老婆当了一年，九个月，三天和两个晚上。我爱她。是的……”他清了清他那模糊不清和越来越语无伦次的嗓子，又开始说道，“我爱她。我以为她也爱我。我是个铁路工程师。但凡家庭里所有的舒适与奢华她都能享受到。我脑子里从来都没想到她会感到不满足。你知道出了什么事吗？”

“呃哼呃！”利奥的嗓子眼里发出了这样的声音。

那人眼睛一刻也没有离开男孩的脸，“她离开了我。有一天晚上我回到家里，屋子里空空如也，她跑了。她离开我了。”

“跟了一个男人？”孩子问道。

那人轻轻地把手掌放在了柜台上，“那是自然，小子。一个女人是不会独自一人那样跑掉的。”

咖啡馆里很安静，外面街上，霏霏细雨在黑暗中无休无止地下着。利奥用他长叉子的尖齿去压了压烤架上的咸肉，“这么说你追寻这骚娘们都追了有十一个年头了。你这没头苍蝇似的老流氓！”

那人头一次把眼光转向利奥，“别这么庸俗好不好。而且我也没在跟你说话。”他又回过头来和孩子说话，用的是一种推心置腹和保守机密的低声，“咱们别理他。好不好？”

报童疑虑重重地点了点头。

“情况是这样的，”那人继续往下说，“我是个对许多事情都很敏感的人。在我的一生里，一件接着一件的事都让我很有感触。月光啦。一个漂亮姑娘的腿啦。一件接着一件。可是问题是：当我喜欢上一样东西的时候就会有一种特殊的感觉，仿佛它在我身体内部分崩离析似的。没有一件是自己走向终结或是结合到别的东西里去的。女人吗？我也并不是没有我的份额的。但是都一样。到后来就在我心中瓦解了。我曾是一个从来没有过爱的人。”

他非常缓慢地合上眼帘，那动作很像是戏演完了一场大幕一点点垂下来似的。等他重新开口说话时他的声音变得很激动，字句吐出来也很快——他两只大大、松松的耳朵的耳垂似乎都颤动了起来。

“后来我遇到了这个女人。我当时五十一岁，她呢，总说自己三十岁。我是在一个加油站遇到她的，没过三天，我们就结婚了。你知道那是什么感觉吗？我真是没法跟你说。我唯一的感觉就是整个人被吸引在这个女人的周围。我心中再也不是分崩离析的了，而是让她给拾掇得服服帖帖的了。”

那人突然停住话头，抚摩起自己的长鼻子来。他的声调降落下来，成为一种恒定、埋怨的陪衬音：“这件事我还是没有解释清楚。所发生的事情是这样的：我以前心中总有些美好的感情和小小的放荡情趣。这个女人对我的心灵来说有点儿像是一条装配线。我的一个个小部件从她那里通过，结果我就变成了一个整体。你现在明白我的意思了吧？”

“她叫什么名字？”男孩问道。

“哦，”他说，“我是管她叫多多的。不过这是不相干的。”

“你就没有想法子把她弄回来吗？”

那人似乎没有听见，“在这样的情况下，你可以想象得出，她一出走我会有什么感觉了。”

利奥把咸肉从炉架上拨出来，将两片肉夹进一只小圆面包。他有一张灰灰的脸，一双细眼睛像是用刀在脸上划出来的，鼻翼夹得很紧，还泛出浅浅的蓝色阴影。一个纺织工人做了个手势要添加咖啡，利奥便给他续上。这一续可不是免费的。这纺纱工每天都在这儿吃早餐，利奥对他的顾客了解得愈透，便对他们益发刻薄。他咬了一小口自己的夹肉面包，仿佛是把一股怨气往自己肚子里咽似的。

“这么说你再也没能逮住她？”

男孩不知道该怎么看这个人，他那张孩子脸显露出在好奇与怀疑之间难以确定的那种表情。他接手这条送报路线还不太久，在黑暗古怪的拂晓时分进入市区，对他来说还是件很陌生的事。

“是的，”那人说道，“我采取了一系列的措施让她回来。我到一些地方去转了转，想找到她的踪迹。我去了塔尔萨，那儿有她娘家的亲人。又去了莫比尔。我去了她向我提到过的每一个市镇，我也追踪过以往跟她有过关系的每一个男人。塔尔萨、亚特兰大、芝加哥、奇霍、孟菲斯……差不多有两年，我走遍全国以便找到她这个人。”

“可是一对狗男女就是生生从地球表面上消失了！”利奥说。

“别听他的，”那人很机密地对男孩说，“而且也干脆把那两年的事忘掉。那不重要。重要的是在第三年上我开始遇上了一件奇怪事儿。”

“什么事儿？”男孩问。

那人把身子朝前弯了弯，侧起酒缸，准备吸一口啤酒。可是当他的脸俯临缸子时他的鼻孔轻轻地翕动起来，他闻出啤酒已经走气，便不喝了。“首先，爱是一件奇异的事情。起初我一心想的仅仅是要把她找回来。那是一种狂热。可是时间一点点过去，我试着去记起她。你知道发生了什么事？”

“不知道。”孩子说。

“当我在一张床上躺下，试着去想起她的时候，我的脑子变得一片空白。我看不到她。我也曾取出她的照片来看。没有用。什么用处都没有。一片空白。你能想象这样的情况吗？”

“嗨，麦克！”利奥朝柜台的另一头喊道，“你能想象这傻瓜蛋的脑袋会成为一片空白吗！”

慢慢地，仿佛是在扇走苍蝇似的，那个人挥动起了他的一只手。他绿眼珠的视线凝聚起来，集中在报童的那张扁平的小脸上。

“可是人行道上突然出现的一片玻璃或是投币唱机里播放的一段通俗音乐、夜晚墙上的一个影子，这些，我倒能够记得。它可能发生在一条街道上，我会哭喊，会用头去撞路灯柱子。你懂我的意思吧。”

“一片玻璃……”孩子说。

“任何东西。我会四下乱转，却控制不住自己如何与何时能想起她。你以为你能树立起一道防护罩，可是回忆不是面对面朝一个人走来的——它是从侧边绕过来的。我听从我见到与听到的一切东西的摆布。突然，不再是我在全国上下左右篦梳那样地细细查找她，而是她开始在我的心灵里追逐我了。是她在追逐我，你可听好了！而且是在我的心灵里。”

男孩终于提出了一个问题：“你当时是在美国的哪个地方？”

“哦唷，”那人呻吟起来了，“我那时是个病人。得的很像是天花。我承认，小子，我酒喝得很凶。我跟人私通。我犯下了种种对我有吸引力的罪恶。我承认这些，连自己都很看不起自己，可是我还是必须承认。我回忆起那个阶段的时候，这一切都在我脑子凝结起来了，那真可怕。”

那人把头低下，在柜台上磕碰他的脑门。有几秒钟，他一直采取这样低着头的姿势，他青筋毕露的后脖颈上满是红荆豆色的头发。他那双有着扭曲的长手指的手，掌心紧贴着对握在一起，姿势很像是一个祈祷者。接着那人伸直了身子，他在微笑。突然，他的脸变得明亮了，颤抖着，显得苍老了。

“那件事发生在第五个年头，”他说，“而我的科学就是由此开始的。”

利奥的嘴扭出了一个淡淡的转瞬即逝的微笑。“行了，咱们这拨当年的小伙子谁也不会重新变得年轻了。”他说。他心中蓦地起了无名火，便把手里那块抹布揉成一团，狠狠地往地上一扔。“你这肮脏邋遢的老罗密欧！”

“究竟发生了什么事嘛？”男孩问道。

老头的声音既高亢也很清晰。“平静。”他回答道。

“什么？”

“很难科学地解释清楚，小子，”他说，“我想合乎逻辑的解释是，长时期以来她和我都想逃离对方，到头来两人竟缠结在了一块，于是便都停下来不动了。于是便是平静。一种奇特而美丽的空白。那是在波特兰，春天时分，每天下午都下雨。整个夜晚我仅仅是在黑暗中躺在床上。科学就是那样降临到我的身上的。”

街车咖啡馆的窗子让拂晓的天光映得蓝幽幽的。两个大兵付了啤酒钱，推开了门——两人离开之前其中的一个梳了梳自己的头发，擦了擦自己的绑腿。三个纺织工人一声不吭，闷头吃自己的早餐。利奥的钟在墙上发出嘀嗒嘀嗒的声音。

“情况是这样的。好好给我听着。对于爱我作过思考，也理清了思路。我弄明白了我们之间有什么不对头。男人初次堕入爱河。那么他们爱上的是什么呢？”

男孩柔软的嘴唇稍稍张开了一些，但是他没有回答。

“一个女人，”那个老人说，“男人不懂科学，没有任何思想可以依靠，便按照这片土地上最最危险和神圣的经验行事。他们爱上了一个女人。是不是这么回事，小子？”

“可不是吗。”男孩含混地应答了一句。

“他们从错误的一头开始爱恋。他们在高潮时开始。你能想象那有多么悲惨吗？你知道男人应该怎样爱恋吗？”

老人把手伸过去，一把揪住男孩皮夹克的领子，将他轻轻摇晃了几下，那双绿眼睛一眨不眨，很严肃地朝底下盯看。

“小子，你可知道爱应该怎么开始吗？”

男孩蜷缩着身子坐着，倾听着，一动也不动。他慢慢地把头摇了摇。老人把身子朝他靠得更紧，用耳语说道：

“一棵树。一块岩石。一朵云。”

外面街上还在下雨，那种灰蒙蒙无休无止的细雨。工厂发出汽笛声，召唤工人去上六点钟的班，三个纺纱工付了账离开了。现在咖啡馆里除了利奥、老人与小报童再也没有别人。

“在波特兰，天气跟现在这儿的差不多，”他说，“就在这个时候我的科学开始出现了。我苦苦思索，小心翼翼地开了个头。我会在街上捡到点儿什么把它带回家。我买了一条金鱼，于是便集中注意力研究金鱼，我爱上了金鱼。我研究透了一件东西又去研究另外的一件。一天一天过去，我技术上也一点点地熟练了。在从波特兰去圣迭戈的路上——”

“哦，别说了！”利奥突然尖声叫起来，“别说了！别说了！”

老人仍然捏住孩子夹克的衣领，他整个人都颤抖起来，他的脸很一本正经，变得熠熠生辉和野气十足。“到现在已经有六个年头了，我一直是单独旅行，并且建立起我的科学体系。现在我是一位大师了，小子。我可以爱任何东西了。现在我甚至都想也不用想了。我见到一条街上挤满了人，于是一道美丽的光便进入我的心中。我看着一只鸟飞行在空中。或者是我在路上遇见一个旅人。一切东西，小子。还有任何一个人。所有的陌生人他们全都为我所爱！你可明白我的这种科学意味着什么吗？”

男孩僵僵地支撑着，他的两只手紧紧地抵在柜台的边缘上。最后他问道：“你最后真的找到那位太太了吗？”

“什么？你说什么哪，小子？”

“我是说，”男孩怯生生地问道，“你有没有重新爱上一个女人？”

老人松开了紧紧捏在男孩衣领上的那只手。他的身子转开了去，那双绿眼睛头一回出现了蒙眬与不集中的神色。他把放在柜台上的缸子举起来，把黄色的啤酒喝了下去。他的脑袋在慢慢地从一边抖动到另一边。接下去他终于回答道：“不，小子。你明白吧，这是我的科学里最后的一个步骤。我往前推进时是非常小心的。再说我也没有完全准备好呢。”

“好嘛！”利奥说，“真有你的呀！”

老人站在开着的门口。“记住了。”他说。在充满曙色那灰暗潮湿光线的门框前，他显得特别枯瘦、邋遢和衰老。不过他的笑容却很灿烂。“记住了，我是爱你的呀，”他说，同时还最后一次点了点头。门在他身后轻轻关上了。

好久好久男孩都没有开口说话。他把额上的刘海往前压压直，又把一只脏兮兮的细细的食指在空杯子内沿刮了一圈。接着他问道，眼睛并没有在看利奥：

“他方才是喝醉了吧？”

“没有。”利奥生硬地说道。

男孩把他清脆的嗓音提高了一些，“那么他是个吸毒的？”

“不是的。”

男孩抬起眼睛看着利奥，他那张扁扁的小脸狠巴巴的，声音又急又尖。“那他是疯了吧？你说他是不是一个疯子？”报童的声音里突然之间充满了疑惑，“利奥？是还是不是？”

可是利奥无意回答他。利奥经营通宵咖啡馆都有十四个年头了，他已把自己看成是判断疯癫的专家了。黑夜里流入到咖啡馆来的既有本地人也有外来的流浪汉。什么怪人他不曾见过？可是他不想搭理这咄咄逼人的小毛孩子。他把那张苍白的脸一板，连一声都不吭。

男孩只好把帽盔的右耳罩放下来，在转身走开时他扔下了一句话，在他看来这是唯一不会遭到嘲笑和轻视的那句：

“他走过的地方肯定不会少。”

译后记

《伤心咖啡馆之歌》（THE BALLAD OF THE SAD CAFÉ）是美国女作家卡森·麦卡勒斯（Carson McCullers，1917—1967）于一九五一年五月出版的小说集。出书前，集子里的几篇作品都在《纽约人》《女士》《小说》等有影响的刊物上发表过。女作家也早就因为一九四零年出版的长篇小说《心是孤独的猎手》、一九四六年出版的长篇小说《婚礼的成员》而获得盛名。前者出版时麦卡勒斯才二十三岁。

我是在“文革”前读到麦卡勒斯的这本小说集的。记得在学部文学研究所的图书馆里，我见到企鹅版此书封三所附的借书单上，签着一个名字。那是上一位也是唯一的一位借书者的名字。出于对这位先生的崇敬与好奇，我把书借出来一口气读完，并留下了深刻的印象。改革开放后，几个喜欢美国文学的人聚集在一起，策划出版一本能反映当代美国文学状况的短篇小说集，主要的方法是由发起者每人提供一篇。我当时自然而然便想起了《伤心咖啡馆之歌》。译出交稿，集稿者汤永宽先生正在筹办《外国文艺》杂志。承他厚意，把我的译文收进一九七九年出版的该刊创刊号，并且列为首篇。《当代美国短篇小说集》接着也出版了，成为当时的文学青年能够读到的为数不多的几本书中的一本。也许是因为这样的原因，不少人至今还能记得这篇作品。后来我又应朱虹先生之约，译出集子中的另一篇作品《家庭困境》。

时光飞逝，四分之一个世纪过去。在此期间，我忙于别的事务，但偶尔也会想起麦卡勒斯与爱密利亚小姐，并且很惋惜未能将全书译出。后来出版翻译年代较近的外国作品必须购买原书版权了，有几家出版社在我怂恿下也试着去办过，惜乎都未有结果。这次上海三联书店购买到麦卡勒斯两部长篇小说的版权，也顺利出版了。编者接下去自然想让麦卡勒斯的中短篇集也一并由他们出版。对此，我乐观其成，在他们事先与我联系时便答应版权购得后一定抽出时间翻译。

这次抽出两三个月的时间翻译了以前未译的五篇作品，又将旧译细细读过一遍，但除改了一两处误植与语言表达方式外，别的均未加改动。我起初还暗暗窃喜，心想区区近三十年前的翻译似乎还经得起时间的考验嘛。后来一想，还是说明自己没有长进，这才是一件真正可悲哀的事。傅雷先生于一九三七年到一九四一年在商务印书馆出版了他译的《约翰·克利斯朵夫》，却因不满译文风格，在二十世纪五十年代初予以重译并交平明出版社出版。可我却没有更高层次的“慧眼”否定旧译，像许多大画家那样来一次“衰年变法”。这不是悲哀又是什么？

不过经过几个月的努力，我总算完成了一件中断多年的工程，而没有使它成为“烂尾楼”。我像一名因故延宕的朝山进香者，终于还是在偶像前还清了多年的心愿。作为一个普通的文学绍介者，这也许已经能对得起作者、读者与自己了吧。

Wunderkind

She came into the living-room, her music satchel plopping against her winter-stockinged legs and her other arm weighted down with school books, and stood for a moment listening to the sounds from the studio. A soft procession of piano chords and the tuning of a violin.Then Mister Bilderbach called out to her in his chunky, guttural tones：

“That you, Bienchen?”

As she jerked off her mittens she saw that her fingers were twitching to the motions of the fugue she had practiced that morning.“Yes，”she answered.“It's me；”

“I，”the voice corrected.“Just a moment.”

She could hear Mister Lafkowitz talking-his words spun out in a silky, unintelligible hum. A voice almost like a woman's, she thought, compared to Mister Bilderbach's.Restlessness scattered her attention.She fumbled with her geometry book and Le Voyage de Monsieur Perrichon before putting them on the table.She sat down on the sofa and began to take her music from the satchel.Again she saw her hands-the quivering tendons that stretched down from her knuckles, the sore finger tip capped with curled, dingy tape.The sight sharpened the fear that had begun to torment her for the past few months.

Noiselessly she mumbled a few phrases of encouragement to herself. A good lesson-a good lesson-like it used to be.Her lips closed as she heard the stolid sound of Mister Bilderbach's footsteps across the foor of the studio and the creaking of the door as it slidopen.

For a moment she had the peculiar feeling that during most of the ffteen years of her life she had been looking at the face and shoulders that jutted from behind the door, in a silence disturbed only by the muted, blank plucking of a violin string. Mister Bilderbach.Her teacher, Mr.Bilderbach.The quick eyes behind the horn-rimmed glasses；the light, thin hair and the narrow face beneath；the lips full and loose shut and the lower one pink and shining from the bites of his teeth；the forked veins in his temples throbbing plainly enough to be observed across the room.

“Aren't you a little early?”he asked, glancing at the clock on the mantelpiece that had pointed to five minutes of twelve for a month.“Josef's in here. We're running over a little sonatino by someone he knows.”

“Good，”she said, trying to smile.“I'll listen.”She could see her fngers sinking powerless into a blur of piano keys. She felt tired-felt that if he looked at her much longer her hands might tremble.

He stood uncertain, halfway in the room. Sharply his teeth pushed down on his bright, swollen lips.“Hungry, Bienchen?”he asked.“There's some apple cake Anna made, and milk.”

“I'll wait till afterward，”she said.“Thanks.”

“After you finish with a very fine lesson-eh?”His smile seemed to crumble at the corners.

There was a sound from behind him in the studio and Mister Lafkowitz pushed at the other panel of the door and stood beside him.

“Frances?”he said, smiling.“And how is the work coming now?”

Without meaning to, Mister Lafkowitz always made her feel clumsy and overgrown. He was such a small man himself, with a weary look when he was not holding his violin.His eyebrows curved high above his sallow, Jewish face as though asking a question, but the lids of his eyes drowsed languorous and indifferent.Todayhe seemed distracted.She watched him come into the room for no apparent purpose, holding his pearl-tipped bow in his still fngers, slowly gliding the white horsehair through a chalky piece of rosin.His eyes were sharp bright slits today and the linen handkerchief that fowed down from his collar darkened the shadows beneath them.

“I gather you're doing a lot now，”smiled Mister Lafkowitz, although she had not yet answered the question.

She looked at Mister Bilderbach. He turned away.His heavy shoulders pushed the door open wide so that the late afternoon sun came through the window of the studio and shafted yellow over the dusty living-room.Behind her teacher she could see the squat long piano, the window, and the bust of Brahms.

“No，”she said to Mister Lafkowitz，“I'm doing terribly.”Her thin fingers flipped at the pages of her music.“I don't know what's the matter，”she said, looking at Mister Bilderbach's stooped muscular back that stood tense and listening.

Mister Lafkowitz smiled.“There are times, I suppose, when one—”

A harsh chord sounded from the piano.“Don't you think we'd better get on with this?”asked Mister Bilderbach.

“Immediately，”said Mister Lafkowitz, giving the bow one more scrape before starting toward the door. She could see him pick up his violin from the top of the piano.He caught her eye and lowered the instrument.“You've seen the picture of Heime?”

Her fingers curled tight over the sharp corner of the satchel.“What picture?”

“One of Heime in the Musical Courier there on the table. Inside the top cover.”

The sonatina began. Discordant yet somehow simple.Empty but with a sharp-cut style of its own.She reached for the magazine and opened it.

There Heime was-in the left-hand corner. Holding his violin with his fngers hooked down over the strings for a pizzicato.Withhis dark serge knickers strapped neatly beneath his knees, a sweater and rolled collar.It was a bad picture.Although it was snapped in profile his eyes were cut around toward the photographer and his fnger looked as though it would pluck the wrong string.He seemed suffering to turn around toward the picture-taking apparatus.He was thinner-his stomach did not poke out now-but he hadn't changed much in six months.

Heime Israelsky, talented young violinist, snapped while at work in his teacher's studio on Riverside Drive. Young Master Israelsky, who will soon celebrate his fifteenth birthday, has been invited to play the Beethoven Concerto with—

That morning, after she had practiced from six until eight, her dad had made her sit down at the table with the family for breakfast. She hated breakfast；it gave her a sick feeling afterward.She would rather wait and get four chocolate bars with her twenty cents lunch money and munch them during school-bringing up little morsels from the pocket under cover of her handkerchief, stopping dead when the silver paper rattled.But this morning her dad had put a fried egg on her plate and she had known that if it burst-so that the slimy yellow oozed over the white-she would cry.And that had happened.The same feeling was upon her now.Gingerly she laid the magazine back on the table and closed her eyes.

The music in the studio seemed to be urging violently and clumsily for something that was not to be had. After a moment her thoughts drew back from Heime and the concerto and the picture-and hovered around the lesson once more.She slid over on the sofa until she could see plainly into the studio-the two of them playing, peering at the notations on the piano, lustfully drawing out all that was there.

She could not forget the memory of Mister Bilderbach's face as he had stared at her a moment ago. Her hands, still twitching unconsciously to the motions of the fugue, closed over her bony knees.Tired, she was.And with a circling, sinking away feelinglike the one that often came to her just before she dropped off to sleep on the nights when she had over-practiced.Like those weary half-dreams that buzzed and carried her out into their own whirling space.

A Wunderkind-a Wunderkind-a Wunderkind. The syllables would come out rolling in the deep German way, roar against her ears and then fall to a murmur.Along with the faces circling, swelling out in distortion, diminishing to pale blobs—Mister Bilderbach, Mrs.Bilderbach, Heime, Mister Lafkowitz.Around and around in a circle revolving to the guttural Wunderkind.Mister Bilderbach looming large in the middle of the circle, his face urging-with the others around him.

Phrases of music seesawing crazily. Notes she had been practicing falling over each other like a handful of marbles dropped downstairs.Bach, Debussy, Prokofeff, Brahms-timed grotesquely to the far-off throb of her tired body and the buzzing circle.

Sometimes-when she had not worked more than three hours or had stayed out from high school-the dreams were not so confused. The music soared clearly in her mind and quick, precise little memories would come back-clear as the sissy“Age of Innocence”picture Heime had given her after their joint concert was over.

A Wunderkind-a Wunderkind. That was what Mister Bilderbach had called her when, at twelve, she first came to him.Older pupils had repeated the word.

Not that he had ever said the word to her.“Bienchen—”（She had a plain American name but he never used it except when her mistakes were enormous.）“Bienchen，”he would say，“I know it must be terrible. Carrying around all the time a head that thick.Poor Bienchen—”

Mister Bilderbach's father had been a Dutch violinist. His mother was from Prague.He had been born in this country and had spent his youth in Germany.So many times she wished she had not been born and brought up in just Cincinnati.How do you say cheesein German?Mister Bilderbach, what is Dutch for I don't understand you?

The frst day she came to the studio. After she played the whole Second Hungarian Rhapsody from memory.The room graying with twilight.His face as he leaned over the piano.

“Now we begin all over，”he said that first day.“It-playing music-is more than cleverness. If a twelve-year-old girl's fngers cover so many keys to a second-that means nothing.”

He tapped his broad chest and his forehead with his stubby hand.“Here and here. You are old enough to understand that.”He lighted a cigarette and gently blew the first exhalation above her head.“And work-work-work—We will start now with these Bach Inventions and these little Schumann pieces.”His hands moved again-this time to jerk the cord of the lamp behind her and point to the music.“I will show you how I wish this practiced.Listen carefully now.”

She had been at the piano for almost three hours and was very tired. His deep voice sounded as though it had been straying inside her for a long time.She wanted to reach out and touch his muscle-fexed fnger that pointed out the phrases, wanted to feel the gleaming gold band ring and the strong hairy back of his hand.

She had lessons Tuesday after school and on Saturday afternoons. Often she stayed, when the Saturday lesson was fnished, for dinner, and then spent the night and took the streetcar home the next morning.Mrs.Bilderbach liked her in her calm, almost dumb way.She was much different from her husband.She was quiet and fat and slow.When she wasn't in the kitchen, cooking the rich dishes that both of them loved, she seemed to spend all her time in their bed upstairs, reading magazines or just looking with a half-smile at nothing.When they had married in Germany she had been a Lieder singer.She didn't sing anymore（she said it was her throat）.When he would call her in from the kitchen to listen to a pupil she would always smile and say that it was gut, very gut.

When Frances was thirteen it came to her one day that the Bilderbachs had no children. It seemed strange.Once she had been back in the kitchen with Mrs.Bilderbach when he had come striding in from the studio, tense with anger at some pupil who had annoyed him.His wife stood stirring the thick soup until his hand groped out and rested on her shoulder.Then she turned-stood placid-while he folded his arms about her and buried his sharp face in the white, nerveless flesh of her neck.They stood that way without moving.And then his face jerked back suddenly, the anger diminished to a quiet inexpressiveness, and he had returned to the studio.

After she had started with Mister Bilderbach and didn't have time to see anything of the people at high school, Heime had been the only friend of her own age. He was Mister Lafkowitz's pupil and would come with him to Mister Bilderbach's on evenings when she would be there.They would listen to their teachers'playing.And often they themselves went over chamber music together—Mozart sonatas or Bloch.

AWunderkind-a Wunderkind.

Heime was a Wunderkind. He and she, then.

Heime had been playing the violin since he was four. He didn't have to go to school；Mister Lafkowitz's brother, who was crippled, used to teach him geometry and European history and French verbs in the afternoon.When he was thirteen he had as fne a technique as any violinist in Cincinnati-everyone said so.But playing the violin must be easier than the piano.She knew it must be.

Heime always seemed to smell of corduroy pants and the food he had eaten and rosin. Half the time, too, his hands were dirty around the knuckles and the cuffs of his shirts peeped out dingily from the sleeves of his sweater.She always watched his hands when he played-thin only at the joints with the hard little blobs of fesh bulging over the short-cut nails and the babyish-looking crease that showed so plainly in his bowing wrist.

In the dreams, as when she was awake, she could remember theconcert only in a blur. She had not known it was unsuccessful for her until months after.True, the papers had praised Heime more than her.But he was much shorter than she.When they stood together on the stage he came only to her shoulders.And that made a difference with people, she knew.Also, there was the matter of the sonata they played together.The Bloch.

“No, no—I don't think that would be appropriate.”Mister Bilderbach had said when the Bloch was suggested to end the programme.“Now that John Powell thing-the Sonate Virginianesque.”

She hadn't understood then；she wanted it to be the Bloch as much as Mister Lafkowitz and Heime.

Mister Bilderbach had given in. Later, after the reviews had said she lacked the temperament for that type of music, after they called her playing thin and lacking in feeling, she felt cheated.

“That oie oie stuff，”said Mister Bilderbach, crackling the newspapers at her.“Not for you, Bienchen. Leave all that to the Heimes and vitses and skys.”

A Wunderkind. No matter what the papers said, that was what he had called her.

Why was it Heime had done so much better at the concert than she?At school sometimes, when she was supposed to be watching someone do a geometry problem on the blackboard, the question would twist knife-like inside her. She would worry about it in bed, and even sometimes when she was supposed to be concentrating at the piano.It wasn't just the Bloch and her not being Jewish-not entirely.It wasn't that Heime didn't have to go to school and had begun his training so early, either.It was—?

Once she thought she knew.

“Play the Fantasia and Fugue，”Mister Bilderbach had demanded one evening a year ago-after he and Mister Lafkowitz had fnished reading some music together.

The Bach, as she played, seemed to her well done. From thetail of her eye she could see the calm, pleased expression on Mister Bilderbach's face, see his hands rise climactically from the chair arms and then sink down loose and satisfed when the high points of the phrases had been passed successfully.She stood up from the piano when it was over, swallowing to loosen the bands that the music seemed to have drawn around her throat and chest.But—

“Frances—”Mister Lafkowitz had said then, suddenly, looking at her with his thin mouth curved and his eyes almost covered by their delicate lids.“Do you know how many children Bach had?”

She turned to him, puzzled.“A good many. Twenty some odd.”

“Well then—”The corners of his smile etched themselves gently in his pale face.“He could not have been so cold-then.”

Mister Bilderbach was not pleased；his guttural effulgence of German words had Kind in it somewhere. Mister Lafkowitz raised his eyebrows.She had caught the point easily enough, but she felt no deception in keeping her face blank and immature because that was the way Mister Bilderbach wanted her to look.

Yet such things had nothing to do with it. Nothing very much, at least, for she would grow older.Mister Bilderbach understood that, and even Mister Lafkowitz had not meant just what he said.

In the dreams Mister Bilderbach's face loomed out and contracted in the center of the whirling circle. The lips urging softly, the veins in his temples insisting.

But sometimes, before she slept, there were such clear memories；as when she pulled a hole in the heel of her stocking down, so that her shoe would hide it.“Bienchen, Bienchen！”And bringing Mrs. Bilderbach's work-basket in and showing her how it should be darned and not gathered together in a lumpy heap.

And the time she graduated from Junior High.

“What you wear?”asked Mrs. Bilderbach the Sunday morning at breakfast when she told them about how they had practiced to march into the auditorium.

“An evening dress my cousin had last year.”

“Ah—Bienchen！”he said, circling his warm coffee cup with his heavy hands, looking up at her with wrinkles around his laughing eyes.“I bet I know what Bienchen wants—”

He insisted. He would not believe her when she explained that she honestly didn't care at all.

“Like this, Anna，”he said, pushing his napkin across the table and mincing to the other side of the room, swishing his hips, rolling up his eyes behind his horn-rimmed glasses.

The next Saturday afternoon, after her lessons, he took her to the department stores downtown. His thick fingers smoothed over the flmy nets and crackling taffetas that the saleswomen unwound from their bolts.He held colors to her face, cocking his head to one side, and selected pink.Shoes, he remembered too.He liked best some white kid pumps.They seemed a little like old ladies'shoes to her and the Red Cross label in the instep had a charity look.But it really didn't matter at all.When Mrs.Bilderbach began to cut out the dress and ft it to her with pins, he interrupted his lessons to stand by and suggest ruffes around the hips and neck and a fancy rosette on the shoulder.The music was coming along nicely then.Dresses and commencement and such made no difference.

Nothing mattered much except playing the music as it must be played, bringing out the thing that must be in her, practising, practising, playing so that Mister Bilderbach's face lost some of its urging look. Putting the thing into her music that Myra Hess had, and Yehudi Menuhin-even Heime！

What had begun to happen to her four months ago?The notes began springing out with a glib, dead intonation. Adolescence, she thought.Some kids played with promise-and worked and worked until, like her, the least little thing would start them crying, and worn out with trying to get the thing across-the longing thing they felt-something queer began to happen—.But not she！She was like Heime.She had to be.She—

Once it was there for sure. And you didn't lose things like that.A Wunderkind……A Wunderkind.……Of her he said it, rolling the words in the sure, deep German way.And in the dreams even deeper, more certain than ever.With his face looming out at her, and the longing phrases of music mixed in with the zooming, circling round, round, round—AWunderkind.AWunderkind.……

This afternoon Mister Bilderbach did not show Mister Lafkowitz to the front door, as he usually did. He stayed at the piano, softly pressing a solitary note.Listening, Frances watches the violinist wind his scarf about his pale throat.

“A good picture of Heime，”she said, picking up her music.“I got a letter from him a couple of months ago-telling about hearing Schnabel and Huberman and about Carnegie Hall and things to eat at the Russian Tea Room.”

To put off going into the studio a moment longer she waited until Mister Lafkowitz was ready to leave and then stood behind him as he opened the door. The frosty cold outside cut into the room.It was growing late and the air was seeped with the pale yellow of winter twilight.When the door swung to on its hinges, the house seemed darker and more silent than ever before she had known it to be.

As she went into the studio Mister Bilderbach got up from the piano and silently watched her settle herself at the keyboard.

“Well, Bienchen，”he said，“this afternoon we are going to begin all over. Start from scratch.Forget the last few months.”

He looked as though he were trying to act a part in a movie. His solid body swayed from toe to heel, he rubbed his hands together, and even smiled in a satisfed, movie way.Then suddenly he thrust this manner brusquely aside.His heavy shoulders slouched and he began to run through the stack of music she had brought in.“The Bach-no, not yet，”he murmured.“The Beethoven?Yes, the Variation Sonata.Opus.26.”

The keys of the piano hemmed her in-stiff and white and dead-seeming.

“Wait a minute，”he said. He stood in the curve of the piano, elbows propped, and looked at her.“Today I expect something from you.Now this sonata-it's the frst Beethoven sonata you ever worked on.Every note is under control-technically-you have nothing to cope with but the music.Only music now.That's all you think about.”

He rustled through the pages of her volume until he found the place. Then he pulled his teaching chair halfway across the room, turned it around and seated himself, straddling the back with his legs.

For some reason, she knew, this position of his usually had a good effect on her performance. But today she felt that she would notice him from the corner of her eye and be disturbed.His back was stiffly tilted, his legs looked tense.The heavy volume before him seemed to balance dangerously on the chair back.“Now we begin，”he said with a peremptory dart of his eyes in her direction.

Her hands rounded over the keys and then sank down. The frst notes were too loud, the other phrases followed dryly.

Arrestingly his hand rose up from the score.“Wait！Think a minute what you're playing. How is this beginning marked?”

“An-andante.”

“All right. Don't drag it into an adagio then.And play deeply into the keys.Don't snatch it off shallowly that way.A graceful, deep-toned andante—”

She tried again. Her hands seemed separate from the music that was in her.

“Listen，”he interrupted.“Which of these variations dominates the whole?”

“The dirge，”she answered.

“Then prepare for that. This is an andante-but it's not salon stuff as you just played it.Start out softly, piano, and make it swell out just before the arpeggio.Make it warm and dramatic.And down here-where it's marked dolce make the counter-melody sing out.You know all that.We've gone over all that side of it before.Now play it.Feel it as Beethoven wrote it down.Feel that tragedy and restraint.”

She could not stop looking at his hands. They seemed to rest tentatively on the music, ready to fy up as a stop signal as soon as she would begin, the gleaming fash of his ring calling her to halt.“Mister Bilderbach-maybe if I—if you let me play on through the frst variation without stopping I could do better.”

“I won't interrupt，”he said.

Her pale face leaned over too close to the keys. She played through the first part, and, obeying a nod from him, began the second.There were no flaws that jarred on her, but the phrases shaped from her fngers before she had put into them the meaning that she felt.

When she had fnished he looked up from the music and began to speak with dull bluntness：“I hardly heard those harmonic fllings in the right hand. And incidentally, this part was supposed to take on intensity, develop the foreshadowings that were supposed to be inherent in the frst part.Go on with the next one, though.”

She wanted to start it with subdued viciousness and progress to a feeling of deep, swollen sorrow. Her mind told her that.But her hands seemed to gum in the keys like limp macaroni and she could not imagine the music as it should be.

When the last note had stopped vibrating, he closed the book and deliberately got up from the chair. He was moving his lower jaw from side to side-and between his open lips she could glimpse the pink healthy lane to his throat and his strong, smoke-yellowed teeth.He laid the Beethoven gingerly on top of the rest of her music and propped his elbows on the smooth, black piano top once more.“No，”he said simply, looking at her.

Her mouth began to quiver.“I can't help it. I—”

Suddenly he strained his lips into a smile.“Listen, Bienchen，”he began in a new, forced voice.“You still play the“HarmoniousBlacksmith”，don't you?I told you not to drop it from your repertoire.”

“Yes，”she said.“I practice it now and then.”

His voice was the one he used for children.“It was among the frst things we worked on together-remember. So strongly you used to play it-like a real blacksmith's daughter.You see, Bienchen, I know you so well-as if you were my own girl.I know what you have—I've heard you play so many things beautifully.You used to—”

He stopped in confusion and inhaled from his pulpy stub of cigarette. The smoke drowsed out from his pink lips and clung in a gray mist around her lank hair and childish forehead.

“Make it happy and simple，”he said, switching on the lamp behind her and stepping back from the piano.

For a moment he stood just inside the bright circle the light made. Then impulsively he squatted down to the foor.“Vigorous，”he said.

She could not stop looking at him, sitting on one heel with the other foot resting squarely before him for balance, the muscles of his strong thighs straining under the cloth of his trousers, his back straight, his elbows staunchly propped on his knees.“Simply now，”he repeated with a gesture of his feshy hands.“Think of the blacksmith-working out in the sunshine all day. Working easily and undisturbed.”

She could not look down at the piano. The light brightened the hairs on the backs of his outspread hands, made the lenses of his glasses glitter.

“All of it，”he urged.“Now！”

She felt that the marrows of her bones were hollow and there was no blood left in her. Her heart that had been springing against her chest all afternoon felt suddenly dead.She saw it gray and limp and shrivelled at the edges like an oyster.

His face seemed to throb out in space before her, come closerwith the lurching motion in the veins of his temples. In retreat, she looked down at the piano.Her lips shook like jelly and a surge of noiseless tears made the white keys blur in a watery line.“I can't，”she whispered.“I don't know why, but I just can't-can't any more.”

His tense body slackened and, holding his hand to his side, he pulled himself up. She clutched her music and hurried past him.

Her coat. The mittens and galoshes.The schoolbooks and the satchel he had given her on her birthday.All from the silent room that was hers.Quickly-before he would have to speak.

As she passed through the vestibule she could not help but see his hands-held out from his body that leaned against the studio door, relaxed and purposeless. The door shut to firmly.Dragging her books and satchel she stumbled down the stone steps, turned in the wrong direction, and hurried down the street that had become confused with noise and bicycles and the games of other children.

The Jockey

The jockey came to the doorway of the dining-room, then after a moment stepped to one side and stood motionless, with his back to the wall. The room was crowded, as this was the third day of the season and all the hotels in the town were full.In the dining-room bouquets of August roses scattered their petals on the white table linen and from the adjoining bar came a warm, drunken wash of voices.The jockey waited with his back to the wall and scrutinized the room with pinched, crêpy eyes.He examined the room until at last his eyes reached a table in a corner diagonally across from him, at which three men were sitting.As he watched, the jockey raised his chin and tilted his head back to one side, his dwarfed body grew rigid, and his hands stiffened so that the fngers curled inward like gray claws.Tense against the wall of the dining-room, he watched and waited in this way.

He was wearing a suit of green Chinese silk that evening, tailored precisely and the size of a costume outfit for a child. The shirt was yellow, the tie striped with pastel colors.He had no hat with him and wore his hair brushed down in a stiff, wet bang on his forehead.His face was drawn, ageless, and gray.There were shadowed hollows at his temples and his mouth was set in a wiry smile.After a time he was aware that he had been seen by one of the three men he had been watching.But the jockey did not nod；he only raised his chin still higher and hooked the thumb of his tense hand in the pocket of his coat.

The three men at the corner table were a trainer, a bookie, anda rich man. The trainer was Sylvester-a large, loosely built fellow with a fushed nose and slow blue eyes.The bookie was Simmons.The rich man was the owner of a horse named Seltzer, which the jockey had ridden that afternoon.The three of them drank whiskey with soda, and a white-coated waiter had just brought on the main course of the dinner.

It was Sylvester who first saw the jockey. He looked away quickly, put down his whiskey glass, and nervously mashed the tip of his red nose with his thumb.“It's Bitsy Barlow，”he said.“Standing over there across the room.Just watching us.”

“Oh, the jockey，”said the rich man. He was facing the wall and he half turned his head to look behind him.“Ask him over.”

“God no，”Sylvester said.

“He's crazy，”Simmons said. The bookie's voice was flat and without inflection.He had the face of a born gambler, carefully adjusted, the expression a permanent deadlock between fear and greed.

“Well, I wouldn't call him that exactly，”said Sylvester.“I've known him a long time. He was O.K.until about six months ago.But if he goes on like this, I can't see him lasting another year.I just can't.”

“It was what happened in Miami，”said Simmons.

“What?”asked the rich man.

Sylvester glanced across the room at the jockey and wet the corner of his mouth with his red, feshy tongue.“An accident. A kid got hurt on the track.Broke a leg and a hip.He was a particular pal of Bitsy's.An Irish kid.Not a bad rider, either.”

“That's a pity，”said the rich man.

“Yeah. They were particular friends，”Sylvester said.“You would always find him up in Bitsy's hotel room.They would be playing rummy or else lying on the floor reading the sports page together.”

“Well, those things happen，”said the rich man.

Simmons cut into his beefsteak. He held his fork prongs downward on the plate and carefully piled on mushrooms with the blade of his knife.“He's crazy，”he repeated.“He gives me the creeps.”

All the tables in the dining room were occupied. There was a party at the banquet table in the center, and green-white August moths had found their way in from the night and futtered about the clear candle flames.Two girls wearing flannel slacks and blazers walked arm in arm across the room into the bar.From the main street outside came the echoes of holiday hysteria.

“They claim that in August Saratoga is the wealthiest town per capita in the world.”Sylvester turned to the rich man.“What do you think?”

“I wouldn't know，”said the rich man.“It may very well be so.”

Daintily, Simmons wiped his greasy mouth with the tip of his forefnger.“How about Hollywood?And Wall Street—”

“Wait，”said Sylvester.“He's decided to come over here.”

The jockey had left the wall and was approaching the table in the corner. He walked with a prim strut, swinging out his legs in a half-circle with each step, his heels biting smartly into the red velvet carpet on the foor.On the way over he brushed against the elbow of a fat woman in white satin at the banquet table；he stepped back and bowed with dandifed courtesy, his eyes quite closed.When he had crossed the room he drew up a chair and sat at a corner of the table, between Sylvester and the rich man, without a nod of greeting or a change in his set, gray face.

“Had dinner?”Sylvester asked.

“Some people might call it that.”The jockey's voice was high, bitter, clear.

Sylvester put his knife and fork down carefully on his plate. The rich man shifted his position, turning sidewise in his chair and crossing his legs.He was dressed in twill riding pants, unpolished boots, and a shabby brown jacket-this was his outfit day andnight in the racing season, although he was never seen on a horse.Simmons went on with his dinner.

“Like a spot of seltzer water?”asked Sylvester.“Or something like that?”

The jockey didn't answer. He drew a gold cigarette case from his pocket and snapped it open.Inside were a few cigarettes and a tiny gold penknife.He used the knife to cut a cigarette in half.When he had lighted his smoke he held up his hand to a waiter passing by the table.“Kentucky bourbon, please.”

“Now, listen, Kid，”said Sylvester.

“Don't Kid me.”

“Be reasonable. You know you got to behave reasonable.”

The jockey drew up the left corner of his mouth in a stiff jeer. His eyes lowered to the food spread out on the table, but instantly he looked up again.Before the rich man was a fsh casserole, baked in a cream sauce and garnished with parsley.Sylvester had ordered eggs Benedict.There was asparagus, fresh buttered corn, and a side dish of wet black olives.A plate of French-fried potatoes was in the corner of the table before the jockey.He didn't look at the food again, but kept his pinched eyes on the center-piece of full-blown lavender roses.“I don't suppose you remember a certain person by the name of McGuire，”he said.

“Now, listen，”said Sylvester.

The waiter brought the whiskey, and the jockey sat fondling the glass with his small, strong, callused hands. On his wrist was a gold link bracelet that clinked against the table edge.After turning the glass between his palms, the jockey suddenly drank the whiskey neat in two hard swallows.He set down the glass sharply.“No, I don't suppose your memory is that long and extensive，”he said.

“Sure enough, Bitsy，”said Sylvester.“What makes you act like this?You hear from the kid today?”

“I received a letter，”the jockey said.“The certain person we were speaking about was taken out from the cast on Wednesday. Oneleg is two inches shorter than the other one.That's all.”

Sylvester clucked his tongue and shook his head.“I realize how you feel.”

“Do you?”The jockey was looking at the dishes on the table. His gaze passed from the fsh casserole to the corn, and fnally fxed on the plate of fried potatoes.His face tightened and quickly he looked up again.A rose shattered and he picked up one of the petals, bruised it between his thumb and forefnger, and put it in his mouth.

“Well, those things happen，”said the rich man.

The trainer and the bookie had finished eating, but there was food left on the serving dishes before their plates. The rich man dipped his buttery fngers in his water glass and wiped them with his napkin.

“Well，”said the jockey.“Doesn't somebody want me to pass them something?Or maybe perhaps you desire to re-order. Another hunk of beefsteak, gentlemen, or—”

“Please，”said Sylvester.“Be reasonable. Why don't you go on upstairs?”

“Yes, why don't I?”the jockey said.

His prim voice had risen higher and there was about it the sharp whine of hysteria.

“Why don't I go up to my god damn room and walk around and write some letters and go to bed like a good boy?Why don't I just—”He pushed his chair back and got up.“Oh, foo，”he said.“Foo to you. I want a drink.”

“All I can say is it's your funeral，”said Sylvester.“You know what it does to you. You know well enough.”

The jockey crossed the dining-room and went into the bar. He ordered a Manhattan, and Sylvester watched him stand with his heels pressed tight together, his body hard as a lead soldier's, holding his little fnger out from the cocktail glass and sipping the drink slowly.

“He's crazy，”said Simmons.“Like I said.”

Sylvester turned to the rich man.“If he eats a lamb chop, youcan see the shape of it in his stomach a hour afterward. He can't sweat things out of him any more.He's a hundred and twelve and a half.He's gained three pounds since we left Miami.”

“A jockey shouldn't drink，”said the rich man.

“The food don't satisfy him like it used to and he can't sweat it out. If he eats a lamb chop, you can watch it tooching out in his stomach and it don't go down.”

The jockey fnished his Manhattan. He swallowed, crushed the cherry in the bottom of the glass with his thumb, then pushed the glass away from him.The two girls in blazers were standing at his left, their faces turned toward each other, and at the other end of the bar two touts had started an argument about which was the highest mountain in the world.Everyone was with somebody else；there was no other person drinking alone that night.The jockey paid with a brand-new ffty-dollar bill and didn't count the change.

He walked back to the dining-room and to the table at which the three men were sitting, but he did not sit down.“No, I wouldn't presume to think your memory is that extensive，”he said. He was so small that the edge of the table-top reached almost to his belt, and when he gripped the corner with his wiry hands he didn't have to stoop.“No, you're too busy gobbling up dinners in dining-rooms.You're too—”

“Honestly，”begged Sylvester.“You got to behave reasonable.”

“Reasonable！Reasonable！”The jockey's gray face quivered, then set in a mean, frozen grin. He shook the table so that the plates rattled, and for a moment it seemed that he would push it over.But suddenly he stopped.His hand reached out toward the plate nearest to him and deliberately he put a few of the French-fried potatoes in his mouth.He chewed slowly, his upper lip raised, then he turned and spat out the pulpy mouthful on the smooth red carpet which covered the foor.“Libertines，”he said, and his voice was thin and broken.He rolled the word in his mouth, as though it had a favor and a substance that gratifed him.“You libertines，”he said again，&nbsp；and turned and walked with his rigid swagger out of the dining-room.

Sylvester shrugged one of his loose, heavy shoulders. The rich man sopped up some water that had been spilled on the tablecloth, and they didn't speak until the waiter came to clear away.

Madame Zilensky and the King of Finland

To Mr. Book, the head of the music department at Ryder College, was due all the credit for getting Madame Zilensky on the faculty.The college considered itself fortunate；her reputation was impressive, both as a composer and as a pedagogue.Mr.Brook took on himself the responsibility of finding a house for Madame Zilensky, a comfortable place with a garden, which was convenient to the college and next to the apartment house where he himself lived.

No one in Westbridge had known Madame Zilensky before she came. Mr.Brook had seen her pictures in musical journals, and once he had written to her about the authenticity of a certain Buxtehude manuscript.Also, when it was being settled that she was to join the faculty, they had exchanged a few cables and letters on practical affairs.She wrote in a clear, square hand, and the only thing out of the ordinary in these letters was the fact that they contained an occasional reference to objects and persons altogether unknown to Mr.Brook, such as“the yellow cat in Lisbon”or“poor Heinrich.”These lapses Mr.Brook put down to the confusion of getting herself and her family out of Europe.

Mr. Brook was a somewhat pastel person；years of Mozart minuets, of explanations about diminished sevenths and minor triads, had given him a watchful vocational patience.For the most part, he kept to himself.He loathed academic fddle-faddle and committees.Years before, when the music department had decided to gang together and spend the summer in Salzburg, Mr.Brook sneakedout of the arrangement at the last moment and took a solitary trip to Peru.He had a few eccentricities himself and was tolerant of the peculiarities of others；indeed, he rather relished the ridiculous.Often, when confronted with some grave and incongruous situation, he would feel a little inside tickle, which stiffened his long, mild face and sharpened the light in his gray eyes.

Mr. Brook met Madame Zilensky at the Westbridge station a week before the beginning of the fall semester.He recognized her instantly.She was a tall, straight woman with a pale and haggard face.Her eyes were deeply shadowed and she wore her dark, ragged hair pushed back from her forehead.She had large, delicate hands, which were very grubby.About her person as a whole there was something noble and abstract that made Mr.Brook draw back for a moment and stand nervously undoing his cuff links.In spite of her clothes-a long, black skirt and a broken-down old leather jacket-she made an impression of vague elegance.With Madame Zilensky were three children, boys between the ages of ten and six, all blond, blank-eyed, and beautiful.There was one other person, an old woman who turned out later to be the Finnish servant.

This was the group he found at the station. The only luggage they had with them was two immense boxes of manuscripts, the rest of their paraphernalia having been forgotten in the station at Springfeld when they changed trains.That is the sort of thing that can happen to anyone.When Mr.Brook got them all into a taxi, he thought the worst difficulties were over, but Madame Zilensky suddenly tried to scramble over his knees and get out of the door.

“My God！”she said.“I left my-how do you say?—my tick-tick-tick—”

“Your watch?”asked Mr. Brook.

“Oh no！”she said vehemently.“You know, my tick-tick-tick，”and she waved her forefnger from side to side, pendulum fashion.

“Tick-tick，”said Mr. Brook, putting his hands to his forehead and closing his eyes.“Could you possibly mean a metronome?”

“Yes！Yes！I think I must have lost it there where we changed trains.”

Mr. Brook managed to quiet her.He even said, with a kind of dazed gallantry, that he would get her another one the next day.But at the time he was bound to admit to himself that there was something curious about this panic over a metronome when there was all the rest of the lost luggage to consider.

The Zilensky ménage moved into the house next door, and on the surface everything was all right.The boys were quiet children.Their names were Sigmund, Boris, and Sammy.They were always together and they followed each other around Indian fle, Sigmund usually the frst.Among themselves they spoke a desperate-sounding family Esperanto made up of Russian, French, Finnish, German, and English；when other people were around, they were strangely silent.It was not any one thing that the Zilenskys did or said that made Mr.Brook uneasy.There were just little incidents.For example, something about the Zilensky children subconsciously bothered him when they were in a house, and fnally he realized that what troubled him was the fact that the Zilensky boys never walked on a rug；they skirted it single fle on the bare foor, and if a room was carpeted, they stood in the doorway and did not go inside.Another thing was this：Weeks passed and Madame Zilensky seemed to make no effort to get settled or to furnish the house with anything more than a table and some beds.The front door was left open day and night and soon the house began to take on a queer, bleak look like that of a place abandoned for years.

The college had every reason to be satisfied with Madame Zilensky. She taught with a fierce insistence.She could become deeply indignant if some Mary Owens or Bernadine Smith would not clean up her Scarlatti trills.She got hold of four pianos for her college studio and set four dazed students to playing Bach fugues together.The racket that came from her end of the departmentwas extraordinary, but Madame Zilensky did not seem to have a nerve in her, and if pure will and effort can get over a musical idea, then Ryder College could not have done better.At night Madame Zilensky worked on her twelfth symphony.She seemed never to sleep；no matter what time of night Mr.Brook happened to look out of his sitting-room window, the light in her studio was always on.No, it was not because of any professional consideration that Mr.Brook became so dubious.

It was in late October when he felt for the first time that something was unmistakably wrong. He had lunched with Madame Zilensky and had enjoyed himself, as she had given him a very detailed account of an African safari she had made in 1928.Later in the afternoon she stopped in at his offce and stood rather abstractly in the doorway.

Mr. Brook looked up from his desk and asked，“Is there anything you want?”

“No, thank you，”said Madame Zilensky. She had a low, beautiful, sombre voice.“I was only just wondering.You recall the metronome.Do you think perhaps that I might have left it with that French?”

“Who?”asked Mr. Brook.

“Why, that French I was married to，”she answered.

“Frenchman，”Mr. Brook said mildly.He tried to imagine the husband of Madame Zilensky, but his mind refused.He muttered half to himself，“The father of the children.”

“But no，”said Madame Zilensky with decision.“The father of Sammy.”

Mr. Brook had a swift prescience.His deepest instincts warned him to say nothing further.Still, his respect for order, his conscience, demanded that he ask，“And the father of the other two?”

Madame Zilensky put her hand to the back of her head and ruffled up her short, cropped hair. Her face was dreamy, and for several moments she did not answer.Then she said gently，“Boris isof a Pole who played the piccolo.”

“And Sigmund?”he asked. Mr.Brook looked over his orderly desk, with the stack of corrected papers, the three sharpened pencils, the ivory-elephant paperweight.When he glanced up at Madame Zilensky, she was obviously thinking hard.She gazed around at the corners of the room, her brows lowered and her jaw moving from side to side.At last she said，“We were discussing the father of Sigmund?”

“Why, no，”said Mr. Brook.“There is no need to do that.”

Madame Zilensky answered in a voice both dignifed and fnal.“He was a fellow-countryman.”

Mr. Brook really did not care one way or the other.He had no prejudices；people could marry seventeen times and have Chinese children so far as he was concerned.But there was something about this conversation with Madame Zilensky that bothered him.Suddenly he understood.The children didn't look at all like Madame Zilensky, but they looked exactly like each other, and as they all had different fathers, Mr.Brook thought the resemblance astonishing.

But Madame Zilensky had fnished with the subject. She zipped up her leather jacket and turned away.

“That is exactly where I left it，”she said, with a quick nod.“Chez that French.”

Affairs in the music department were running smoothly. Mr.Brook did not have any serious embarrassments to deal with, such as the harp teacher last year who had fnally eloped with a garage mechanic.There was only this nagging apprehension about Madame Zilensky.He could not make out what was wrong in his relations with her or why his feelings were so mixed.To begin with, she was a great globe-trotter, and her conversations were incongruously seasoned with references to far-fetched places.She would go along for days without opening her mouth, prowling through the corridor with her hands in the pockets of her jacket and her face lockedin meditation.Then suddenly she would buttonhole Mr.Brook and launch out on a long, volatile monologue, her eyes reckless and bright and her voice warm with eagerness.She would talk about anything or nothing at all.Yet, without exception, there was something queer, in a slanted sort of way, about every episode she ever mentioned.If she spoke of taking Sammy to the barbershop, the impression she created was just as foreign as if she were telling of an afternoon in Bagdad.Mr.Brook could not make it out.

The truth came to him very suddenly, and the truth made everything perfectly clear, or at least clarified the situation. Mr.Brook had come home early and lighted a fre in the little grate in his sitting-room.He felt comfortable and at peace that evening.He sat before the fre in his stocking feet, with a volume of William Blake on the table by his side, and he had poured himself a half-glass of apricot brandy.At ten o'clock he was drowsing cozily before the fre, his mind full of cloudy phrases of Mahler and foating half-thoughts.Then all at once, out of this delicate stupor, four words came to his mind：“The King of Finland.”The words seemed familiar, but for the first moment he could not place them.Then all at once he tracked them down.He had been walking across the campus that afternoon when Madame Zilensky stopped him and began some preposterous rigamarole, to which he had only half listened；he was thinking about the stack of canons turned in by his counterpoint class.Now the words, the infections of her voice, came back to him with insidious exactitude, Madame Zilensky had started off with the following remark：“One day, when I was standing in front of a pâtisserie, the King of Finland came by in a sled.”

Mr. Brook jerked himself up straight in his chair and put down his glass of brandy.The woman was a pathological liar.Almost every word she uttered outside of class was an untruth.If she worked all night, she would go out of her way to tell you she spent the evening at the cinema.If she ate lunch at the Old Tavern, she would be sure to mention that she had lunched with her children at home.The woman was simply a pathological liar, and that accounted for everything.

Mr. Brook cracked his knuckles and got up from his chair.His frst reaction was one of exasperation.That day after day Madame Zilensky would have the gall to sit there in his offce and deluge him with her outrageous falsehoods！Mr.Brook was intensely provoked.He walked up and down the room, then he went into his kitchenette and made himself a sardine sandwich.

An hour later, as he sat before the fre, his irritation had changed to a scholarly and thoughtful wonder. What he must do, he told himself, was to regard the whole situation impersonally and look on Madame Zilensky as a doctor looks on a sick patient.Her lies were of the guileless sort.She did not dissimulate with any intention to deceive, and the untruths she told were never used to any possible advantage.That was the maddening thing；there was simply no motive behind it all.

Mr. Brook fnished off the rest of the brandy.And slowly, when it was almost midnight, a further understanding came to him.The reason for the lies of Madame Zilensky was painful and plain.All her life long Madame Zilensky had worked-at the piano, teaching, and writing those beautiful and immense twelve symphonies.Day and night she had drudged and struggled and thrown her soul into her work, and there was not much of her left over for anything else.Being human, she suffered from this lack and did what she could to make up for it.If she passed the evening bent over a table in the library and later declared that she had spent that time playing cards, it was as though she had managed to do both those things.Through the lies, she lived vicariously.The lies doubled the little of her existence that was left over from work and augmented the little rag-end of her personal life.

Mr. Brook looked into the fire, and the face of Madame Zilensky was in his mind-a severe face, with dark, weary eyes and delicately disciplined mouth.He was conscious of a warmthin his chest, and a feeling of pity, protectiveness, and dreadful understanding.For a while he was in a state of lovely confusion.

Later on he brushed his teeth and got into his pajamas. He must be practical.What did this clear up?That French, the Pole with the piccolo, Bagdad?And the children, Sigmund, Boris, and Sammy-who were they?Were they really her children after all, or had she simply rounded them up from somewhere?Mr.Brook polished his spectacles and put them on the table by his bed.He must come to an immediate understanding with her.Otherwise, there would exist in the department a situation which could become most problematical.It was two o'clock.He glanced out of his window and saw that the light in Madame Zilensky's workroom was still on.Mr.Brook got into bed, made terrible faces in the dark, and tried to plan what he would say next day.

Mr. Brook was in his offce by eight o'clock.He sat hunched up behind his desk, ready to trap Madame Zilensky as she passed down the corridor.He did not have to wait long, and as soon as he heard her footsteps he called out her name.

Madame Zilensky stood in the doorway. She looked vague and jaded.“How are you?I had such a fne night's rest，”she said.

“Pray be seated, if you please，”said Mr. Brook.“I would like a word with you.”

Madame Zilensky put aside her portfolio and leaned back wearily in the armchair across from him.“Yes?”she asked.

“Yesterday you spoke to me as I was walking across the campus，”he said slowly.“And if I am not mistaken, I believe you said something about a pastry shop and the King of Finland. Is that correct?”

Madame Zilensky turned her head to one side and stared retrospectively at a corner of the window sill.

“Something about a pastry shop，”he repeated.

Her tired face brightened.“But of course，”she said eagerly.“I told you about the time I was standing in front of this shop and theKing of Finland—”

“Madame Zilensky！”Mr. Brook cried.“There is no King of Finland.”

Madame Zilensky looked absolutely blank. Then, after an instant, she started off again.“I was standing in front of Bjarne's pâtisserie when I turned away from the cakes and suddenly saw the King of Finland—”

“Madame Zilensky, I just told you that there is no King of Finland.”

“In Helsingfors，”she started off again desperately, and again he let her get as far as the King, and then no further.

“Finland is a democracy，”he said.“You could not possibly have seen the King of Finland. Therefore, what you have just said is an untruth.A pure untruth.”

Never afterward could Mr. Brook forget the face of Madame Zilensky at that moment.In her eyes there was astonishment, dismay, and a sort of cornered horror.She had the look of one who watches his whole interior world split open and disintegrate.

“It is a pity，”said Mr. Brook with real sympathy.

But Madame Zilensky pulled herself together. She raised her chin and said coldly，“I am a Finn.”

“That I do not question，”answered Mr. Brook.On second thought, he did question it a little.

“I was born in Finland and I am a Finnish citizen.”

“That may very well be，”said Mr. Brook in a rising voice.

“In the war，”she continued passionately，“I rode a motor-cycle and was a messenger.”

“Your patriotism does not enter into it.”

“Just because I am getting out the frst papers—”

“Madame Zilensky！”said Mr. Brook.His hands grasped the edge of the desk.“That is only an irrelevant issue.The point is that you maintained and testified that you saw-that you saw—”But he could not fnish.Her face stopped him.She was deadly pale andthere were shadows around her mouth.Her eyes were wide open, doomed, and proud.And Mr.Brook felt suddenly like a murderer.A great commotion of feelings-understanding, remorse, and unreasonable love-made him cover his face with his hands.He could not speak until this agitation in his insides quieted down, and then he said very faintly，“Yes.Of course.The King of Finland.And was he nice?”

An hour later, Mr. Brook sat looking out of the window of his offce.The trees along the quiet Westbridge street were almost bare, and the gray buildings of the college had a calm, sad look.As he idly took in the familiar scene, he noticed the Drakes'old Airedale waddling along down the street.It was a thing he had watched a hundred times before, so what was it that struck him as strange?Then he realized with a kind of cold surprise that the old dog was running along backward.Mr.Brook watched the Airedale until he was out of sight, then resumed his work on the canons which had been turned in by the class in counterpoint

The Sojourner

The twilight border between sleep and waking was a Roman one this morning；splashing fountains and arched, narrow streets, the golden lavish city of blossoms and age-soft stone. Sometimes in this semi-consciousness he sojourned again in Paris, or war German rubble, or Swiss ski-ing and a snow hotel.Sometimes, also, in a fallow Georgia feld at hunting dawn.Rome it was this morning in the yearless region of dreams.

John Ferris awoke in a room in a New York hotel. He had the feeling that something unpleasant was awaiting him-what it was, he did not know.The feeling, submerged by matinal necessities, lingered even after he had dressed and gone downstairs.It was a cloudless autumn day and the pale sunlight sliced between the pastel skyscrapers.Ferris went into the next-door drugstore and sat at the end booth next to the window glass that overlooked the sidewalk.He ordered an American breakfast with scrambled eggs and sausage.

Ferris had come from Paris to his father's funeral which had taken place the week before in his home town in Georgia. The shock of death had made him aware of youth already passed.His hair was receding and the veins in his now naked temples were pulsing and prominent and his body was spare except for an incipient belly bulge.Ferris had loved his father and the bond between them had once been extraordinarily close-but the years had somehow unravelled this flial devotion；the death, expected for a long time, had left him with an unforeseen dismay.He had stayed as long as possible to be near his mother and brothers at home.His plane forParis was to leave the next morning.

Ferris pulled out his address book to verify a number. He turned the pages with growing attentiveness.Names and addresses from New York, the capitals of Europe, a few faint ones from his home state in the South.Faded, printed names, sprawled drunken ones.Betty Wills：a random love, married now.Charlie Williams：wounded in the Hurtgen Forest, unheard of since.Grand old Williams-did he live or die?Don Walker：a B.T.O.in television, getting rich.Henry Green：hit the skids after the war, in a sanitarium now, they say.Cozie Hall：he had heard that she was dead.Heedless, laughing Cozie-it was strange to think that she too, silly girl, could die.As Ferris closed the address book, he suffered a sense of hazard, transience, almost of fear.

It was then that his body jerked suddenly. He was staring out of the window when there, on the sidewalk, passing by, was his ex-wife.Elizabeth passed quite close to him, walking slowly.He could not understand the wild quiver of his heart, nor the following sense of recklessness and grace that lingered after she was gone.

Quickly Ferris paid his check and rushed out to the sidewalk. Elizabeth stood on the corner waiting to cross Fifth Avenue.He hurried toward her meaning to speak, but the lights changed and she crossed the street before he reached her.Ferris followed.On the other side he could easily have overtaken her, but he found himself lagging unaccountably.Her fair brown hair was plainly rolled, and as he watched her Ferris recalled that once his father had remarked that Elizabeth had a“beautiful carriage.”She turned at the next corner and Ferris followed, although by now his intention to overtake her had disappeared.Ferris questioned the bodily disturbance that the sight of Elizabeth aroused in him, the dampness of his hands, the hard heart-strokes.

It was eight years since Ferris had last seen his ex-wife. He knew that long ago she had married again.And there were children.During recent years he had seldom thought of her.But at first, after the divorce, the loss had almost destroyed him.Then after the anodyne of time, he had loved again, and then again.Jeannine, she was now.Certainly his love for his ex-wife was long since past.So why the unhinged body, the shaken mind?He knew only that his clouded heart was oddly dissonant with the sunny, candid autumn day.Ferris wheeled suddenly and, walking with long strides, almost running, hurried back to the hotel.

Ferris poured himself a drink, although it was not yet eleven o'clock. He sprawled out in an armchair like a man exhausted, nursing his glass of bourbon and water.He had a full day ahead of him as he was leaving by plane the next morning for Paris.He checked over his obligations：take luggage to Air France, lunch with his boss, buy shoes and an overcoat.And something-wasn't there something else?Ferris fnished his drink and opened the telephone directory.

His decision to call his ex-wife was impulsive. The number was under Bailey, the husband's name, and he called before he had much time for self-debate.He and Elizabeth had exchanged cards at Christmastime, and Ferris had sent a carving set when he received the announcement of her wedding.There was no reason not to call.But as he waited, listening to the ring at the other end, misgiving fretted him.

Elizabeth answered；her familiar voice was a fresh shock to him. Twice he had to repeat his name, but when he was identifed, she sounded glad.He explained he was only in town for that day.They had a theater engagement, she said-but she wondered if he would come by for an early dinner.Ferris said he would be delighted.

As he went from one engagement to another, he was still bothered at odd moments by the feeling that something necessary was forgotten. Ferris bathed and changed in the late afternoon, often thinking about Jeannine：he would be with her the following night“Jeannine，”he would say，“I happened to run into my ex-wifewhen I was in New York.Had dinner with her.And her husband, of course.It was strange seeing her after all these years.”

Elizabeth lived in the East Fifties, and as Ferris taxied uptown he glimpsed at intersections the lingering sunset, but by the time he reached his destination it was already autumn dark. The place was a building with a marquee and a doorman, and the apartment was on the seventh foor.

“Come in, Mr. Ferris.”

Braced for Elizabeth or even the unimagined husband, Ferris was astonished by the freckled red-haired child；he had known of the children, but his mind had failed somehow to acknowledge them. Surprise made him step back awkwardly.

“This is our apartment，”the child said politely.“Aren't you Mr. Ferris?I'm Billy.Come in.”

In the living-room beyond the hall, the husband provided another surprise；he too had not been acknowledged emotionally. Bailey was a lumbering red-haired man with a deliberate manner.He rose and extended a welcoming hand.

“I'm Bill Bailey. Glad to see you.Elizabeth will be in, in a minute.She's fnishing dressing.”

The last words struck a gliding series of vibrations, memories of the other years. Fair Elizabeth, rosy and naked before her bath.Half-dressed before the mirror of her dressing table, brushing her fne, chestnut hair.Sweet, casual intimacy, the soft-feshed loveliness indisputably possessed.Ferris shrank from the unbidden memories and compelled himself to meet Bill Bailey's gaze.

“Billy, will you please bring that tray of drinks from the kitchen table?

The child obeyed promptly, and when he was gone Ferris remarked conversationally，“Fine boy you have there.”

“We think so.”

Flat silence until the child returned with a tray of glasses and a cocktail shaker of Martinis. With the priming drinks they pumped upconversation：Russia, they spoke of, and the New York rain-making, and the apartment situation in Manhattan and Paris.

“Mr. Ferris is flying all the way across the ocean tomorrow，”Bailey said to the little boy who was perched on the arm of his chair, quiet and well behaved.“I bet you would like to be a stowaway in his suitcase.”

Billy pushed back his limp bangs.“I want to fy in an airplane and be a newspaperman like Mr. Ferris.”He added with sudden assurance，“That's what I would like to do when I am big.”

Bailey said，“I thought you wanted to be a doctor.”

“I do！”said Billy.“I would like to be both. I want to be a atom-bomb scientist too.”

Elizabeth came in carrying in her arms a baby girl.

“Oh, John！”she said. She settled the baby in the father's lap.“It's grand to see you.I'm awfully glad you could come.”

The little girl sat demurely on Bailey's knees. She wore a pale pink crêpe-de-Chine frock, smocked around the yoke with rose, and a matching silk hair ribbon tying back her pale soft curls.Her skin was summer tanned and her brown eyes flecked with gold and laughing.When she reached up and fngered her father’s horn-rimmed glasses, he took them off and let her look through them a moment.“How’s my old Candy?”

Elizabeth was very beautiful, more beautiful perhaps than he had ever realized. Her straight clean hair was shining.Her face was softer, glowing and serene.It was a madonna loveliness, dependent on the family ambiance.

“You've hardly changed at all，”Elizabeth said，“but it has been a long time.”

“Eight years.”His hand touched his thinning hair self-consciously while further amenities were exchanged.

Ferris felt himself suddenly a spectator-an interloper among these Baileys. Why had he come?He suffered.His own life seemed so solitary, a fragile column supporting nothing amidst the wreckageof the years.He felt he could not bear much longer to stay in the family room.

He glanced at his watch.“You're going to the theater?”

“It's a shame，”Elizabeth said，“but we've had this engagement for more than a month. But surely, John, you'll be staying home one of these days before long.You're not going to be an expatriate, are you?”

“Expatriate，”Ferris repeated.“I don't much like the word.”

“What's a better word?”she asked.

He thought for a moment.“Sojourner might do.”

Ferris glanced again at his watch, and again Elizabeth apologized.“If only we had known ahead of time—”

“I just had this day in town. I came home unexpectedly.You see, Papa died last week.”

“Papa Ferris is dead?”

“Yes, at Johns-Hopkins. He had been sick there nearly a year.The funeral was down home in Georgia.”

“Oh, I'm so sorry, John. Papa Ferris was always one of my favorite people.”

The little boy moved from behind the chair so that he could look into his mother's face. He asked，“Who is dead?”

Ferris was oblivious to apprehension；he was thinking of his father's death. He saw again the outstretched body on the quilted silk within the coffin.The corpse flesh was bizarrely rouged and the familiar hands lay massive and joined above a spread of funeral roses.The memory closed and Ferris awakened to Elizabeth's calm voice.

“Mr. Ferris's father, Billy.A really grand person.Somebody you didn't know.”

“But why did you call him Papa Ferris?”

Bailey and Elizabeth exchanged a trapped look. It was Bailey who answered the questioning child.“A long time ago，”he said，“your mother and Mr.Ferris were once married.Before you wereborn-a long time ago.”

“Mr. Ferris?”

The little boy stared at Ferris, amazed and unbelieving. And Ferris'eyes, as he returned the gaze, were somehow unbelieving too.Was it indeed true that at one time he had called this stranger, Elizabeth, Little Butterduck during nights of love, that they had lived together, shared perhaps a thousand days and nights and-fnally-endured in the misery of sudden solitude the fber by fber（jealousy, alcohol and money quarrels）destruction of the fabric of married love.

Bailey said to the children，“It's somebody's supper-time. Come on now.”

“But Daddy！Mama and Mr. Ferris—I—”

Billy's everlasting eyes-perplexed and with a glimmer of hostility-reminded Ferris of the gaze of another child. It was the young son of Jeannine-a boy of seven with a shadowed little face and knobby knees whom Ferris avoided and usually forgot.

“Quick march！”Bailey gently turned Billy toward the door.“Say good night now, son.”

“Good night, Mr. Ferris.”He added resentfully，“I thought I was staying up for the cake.”

“You can come in afterward for the cake，”Elizabeth said.“Run along now with Daddy for your supper.”

Ferris and Elizabeth were alone. The weight of the situation descended on those frst moments of silence.Ferris asked permission to pour himself another drink and Elizabeth set the cocktail shaker on the table at his side.He looked at the grand piano and noticed the music on the rack.

“Do you still play as beautifully as you used to?”

“I still enjoy it.”

“Please play, Elizabeth.”

Elizabeth arose immediately. Her readiness to perform when asked had always been one of her amiabilities；she never hung back, apologized.Now as she approached the piano there was the added readiness of relief.

She began with a Bach prelude and fugue. The prelude was as gaily iridescent as a prism in a morning room.The first voice of the fugue, an announcement pure and solitary, was repeated intermingling with a second voice, and again repeated within an elaborated frame, the multiple music, horizontal and serene, fowed with unhurried majesty.The principal melody was woven with two other voices, embellished with countless ingenuities-now dominant, again submerged, it had the sublimity of a single thing that does not fear surrender to the whole.Toward the end, the density of the material gathered for the last enriched insistence on the dominant frst motif and with a chorded fnal statement the fugue ended.Ferris rested his head on the chair back and closed his eyes.In the following silence a clear, high voice came from the room down the hall.

“Daddy, how could Mama and Mr. Ferris—”A door was closed.

The piano began again-what was this music?Unplaced, familiar, the limpid melody had lain a long while dormant in his heart. Now it spoke to him of another time, another place-it was the music Elizabeth used to play.The delicate air summoned a wilderness of memory.Ferris was lost in the riot of past longings, conficts, ambivalent desires.Strange that the music, catalyst for this tumultuous anarchy, was so serene and dear.The singing melody was broken off by the appearance of the maid.

“Miz Bailey, dinner is out on the table now.”

Even after Ferris was seated at the table between his host and hostess, the unfnished music still overcast his mood. He was a little drunk.

“L'improvisation de la vie humaine，”he said.“There's nothing that makes you so aware of the improvisation of human existence as a song unfnished. Or an old address book.”

“Address book?”repeated Bailey. Then he stopped, noncommittal and polite.

“You're still the same old boy, Johnny，”Elizabeth said with a trace of the old tenderness.

It was a Southern dinner that evening, and the dishes were his old favorites. They had fried chicken and corn pudding and rich, glazed candied sweet potatoes.During the meal Elizabeth kept alive a conversation when the silences were overlong.And it came about that Ferris was led to speak of Jeannine.

“I first knew Jeannine last autumn-about this time of the year-in Italy. She's a singer and she had an engagement in Rome.I expect we will be married soon.”

The words seemed so true, inevitable, that Ferris did not at frst acknowledge to himself the lie. He and Jeannine had never in that year spoken of marriage.And indeed, she was still married-to a White Russian moneychanger in Paris from whom she had been separated for fve years.But it was too late to correct the lie.Already Elizabeth was saying：“This really makes me glad to know.Congratulations, Johnny.”

He tried to make amends with truth.“The Roman autumn is so beautiful. Balmy and blossoming.”He added，“Jeannine has a little boy of six.A curious trilingual little fellow.We go to the Tuileries sometimes.”

A lie again. He had taken the boy once to the gardens.The sallow foreign child in shorts that bared his spindly legs had sailed his boat in the concrete pond and ridden the pony.The child had wanted to go in to the puppet show.But there was not time, for Ferris had an engagement at the Scribe Hotel.He had promised they would go to the guignol another afternoon.Only once had he taken Valentin to the Tuileries.

There was a stir. The maid brought in a white-frosted cake with pink candles.The children entered in their night clothes.Ferris still did not understand.

“Happy birthday, John，”Elizabeth said.“Blow out the candles.”

Ferris recognized his birthday date. The candles blew out lingeringly and there was the smell of burning wax.Ferris was thirty-eight years old.The veins in his temples darkened and pulsed visibly.

“It's time you started for the theater.”

Ferris thanked Elizabeth for the birthday dinner and said the appropriate good-byes. The whole family saw him to the door.

A high, thin moon shone above the jagged, dark skyscrapers. The streets were windy, cold.Ferris hurried to Third Avenue and hailed a cab.He gazed at the nocturnal city with the deliberate attentiveness of departure and perhaps farewell.He was alone.He longed for fighttime and the coming journey.

The next day he looked down on the city from the air, burnished in sunlight, toylike, precise. Then America was left behind and there was only the Atlantic and the distant European shore.The ocean was milky pale and placid beneath the clouds.Ferris dozed most of the day.Toward dark he was thinking of Elizabeth and the visit of the previous evening.He thought of Elizabeth among her family with longing, gentle envy and inexplicable regret.He sought the melody, the unfinished air, that had so moved him.The cadence, some unrelated tones, were all that remained；the melody itself evaded him.He had found instead the frst voice of the fugue that Elizabeth had played-it came to him, inverted mockingly and in a minor key.Suspended above the ocean the anxieties of transience and solitude no longer troubled him and he thought of his father's death with equanimity.During the dinner hour the plane reached the shore of France.

At midnight Ferris was in a taxi crossing Paris. It was a clouded night and mist wreathed the lights of the Place de la Concorde.The midnight bistros gleamed on the wet pavements.As always after a transocean flight the change of continents was too sudden.New York at morning, this midnight Paris.Ferris glimpsed the disorderof his life：the succession of cities, of transitory loves；and time, the sinister glissando of the years, time always.

“Vite！Vite！”he called in terror.“Dépêchez-vous.”

Valentin opened the door to him. The little boy wore pajamas and an outgrown red robe.His grey eyes were shadowed and, as Ferris passed into the fat, they fickered momentarily.

“J'attends Maman.”

Jeannine was singing in a night dub. She would not be home before another hour.Valentin returned to a drawing, squatting with his crayons over the paper on the floor.Ferris looked down at the drawing-it was a banjo player with notes and wavy lines inside a comic-strip balloon.

“We will go again to the Tuileries.”

The child looked up and Ferris drew him closer to his knees. The melody, the unfnished music that Elizabeth had played, came to him suddenly.Unsought, the load of memory jettisoned-this time bringing only recognition and sudden joy.

“Monsieur Jean，”the child said，“did you see him?”

Confused, Ferris thought only of another child-the freckled, family-loved boy.“See who, Valentin?”

“Your dead papa in Georgia.”The child added，“Was he okay?”

Ferris spoke with rapid urgency：“We will go often to the Tuileries. Ride the pony and we will go into the guignol.We will see the puppet show and never be in a hurry any more.”

“Monsieur Jean，”Valentin said.“The guignol is now closed.”

Again, the terror the acknowledgment of wasted years and death. Valentin, responsive and confdent, still nestled in his arms.His cheek touched the soft cheek and felt the brush of the delicate eyelashes.With inner desperation he pressed the child close-as though an emotion as protean as his love could dominate the pulse of time.

A Domestic Dilemma

On Thursday Martin Meadows left the office early enough to make the frst express bus home. It was the hour when the evening lilac glow was fading in the slushy streets, but by the time the bus had left the mid-town terminal the bright city night had come.On Thursdays the maid had a half-day off and Martin liked to get home as soon as possible, since for the past year his wife had not been-well.This Thursday he was very tired and, hoping that no regular commuter would single him out for conversation, he fastened his attention to the newspaper until the bus had crossed the George Washington Bridge.Once on 9-W Highway Martin always felt that the trip was halfway done, he breathed deeply, even in cold weather when only ribbons of draught cut through the smoky air of the bus, confdent that he was breathing country air.It used to be that at this point he would relax and begin to think with pleasure of his home.But in this last year nearness brought only a sense of tension and he did not anticipate the journey's end.This evening Martin kept his face close to the window and watched the barren fields and lonely lights of passing townships.There was a moon, pale on the dark earth and areas of late, porous snow；to Martin the countryside seemed vast and somehow desolate that evening.He took his hat from the rack and put his folded newspaper in the pocket of his overcoat a few minutes before time to pull the cord.

The cottage was a block from the bus stop, near the river but not directly on the shore；from the living-room window you could look across the street and opposite yard and see the Hudson. The cottagewas modern, almost too white and new on the narrow plot of yard.In summer the grass was soft and bright and Martin carefully tended a fower border and a rose trellis.But during the cold, fallow months the yard was bleak and the cottage seemed naked.Lights were on that evening in all the rooms in the little house and Martin hurried up the front walk.Before the steps he stopped to move a wagon out of the way.

The children were in the living-room, so intent on play that the opening of the front door was at first unnoticed. Martin stood looking at his safe, lovely children.They had opened the bottom drawer of the secretary and taken out the Christmas decorations.Andy had managed to plug in the Christmas tree lights and the green and red bulbs glowed with out-of-season festivity on the rug of the living-room.At the moment he was trying to trail the bright chord over Marianne's rocking horse.Marianne sat on the foor pulling off an angel's wings.The children wailed a startling welcome.Martin swung the fat little baby girl up to his shoulder and Andy threw himself against his father's legs.

“Daddy, Daddy, Daddy！”

Martin set down the little girl carefully and swung Andy a few times like a pendulum. Then he picked up the Christmas-tree cord.

“What's all this stuff doing out?Help me put it back in the drawer. You're not to fool with the light socket.Remember I told you that before.I mean it, Andy.”

The six-year-old child nodded and shut the secretary drawer. Martin stroked his fair soft hair and his hand lingered tenderly on the nape of the child's frail neck.

“Had supper yet, Bumpkin?”

“It hurt. The toast was hot.”

The baby girl stumbled on the rug and, after the frst surprise of the fall, began to cry；Martin picked her up and carried her in his arms back to the kitchen.

“See, Daddy，”said Andy.“The toast—”

Emily had laid the children's supper on the uncovered porcelain table. There were two plates with the remains of cream-of-wheat and eggs and silver mugs that had held milk.There was also a platter of cinnamon toast, untouched except for one tooth-marked bite.Martin sniffed the bitten piece and nibbed gingerly.Then he put the toast into the garbage pail.

“Hoo-phui—What on earth！”

Emily had mistaken the tin of cayenne for the cinnamon.

“I like to have burnt up，”Andy said.“Drank water and ran outdoors and opened my mouth. Marianne didn't eat none.”

“Any，”corrected Martin. He stood helpless, looking around the walls of the kitchen.“Well, that's that, I guess，”he said fnally.“Where is your mother now?”

“She's up in you alls'room.”

Martin left the children in the kitchen and went up to his wife. Outside the door he waited for a moment to still his anger.He did not knock and once inside the room he closed the door behind him.

Emily sat in the rocking chair by the window of the pleasant room. She had been drinking something from a tumbler and as he entered she put the glass hurriedly on the foor behind the chair.In her attitude there was confusion and guilt which she tried to hide by a show of spurious vivacity.

“Oh, Marty！You home already?The time slipped up on me. I was just going down—”She lurched to him and her kiss was strong with sherry.When he stood unresponsive she stepped back a pace and giggled nervously.

“What's the matter with you?Standing there like a barber pole. Is anything wrong with you?”

“Wrong with me?”Martin bent over the rocking chair and picked up the tumbler from the foor.“If you could only realize how sick I am-how bad it is for all of us.”

Emily spoke in a false, airy voice that had become too familiar to him. Often at such times she affected a slight English accent, copying perhaps some actress she admired，“I haven't the vaguest idea what you mean.Unless you are referring to the glass I used for a spot of sherry.I had a fnger of sherry-maybe two.But what is the crime in that, pray tell me?I'm quite all right.Quite all right.”

“So anyone can see.”

As she went into the bathroom Emily walked with careful gravity. She turned on the cold water and dashed some on her face with her cupped hands, then patted herself dry with the corner of a bath towel.Her face was delicately featured and young, unblemished.

“I was just going down to make dinner.”She tottered and balanced herself by holding to the door frame.

“I'll take care of dinner. You stay up here.I'll bring it up.”

“I'll do nothing of the sort. Why, whoever heard of such a thing?”

“Please，”Martin said.

“Leave me alone. I'm quite all right.I was just on the way down—”

“Mind what I say.”

“Mind your grandmother.”

She lurched toward the door, but Martin caught her by the arm.“I don't want the children to see you in this condition. Be reasonable.”

“Condition！”Emily jerked her arm. Her voice rose angrily.“Why, because I drink a couple of sherries in the afternoon you're trying to make me out a drunkard.Condition！Why, I don't even touch whiskey.As well you know.I don't swill liquor at bars.And that's more than you can say.I don't even have a cocktail at dinnertime.I only sometimes have a glass of sherry.What, I ask you, is the disgrace of that?Condition！”

Martin sought words to calm his wife.“We'll have a quiet supper by ourselves up here. That's a good girl.”Emily sat on the side of the bed and he opened the door for a quick departure.

“I'll be back in a jiffy.”

As he busied himself with the dinner downstairs he was lost in the familiar question as to how this problem had come upon his home. He himself had always enjoyed a good drink.When they were still living in Alabama they had served long drinks or cocktails as a matter of course.For years they had drunk one or two-possibly three drinks before dinner, and at bedtime a long nightcap.Evenings before holidays they might get a buzz on, might even become a little tight.But alcohol had never seemed a problem to him, only a bothersome expense that with the increase in the family they could scarcely afford.It was only after his company had transferred him to New York that Martin was aware that certainly his wife was drinking too much.She was tippling, he noticed, during the day.

The problem acknowledged, he tried to analyze the source. The change from Alabama to New York had somehow disturbed her；accustomed to the idle warmth of a small Southern town, the matrix of the family and cousinship and childhood friends, she had failed to accommodate herself to the stricter, lonelier mores of the North.The duties of motherhood and housekeeping were onerous to her.Homesick for Paris City, she had made no friends in the suburban town.She read only magazines and murder books.Her interior life was insuffcient without the artifce of alcohol.

The revelations of incontinence insidiously undermined his previous conceptions of his wife. There were times of unexplainable malevolence, times when the alcoholic fuse caused an explosion of unseemly anger.He encountered a latent coarseness in Emily, inconsistent with her natural simplicity.She lied about drinking and deceived him with unsuspected stratagems.

Then there was an accident. Coming home from work one evening about a year ago, he was greeted with screams from the children's room.He found Emily holding the baby, wet and naked from her bath.The baby had been dropped, her frail, frail skull striking the table edge, so that a thread of blood was soaking into the gossamer hair.Emily was sobbing and intoxicated.As Martincradled the hurt child, so infnitely precious at that moment, he had an affrighted vision of the future.

The next day Marianne was all right. Emily vowed that never again would she touch liquor, and for a few weeks she was sober, cold and downcast.Then gradually she began-not whisky or gin-but quantities of beer, or sherry, or outlandish liqueurs；once he had come across a hatbox of empty crême-de-menthe bottles.Martin found a dependable maid who managed the household competently.Virgie was also from Alabama and Martin had never dared tell Emily the wage scale customary in New York.Emily’s drinking was entirely secret now, done before he reached the house.Usually the effects were almost imperceptible-a looseness of movement or the heavy-lidded eyes.The times of irresponsibilities, such as the cayenne-pepper toast, were rare, and Martin could dismiss his worries when Virgie was at the house.But, nevertheless, anxiety was always latent, a threat of indefned disaster that underlay his days.

“Marianne！”Martin called, for even the recollection of that time brought the need for reassurance. The baby girl, no longer hurt, but no less precious to her father, came into the kitchen with her brother.Martin went on with the preparations for the meal.He opened a can of soup and put two chops in the frying-pan.Then he sat down by the table and took his Marianne on his knees for a pony ride.Andy watched them, his fngers wobbling the tooth that had been loose all that week.

“Andy-the-candyman！”Martin said.“Is that old critter still in your mouth?Come closer, let Daddy have a look.”

“I got a string to pull it with.”The child brought from his pocket a tangled thread.“Virgie said to tie it to the tooth and tie the other end of the doorknob and shut the door real suddenly.”

Martin took out a clean handkerchief and felt the loose tooth carefully.“That tooth is coming out of my Andy's mouth tonight. Otherwise I'm awfully afraid we'll have a tooth tree in the family.”

“A what?”

“A tooth tree，”Martin said.“You'll bite into something and swallow that tooth. And the tooth will take root in poor Andy's stomach and grow into a tooth tree with sharp little teeth instead of leaves.”

“Shoo, Daddy，”Andy said. But he held the tooth frmly between his grimy little thumb and forefnger.“There ain't any tree like that.I never seen one.”

“There isn't any tree like that and I never saw one.”

Martin tensed suddenly. Emily was coming down the stairs.He listened to her fumbling footsteps, his arm embracing the little boy with dread.When Emily came into the room he saw from her movements and her sullen face that she had again been at the sherry bottle.She began to yank open drawers and set the table.

“Condition！”she said in a furry voice.“You talk to me like that. Don't think I'll forget.I remember every dirty lie you say to me.Don't you think for a minute that I forget.”

“Emily！”he begged.“The children—”

“The children-yes！Don't think I don't see through your dirty plots and schemes. Down here trying to turn my own children against me.Don't think I don't see and understand.”

“Emily！I beg you-please go upstairs.”

“So you can turn my children-my very own children—”Two large tears coursed rapidly down her cheeks.“Trying to turn my little boy, my Andy, against his own mother.”

With drunken impulsiveness Emily knelt on the foor before the startled child. Her hands on his shoulders balanced her.“Listen, my Andy-you wouldn't listen to any lies your father tells you?You wouldn't believe what he says?Listen, Andy, what was your father telling you before I came downstairs?”Uncertain, the child sought his father's face.“Tell me.Mama wants to know.”

“About the tooth tree.”

“What?”

The child repeated the words and she echoed them withunbelieving terror.“The tooth tree！”She swayed and renewed her grasp on the child's shoulder.“I don't know what you're talking about. But listen, Andy, Mama is all right, isn't she?”The tears were spilling down her face and Andy drew back from her, for he was afraid.Grasping the table edge, Emily stood up.

“See！You have turned my child against me.”

Marianne began to cry, and Martin took her in his arms.

“That's all right, you can take your child. You have always shown partiality from the very first.I don't mind, but at least you can leave me my little boy.”

Andy edged close to his father and touched his leg.“Daddy，”he wailed.

Martin took the children to the foot of the stairs.“Andy, you take up Marianne and Daddy will follow you in a minute.”

“But Mama?”the child asked, whispering.

“Mama will be all right. Don't worry.”

Emily was sobbing at the kitchen table, her face buried in the crook of her arm. Martin poured a cup of soup and set it before her.Her rasping sobs unnerved him；the vehemence of her emotion, irrespective of the source, touched in him a strain of tenderness.Unwillingly he laid his hand on her dark hair.“Sit up and drink the soup.”Her face as she looked up at him was chastened and imploring.The boy's withdrawal or the touch of Martin's hand had turned the tenor of her mood.

“Ma-Martin，”she sobbed.“I'm so ashamed.”

“Drink the soup.”

Obeying him, she drank between gasping breaths. After a second cup she allowed him to lead her up to their room.She was docile now and more restrained.He laid her nightgown on the bed and was about to leave the room when a fresh round of grief, the alcoholic tumult, came again.

“He turned away. My Andy looked at me and turned away.”

Impatience and fatigue hardened his voice, but he spoke warily.“You forget that Andy is still a little child-he can't comprehend the meaning of such scenes.”

“Did I make a scene?Oh, Martin, did I make a scene before the children?”

Her horrified face touched and amused him against his will.“Forget it Put on your nightgown and go to sleep.”

“My child turned away from me. Andy looked at his mother and turned away.The children—”

She was caught in the rhythmic sorrow of alcohol. Martin withdrew from the room saying：“For God's sake go to sleep.The children will forget by tomorrow.”

As he said this he wondered if it was true. Would the scene glide so easily from memory-or would it root in the unconscious to fester in the after-years?Martin did not know, and the last alternative sickened him.He thought of Emily, foresaw the morning-after humiliation：the shards of memory, the lucidities that glared from the obliterating darkness of shame.She would call the New York offce twice-possibly three or four times.Martin anticipated his own embarrassment, wondering if the others at the offce could possibly suspect.He felt that his secretary had divined the trouble long ago and that she pitied him.He suffered a moment of rebellion against his fate；he hated his wife.

Once in the children's room he closed the door and felt secure for the first time that evening. Marianne fell down on the floor, picked herself up and calling：“Daddy, watch me，”fell again, got up, and continued the falling-calling routine.Andy sat in the child's low chair, wobbling the tooth.Martin ran the water in the tub, washed his own hands in the lavatory, and called the boy into the bathroom.

“Let's have another look at that tooth.”Martin sat on the toilet, holding Andy between his knees. The child's mouth gaped and Martin grasped the tooth.A wobble, a quick twist and the nacreous milk tooth was free.Andy's face was for the first moment split between terror, astonishment, and delight.He mouthed a swallow ofwater and spat into the lavatory.

“Look, Daddy！It's blood. Marianne！”

Martin loved to bathe his children, loved inexpressibly the tender, naked bodies as they stood in the water so exposed. It was not fair of Emily to say that he showed partiality.As Martin soaped the delicate boy-body of his son he felt that further love would be impossible.Yet he admitted the difference in the quality of his emotions for the two children.His love for his daughter was graver, touched with a strain of melancholy, a gentleness that was akin to pain.His pet names for the little boy were the absurdities of daily inspiration-he called the little girl always Marianne, and his voice as he spoke it was a caress.Martin patted dry the fat baby stomach and the sweet little genital fold.The washed child faces were radiant as fower petals, equally loved.

“I'm putting the tooth under my pillow. I'm supposed to get a quarter.”

“What for?”

“You know, Daddy. Johnny got a quarter for his tooth.”

“Who puts the quarter there?”asked Martin.“I used to think the fairies left it in the night. It was a dime in my day, though.”

“That's what they say in kindergarten.”

“Who does put it there?”

“Your parents，”Andy said.“You！”

Martin was pinning the cover on Marianne's bed. His daughter was already asleep.Scarcely breathing.Martin bent over and kissed her forehead, kissed again the tiny hand that lay palm-upward, fung in slumber beside her head.

“Good night, Andy-man.”

The answer was only a drowsy murmur. After a minute Martin took out his change and slid a quarter underneath the pillow.He left a night-light in the room.

As Martin prowled about the kitchen making a late meal, it occurred to him that the children had not once mentioned their motheror the scene that must have seemed to them incomprehensible. Absorbed in the instant-the tooth, the bath, the quarter-the fluid passage of child-time had borne these weightless episodes like leaves in the swift current of a shallow stream while the adult enigma was beached and forgotten on the shore.Martin thanked the Lord for that.

But his own anger, repressed and lurking, arose again. His youth was being frittered by a drunkard's waste, his very manhood subtly undermined.And the children, once the immunity of incomprehension passed-what would it be like in a year or so?With his elbows on the table he ate his food brutishly, untasting.There was no hiding the truth-soon there would be gossip in the offce and in the town；his wife was a dissolute woman.Dissolute.And he and his children were bound to a future of degradation and slow ruin.

Martin pushed away from the table and stalked into the living-room. He followed the lines of a book with his eyes but his mind conjured miserable images：he saw his children drowned in the river, his wife a disgrace on the public street.By bedtime the dull, hard anger was like a weight upon his chest and his feet dragged as he climbed the stairs.

The room was dark except for the shafting light from the half-opened bathroom door. Martin undressed quietly.Little by little, mysteriously, there came in him a change.His wife was asleep, her peaceful respiration sounding gently in the room.Her high-heeled shoes with the carelessly dropped stockings made to him a mute appeal.Her underclothes were fung in disorder on the chair.Martin picked up the girdle and the soft, silk brassiere and stood for a moment with them in his hands.For the frst time that evening he looked at his wife.His eyes rested on the sweet forehead, the arch of the fne brow.The brow had descended to Marianne, and the tilt at the end of the delicate nose.In his son he could trace the high cheekbones and pointed chin.Her body was full-bosomed, slenderand undulant.As Martin watched the tranquil slumber of his wife the ghost of the old anger vanished.All thoughts of blame or blemish were distant from him now.Martin put out the bathroom light and raised the window.Careful not to awaken Emily he slid into the bed.By moonlight he watched his wife for the last time.His hand sought the adjacent flesh and sorrow paralleled desire in the immense complexity of love.

A Tree, a Rock, a Cloud

It was raining that morning, and still very dark. When the boy reached the streetcar café he had almost finished his route and he went in for a cup of coffee.The place was an all-night café owned by a bitter and stingy man called Leo.After the raw, empty street, the café seemed friendly and bright：along the counter there were a couple of soldiers, three spinners from the cotton-mill, and in a corner a man who sat hunched over with his nose and half his face down in a beer mug.The boy wore a helmet such as aviators wear.When he went into the café he unbuckled the chin-strap and raised the right fap up over his pink little ear；often as he drank his coffee someone would speak to him in a friendly way.But this morning Leo did not look into his face and none of the men were talking.He paid and was leaving the café when a voice called out to him：

“Son！Hey Son！”

He turned back and the man in the corner was crooking his fnger and nodding to him. He had brought his face out of the beer mug and he seemed suddenly very happy.The man was long and pale, with a big nose and faded orange hair.

“Hey, Son！”

The boy went towards him. He was an undersized boy of about twelve, with one shoulder drawn higher than the other because of the weight of the paper-sack.His face was shallow, freckled, and his eyes were round child eyes.

“Yeah, Mister?”

The man laid one hand on the paper-boy's shoulders, thengrasped the boy's chin and turned his face slowly from one side to the other. The boy shrank back uneasily.

“Say！What's the big idea?”

The boy's voice was shrill；inside the café it was suddenly very quiet.

The man said slowly.“I love you.”

All along the counter the men laughed. The boy, who had scowled and sidled away, did not know what to do.He looked over the counter at Leo, and Leo watched him with a weary, brittle jeer.The boy tried to laugh also.But the man was serious and sad.

“I did not mean to tease you, Son，”he said.“Sit down and have a beer with me. There is something I have to explain.”

Cautiously, out of the corner of his eye, the paper-boy questioned the men along the counter to see what he should do. But they had gone back to their beer or their breakfast and did not notice him.Leo put a cup of coffee on the counter and a little jug of cream.

“He is a minor，”Leo said.

The paper-boy slid himself up on to the stool. His ear beneath the upturned fap of the helmet was very small and red.The man was nodding at him soberly.“It is important，”he said.Then he reached in his hip pocket and brought out something which he held up in the palm of his hand for the boy to see.

“Look very carefully，”he said.

The boy stared, but there was nothing to look at very carefully. The man held in his big, grimy palm a photograph.It was the face of a woman, but blurred, so that only the hat and the dress she was wearing stood out clearly.

“See?”the man asked.

The boy nodded and the man placed another picture in his palm. The woman was standing on a beach in a bathing suit.The suit made her stomach very big, and that was the main thing you noticed.

“Got a good look?”He leaned over closer and finally asked：“You ever seen her before?”

The boy sat motionless, staring slantwise at the man.“Not so I know of.”

“Very well.”The man blew on the photographs and put them back into his pocket.“That was my wife.”

“Dead?”the boy asked.

Slowly the man shook his head. He pursed his lips as though about to whistle and answered in a long-drawn way：“Nuuu—”he said.“I will explain.”

The beer on the counter before the man was in a large brown mug. He did not pick it up to drink.Instead he bent down and, putting his face over the rim, he rested there for a moment.Then with both hands he tilted the mug and sipped.

“Some night you'll go to sleep with your big nose in a mug and drown，”said Leo.“Prominent transient drowns in beer. That would be a cute death.”

The paper-boy tried to signal to Leo. While the man was not looking he screwed up his face and worked his mouth to question soundlessly：“Drunk?”But Leo only raised his eyebrows and turned away to put some pink strips of bacon on the grill.The man pushed the mug away from him, straightened himself, and folded his loose crooked hands on the counter.His face was sad as he looked at the paper-boy.He did not blink, but from time to time the lids closed down with delicate gravity over his pale green eyes.It was nearing dawn and the boy shifted the weight of the paper-sack.

“I am talking about love，”the man said.“With me it is a science.”

The boy half slid down from the stool. But the man raised his forefnger, and there was something about him that held the boy and would not let him go away.

“Twelve years ago I married the woman in the photograph. She was my wife for one year, nine months, three days, and two nights.I loved her.Yes……”He tightened his blurred, rambling voice and said again：“I loved her.I thought also that she loved me.I was arailroad engineer.She had all home comforts and luxuries.It never crept into my brain that she was not satisfed.But do you know what happened?”

“Mgneeow！”said Leo.

The man did not take his eyes from the boy's face.“She left me. I came in one night and the house was empty and she was gone.She left me.”

“With a fellow?”the boy asked.

Gently the man placed his palm down on the counter.“Why naturally, Son. A woman does not run off like that alone.”

The café was quiet, the soft rain black and endless in the street outside.Leo pressed down the frying bacon with the prongs of his long fork.“So you have been chasing the foozie for eleven years.You frazzled old rascal！”

For the first time the man glanced at Leo.“Please don't be vulgar. Besides, I was not speaking to you.”He turned back to the boy and said in a trusting and secretive undertone.“Let's not pay any attention to him.O.K.?”

The paper-boy nodded doubtfully.

“It was like this，”the man continued.“I am a person who feels many things. All my life one thing after another has impressed me.Moonlight.The leg of a pretty girl.One thing after another.But the point is that when I had enjoyed anything there was a peculiar sensation as though it was laying around loose in me.Nothing seemed to fnish itself up or ft in with the other things.Women?I had my portion of them.The same.Afterwards laying around loose in me.I was a man who had never loved.”

Very slowly he closed his eyelids, and the gesture was like a curtain drawn at the end of a scene in a play. When he spoke again his voice was excited and the words came fast-the lobes of his large, loose ears seemed to tremble.

“Then I met this woman. I was fifty-one years old and she always said she was thirty.I met her at a flling station and we weremarried within three days.And do you know what it was like?I just can't tell you.All I had ever felt was gathered together around this woman.Nothing lay around loose in me any more but was fnished up by her.”

The man stopped suddenly and stroked his long nose. His voice sank down to a steady and reproachful undertone：“I'm not explaining this right.What happened was this.There were these beautiful feelings and loose little pleasures inside me.And this woman was something like an assembly line for my soul.I run these little pieces of myself through her and I come out complete.Now do you follow me?”

“What was her name?”the boy asked.

“Oh，”he said.“I called her Dodo. But that is immaterial.”

“Did you try to make her come back?”

The man did not seem to hear.“Under the circumstances you can imagine how I felt when she left me.”

Leo took the bacon from the grill and folded two strips of it between a bun. He had a gray face, with slitted eyes, and a pinched nose saddled by faint blue shadows.One of the mill workers signaled for more coffee and Leo poured it.He did not give reflls on coffee free.The spinner ate breakfast there every morning, but the better Leo knew his customers the stingier he treated them.He nibbled his own bun as though he grudged it to himself.

“And you never got hold of her again?”

The boy did not know what to think of the man, and his child's face was uncertain with mingled curiosity and doubt. He was new on the paper route；it was still strange to him to be out in the town in the black, queer early morning.

“Yes，”the man said.“I took a number of steps to get her back. I went around trying to locate her.I went to Tulsa where she had folks.And to Mobile.I went to every town she had ever mentioned to me, and I hunted down every man she had formerly been connected with.Tulsa, Atlanta, Chicago, Cheehaw, Memphis……the better partof two years I chased around the country trying to lay hold of her.”

“But the pair of them had vanished from the face of the earth！”said Leo.

“Don't listen to him，”the man said confidentially.“And also just forget those two years. They are not important.What matters is that around the third year a curious thing begun to happen to me.”

“What?”the boy asked.

The man leaned down and tilted his mug to take a sip of beer. But as he hovered over the mug his nostrils fluttered slightly；he sniffed the staleness of the beer and did not drink.“Love is a curious thing to begin with.At frst I thought only of getting her back.It was a kind of mania.But then as time went on I tried to remember her.But do you know what happened?”

“No，”the boy said.

“When I laid myself down on a bed and tried to think about her my mind became a blank. I couldn't see her.I would take out her pictures and look.No good.Nothing doing.A blank.Can you imagine it?”

“Say, Mac！”Leo called down the counter.“Can you imagine this bozo's mind a blank！”

Slowly, as though fanning away fies, the man waved his hand. His green eyes were concentrated and fxed on the shallow little face of the paper-boy.

“But a sudden piece of glass on a sidewalk. Or a nickel tune in a music box.A shadow on a wall at night.And I would remember.It might happen in a street and I would cry or bang my head against a lamp-post.You follow me?”

“A piece of glass……”the boy said.

“Anything. I would walk around and I had no power of how and when to remember her.You think you can put up a kind of shield.But remembering don't come to a man face forward-it corners around sideways.I was at the mercy of everything I saw and heard.Suddenly instead of me combing the countryside to find her shebegun to chase me around in my very soul.She chasing me, mind you！And in my soul.”

The boy asked fnally：“What part of the country were you in then?”

“Ooh，”the man groaned.“I was a sick mortal. It was like smallpox.I confess, Son, that I boozed.I fornicated.I committed any sin that suddenly appealed to me.I am loath to confess it but I will do so.When I recall that period it is all curdled in my mind, it was so terrible.”

The man leaned his head down and tapped his forehead on the counter. For a few seconds he stayed bowed over in this position, the back of his stringy neck covered with orange furze, his hands with their long warped fngers held palm to palm in an attitude of prayer.Then the man straightened himself；he was smiling and suddenly his face was bright and tremulous and old.

“It was in the ffth year that it happened，”he said.“And with it I started my science.”

Leo's mouth jerked with a pale, quick grin.“Well none of we boys are getting any younger，”he said. Then with sudden anger he balled up a dish-cloth he was holding and threw it down hard on the foor.“You draggle-tailed old Romeo！”

“What happened?”the boy asked.

The old man's voice was high and dear：“Peace，”he answered.

“Huh?”

“It is hard to explain scientifcally, Son，”he said.“I guess the logical explanation is that she and I had feed around from each other for so long that fnally we just got tangled up together and lay down and quit. Peace.A queer and beautiful blankness.It was spring in Portland and the rain came every afternoon.All evening I just stayed there on my bed in the dark.And that is how the science come to me.”

The windows in the streetcar were pale blue with light. The two soldiers paid for their beers and opened the door-one of thesoldiers combed his hair and wiped off his muddy puttees before they went outside.The three mill workers bent silently over their breakfasts.Leo's clock was ticking on the wall.

“It is this. And listen carefully.I meditated on love and reasoned it out.I realized what is wrong with us.Men fall in love for the frst time.And what do they fall in love with?”

The boy's soft mouth was partly open and he did not answer.

“A woman，”the old man said.“Without science, with nothing to go by, they undertake the most dangerous and sacred experience in God's earth. They fall in love with a woman.Is that correct, Son?”

“Yeah，”the boy said faintly.

“They start at the wrong end of love. They begin at the climax.Can you wonder it is so miserable?Do you know how men should love?”

The old man reached over and grasped the boy by the collar of his leather jacket. He gave him a gentle little shake and his green eyes gazed down unblinking and grave.

“Son, do you know how love should be begun?”

The boy sat small and listening and still. Slowly he shook his head.The old man leaned closer and whispered：

“A tree. A rock.A cloud.”

It was still raining outside in the street：a mild, gray, endless rain. The mill whistle blew for the six o'clock shift and the three spinners paid and went away.There was no one in the café but Leo, the old man, and the little paper-boy.

“The weather was like this in Portland，”he said.“At the time my science was begun. I meditated and I started very cautious.I would pick up something from the street and take it home with me.I bought a goldfsh and I concentrated on the goldfsh and I loved it.I graduated from one thing to another.Day by day I was getting this technique.On the road from Portland to San Diego—”

“Aw shut up！”screamed Leo suddenly.“Shut up！Shut up！”

The old man still held the collar of the boy's jacket；he wastrembling and his face was earnest and bright and wild.“For six years now I have gone around by myself and built up my science. And now I am a master, Son.I can love anything.No longer do I have to think about it even.I see a street full of people and a beautiful light comes in me.I watch a bird in the sky.Or I meet a traveler on the road.Everything, Son.And anybody.All stranger and all loved！Do you realize what a science like mine can mean?”

The boy held himself stiffy, his hands curled tight around the counter edge. Finally he asked：“Did you ever really fnd that lady?”

“What?What say, Son?”

“I mean，”the boy asked timidly.“Have you fallen in love with a woman again?”

The old man loosened his grasp on the boy's collar. He turned away and for the frst time his green eyes had a vague and scattered look.He lifted the mug from the counter, drank down the yellow beer.His head was shaking slowly from side to side.Then fnally he answered：“No, Son.You see that is the last step in my science.I go cautious.And I am not quite ready yet.”

“Well！”said Leo.“Well, well, well！”

The old man stood in the open doorway.“Remember，”he said. Framed there in the gray damp light of the early morning he looked shrunken and seedy and frail.But his smile was bright.“Remember I love you，”he said with a last nod.And the door closed quietly behind him.

The boy did not speak for a long time. He pulled down the bangs on his forehead and slid his grimy little forefnger around the rim of his empty cup.Then without looking at Leo he fnally asked：

“Was he drunk?”

“No，”said Leo shortly.

The boy raised his clear voice higher.“Then was he a dope fend?”

“No.”

The boy looked up at Leo, and his fat little face was desperate, his voice urgent and shrill.“Was he crazy?Do you think he was a lunatic?”The paper-boy's voice dropped suddenly with doubt.“Leo?Or not?”

But Leo would not answer him. Leo had run a night café for fourteen years, and he held himself to be a critic of craziness.There were the town characters and also the transients who roamed in from the night.He knew the manias of all of them.But he did not want to satisfy the questions of the waiting child.He tightened his pale face and was silent.

So the boy pulled down the right fap of his helmet and as he turned to leave he made the only comment that seemed safe to him, the only remark that could not be laughed down and despised：

“He sure has done a lot of traveling.”

[1]在美国俚语中，小花生米指矮小的人。

[2]大西洋太平洋公司，美国的一家联营超市，在各大小城市都有分号。

[3]“洛”是“李蒙”第一个音节的转音，是一种爱称。

[4]美俗每年的二月二日为圣烛节，又叫“土拨鼠节”。相传土拨鼠于该日结束冬眠出洞，如天晴见到自己影子，即退入洞中继续冬眠。

[5]法语，《贝里松先生游记》应是一部法语的少儿文学作品。

[6]此处以及标题中的“神童”均用德语“wunderkind”，故有此语。

[7]美国俄亥俄州西南部城市。

[8]匈牙利作曲家李斯特的作品。

[9]德语，gut。

[10]恩斯特·布洛克（1880—1959），瑞士作曲家，后入美国籍。

[11]约翰·鲍威尔（1882—1963），美国钢琴家、作曲家。

[12]原文为“vitses”，应是“wizards”的不正确发音。

[13]这两位都是二十世纪美国音乐界的奇才，少年时即负盛名。前者是钢琴家，后者为小提琴家。

[14]当时的两位音乐家。前者为钢琴家，后者为小提琴家。

[15]萨拉托加温泉，在纽约州。该处每年夏天举行马赛。

[16]迪特里希·布克斯特胡德（1637—1707），丹麦裔德国管风琴家与作曲家。

[17]奥地利文化名城，莫扎特的出生地。

[18]多梅尼科·斯卡拉蒂（1685—1757），意大利作曲家。

[19]法语，Chez，“留在”“落在”之意。

[20]音乐术语，对位模仿的一种手法。

[21]法语，pâtisserie。

[22]芬兰首都应是赫尔辛基。

[23]法语，L’improvisation de la vie humaine，意同紧接下去的英语表述。

[24]法国王宫，在巴黎卢浮宫附近。

[25]音乐演奏术语。如弹钢琴，便是用指甲在琴键上迅速刮滑。

[26]法语，“Vite！Vite！”“Dépêchez-vous.”

[27]法语，J’attends Maman.

[28]这里指的是美国南方的一个小镇，不是法国首都。

[29]估计是利用废弃的有轨电车车厢开设的咖啡馆。

第一章　樵夫的小屋

从前，有一个樵夫，他和他的妻子住在一个小木屋里，那个木屋位于一片广袤而古老的森林边上。他们有两个可爱的孩子，这两个孩子经历了一场非常不可思议的历险。

但是讲述这段历险故事之前，我必须描述一下这两个孩子，以便你们了解他们的性格，因为他们如果不是那么可爱、勇敢和坚定，那么接下来你们要听到的这个奇妙的故事便根本不会发生。

泰泰尔——这是我们的主人公的名字——今年十岁，他的小妹妹麦泰尔只有六岁。

泰泰尔是一个样貌好看、个子高挑的小家伙，他身体壮实，黑色的头发卷卷的，经常乱成一团，因为他很喜欢嬉笑打闹。大家都很喜欢他，他的脸上总是挂着十分和气的笑容，眼睛中闪耀着明亮的光。而他最大的优点，就是他行事如同一个勇敢无畏的小大人，展示出了他高贵的内心。清晨时分，当他和父亲樵夫泰尔一起走在林中的小路上时，尽管身穿褴褛的旧衣，他看起来依然非常骄傲，带着一种庄严的气质，仿佛大地上和天空中所有美丽的事物都在等候他，在他经过的时候对他微笑。

他的小妹妹则非常不同，看上去特别甜美可爱，她穿着长裙，尽管上面打了很多补丁，不过泰尔太太将补丁缝得非常干净整齐。虽然她哥哥的头发乌黑，但是她的头发颜色却很浅，她那透着羞怯的大眼睛湛蓝湛蓝的，就如同田野中的勿忘我。任何事情都会吓到她，她可能因为任何一件小事情哭出来。但是她稚嫩的灵魂中已经具备了女性最高贵的品质——她极富爱心，性情温柔，全身心地爱着她的哥哥，不愿离开哥哥，所以便毫不犹豫地与哥哥一起踏上了漫长而危险的旅程。

我们的故事要说的，就是我们的两个小主人公为什么会在一个晚上出发去寻找幸福，一路上又发生了什么。

泰尔爸爸的小屋是乡下最破的，这房子看起来格外凄凉，因为对面是一座富丽堂皇的大房子，里面住着有钱人家的孩子们。当傍晚大房子的餐厅和客厅灯亮起来的时候，你就能透过小屋的窗户看到大房子里面的情形。而白天，你可以看到小孩们在露台、花园和暖房中玩耍。暖房里一年四季都长满了奇花异草，经常有城里的人来这里参观。

有一个晚上和其他的夜晚不太一样，因为这是圣诞节前夜，泰尔妈妈把孩子们安顿到床上，带着比平常更多的爱意亲吻了他们。她有点儿伤心，由于暴风雪，泰尔爸爸没能去森林中干活，因此她没有钱买礼物装进泰泰尔和麦泰尔的长筒袜里。孩子们很快就进入了梦乡，万籁俱寂，一片安然，除了猫的咕噜声、狗的呼噜声和祖父留下的钟的嘀嗒声，便再也听不到别的声音了。但突然间，一道像白昼一样明亮的光透过百叶窗照了进来，桌子上的灯自己又亮了起来，床上的两个孩子醒了，打着哈欠，揉着眼睛，伸展着胳膊。泰泰尔用小心谨慎的声音叫道：

“麦泰尔？”

“嗯，泰泰尔？”他的妹妹回答。

“你睡着了吗？”

“你呢？”

“没有。”泰泰尔说，“我怎么会睡着呢，我正和你说话呢。”

“我说，现在是圣诞节了吗？”妹妹问。

“还没到。明天才是圣诞节。不过今年圣诞老人不会给我们带任何礼物了。”

“为什么不会呢？”

“我听妈妈说，她没办法到城里去告诉圣诞老人。但是他明年会来的。”

“明年远吗？”

“还要过很久。”泰泰尔说，“但他今晚会去看那些有钱的孩子。”

“真的吗？”

“嘿！”突然间泰泰尔叫道，“妈妈忘了熄灯了！……我有了一个主意。”

“什么主意？”

“咱们起床吧。”

“但咱们不能起床呀。”麦泰尔说，她总是很听话。

“哎呀，周围没有人！……你看到百叶窗那边了吗？”

“啊，真亮啊！”

“那是派对的灯光。”泰泰尔说。

“什么派对？”

“对面有钱的孩子的派对。那是圣诞树。咱们把百叶窗打开吧……”

“咱们可以打开吗？”麦泰尔胆怯地问。

“当然可以。没有人拦着我们……你听到音乐声了吗？咱们起床吧。”

于是两个孩子跳下床，跑到窗户边，爬上窗边的小凳子，拉开了百叶窗。一片明亮的光填满了整个房间，孩子们充满期待地看着外面。

“一切都看得清清楚楚呢！”泰泰尔说。

“我看不到。”可怜的小麦泰尔说，凳子上几乎没有她落脚的地方了。

“下雪了。”泰泰尔说，“那里有两辆马车，每辆车都有六匹马拉着。”

“有十二个男孩从车里出来了！”麦泰尔说，她努力踮着脚向窗外看。

“别说傻话了！……那些是小女孩……”

“可他们都穿着灯笼裤啊……”

“安静！看着！”

“那些金色的东西是什么？就是挂在树枝上的那些？”

“哎呀，是玩具啊，肯定的！”泰泰尔说，“宝剑、手枪、士兵、大炮……”

“那些呢，桌子上摆的那些呢？”

“蛋糕、水果、奶油馅饼。”

“啊，那些孩子多漂亮啊！”麦泰尔拍着手说。

“他们一直在笑呢，笑得多开心啊！”泰泰尔答道。

“那些小孩儿在跳舞！……”

“是啊，是啊，咱们也跳吧！”泰泰尔说。

两个孩子开心地在凳子上跺着脚。

“哦，真好玩！”麦泰尔说。

“他们去拿蛋糕了！”泰泰尔叫道，“他们拿起蛋糕了！……他们开始吃了，他们吃了，他们吃了！……哦，多可爱的蛋糕，太可爱了！……”

麦泰尔开始数着想象中的蛋糕。

“我有十二个！……”

“我有四个十二个！”泰泰尔说，“不过我会分给你一些的……”

我们的两个小朋友又跳又笑，开心地尖叫着，沉浸在其他孩子的喜悦里，而忘了自己的贫穷和匮乏。他们很快就会得到奖励的。突然之间，响起了重重的敲门声。两个孩子一惊，停止嬉闹，一动也不敢动。然后，大大的木头门闩自己抬了起来，“吱嘎”一声，门缓缓地打开了，一个小个子老妇人走进来，她穿着一身绿色的衣服，头戴一顶红兜帽，背是驼的，脚是跛的，她只有一只眼睛，鼻子几乎要碰到下巴，还拄着一根拐杖。她肯定是一位仙女。

她蹒跚着走向孩子们，用带着鼻音的声音问道：

“你们有会唱歌的草和青色的鸟儿吗？”

“我们有一些草，”泰泰尔浑身颤抖着回答，“但是那些草不会唱歌……”

“泰泰尔有一只鸟儿。”麦泰尔说。

“但是我不能把它送人，因为它是我的。”小家伙飞快地补充道。

这难道不是最充足的理由吗？

仙女戴上她那大大的圆眼镜，仔细地看了看那只鸟儿。

“这只颜色不够青。”她说，“我需要的是完全青色的鸟儿。这是为了我的小女儿，她病得很厉害……你们知道青鸟代表什么吗？不知道？我想你们也不知道。不过因为你们是好孩子，所以我会告诉你们的。”

仙女抬起弯曲的手指，放在长长的尖鼻子边，用一种神秘的声音低声说：

“青鸟代表着幸福。我希望你们能够明白，我的小女儿必须得到幸福，才能好起来。因此，我命令你们出发去探索世界，为她寻找青鸟。你们要立刻出发……你们知道我是谁吗？”

孩子们困惑地看了看彼此。实际上，他们过去从来都没有见过仙女，因此有点儿害怕她。不过，泰泰尔很快便礼貌地回答：

“你很像我们的邻居，柏林格特太太……”

泰泰尔觉得这么说是对这位仙女的恭维，因为柏林格特太太的店——就在他们小屋的隔壁——是一个令人非常愉快的地方。里面装满了糖果、弹珠、巧克力雪茄、糖娃娃、糖母鸡。每到集市的时候，那里会有裹着金箔纸的大姜饼娃娃。柏林格特太太的鼻子就像仙女的一样丑，她的年纪也很大了。另外，她也像仙女一样，走路的时候驼背弯腰。但是她非常和气，她还有一个可爱的小女儿，过去总在星期天和樵夫家的孩子们一块玩。不幸的是，那个可怜的金黄头发的漂亮小东西总是承受着某种不知名的病痛，因此她不得不经常待在床上。每次卧床的时候，她就会乞求能和泰泰尔的鸽子一起玩耍，但是泰泰尔太喜欢那只鸟儿了，不愿意给她。小男孩觉得，这一切都和仙女告诉他的事情很像，所以他觉得仙女像柏林格特太太。

令他惊讶的是，仙女勃然大怒，脸涨得通红。她喜欢与众不同，因为她是一个仙女，可以变换自己的容貌，只要她愿意，随时都可以。那天晚上，她碰巧是一个丑陋的驼背老太太，失去了一只眼睛，两小绺灰色的头发垂在肩膀上。

“我看起来是什么样子？”她问泰泰尔，“我是漂亮还是丑陋？苍老还是年轻？”

她问这些问题是为了考验小男孩是否善良。但小男孩扭开头，不敢说出自己对她的外貌的看法。然后，她喊道：

“我是仙女贝丽露娜！”

“哦，那太好了。”泰泰尔回答，此时他浑身都在发抖。

这回答让仙女很满意。孩子们都还穿着睡衣，她告诉他们换衣服。她一边亲自动手帮麦泰尔换衣服，一边问：

“你们的爸爸妈妈呢？”

“在那里。”泰泰尔指着右边的门，“他们在睡觉。”

“你们的爷爷奶奶呢？”

“他们死了……”

“你们的弟弟妹妹……你们有弟弟妹妹吗？”

“哦，有的，三个小弟弟！”泰泰尔说。

“还有四个小妹妹。”麦泰尔补充。

“他们在哪儿？”仙女问。

“他们也死了。”泰泰尔回答。

“你们还想再见到他们吗？”

“噢，想！……一次就行！……让我们看看他们！……”

“我可没有把他们装在我的口袋里。”仙女说，“不过很幸运，在你们经过回忆之地的时候就可以见到他们了。那里在去寻找青鸟的路上，经过第三个岔路口向左拐……我敲门的时候你们在做什么？”

“我们在玩‘吃蛋糕’。”泰泰尔说。

“你们有蛋糕吗？……蛋糕在哪儿？……”

“在那些有钱孩子的房子里……过来看，非常可爱呢！”

泰泰尔拉着仙女到窗边去。

“可是吃蛋糕的是别人啊！”她说。

“是的，但是我们能看着他们吃啊。”泰泰尔说。

“你们不生他们的气吗？”

“为什么要生他们的气？”

“因为他们吃了所有的蛋糕。我觉得他们一点儿都不给你们，这非常不对。”

“一点儿也不生气。他们有钱！……啊，那边真漂亮啊！”

“这里也同样漂亮，只是你看不到……”

“我能看见。”泰泰尔说，“我的眼神非常好。我能看到教堂钟楼上的时间，爸爸就看不到！”

仙女突然生起气来。

“我跟你说了你看不见！”她说。

她越来越生气。好像能不能看到教堂钟楼上的时间是件至关重要的事儿。

当然，小男孩并不瞎，但他是个善良的孩子，理应开心快乐，仙女希望能教他看到万物内在的美好。这并不是简单的事情，因为她很清楚，大多数的人，无论生还是死，都没有享受过就在他们周围的快乐。不过，因为她是一个仙女，她是万能的，所以，她决定给泰泰尔一顶有颗魔法钻石的小帽子，这颗魔法钻石拥有一种特别的魔力，可以永远向他展示出真相，能够帮助他看到万物的内在，从而教会他，万物都有各自的生命，是独特的存在，被创造出来与我们的生命和存在相配，会令我们更快乐。

仙女从挂在身侧的一个大包中拿出了一顶小帽子。这帽子是绿色的，上面有一个白色的帽章，中间闪耀着一颗大大的钻石。泰泰尔十分高兴。仙女给他讲解了那颗钻石如何使用：按一下钻石，你就可以看到事物的灵魂，如果把它往右转一转，你就会发现过去，把它转向左边，你就会看到未来。

泰泰尔的脸上神采奕奕，他开心地手舞足蹈。然后，他立刻又开始担心会失去这顶小帽子。

“爸爸会把它从我这里拿走的！”他喊道。

“不会的，”仙女说，“因为只要你把它戴到头上，就没人能看到它……你想试试吗？”

“好啊，好啊！”孩子们拍着手叫道。

那帽子一戴到小男孩的头上，一切都发生了神奇的变化。老仙女变成了一个年轻漂亮的公主，穿着丝绸的衣服，戴着闪闪发光的珠宝，小屋的墙壁变得透明，就像珍贵的宝石一样熠熠发光，简陋的松木家具就像大理石一样闪着光泽。两个孩子跑来跑去，拍着手，快乐地叫着。

“啊，真可爱，真可爱！”泰泰尔叫道。

而麦泰尔，天生是个爱美的小东西，看到仙女公主美丽的衣裙，像是着迷了一样呆住了。

不过，还有更多更大的惊喜在等着他们。仙女不是说过吗，所有物品，所有动物，都会活过来，就像人一样说话行动？看啊，看啊，祖父那个老钟表的门突然间就打开了，寂静被最甜美的音乐填充，十二个穿着优雅、笑容灿烂的小小舞者开始围着孩子们跳跃旋转。

“这是你们生命中的时间。”仙女说。

“我能和她们一起跳舞吗？”泰泰尔说，他羡慕地望着这些美丽的生灵，她们就像小鸟一样在地板上跳跃飞腾。

但就在这时，他爆发出一阵大笑。有个好笑的胖家伙，胖得都喘不过气来，浑身挂着面粉，挣扎着从面包烤盘里爬出来向孩子们鞠躬。这是谁啊？这是面包！面包趁现在能够自由，出来到地上溜达一下！他看上去像个矮胖而滑稽的老先生。他的脸是鼓胀的面团，在粗壮的胳膊末端是一双大手，两只手放在圆滚滚的大肚子上时，根本没办法握在一起。他穿着一件紧身的面包皮色的衣服，胸前有些条纹，就像我们当作早餐的漂亮的黄油面包卷一样。他的头上——想想看吧——他顶着一个巨大的圆面包，就像是戴着一条滑稽的头巾。

他刚跌跌撞撞地从烤盘里出来，这时就有别的和他一样的面包——不过更小一些——跟在他后面，和时间们一起跳舞，完全不在乎他们抖落到那些漂亮小姐身上的面粉，把她们包裹在一大片白色的云雾里。

这是一个奇怪而迷人的舞会。孩子们十分开心。时间们和面包们跳着华尔兹，盘子们也加入了其中，在厨具柜上冒着掉下去摔得粉碎的危险上蹿下跳，橱柜里的玻璃杯彼此相碰，祝愿所有人都身体健康。至于叉子，他们和餐刀聊个没完，嗓门很大，大到你都听不到自己的声音了……

如果这喧闹持续的时间更长一些的话，谁也不知道会发生什么。泰尔爸爸和泰尔妈妈肯定会被吵醒。幸好，当这场嬉闹到达高潮的时候，一团巨大的火焰从灯罩中跳了出来，令整个房间闪耀着明亮的红光，就像是整个房子着了火一样。所有人都惊慌地躲到了墙角，而泰泰尔和麦泰尔则害怕地抽泣着，把头藏到了好仙女的斗篷下面。

“别害怕，”她说，“这只是火而已，他是来和你们一起玩的。他是个好人，但你们最好不要碰他，因为他是个暴脾气。”

孩子们透过仙女斗篷上漂亮的金色蕾丝边紧张地往外看，看到了一个红色的高个子也正看着他们，在笑话他们的胆小呢。他穿着猩红色的紧身衣，上面缀满了亮片。当他挥动长胳膊的时候，肩膀上垂下来的丝绸披肩就像火焰一样。他的头发在头上一缕缕地直竖着，发着亮光。他甩着双臂和双腿，就像个疯子一样在房间中跳来跳去。

泰泰尔尽管感觉稍微放松了一些，不过仍然不敢离开自己的庇护所。这时，仙女贝丽露娜有了一个极好的主意，她用她的魔棒指了指水龙头，立刻，出现了一个年轻女孩，她不停哭泣，就像不会枯竭的喷泉一样。这是水。她非常漂亮，但是她的样子悲伤极了。她唱着歌，声音柔美，如同泉水的叮咚声。她长长的头发一直垂到脚面，也许是用海藻做的。她身上只穿着睡袍，但身上流淌着的水仿佛衣服一样裹着她，泛着盈盈的光。她起初有些犹豫，然后环顾四周，看到还在像个无法自控的疯子一样乱转的火，便恼怒而气愤地扑向了他，向他的脸上喷水，用尽全力将他弄湿。火暴跳如雷，开始冒烟。不过，他突然发现向自己发难的是他的宿敌，就觉得还是躲到角落里比较明智。水也撤到了一边，一切似乎又归于平静。

两个孩子终于从惊恐中恢复过来，问仙女接下来会发生什么。就在这时，陶罐碎裂的声音把大家吓了一跳，他们转头看向桌子那里。真是让人惊讶啊！地板上的牛奶罐碎成了无数片，从碎片中站起一位迷人的女子，她惊恐地低叫了几声，紧握着双手，抬起充满恳求的双眼。

泰泰尔赶忙上前去安慰她，因为他立刻就认出她是牛奶。他非常喜欢她，给了她一个善意的吻。她就像一个挤奶小女工一样清新美丽，覆盖着奶油的白色裙子散发着一股香甜的干草气味。

这个时候，麦泰尔正看着糖块，他似乎也要活过来了。糖块在门旁边的一个架子上，裹在蓝色糖纸中，他不断地晃来晃去，左摇右摆，但没有任何用处。最后，一条长长细细的胳膊伸了出来，然后是一个尖脑袋撑破纸钻了出来，再然后是另一条胳膊和两条长到没边儿的腿。哎呀，你们真应该看看糖先生有多好笑，非常好笑，真的，孩子们看到他的脸，就都情不自禁地大笑起来。不过，他们都很愿意友好待他，因为他们听到仙女这么介绍他：

“泰泰尔，这是糖的灵魂。他的口袋里面装满了糖，他的手指都是糖棍儿。”

有一位由糖做成的朋友是多好的事啊，只要你想吃糖了，就可以从他身上咬下一块。

“汪，汪，汪！早上好，早上好，我的小上帝！……我们终于，终于可以交谈了。尽管以前我可以叫或是摇动尾巴，但你们从来都不懂我的意思！……我爱你们！我爱你们！”

这个独特的人是谁啊？这个围着所有人打转，让整个屋子充满了他欢乐的喧闹声的人是谁啊？我们一眼就认出了他。这是泰罗，一只善良的狗，全心全意地想理解人类，他是陪着孩子们去森林的天性善良的动物，是守护大门的忠诚护卫，是永远真诚忠实的可靠朋友。他用两只后腿走过来——这两只腿显得有些太短了，两只前腿举在空中挥来舞去，像是一个笨拙的小人儿一样比画着。他一点儿都没有变，依然有着光滑的芥末色皮毛，喜气洋洋的斗牛犬的脑袋，顶着黑色的鼻子，但是他比原来大了很多，而且会说话了！他说得飞快，好像是想抓紧时间为自己的种群平反，他们已经沉默了好几百年了。他什么话题都想说一说，因为他终于能说话了。他吻了他的小主人们，叫他们“我的小上帝”，这情景真是太感人了。他一会儿坐下，一会儿又跳起来满屋子跑，弄翻家具，用他柔软的大爪子扑倒了麦泰尔，伸舌头，摇尾巴，呼哧呼哧地喘着粗气，就像在外面打猎一样。我们一下子就看出他生性淳朴而慷慨。他深信自己的重要性，觉得自己可是这个新世界当中必不可少的一分子呢。

在两个孩子面前尽情表现之后，他便把注意力投到了其他人身上，他认为每个人都必然需要他的关注。他的快乐自由地释放出来，无拘无束，因为他是最富有爱心的生物，如果他变成人形之后，没有保留他那些做小狗时的缺点，他也应该是最快乐的。他的缺点是嫉妒！他非常爱嫉妒！看到猫咪泰莱特也变成了人形，而且就像他一样，也得到了孩子们的爱抚和亲吻，他的心感觉到一阵剧痛。噢，天啊，他真是讨厌那只猫！看着她在他身边晃悠，看着她也分享着这个家庭的关爱，便是命运要他做出的最大牺牲。但是，他还是毫无怨言地接受了，因为这会令他的小上帝们开心，不过他总是尽可能和那只猫保持距离。但是因为她，他已经犯了很多令他内疚的罪行！难道他没有在一天晚上，偷偷摸摸地溜进柏林格特太太的厨房，想要把那只与他无冤无仇的老公猫掐死？难道他没有把对面房子里的波斯猫的脊背抓破？他偶尔会去城里不就为了追捕那些猫，给他们的生命画上句号，以此发泄他的恶意吗？而现在，泰莱特也要说话了，就像他一样！在这个出现在他面前的新世界中，泰莱特也会和他平分秋色！

“唉，这世界上简直没有公道了！”他苦涩地想着，“没有公道了！”

而这个时候，那只猫，刚刚清理完自己的毛，舔过她的爪子，正温柔地将爪子放在小女孩身上。

她真的是一只特别漂亮的猫。如果我们的朋友泰罗的嫉妒不是那么丑恶的一种感情的话，我们都可能会忽略这种嫉妒了。你怎么可能不被泰莱特的眼睛吸引呢？那就像是镶在祖母绿中的黄宝石一样璀璨啊。你怎么能抗拒轻抚那黑丝绒般美丽的后背的乐趣呢？你怎么能不爱上她那优雅、温柔和高贵的仪态呢？

她温和地笑着，字斟句酌地对麦泰尔说：

“早上好，小姐！你今天早上真是漂亮极了！”

孩子们也同样爱抚着她。

泰罗一直从房间的另一端望着猫。

“现在她也像个人一样用后腿直立着呢，”他低声咕哝道，“她看上去就像个魔鬼，看她那尖耳朵，那长尾巴，还有那黑得像墨水一样的衣服！”他不可自控地低声嘶吼，“她还像那个扫烟囱的乡下人！”他继续咕哝，“那个人我也不喜欢，我也讨厌，我绝对不会将他当作一个真正的人看待，不管我的小上帝们会怎么说……真幸运，”他叹了口气又说，“我知道的东西可比他们多多了！”

但是突然间，他再也没有办法控制自己了，便飞扑向那只猫，他大笑一声，不过更像是咆哮，嘴里喊着：

“我要吓吓泰莱特！汪，汪，汪！”

不过那只猫，在还是动物的时候就自视甚高，现在变成了人形，觉得自己注定是最高贵的。她认为，现在应该在自己和那只狗之间树立一道高高的壁垒，那只狗在她眼中不过是一个没什么教养的人而已，她轻蔑地退后一步，说道：

“先生，我可不认识你！”

面对这种羞辱，泰罗猛地跃起，而那只猫咪则竖起毛发，捻着她粉色小鼻子下面的胡须——这两绺白色的胡须一直让她引以为傲，她觉得这为她全身黑色的皮毛更添光彩——然后，她拱起背，竖直了尾巴，嘴里发出呜呜的声音，她一动不动地站在抽屉柜上，就像中国花瓶盖子上的龙一样。

泰泰尔和麦泰尔都爆笑出声，不过，如果这个时候没有发生一件了不得的事情，这场对峙的结局肯定很糟糕。就在夜里的十一点钟，在冬夜夜半时分，一束极强的光，如同正午时分的阳光，闪闪发亮，璀璨夺目，照射进了小屋当中。

“呀，天亮了！”小男孩不知道是怎么回事，“爸爸会怎么说呢？”

但是，还没等仙女给他指点迷津，泰泰尔就明白了一切，他满怀惊叹，跪在了这一幕刚出现的景象前。

在窗口处，一个大大的光环中间出现了一位无比可爱的女子，她个子高挑，就如同一束金色的麦束。她披着闪亮的纱巾，但这纱巾遮挡不住她的美丽；她光洁的胳膊伸展着，做出了给予的姿势，像是透明的一般；她澄澈的大眼睛让每一个人都感觉如同被环绕在温柔的拥抱当中。

“女王！”泰泰尔说。

“是仙女公主！”麦泰尔叫道，她跪在了哥哥的旁边。

“不对，孩子们，”仙女说，“这是光。”

光微笑着，走向两个孩子。她，来自天国的光，尘世间的力量和美丽，她为自己担负的谦卑使命而骄傲，过去她从来都无拘无束，生活在无尽的空间中，将她的慷慨馈赠给所有人，一视同仁，而此刻她愿意暂时因为一个短暂的魔咒，被限制为人类的形态，以便引领孩子们走入外面的世界，教他们去认识其他的光——思想之光——这种光我们从来都看不见，却可以帮助我们看清一切。

“是光啊！”所有物品和所有动物齐声叫道。因为他们都爱她，开始欢声笑语地围绕着她跳起舞来。

泰泰尔和麦泰尔也喜悦得手舞足蹈。他们从来都没有想过会有这么有趣、这么美丽的派对，他们的叫声盖过了所有声音。

然后，避免不了的事情发生了。突然，响起了三声敲墙的声音，大得足以把房子掀翻。是泰尔爸爸，他被喧闹声吵醒，威胁要过来制止。

“快转动钻石！”仙女对泰泰尔喊道。

我们的小主人公赶紧照办，但是他还没有掌握转动宝石的窍门，一想到爸爸就要过来了，他的手就不住地颤抖。实际上，他现在笨手笨脚的，几乎把那宝贝扯坏。

“别那么快，别那么快！”仙女说，“噢，亲爱的，你转得太快了，他们没有时间回归原位，我们可要有不少麻烦了！”

接着就像是大逃亡一样。小屋的墙壁都失去了光彩，大家都四散奔逃，好变回自己原来的形态。火找不到灯罩了，水跑着奔向水龙头，糖在撕裂的糖纸前站着哭泣，最大的那块面包没有办法挤进自己的烤盘里了，因为其他的面包杂乱无章地挤了进去，把所有空间都占满了。至于那只狗，他现在个子太大，没有办法钻进狗舍的入口，猫也没有办法进自己的篮子里。只有时间们例外，她们一向比人们希望的走得快，此刻毫不迟疑地溜回到了钟表里。

只有光一动不动地站着，镇定平静，给其他人树立了一个镇定的榜样，但这没有什么用，其他人全都在仙女周围啜泣哀号。

“接下来会发生什么？”他们问道，“会有危险吗？”

“好吧，”仙女说，“我应该把真话告诉你们，那些陪伴这两个孩子的人都会在旅途的终点死去。”

他们都拼命地哭起来，除了那只狗，他很高兴能够保持人形，觉得这样就很幸福。现在他已经站在了光的旁边，以便能够走在他的小主人们前面。

就在这时，又响起了一阵更加可怕的敲墙声。

“还是爸爸！”泰泰尔说，“这次他起来了，我能听到他走路的声音……”

“你们看，”仙女说，“现在你们没有选择了，太晚了，你们必须全都跟着我们上路了……但是你，火，不要靠近别人。你，狗，不要欺负猫。你，水，不要流得四处都是。还有你，糖，不要哭了，除非你自己想要化掉。面包拿上装青鸟的笼子。你们全都要到我家，然后我会把动物们和物品们都打扮整齐……咱们从这边走！”

她说着，举起魔杖指向窗户，窗户神奇地向下扩展，变得像是一道门一样。他们都踮着脚尖走出那扇门，然后窗户就又变回了原来的样子。在圣诞夜清澈的月光下，钟声当当地响起，宣告着耶稣诞生的那个时刻。而就在这时，泰泰尔和麦泰尔踏上了寻找能带给人们幸福的青鸟的旅程。

第二章　在仙女家

仙女贝丽露娜的宫殿位于一座很高很高的山顶上，就在通向月亮的路上。那里离月亮非常近，在夏天的晚上，当天空很晴朗的时候，在宫殿的阳台上，你可以清楚地看到月亮上的山脉和峡谷，湖泊和海洋。仙女就在那里观察星象，解读它们的秘密，因为从很久以前，地球就已经没有什么新鲜东西可以供她学习了。

“这个古老的星球已经没有什么能引起我的兴趣了！”她总是对她的朋友山中巨人们这么说，“地球上的人们依然闭着眼睛生活！可怜的东西啊，我真可怜他们！我时不时地到人间去，但也只是出于慈悲，想要拯救那些可怜的孩子，让他们避开黑暗中等待着他们的不幸命运。”

就是因为这个，仙女才在圣诞前夜来到了泰尔家的小屋。

现在还是来说说我们的旅行家们吧。他们还没有走上大路，仙女就想起来，他们不能这样穿过村子，因为过节，现在村子里还灯火通明。不过，她的博闻多识让她无所不能，立刻就能找到实现愿望的办法。她轻轻地按了按泰泰尔的头，许愿说希望他们可以通过魔法到达她的宫殿。立刻就有一团萤火虫围住了我们的旅行家，轻轻地将他们带上了天空。他们还没来得及收起惊奇，就已经到达了仙女的宫殿。

“跟我走。”她说，带着他们穿过一个个房间，一道道走廊，这些房间和走廊全都是金银筑成的。

他们在一个大房间里停了下来，这里四面墙都是镜子，房内还有一个特别大的衣橱，有光从衣橱门缝中流泻出来。仙女贝丽露娜从口袋中掏出一把钻石钥匙，打开了衣橱门。所有人异口同声地发出了惊叹声。里面装着各种奇珍异宝，层层叠叠的，有缀着宝石的披风，各个国家的各种各样的服装，珍珠宝冠，祖母绿的项链，红宝石的手镯……孩子们从来都没有见过这么贵重的东西！而至于那些动物和物品的灵魂，则完全目瞪口呆。这是自然的，你得理解，这是他们第一次看到这个世界，而这个世界展现出来的方式则是非常奇特的。

仙女帮助他们做出了自己的选择。首先，火、糖和猫展示出了特别的品位。火只喜欢红色，立刻就选择了一件带金色亮片的亮红色长袍。他没有戴帽子或围巾，因为他的头总是非常热。糖只能接受白色和灰蓝色的东西，亮色和他甜美的天性不符。他选择了一件蓝白两色的长袍，一顶尖尖的帽子，这帽子就像是个蜡烛熄灭器，他戴在头顶上，显得非常滑稽，但是他自己太蠢了，没有注意这一点，一直像个陀螺一样在镜子前面转来转去，盲目快乐地欣赏着自己。

一直以淑女自居的猫习惯了自己暗色的衣服，总认为黑色看起来很好看，不管什么情况都好看，特别是现在，他们没有带行李旅行，黑色更是极好的选择。她穿上了一套黑色的紧身衣，上面还有黑色的绣花，她的肩上挂着一件长长的天鹅绒斗篷，她光洁小巧的头上戴着一顶大大的骑士帽，帽子上有一根长长的羽毛。然后，她又要了一双山羊皮的软靴，以纪念她那杰出的祖先“穿靴子的猫”，她在前爪上戴了一副手套，保护它们以免被路上的尘土弄脏。

打扮好之后，她满意地照了照镜子。然后她眨着紧张而焦虑的眼睛，翕动着粉色的鼻子，匆匆忙忙地要求糖和火跟她一起出去转转。所以，别人还在选衣服，他们三个便走了出去。我们把注意力放在他们身上一会儿吧，因为我们已经渐渐喜欢上我们勇敢的小泰泰尔了，所以想听听任何可能对他有帮助或是对他造成阻碍的事情。

他们一路穿过了好几条富丽堂皇的走廊，这些走廊就如同悬在天空之中的露台一样，我们的三个密友最后停在大厅中，猫立刻压低声音开始了密会讲话：

“我带你们来这里，是为了讨论一下我们目前的处境。我们一定要珍惜我们最后的自由时光……”

但一阵狂烈的叫声打断了她：

“汪，汪，汪！”

“听！”猫叫道，“是那只傻狗！他闻到咱们的气味了！真是一分钟安宁都没有。咱们藏到栏杆后面去吧。他最好没听到我刚才说的话。”

“来不及了。”糖说，他是站在门口的。

确实来不及了，泰罗过来了，跳着，叫着，喘着粗气，兴高采烈。

一看到他，猫便厌恶地转过了身。

“他穿的是灰姑娘的马车仆从的制服……这还真是配他，他骨子里就是个马屁精！”

她说完这些话，又呜呜叫了两声，然后捻着胡子，充满挑衅地站在糖和火中间。那只善良的小狗没有注意到她的小把戏。他整个心思都沉浸在被打扮得华美的喜悦中，一圈一圈地跳着。这画面很有意思，他的天鹅绒外套像旋转木马一样转来转去，衣服的下摆时不时地飞起来，露出他那被截断过的小尾巴，就因为尾巴时隐时露，所以更具表现力。我必须得告诉你，就像所有良种斗牛犬一样，泰罗在还是小狗的时候，尾巴和耳朵就被剪短了。

可怜的家伙，一直都很嫉妒他的兄弟们的尾巴——长长的尾巴能表达更多的意思。但是身体上的缺陷和命运的艰辛会强化我们的内在品质。由于缺乏自我表达的外在方式，泰罗的灵魂一直在沉默中成长，他的表情总是充满了爱意，非常生动。

今天，他黑色的大眼睛里闪烁着快乐，他突然间变成了一个人！他浑身上下穿着华丽的衣裳，他将陪着小上帝们周游世界，去完成一项伟大的使命！

“瞧瞧！”他说，“瞧瞧！我们多好啊！……看看这花边和绣花！……这是真金的，肯定是的！”

他没有看出其他人在嘲笑他，说实话，他的样子确实非常滑稽。但是就像所有淳朴的生命一样，他没有幽默感。他为他那身天生的黄色皮毛而骄傲，所以他没有穿马甲，确保没有人会质疑他的来历。出于同样考虑，他保留着他的项圈，上面写着他的地址。他外面穿着一件镶着重重的金子花边的红色天鹅绒大外套，一直垂到膝盖处。他认为两侧的大口袋可以装上些食物，因为泰罗很贪吃。他的左耳上斜扣着一顶小圆帽，上面插着一根鱼鹰的羽毛，为了把帽子固定在他那大大的方脑袋上，他用了一根橡皮筋，这将他肥胖松弛的大脸勒成了两半。他的另一只耳朵依然露在外面。这只耳朵被修剪得很小，贴近头部，就像是小小的装螺丝的三角形纸袋子，这只耳朵非常警觉，聆听着所有的声音。所有的声音都像是石头落入水面一样，吸引他的注意力。

他还在后腿上穿上了一双白色鞋面的漆皮马靴，但是他认为他的前爪得经常使用，所以什么样的手套都无法吸引他。泰罗天生性格坚定，不会在一天之间改变习惯，所以，尽管他化身为高贵的人，还是允许自己做一些不合身份的事情。此刻，他正趴在大厅的台阶上，用爪子挠着地面，嗅着墙壁的味道，然后突然间猛地一抖，开始哀号！他的下嘴唇剧烈颤抖着，就像要哭出来一样。

“那个蠢蛋怎么了？”猫问道，她一直在用眼角的余光看着狗。

但是她立刻就明白了：从远处传来了一阵甜美的歌声，泰罗是受不了这歌声。歌声越来越近，一个女孩清亮的声音飘荡在高耸的拱门的阴影里，水出现了。她高高的，纤弱柔美，白得像珍珠一样，她似乎是飘过来的，而不是走过来的。她的动作轻柔而优雅，如梦似幻。她美丽的银色裙子飘荡着，一直垂到膝盖的头发上装点着珊瑚。

一看到她，火就露出粗鲁而充满恶意的本来面目，嗤之以鼻地说：

“她居然没有带把伞！”

但是水是个非常聪明的人，她知道两个人当中她是强大的那个，看着火那炽热的红鼻子，她愉快地打趣他说：

“抱歉，你说什么？……我猜你是在说我前几天看到的那个大红鼻子吧！”

其他人都笑话起火来，他的脸总是像烧红的煤一样。火气得蹿到了屋顶上，准备过会儿再复仇。这个时候，猫走到水的身边，小心翼翼地，极力恭维水的裙子。不用我说大家也都知道，她的话没有一句是真心的，但是她希望能和所有人保持友好，因为她希望得到他们的支持，才能实现她的计划。没有看到面包，她很焦虑，因为她不想在人到齐之前开始说话。

“他到底在做什么呢？”她喵喵地说着，问了一遍又一遍。

“他在挑衣服，挑来挑去没个完。”狗说，“最后，他终于看上了一件土耳其长袍，配了一柄弯刀，和一条土耳其头巾。”

他的话还没说完，一个穿得五颜六色、看不出形状的大块头就过来了，这个大块头堵住了大厅的窄门。原来是面包的大肚子占满了整个门口。不知道为什么，他总是跌跌撞撞的，可能因为他并不怎么聪明，另外，他也不习惯在人类的屋子里面走动。最后，他终于灵光一闪，弯下腰侧着身子挤进门，总算进了大厅。

当然，这进入的过程并不怎么顺利，但是他还是非常高兴。

“我来啦！”他说，“我来啦！我穿上了蓝胡子(1)最好的衣服……你们觉得怎么样？”

狗开始绕着他打转，他觉得面包实在太棒了。那件黄色的天鹅绒衣服上面点缀着银色的月牙儿，让泰罗想到了他喜欢的美味马蹄形面包卷，还有面包头上那花哨的大头巾，真的非常非常像是一个美味的圆面包。

“他多好看啊！”狗叫道，“他多好看啊！”

牛奶羞怯地跟在面包身后。她的心思淳朴，因此比起仙女建议她穿的那些漂亮衣服，她更喜欢自己的奶油外衣。她真的是个谦逊的姑娘。

面包开始谈论起泰泰尔、光和麦泰尔的衣服，这时，猫用一种权威的声音打断了他的话。

“我们到时候就会看到他们的。”她说，“别闲聊了，听我说，时间紧迫，我们的未来很危险……”

大家都迷惑地望着她。他们都明白这是一个严肃的时刻，但是人类的语言对他们来说依然非常难懂。糖痛苦地绞着长手指；面包拍着大肚子；水躺在地板上，似乎在承受着巨大的痛苦；而牛奶只是看着面包，他们俩是多年的好友了。

猫非常不耐烦地继续说：

“仙女说过，旅程的终点也就是我们生命的终点。所以，我们应该用各种办法，尽可能让旅途漫长……”

面包害怕如果自己不再维持人形就会被吃掉，立刻表示赞同；但是狗站得离他们有些远，假装没有听见，内心深处却在怒吼。他非常清楚猫在暗示什么。猫咪泰莱特最后说道：“我们必须不惜一切代价拖延旅程，阻止他们找到青鸟，哪怕会危及那两个孩子的性命。”而那善良的狗，只愿遵从自己内心的意愿，听到这些话立刻就扑向猫去咬她。糖、面包和火迅速地拦到两人中间。

“注意秩序！注意秩序！”面包傲慢地说，“我现在可主持着会议呢。”

“是谁选你做会议主席的？”火吼道。

“谁要你跟着掺和的？”水把自己湿漉漉的头发甩向火。

“抱歉，”糖浑身发抖，却用安抚的语调说，“抱歉……现在是个很重要的时刻……咱们还是友好点儿交谈吧。”

“我十分赞同糖和猫。”面包说，似乎觉得这话能够结束一切。“太荒唐了！”狗说，他吠叫着，露出了牙齿，“那是人类，人类就是一切！……我们必须服从于人类，听从他们的吩咐！……除了人类，我谁也不认！……人类万岁！……人类万岁！……不管生死，全都听人类的！……人类就是一切！”

但是猫那尖锐的声音盖住了其他人的声音。她对人类充满了怨恨，她希望能好好利用化成人形的短暂时刻，给自己的整个种族复仇。

“我们所有人都在这里，”她说，“动物们，物品们，元素们，都拥有自己的灵魂，人类并不了解我们的灵魂。这也是我们保有自己独立性的原因，但如果人类找到了青鸟，他们就会知道一切，他们就会看到一切，我们就会完全任人摆布……想想我们曾自由自在行走在大地上的日子！”但是突然间，她的脸色变了，她的声音变成了低语的嘶嘶声，“注意！我听到仙女和光来了。不用我告诉你们，你们也知道光已经站在了人类那一边，她会用尽办法支持他们，她是我们最可怕的敌人……小心！”

但是我们的朋友们都没有什么耍花招的经验，觉得心中有愧，气氛一时尴尬而不自然，所以，仙女一进门，就问道：

“你们躲在角落里干什么呢？……你们看上去就像是一伙阴谋家！”

他们非常害怕，觉得仙女已经猜到了他们邪恶的企图，他们都跪在了仙女的面前。不过，他们很幸运，仙女根本没有想他们的小脑袋瓜里到底在想些什么。她过来是向孩子们说明旅途开始部分的安排，告知每个人都应该做什么。泰泰尔和麦泰尔手牵着手站在她面前，他们身上穿着华丽的衣服，看起来有点儿惶恐和不知所措。他们用孩子的那种赞赏的目光看着彼此。

小女孩穿了一件黄色的丝绸长裙，裙子上绣着粉色的花朵，缀着金亮片。她的头上戴着一顶可爱的橘色天鹅绒帽子，肩上还罩着笔挺的平纹布小抵肩。泰泰尔穿着红色夹克和蓝色灯笼裤，一身都是天鹅绒的，当然，他头顶上戴着那顶神奇的小帽子。

仙女对他们说：

“青鸟有可能躲在回忆之地——你们祖父母的家里，所以你们要先到那里去。”

“但是他们已经死了，我们怎么才能见到他们呢？”泰泰尔问。

善良的仙女解释说，只要他们的孙子孙女还在想念着他们，他们就不会真正死去。

“人们不知道这个秘密，”她补充说，“但是，因为这颗钻石，泰泰尔，你会看到，那些我们想念的逝者依然快乐地生活着，就像他们没去世时一样。”

“你和我们一起去吗？”男孩转头问光。光就站在刚进门的地方，将整个大厅照得十分明亮。

“不。”仙女说，“光不能回到过去。她的能量必须留着给未来。”

在两个孩子正准备上路时，突然觉得非常饿。仙女立刻吩咐面包给他们一些吃的东西。那个大胖子非常高兴自己得此重任，便解开长袍，拔出弯刀，从肚子上切了两块下来。两个孩子欢欣雀跃。泰罗暂时抛开了不开心，也要了一点儿面包。大家都互道珍重。糖认为自己很重要，为了给大家留下好印象，就掰下了自己的两根手指，递给了吃惊不已的孩子。

所有人都向门口走去，仙女贝丽露娜拦住了他们。

“今天还不行。”她说，“孩子们必须独自上路，有别人陪着他们并不合适，他们是要去和他们已故的家人共度这个夜晚。所以，出发吧！再见，亲爱的孩子们，记着要按时回来，这非常重要！”

两个孩子手拉着手，拎着大鸟笼子，走出大厅。而他们的朋友们，在仙女的指挥下，排好队准备回到宫殿中。我们的朋友泰罗，是唯一一个没有在点名的时候回应的。他听到仙女说孩子们要独自前往，便立刻决定无论发生什么事都要跟过去照顾他们。于是在其他人道别的时候，他躲到了门后面。但是这可怜的家伙并没有想到没有什么能逃过仙女贝丽露娜那无所不见的眼睛。

“泰罗！”她叫道，“泰罗！过来！”

可怜的小狗一向驯服听话，不敢抗拒这命令，只好夹着尾巴回来了，站在了队伍当中。他绝望地低声呜咽着，看着他的两个小主人消失在巨大的黄金楼梯的尽头。

————————————————————

(1) 是法国民间传说中连续杀害自己六任妻子的人。

第三章　回忆之地

仙女贝丽露娜告诉过两个孩子，回忆之地并不远，可要到达那里，必须穿过一片森林，那片森林浓密而古老，身处其间，眼睛都无法看到树顶。而且，森林里总是被浓重的雾气笼罩着，如果仙女没有提前告诉他们“就在正前方，只有那一条路”，他们肯定会迷路的。

林中的地上铺满了鲜花，这些花几乎都是同一种，全都是雪白色的三色堇，非常漂亮。但是因为这些花从来都见不到阳光，所以全都没有香味。

这些小花让本来感到非常孤单的孩子们得到了一些安慰。他们身处无边而神秘的寂静之中，浑身发抖，心里有一种恐惧的感觉，但又交织着快乐，这种感觉他们从来都没有过。

“咱们给奶奶带一束花吧。”麦泰尔说。

“好主意！她肯定会喜欢的！”泰泰尔大声说。

于是，他们一边走，一边摘花，很快就摘了一束漂亮的白色花朵。这两个可爱的小家伙并不知道，他们摘下的每一朵三色堇（三色堇的花语是“一份思念”）都令他们与祖父母更近一些。很快他们便看到眼前有一棵大橡树，上面钉了一个告示牌。

“我们到了！”男孩喜悦地叫道，他顺着橡树的一条根爬上去，读道：“回忆之地。”

他们已经到了，但是他们看了看四周，却什么都没有看到。

“我什么也看不到。”麦泰尔低声啜泣，“我觉得很冷！……还累了！……我不想再走了！”

泰泰尔一心沉浸在自己的使命中，因此便发起了脾气：

“好啦，别像水一样总哭个不停！……你这么做很丢脸啊！”他说，“嘿！看啊！快看！雾散了！”

的确，他们眼前的雾散开了，就像是面纱被一只看不到的手撕裂，大树纷纷隐去，所有的东西都消失了，然后出现了一个漂亮的小农舍，小屋在一个小花园当中，屋上爬满了藤萝，花园里开满了鲜花，还有果实累累的树木。

孩子们立刻就认出了果园中那头可爱的奶牛、门口那儿的看门狗、柳条鸟笼中的黑鹂。一切都沐浴在淡淡的光晕中，温馨而美丽。

泰泰尔和麦泰尔呆住了。这就是回忆之地！这里的天气多好啊！待在这里感觉真舒服啊！他们立刻就决定要经常回到这里，因为他们已经认识路了。而最令他们开心的是，当迷雾最终散尽的时候，他们看到，在离他们几步远的地方，爷爷和奶奶正坐在一条长椅上沉沉地睡着。两个孩子拍着手，高兴地大声喊道：

“是爷爷！是奶奶！……他们在这儿！他们在这儿！”

但是，他们对这神奇的一幕有点儿害怕，不敢从树后面出来。他们站在原地，看着亲爱的爷爷奶奶。两个老人已经渐渐醒了过来。然后，他们听到泰尔奶奶颤抖的声音说：

“我觉得我们那还活着的孙子孙女今天要来看我们。”

泰尔爷爷回答道：

“他们肯定想着我们呢，因为我也有种奇怪的感觉，有点儿坐立不安呢。”

“我觉得他们肯定就在附近，”奶奶说，“因为我看到喜悦的眼泪就在我眼前舞动，而且……”

奶奶的话还没有说完，两个孩子就投入了她的怀抱！……这可真是开心啊！他们又是亲吻，又是拥抱！多惊喜啊！这种幸福简直难以用语言来形容。他们大笑着，却说不出什么，只是一直欣喜地望着彼此。真是再没有这么令人开心、令人惊喜的相见了啊！当最初的激动过去后，他们立刻聊了起来。

“你现在长得真是又高又壮啊，泰泰尔！”奶奶说。

爷爷也喊道：“还有麦泰尔！看看啊，多美的头发，多漂亮的眼睛啊！”

两个孩子手舞足蹈，高兴地拍着手，争抢着投入爷爷奶奶的怀抱中。

最后，他们终于平静了一些，麦泰尔依偎在爷爷的胸口，泰泰尔舒服地坐在奶奶的膝头，他们开始谈论家里的事情。

“你们的爸爸妈妈怎么样了？”奶奶问。

“他们很好，奶奶。”泰泰尔说，“我们出门的时候他们正在睡觉。”

奶奶亲了亲他们，又说：

“天啊，他们两个真是又漂亮又可爱又干净！……你们怎么不多来看看我们呢？你们已经把我们忘了很长很长时间了，我们谁也见不到……”

“我们来不了，奶奶，”泰泰尔说，“今天是因为仙女的帮助，我们才能来的。”

“我们一直都在这里，”泰尔奶奶说，“等着那些我们活着时认识的人来访。你们上一次来这里，还是在万圣节的时候……”

“万圣节？那天我们没有出门啊，我们俩都感冒了！”

“但是那天你们想我们了！每次你们想到我们，我们就会醒来，能再看到你们。”

泰泰尔想起仙女跟他说过这一点。那时候他觉得这是不可能的，但现在，当他的头贴在他非常想念的奶奶的胸口时，他开始懂了，他觉得他的祖父母并没有完全离开他。他问：

“你们是真的死了吗？”

爷爷奶奶放声大笑。现在，他们用原来在尘世的生活换了另一种更加舒服更加幸福的生活，他们已经忘了“死”这个字眼了。

“‘死’是什么意思？”爷爷问。

“嗯，就是一个人不再活着了。”泰泰尔说。

爷爷和奶奶只是耸了耸肩。

“活着的人谈到其他的存在形式时是多么愚蠢啊！”两个老人说。

他们又继续谈论起过去的事情，享受着能够和孩子们交谈的快乐。

老人都爱谈论过去。对于他们来说，未来已经消失了，所以他们总是沉浸在现在与过去。但是我们和泰泰尔都开始没有耐心了，相比听他们说下去，我们更愿意关注我们小朋友的举动。

泰泰尔从奶奶的膝盖上跳下来，四处翻弄，很高兴地发现各种各样他知道并且记得的东西。

“什么都没变，一切都还在原来的位置！”他喊道。而且，因为他已经有很长时间没有来爷爷奶奶家了，对他来说，一切都显得更加可爱。然后，他用一种了然一切的声音补充道：“所有东西都更漂亮了！……嘿，这是那个钟，我有一回把那个大指针的尖儿给弄断了。还有这个我在门上弄出来的洞，那天我发现了爷爷的手钻……”

“是啊，那时候你可真搞了不少破坏啊！”爷爷说，“这是那棵李子树，我看不到的时候，你们总是喜欢往树上爬……”

泰泰尔并没有忘记自己的使命，问道：

“我猜，青鸟是不是碰巧在你们这里啊？”

就在这时，麦泰尔也抬起了头，她看到了一个鸟笼，“嘿，是那只老黑鹂！……它还唱歌吗？”

她正说着，黑鹂就醒了过来，大声地唱了起来。

“你看，”奶奶说，“只要有人想到它……”

泰泰尔惊讶地看着眼前的一切。

“它是青色的啊！”他喊道，“哎呀，就是这只鸟儿，这就是青鸟！……它是青色的，青色的，就像是青玻璃球那样的青色！……你们能把它给我吗？”

爷爷奶奶欣然同意。泰泰尔满怀着胜利的喜悦，去大树边拿来他刚刚放在那里的笼子。他小心翼翼地把那只神奇的鸟儿放进笼子，鸟儿在它的新家中跳来跳去。

“仙女会多开心啊！”男孩看着青鸟喜悦不已，“光也会高兴的！”

“过来，”爷爷奶奶说，“过来看看奶牛和蜜蜂。”

两个老人步履蹒跚地穿过花园时，孩子们突然问，他们死去的小弟弟和小妹妹们是不是也在这里。就在这个时候，七个本来一直在屋子里睡觉的小孩儿突然大哭着跑进了花园。泰泰尔和麦泰尔跑向他们，他们挤在一起，互相拥抱着，一起跳着、转着，开心地大声叫着。

“他们来了，他们来了，”奶奶说，“你一说到他们，他们就出现了，这些小淘气鬼！”

泰泰尔揪住一个小孩子的头发。

“嘿，皮埃罗！咱们再打一架啊，就像过去一样！……还有罗伯特！……我说，吉恩，你的陀螺呢？……玛德琳，皮尔丽特，还有波琳！嘿，雷奎特！”

麦泰尔大笑着说：

“雷奎特现在还是只能爬来爬去的呢！”

泰泰尔注意到有一只小狗在他们周围叫着，“那是奇奇，我用波琳的剪刀剪了它的尾巴……它也没有变……”

“是啊，”爷爷语重心长地说，“这里什么都没有变！”

但是，突然之间，在一派欢乐的气氛中，老人们呆住了，就像是中了魔法一样——他们刚刚隐约听到屋里的钟敲了八下。

“怎么回事啊？”他们问道，“它从来都不报时的……”

“那是因为我们从来都不想时间的问题，”奶奶说，“有谁刚刚想到了时间吗？”

“有，我想了，”泰泰尔说，“是八点钟了吗？……我得走了，因为我答应过光要在九点之前回去的……”

他想去拿笼子，但其他人都正是开心的时候，不想让他这么快就走，这样就告别，实在太糟糕了！奶奶想到了一个好主意，她知道泰泰尔是个小贪吃鬼。现在是吃晚饭时候了，而且幸运的是，还有美味的卷心菜汤和漂亮的李子馅饼。

“好吧，”我们的小主人公说，“反正我已经找到了青鸟！……但卷心菜汤可不是天天都能喝到的！”

他们很快就把桌子抬到屋外，在上面铺了一块漂亮的白色桌布，给每个人摆了一个盘子。最后，奶奶端出了热气腾腾的汤盆。灯被点亮了，爷爷奶奶和孩子们都坐下来吃饭。孩子们互相推挤，用胳膊肘顶着彼此，开心地又笑又闹。之后，有一段时间，除了木头勺子和汤盘撞击的声音，就没有别的声音了。

“真好吃啊！啊，真好吃啊！”泰泰尔喊道，他一直狼吞虎咽地吃着，“我还想要！还要！还要！还要！”

“好啦，好啦，安静一些，”爷爷说，“你还像过去一样没规矩，你会把盘子打破的……”

泰泰尔没有理会这批评，他站到凳子上，抓住汤盆，拉向自己，结果却把汤盆打翻了，热汤洒得四处都是，流到了所有人的大腿上。孩子们疼得尖叫起来。奶奶被吓了一大跳。爷爷气坏了，他使劲扇了泰泰尔一个耳光。

泰泰尔呆了一阵儿，然后他狂喜地把手放在了脸颊上，叫道：

“爷爷，真好，真是太好了！这和你活着的时候打我的耳光一模一样！……我一定要亲亲你！”

大家都笑了。

“你要是喜欢，可还有很多！”爷爷气呼呼地说。

但同时，他心里也感动了，扭头擦了擦眼泪。

“天啊！”泰泰尔猛地一惊，“八点半了！……麦泰尔，我们得走了！”

奶奶恳求他们再多留一会儿，但是没有用。

“不，我们不能留了，”泰泰尔坚定地说，“我向光保证过的。”然后他匆匆地拿起那个宝贵的鸟笼。

“再见，爷爷……再见，奶奶……再见，弟弟妹妹们！皮埃罗，罗伯特，波琳，玛德琳，雷奎特，还有你，奇奇……我们得走了……奶奶，别哭，我们会经常回来的！”

可怜的老爷爷非常伤心，大声抱怨着：

“天啊，活在世上的人可真烦啊，总有许多不得不做的事情！”

泰泰尔努力安慰他，再次保证会经常回来的。

“每天都回来！”奶奶说，“这是我们仅存的快乐了，当你们想到我们，就是来看我们，对我们来说就是快乐。”

“再见！再见！”弟弟妹妹们齐喊着，“要快回来啊！给我们带些麦芽糖！”

他们亲了又亲，挥舞着手绢，大声告别。但他们的身形开始渐渐消失了，声音越来越小，渐渐听不到了。两个孩子再一次身处迷雾之中，古老的森林仿佛巨大的黑幕将他们包围起来。

“我害怕！”麦泰尔低声说，“牵着我的手，小哥哥！我好害怕！”

泰泰尔也在发抖，但是他有责任安慰和保护小妹妹。

“嘘！”他说，“记住，我们带了青鸟回去呢！”

他的话刚说完，一道细细的光就划破阴霾，小男孩向着光走去。他紧紧地抱着鸟笼，借着光看了一眼那只鸟儿……啊呀，天啊，真是令他失望极了！来自回忆之地的美丽青鸟现在变成了黑色的！泰泰尔一直盯着它，可鸟儿就是黑色的！唉，就是他熟悉的那只——过去挂在门口的柳条笼子中唱歌的黑鹂啊！到底怎么回事？真是令人痛心！生活对他们来说多残酷啊！

他怀着强烈的渴望和喜悦踏上旅途，从来都没有想过会遇到什么困难和危险。他信心满满，无所畏惧，满怀善意，相信自己能够找到给仙女的小女儿带来幸福的美丽青鸟。而现在，他的所有希望都破碎了！我们可怜的朋友第一次意识到等待着他的还有磨难、烦恼和困难。唉，他是在尝试一件不可能的事情吗？仙女是拿他寻开心吗？他会找到青鸟吗？他所有的勇气似乎都消失了。

而更加不幸的是，他找不到来时的那条直路了。地上一朵白色三色堇都没有，他哭了起来。

不过幸运的是，我们的小朋友的麻烦并没有持续太久。仙女曾经保证过光会守护着他们。第一次的磨难结束了。就如同刚才在爷爷奶奶家门外的时候一样，迷雾突然间散开了。只是这次出现的不是一幅平静、温馨、柔美的居家图景，而是一座美轮美奂的庙宇，庙宇中射出了耀眼的光芒。

光就站在庙门处，穿着她那钻石色泽的衣服，美丽夺目。她微笑着听泰泰尔讲述自己遭遇的失败。她知道两个孩子在寻找什么，她知道一切。因为光用她的爱包围着所有世人，只是没有人能毫无保留地喜爱她，接受她，所以没有人知道真理的所有秘密。而现在，由于仙女给男孩的那颗钻石，她将第一次开启人的灵魂。

“别难过，”她对孩子们说，“难道你们见到爷爷奶奶不开心吗？这一天收获这么多幸福还不够吗？你们难道不高兴老黑鹂复活吗？听，它在唱歌呢！”

老黑鹂正起劲儿地唱着歌，它在大笼子中跳来跳去，黄色小眼睛中闪烁着喜悦的光芒。

“当你们在寻找青鸟的过程中，我亲爱的孩子，要学会去爱你们在路上找到的灰色的鸟儿。”

光满含深意地点了点头，很显然，她知道青鸟在哪里。但是生活中总是充满美丽的谜团，对此我们必须心怀敬意，不要去破坏。如果光直接告诉孩子们青鸟在哪里，那么，他们就根本找不到青鸟。我会在这个故事结尾的时候告诉你们为什么。

现在，让我们两个小朋友在光的照顾下，在美丽的白云上美美睡上一觉吧。

第四章　夜宫

在第一缕晨曦出现后不久，孩子们和他们的朋友会合了，他们要去夜宫，希望能在那里找到青鸟。点名的时候，好几个伙伴都没有到。对于牛奶来说，任何刺激都是可怕的，所以，她一直留在她的房间里面。水给出的理由是：她习惯了躺在苔藓床上旅行，现在她因为直立行走已经累得半死，害怕会累病。至于光，从创世之初她就和夜不合。而火，和光是亲戚，自然同仇敌忾。光亲了亲两个孩子，把去夜宫的路告诉了泰罗，因为他是负责带路的，然后，这个小队就出发了。

你们可以想象这幅画面：亲爱的泰罗走在前面，他用后腿走路，就像个小人儿一样，昂着头鼻子朝天，舌头垂过下巴，前爪交叠在胸前。他一刻都闲不下来，嗅来嗅去，跑前跑后，把所有的路都跑了两遍，根本不在乎有多累。他知道自己责任重大，根本不理会路上的诱惑：垃圾堆他理都不理，完全不关注他看到的任何东西，过去的老朋友他也不理会。

可怜的泰罗啊！他很高兴变成人形，但他并不比以前幸福多少！当然，对他来说，生活并没有什么变化，因为他的本性并没有任何变化。他依然像一只狗一样去感知，去思考，就算变成了人形，又有什么用呢？实际上，因为现在承担的责任，他的麻烦反而增加了一百倍。

“唉！”他叹了口气。他不假思索地加入了他的小上帝们的探寻之旅，从来都没有想过，旅途结束时他的生命也会结束。“唉，”他说，“如果我能够抓住青鸟那个淘气鬼，相信我，我连舔都不会舔它一下的，哪怕它可能肥美得像只鹌鹑。”

面包郑重地跟在他后面，手里拎着鸟笼。接着是两个孩子，糖走在最后。

但是，猫去哪儿了呢？要找到她缺席的原因，我们必须回溯前面，去探究一下她的想法。当泰莱特在仙女宫殿大厅召集动物和物品们一起开会的时候，她就在酝酿一个拖延行程的计划。但是她没有想到听众们那么傻。

“那些傻瓜，”她想，“全都傻乎乎地跪在仙女脚下，就像是犯了什么罪一样，差点就把我的计划全盘托出了。我最好还是自力更生。在我的猫生中，我们所有的训练都建立在怀疑之上，我明白在人类的生活中也是如此。那些信任他人的人，总是遭到背叛，最好的处世之道是保持沉默，自己做个背叛者。”

我亲爱的小读者们，你们应该看明白了，猫和狗是一样的，她也没有改变她的灵魂，仍然继续参照之前的生活经验。但是，可以确定的是，她非常邪恶，而我们亲爱的泰罗则非常善良。因此，泰莱特决定要独自行动，在天亮之前就出发，去拜访夜——夜和她是老朋友了。

通往夜宫的路漫长而危险。路的两边都是峭壁，你必须在高耸嶙峋的岩石间爬上爬下，再爬上。那些高耸的岩石好像随时都有可能砸到路人身上。最后，你会来到一个黑暗圆圈的边缘。你必须从那里向下走几千级台阶，才能到达夜居住的黑色大理石的地下宫殿。

猫过去经常去那里，她一路飞奔，轻盈得如同一片羽毛。她的斗篷被风吹得撑了起来，就像一面旗帜，在她身后飘荡。她帽子上的羽毛饰品优雅地微微颤动，她灰色的小山羊皮靴几乎都不着地。很快，她就到达了她的目的地，跳跃了几下之后，便来到了夜所在的宫殿大厅。

这里的景象真的非常神奇。夜如同女王一样高贵威严，靠在她的王座之中，她睡着了。她的周围没有一丝亮光、一颗星星。但是我们知道，对猫来说，夜没有秘密，猫的眼睛拥有看穿黑暗的能力，所以泰莱特看夜，就如同在明亮的日光下那么清晰。

在唤醒她之前，猫充满爱意地望了望那慈爱而熟悉的脸庞。那张脸白白的，泛着银光，如同月亮一般。脸上的五官透着坚定，令人既敬又畏。夜围着长长的黑纱巾，她若隐若现的身体如同希腊雕像一样美。她有一双修长的手臂，还有一对巨大的翅膀，现在，这对翅膀在睡梦中收了起来，它们从夜的肩膀一直垂到脚面，让她显出一种无与伦比的威严之感。尽管泰莱特对夜感情深厚，此刻却没有浪费太多时间打量她。现在可是生死攸关的时刻，时间紧迫。她疲惫不堪，痛苦烦乱，瘫在了王座的台阶上，悲伤地喵喵叫着。

“是我呀，夜妈妈！……我累坏了！”

夜生性焦虑，非常容易紧张。夜的美丽由平静与安宁构筑，沉默是其美丽的秘密，而生命却始终不断地打扰着这份寂静：一颗星星划过天际，一片叶子飘向大地，猫头鹰啸叫，甚至是几乎无法耳闻的动静，都足以撕裂她每晚罩向人间的黑色天鹅绒帷幕。所以，猫还没有说完，夜便坐了起来，浑身颤抖。她巨大的翅膀在身侧挥动着，她用一种颤抖的声音询问泰莱特。当她得知即将到来的危险时，便开始哀叹自己的命运。什么！一个人类的孩子要来她的宫殿！而且，有可能在魔法钻石的帮助下，发现她的秘密！她应该怎么办？她会怎么样？她该如何保护自己？夜此刻也忘了自己会冒犯沉默——她自己特别的神，开始放声尖叫。陷入如此混乱的状态，她很难找到应对麻烦的良方。幸运的是，泰莱特已经见惯了人类的烦恼和焦虑，抵抗能力更强。她比孩子们提前出发，已经有了计划，她希望能够说服夜采纳这个计划。于是，她简明地向夜解说：

“尊贵的夜，我看只有一个办法了。因为来的是孩子，我们必须要吓吓他们，吓得他们不敢坚持打开大殿最里面的那扇大门，这样便无法找到门内的月鸟和青鸟。而其他隐室内的秘密肯定会吓到他们的。我们的安全就指望你让他们感到恐惧了。”

显然，也没有别的办法了。夜还没来得及回答，就听到了一个声音。她美丽的脸孔皱了起来，她的翅膀愤怒地伸展开，她所有的举动都在告诉泰莱特，她已经同意了泰莱特的这个计划。

“他们来了！”猫叫道。

小团队正沿着夜宫的阴暗台阶向下走。泰罗勇敢地大步走在前面，泰泰尔紧张地四处打量。他找不到任何让他安心的东西。这里非常大，也非常吓人——请想象一个巨大而神奇的黑色大理石大厅，如同墓穴一样肃穆壮观。这里看不到屋顶，圆形剧场周围的乌木廊柱直指天空。只有当你抬头向上看的时候，才能看到来自星星的隐约光芒。四周被最浓重的黑暗笼罩着。在一扇丰碑一样的铜门前，是夜的王座，王座两侧闪动着两团不安的火焰——只有两团而已。再往两侧，柱子和柱子之间，隐约可见一扇扇青铜大门。

猫冲到孩子们身旁说：

“这边走，小主人，这边走！……我已经跟夜说过你们要来的事情了，她很高兴见到你们。”

泰莱特声音温柔，笑意盈盈，让泰泰尔安定了下来。他迈着勇敢而自信的步子，走向王座。

“日安，夜夫人。”

这声问候让夜感到被冒犯了，“日安”令她想到了她的宿敌——光。她冷冷地答道：

“日安？我可不习惯这个说法！……你应该说，晚安，至少该说晚上好！”

我们的小主人公不想争执。在这位庄严的女士面前，他觉得自己很渺小。他立刻道歉，以他能表现出的最和气的态度，非常温柔地请求夜允许他们去她的宫殿内寻找青鸟。

“我从没见过青鸟，它不在这儿。”夜说，她拍动着巨大的翅膀，想要吓住男孩。

但是男孩十分坚持，没有表现出恐惧，而夜已经开始担心那颗钻石了，怕那钻石将照亮她的黑暗，将彻底摧毁她的力量。她认为最好还是假装自己一时冲动愿意慷慨大方一回，所以，便立刻指了指王座台阶上的大钥匙。

泰泰尔没有丝毫犹豫地拿起钥匙，跑到了大厅的第一扇门前。

大家都在恐惧地颤抖。面包的牙齿嘎嘎作响，糖站得远一些，痛苦万分地嘟囔着。麦泰尔哭着说：

“糖去哪儿了？……我想回家！”

泰泰尔虽然脸色苍白，却依然坚定，他正在开门。而夜阴沉的声音盖过了一片喧闹声，宣布了第一重危险。

“那里是鬼魂！”

“啊，天啊，”泰泰尔想，“我从来都没有见过鬼魂，肯定可怕极了！”

忠诚的泰罗站在泰泰尔身边，拼命地喘着粗气，因为狗讨厌所有诡异的东西。

最后，钥匙开始在锁孔中转动。沉默就如同黑暗一般浓重。没有人敢喘一下气。然后，门开了，眨眼间黑暗之中就飘满了白色的影子，四处窜来窜去。有些长得直耸天际，有些缠绕在柱子上，有些在地上飘来荡去。他们有点儿像人，但面貌却模糊不清，眼睛根本看不清他们。你一看着他们，他们就会变成白色的薄雾。泰泰尔尽全力去追逐他们。而夜夫人在依照猫想出的计划行事，假装很害怕。其实，千百年来，她和鬼魂一直是好朋友，只要一出声就能将他们赶回门内，但是她很谨慎，坚决不这么做，像疯了一样挥舞着翅膀，呼天喊地尖叫：

“把他们赶走！把他们赶走！救命！救命！”

不过，那些可怜的鬼魂，因为人类不再相信他们的存在，他们都没什么机会出来了，现在能够自由呼吸简直欣喜若狂，如果不是害怕一直要咬他们腿的泰罗，他们肯定不会回到门内去。

“呜汪！”最后，门终于关上了，狗气喘吁吁地说：“上帝知道的，我的牙齿可锋利了！但我真没见过那样的家伙！你咬他们的时候，会觉得他们的腿是棉花做的。”

这个时候，泰泰尔走到了第二扇门前，问道：

“这扇门后面是什么？”

夜做了个手势，像是要阻拦他。这个固执的小家伙真的想把什么都看一遍吗？

“我打开的时候需要很小心吗？”泰泰尔问。

“不用，”夜说，“没必要。里面是疾病。他们都是很安静很可怜的小东西。过去一段时间，人类一直在和他们作战！……你自己去打开看吧……”

泰泰尔把门开得大大的，站在那里惊讶得说不出一句话来：里面什么都没有……

他正准备把门重新关上，这时，他被一个小人儿给挤到了一边。那小人儿穿着睡衣，戴着棉布睡帽，在大厅里面跳来跳去，摇晃着脑袋，咳嗽个不停，还不断地擤鼻涕，而她脚上的拖鞋太大了，根本不合脚，一直往下掉，她只能拖着走路。糖、面包和泰泰尔都不再害怕，而是笑成了一团。但是他们一靠近那个戴着棉布睡帽的小人儿，也都开始咳嗽和流鼻涕。

“这是疾病里面最无足轻重的一个，”夜说，“这是鼻伤风。”

“啊，天啊，啊，天啊，”糖想，“如果我的鼻涕一直都像这样流个不停，我会完蛋的，我会化掉的！”

可怜的糖啊！他不知道能躲到哪里去。自从旅行开始，他就热爱上了生活，因为他全身心地陷入了对水的爱恋。而这份爱给他带来的是巨大的苦恼。水小姐四处留情，总是希望得到深切的关注，但不特别在意是和谁在一起。和水相处太多，代价是非常高昂的，可怜的糖就发现了这一点，每一次他亲吻水，他自己就会消失一点儿，他已经开始为自己的生命担忧了。

发现自己遭到了鼻伤风的攻击，他真想逃出夜宫，不过他得到了我们亲爱的泰罗的及时救助。泰罗追着那个小妖婆，在泰泰尔和麦泰尔的笑声中将她赶回了门内。两个孩子高兴地意识到，到目前，他们的遭遇都还不怎么可怕。

因此，泰泰尔以更加勇敢的心态跑到了下一扇门边。

“小心！”夜用恐怖的声音叫道，“那里是战争！他们比一切都要更有威力！我不敢想象，如果有人放它们出来，会是什么局面！你们全都站在那儿，准备好了，把那扇门关回去！”

夜的警告还没有说完，我们勇敢的小朋友就开始为自己的鲁莽轻率后悔了。他费力地想把打开的门关上，但没有用，一股强大的力量从里面向外推着门，如潮的鲜血从门缝中往外涌，火焰蹿了出来，呐喊、咒骂和呻吟声中还混杂着炮火和机枪的声音。夜宫中的所有人都慌作一团，疲于逃命。面包和糖想要逃出去，却找不到出口，最后，大家又回到泰泰尔身边，用尽了全力拿他们的肩膀顶着大门。

猫做出非常恐慌的样子，心中却暗暗高兴。

“也许一切到此就结束了，”她捻着胡须咕哝道，“他们不敢再继续下去了。”

亲爱的泰罗拼尽全力帮助他的小主人，而麦泰尔却站在一个角落里哭个不停。

最后，我们的主人公终于发出了胜利的欢呼：

“太好啦！他们撤退了！胜利了！胜利了！门被关上了！”

说着，他走下台阶，整个人精疲力竭，用他那因为恐惧还在颤抖的可怜的小手抹着额头上的汗。

“好吧，”夜厉声问，“你们满意了吗？你们看到他们了吗？”

“是啊，是啊，”小东西抽泣着回答说，“他们都很丑，而且很可怕，我觉得他们没有青鸟。”

“你应该可以肯定他们没有。”夜愤怒地说，“要是有，他们会当即就把它吃了……你们看，这里已经没有别的了……”

泰泰尔骄傲地挺直身体。

“我必须看完，”他朗声说，“光是这么说的……”

“说起来总是容易，”夜反驳道，“尤其是说这话的人是个胆小鬼，自己躲在家里面！”

“咱们看下一扇门吧，”泰泰尔十分坚定，“那里有什么？”

“这是我关阴暗和恐惧的地方。”

泰泰尔思考了一会儿。

“阴暗啊，”他想，“夜夫人是在开玩笑吧。我来到她的房子已经一个多小时了，见到的都是阴暗，我真希望能够再见到日光。而至于恐惧，如果他们是像鬼魂那样的东西，我们就又有乐子了。”

我们的朋友就走过去将门打开，他的同伴根本就来不及阻止。他们现在全坐在地板上，经历过刚才的一战后都累得精疲力竭，惊奇地看着彼此，因劫后余生而庆幸。就在这时，泰泰尔拉开了门，什么都没有出来。

“这里什么都没有！”他说。

“有，有的！有，有的！小心啊！”夜依然在假装害怕。

她真的怒火中烧。她本来希望利用恐惧吓住他们，但是，看啊，那些被人类冷落的可怜虫现在反而怕人。她用温和的语言鼓励他们，成功引诱了几个披着灰纱巾的高个子出来。他们开始在大厅里跑来跑去，但听到孩子们的笑声时，他们感到了恐惧，便匆匆跑回了门内。夜的尝试又失败了，最可怕的时刻来临了。泰泰尔已经走向了大厅尽头的那扇大门。夜发出了最后的警告。

“不要打开那扇门。”夜用畏惧的声音说。

“为什么不能？”

“因为这是被禁止的。”

“那么，这儿就是青鸟藏身的地方。”

“不要再继续了，不要玩火，不要打开那扇门！”

“但是为什么？”泰泰尔固执地问。

夜被泰泰尔的坚持给激怒了，她火冒三丈，向泰泰尔抛出了最恐怖的威胁：

“只要是打开那扇门的人，哪怕只打开了一丝头发大小的缝隙，都没有活下来见到日光的！打开这扇门就意味着必死无疑。如果你还坚持要去打开这扇门的话，那你就会知道尘世间人们所说的所有恐惧、可怕、骇人的事情，都不如这扇门后等着你的东西可怕。”

“不要去开门，亲爱的主人。”面包的牙齿在咯咯作响，“千万不要开门！可怜可怜我们吧！我跪下求你了！”

“你是要把我们所有人的生命都牺牲掉。”猫喵喵叫着说。

“我不要你去！我不想要你去！”麦泰尔抽泣着说。

“可怜可怜我们吧！”糖绞着手指呜咽道。

他们所有人都在哭泣，所有人都挤在泰泰尔身边。只有亲爱的泰罗除外，他非常尊重小主人的意愿，不敢多说一句话，不过他也十分确信他的生命快到终点了。他的两只大耳朵垂到了脸颊上，他绝望地舔着泰泰尔的手。这一幕真是令人动容啊。有一瞬间，我们的小主人公动摇了。他的心怦怦地狂跳，喉咙因苦恼而干涩，他想要说点儿什么，却什么也说不出来，另外，他也不想在这些不幸的同伴面前表现出怯懦来。

“如果我没有能力去完成使命，”他对自己说，“那么谁能去完成它？如果我的朋友们注意到我的绝望，那我就完蛋了，他们不会让我去继续我的使命，我就根本找不到青鸟。”

想到这里，男孩的心又受到鼓舞，他那豪迈的天性再度被唤起。如果幸福就在咫尺之遥，不去尝试努力一下是绝对不行的，即便是冒着在尝试中死去的危险，也要去努力找到它，将它交给全人类。

就这样了！泰泰尔决定要牺牲自己。他就像是一个真正的英雄，挥舞着沉重的金钥匙，大声说：

“我必须打开这扇门！”

他跑到那扇大门边，泰罗跟在他身旁。可怜的狗已经怕得半死，但是他的骄傲和他对泰泰尔的忠诚促使他压抑住了自己的恐惧。

“我要留下来，”他对自己的主人说，“我不怕！我要和我的小上帝一起进退！”

这个时候，其他人都逃掉了。面包躲在一根柱子后面浑身抖得像筛糠一样。糖搂着麦泰尔缩在一个角落里，害怕得快化掉了。夜和猫在大厅的另一端，也一直在发抖，但她们是因为愤怒，而非恐惧。

泰泰尔给了泰罗最后一吻，把他抱在自己胸前，然后稳稳地将钥匙插入了锁孔中。恐怖的叫声从人们躲避的各个角落传来。两扇沉重的大门在我们的小朋友面前神奇地打开时，面对门内的景象，赞叹和欣喜让他一句话都说不出来。这是多么巨大的惊喜啊！在他面前的，是一个神奇的花园，一个梦幻的花园，花园当中，花朵如同星星一样熠熠闪耀，瀑布从天空中倾泻而下，树木沐浴在银色的月光之下。在玫瑰花丛中，有一小片青色云朵状的东西在盘旋。泰泰尔揉了揉自己的眼睛，他简直不敢相信自己看到的。他等了一会儿，又仔细看了一遍，接着就冲入了花园，边跑边像疯子一样大喊：

“快来呀！……快来呀！……它们在这里！……我们终于找到它们了！……这有好多青鸟！……成千上万只！来啊，麦泰尔！……过来，泰罗！……大家都过来！……帮帮我！……一抓就是一把！……”

他的朋友们终于安下心来，全都跑了过来，冲到了鸟群当中，比赛看谁抓得最多。

“我已经抓到七只了！”麦泰尔叫道，“我的手拿不过来了！”

“我也是！”泰泰尔说，“我也抓到太多了！……它们从我怀里逃走了！……泰罗也抓住了一些！……咱们出去吧，咱们走吧！……光在等着我们呢！……她得有多高兴啊！……这边走，这边走！……”

出去的时候，他们全都兴奋雀跃，手舞足蹈，唱着胜利的歌曲。

夜和猫没有像其他人一样感到喜悦，她们担忧地溜到了大门边。夜哀哀地说：

“他们没抓到它，是不是？”

“没有，”猫说，她看到真正的青鸟栖息在一束高高的月光上，“他们够不到它的，它落得太高了……”

我们的朋友全都加紧步伐，沿着连接黑夜与白昼之间数不清的台阶向上爬，走向日光。他们每个人怀中都抱着自己抓到的青鸟，却都没有想到，他们每走上一级台阶，向着光芒靠近一步，对那些可怜的小东西来说都是致命的，等他们走到台阶的顶端，他们带着的，就只是一堆死鸟了。

光正在焦急地等着他们。

“嗯，你们抓住青鸟了吗？”她问。

“是的，是的！”泰泰尔说，“那里有很多青鸟呢！有几千只！看！”

他说着，将这些珍贵的鸟儿递给光看，令他失望的是，那些鸟儿都变成了毫无生命的尸体：它们可怜的小翅膀已经断了，它们的头让人心酸地垂了下来！满心绝望的男孩转头看向他的同伴们。天哪，他们抱着的也都是死鸟！

于是，泰泰尔哭着扑到了光的怀里。又一次，他的希望全都碎成了粉末。

“不要哭，我的孩子，”光说，“你们没有抓住那只能在明亮的日光中生存的青鸟……不过我们会找到它的……”

“当然，我们会找到它的。”面包和糖异口同声地说。

这两个都是傻瓜，不过他们都想安慰男孩。至于我们的朋友泰罗，他实在是气坏了，有一瞬间忘记了自己的尊严，看着那些死鸟说：

“我想知道，它们好吃吗？”

小团队步行返回光的神庙休息。这是一段不愉快的旅程，所有人都在怀念在家时的安乐，都有责备泰泰尔不够细心的冲动。糖蹭到面包身边，在他耳边低语道：

“主席先生，你不觉得这一切都没有什么意义吗？”

面包先生简直受宠若惊，他故作高傲地回答：

“千万不要害怕，我亲爱的朋友，我会把一切修正。如果我们必须唯那个小疯子的疯念头是从，那简直无法容忍！……明天，我们就留在床上！……”

他们都忘了，如果不是那个他们嗤之以鼻的小男孩，他们根本不会活过来，如果小男孩突然间告诉面包他必须要回到烤盘里等着被人吃掉，或是告诉糖他必须被切成小块方糖，加到泰尔爸爸的咖啡里，或是泰尔妈妈的糖浆里，他们肯定会跪倒在小男孩的脚下，乞求慈悲。实际上，他们在不得不面对悲惨结局之前根本就不懂得珍惜自己的好运。

可怜的东西啊！仙女贝丽露娜给他们人的形体时，应该再给他们一些人的智慧。不过，也不应该太过责怪他们，他们只不过是在仿效人而已。给了他们说话的能力，他们就只会信口闲聊；拥有了评判能力，他们就去谴责别人；能够感觉，他们就抱怨。他们的心只会增加恐惧，不会感到快乐。至于他们的脑袋，本可以轻松地将一切安排妥当，但是他们却很少使用，导致那些脑袋都生锈了；如果你打开他们的头颅看一看他们生命内在的结构，你只会看到很可怜的大脑——这是他们最宝贵的资产——却像是豆荚里的干豆子，随着他们的一举一动跳荡，在他们空空的头颅中作响。

幸好，光具有非凡的洞察力，知道他们所有的心思。因此她决定不要过分要求这些元素和物品(1)。

“他们有用，”她想，“至少能够在路上给孩子们提供食物和快乐。但是他们必然无法共同面对困难，因为他们既没有勇气，也没有信念。”

小团队向前走着，路越来越宽阔，越来越明亮，最后，光的神庙出现在眼前，那神庙耸立在一片水晶高地上，散发着万丈光芒。疲惫的孩子们轮流被狗驮着，到达闪光的台阶那里时，他们已经快要睡着了。

————————————————————

(1) 元素指水和火，物品指面包、糖和牛奶。

第五章　未来国度

第二天早晨，泰泰尔和麦泰尔醒来，非常开心。因为孩子无忧无虑的天性，他们已经将失望抛在脑后了。泰泰尔因为光对他的夸奖而非常高兴。光似乎十分开心，就像是泰泰尔已经将青鸟带回来了。

光微笑着，轻抚着孩子乌黑的鬈发，说：

“我非常欣慰。你是一个善良、勇敢的男孩，你很快就能找到你在寻找的东西。”

泰泰尔并不理解她话中的深层含义，不过他听到这些话仍然很开心。另外，光还许诺说在今天的新旅程中他不会遇到任何恐怖的事情。相反，他会遇到成千上万个孩子，这些孩子会让他见识到世上所有人都没有见过的、最奇妙的玩具。光还告诉他，这一次，他和小妹妹两个人要和她一起上路，而其他人则趁这个机会休息一下。

所以，在本章开始的时候，所有人都在神庙的地窖中相会。光觉得最好将那些元素和物品锁起来。她很清楚，如果放任他们随心所欲，他们可能会跑出去闯出什么祸来。她这样做并不算残酷，因为她神庙的地窖比人类房屋的高层还要明亮宜人，只是没有她的允许你无法离开而已。只有她有魔力打开地窖，她用魔法棒轻轻一点，走廊尽头的祖母绿宝石墙上就会出现一道细细的缺口，慢慢变宽，通过这个缺口，走下几级水晶台阶，然后你就会来到一个像是山洞的地方，里面泛着澄净的绿色光辉，就如同是阳光穿过森林一般。

通常，这个大厅是空荡荡的，但是现在，里面安置了沙发和一张金子做的桌子，桌上摆满了水果、蛋糕、奶油和美味的酒，这是光的仆人刚刚安排好的。光的仆人们都非常奇怪！他们总是能令孩子们大笑：他们穿着白缎长袍，头戴黑色小帽，帽尖上是一簇小火焰，他们的样子就像点燃的蜡烛一样。他们的女主人吩咐他们退下，然后她告诉动物们和物品们尽情享受，问他们是否想要些书或是想玩什么游戏，他们大笑着回答说没什么比吃和睡更令他们开心的了，他们很高兴能够留在这里。

当然，泰罗并不这么认为。他心底的声音盖过了他的贪吃和懒惰，他黑色的眼睛恳求地望向泰泰尔。如果光没有严禁带着狗去的话，泰泰尔是非常愿意带上他忠实的伙伴的。

“我也没有办法，”男孩吻了狗一下，“似乎狗是不能去我们要去的地方的。”

泰罗突然欣喜地跳了起来：一个绝妙的主意出现在他脑海中。他脱离犬类生活的时间还不久，过去的生活都还记得，特别是他的那些烦恼。最烦恼的一点是什么呢？不就是那条锁链吗？被拴在一个铁环上的时间是多么难熬啊！当樵夫带着他去村子里的时候，他忍受着多么大的屈辱啊！真是说不出的蠢，被拴着走在众人面前，让他都没有办法享受和朋友们打招呼的乐趣，也没有办法去闻每个街角、每条沟渠中散发出来的诱人气味。

“好吧，”他自言自语道，“为了和我的小上帝同行，我不得不再忍受一次那种屈辱。”

泰罗恪守传统，尽管他穿着精致的衣服，但还是留着自己的项圈，只不过没有了链子。该怎么办呢？他又一次绝望了，这时，他看到了躺在沙发上的水正心不在焉地抚弄着她的那串长长的珊瑚项链。他以最优雅的姿态跑过去，给水献上了一大堆恭维话，乞求她将最大的那串项链借给他。水的脾气很好，不仅答应了狗的要求，还很友善地将珊瑚链子挂在了泰罗的项圈上。泰罗开心地走到主人身边，将这项链做的链子递给主人，然后跪在主人脚边说：

“请这样带我去吧，我的小上帝！人们不会介意一只被拴着的狗的。”

“唉，就算是这样，你也是不能去的！”光说。她被狗这种自我牺牲的行为感动了，为了令他振作起来，便告诉他，命运很快就会给孩子们安排一场考验，那时候会非常需要他的帮助。

说完这些话，光触碰了一下祖母绿的墙壁，一条通道出现了，她和孩子们走了出去。

她的敞篷马车停在神庙的入口处，这辆车的外壳是翠玉做的，内里镶着金子。三个人在座位上坐好，车前套着的两只白色的大鸟立刻就飞起来冲入云霄。车的速度非常快，他们在路上的时间并不长，这令孩子们感到十分遗憾，因为他们很享受这段行程，不停地笑着。不过，等着他们的将是更美丽的惊喜。

他们身边的云散开，突然间，他们就发现自己身处一个蓝得炫目的宫殿中。这里的一切都是蓝色的，光、石板路、柱子、穹顶，一切，哪怕是最小的东西，都是童话般的深蓝色。这宫殿一眼望不到尽头，眼睛都会迷失在无尽的蔚蓝色之中。

“这一切都多么美好啊！”泰泰尔抑制不住自己的惊讶之情，“天啊，真是美好！……我们这是在哪里啊？”

“我们是在未来国度。”光说，“在还没有出生的孩子中间。魔法钻石让我们可以清楚地看到这片世人看不到的领域，我们也许会在这里找到青鸟……看啊！看看那些跑过来的孩子！”

一群群的孩子从各个方向跑了过来，他们从头到脚都穿着蓝色衣服，头发有的是黑色，有的是金色，全都长得非常漂亮，他们开心地叫着：

“活小孩儿！……来看看活着的小孩儿！”

“他们为什么要叫我们活小孩儿？”泰泰尔问光。

“因为他们自己还不是活的。他们还在等着他们出生的时刻，孩子们都是从这里降生到人间的。当父母们想要孩子的时候，那扇大门就会打开，你能看到的，就在那边，在后边。小孩子们会从那里下去……”

“这里有那么多孩子！有那么多孩子啊！”泰泰尔大声叫道。

“还有更多呢，”光说，“没有人能够数清楚。再走一点儿，你就会看到更多别的东西。”

泰泰尔听了她的吩咐，挤着往前走。不过他很难移动，因为他们周围挤了一大群穿着蓝衣服的孩子。最后，我们的小朋友踏上了一级台阶，终于能越过这一片好奇的小脑袋，看到大厅的各个角落。这里真是太不寻常了！泰泰尔从来都没有想过有这样的地方！他高兴得手舞足蹈，麦泰尔紧紧拉着他的手，踮着脚尖，努力向外看，拍着小手，发出阵阵惊喜的大叫。

他们周围有上百万个孩子，全都穿着蓝衣服，有的在玩耍，有的在散步，有的在说话，有的在沉思。很多在睡觉，也有很多在干活。他们制作的乐器、工具、机械，他们种植或采集的植物、鲜花和水果，全都散发着同样明媚而庄严的蓝光，和整个宫殿的环境十分相称。在孩子中间，有些同样穿着蓝衣的高个子走来走去，他们都非常英俊，看上去就像天使。他们走到光的近前，微笑着温柔地推开周围的蓝衣孩子，蓝衣孩子们很安静地退回去做自己的事了，不过依然用好奇的眼睛打量着我们的朋友。

不过，其中有一个孩子，仍然站在泰泰尔身边。他的个子非常小。在他长长的天蓝色丝绸长袍下面，露出了两只粉嫩嫩、肥嘟嘟的赤裸小脚。他的眼睛好奇地盯着这个活的小男孩，仿佛是不由自主地走向泰泰尔。

“我能和他说话吗？”泰泰尔有点儿开心，但也有点儿害怕。

“当然，”光说，“你们必须要交朋友……我让你们单独留在这里，你们会更加放松的……”

这么说着，她便走开了，留下两个孩子面对着面，羞怯地笑着。突然，他们便开口交谈了。

“你好！”泰泰尔把手递给了那个孩子。

但是那个孩子并不懂这是什么意思，站在原地没有动。

“这是什么？”泰泰尔继续说，他摸了摸孩子的蓝衣服。

孩子一心一意地看着他要看的东西，没有回答，不过用手指一本正经地触碰了一下泰泰尔的帽子。

“这是什么？”他口齿不清地问。

“这？……这是我的帽子，”泰泰尔说，“你没有帽子吗？”

“没有，这是干什么用的？”孩子问。

“这是问好的时候用的，”泰泰尔回答，“另外还有冷的时候……”

“‘冷的时候’是什么意思？”孩子问。

“冷，就是你浑身发抖，像这样朝手上呵气！”泰泰尔说，“你还这样搓胳膊。”他把胳膊抱在身前使劲搓来搓去。

“人间冷吗？”孩子问。

“是的，有时候，冬天，没有炉火的时候。”

“为什么没有炉火？”

“因为很贵，需要花钱去买木头……”

孩子又望向泰泰尔，看样子他根本没有听懂泰泰尔说了什么，这下子，泰泰尔看起来也十分惊讶。

“很显然，他对生活中最常见的东西一无所知。”我们的主人公想，而那个孩子以非常崇拜的目光看着什么都懂的“活的小男孩”。

然后，他问泰泰尔钱是什么。

“哎呀，就是你付给人家的东西啊！”泰泰尔不愿做进一步解释了。

“噢！”孩子很严肃地说。

当然，他还是不懂。这个小男孩一直都生活在天堂中，在这里，就连最微不足道的愿望，在他说出口之前就会变成现实，他怎么能明白那一切呢？

“你多大了？”泰泰尔问，继续他们之间的对话。

“我很快就要出生了，”孩子说，“再过十二年，我就出生了……出生是不是很美好？”

“噢，是啊，”泰泰尔不假思索地答道，“非常好玩！”

但是当小男孩问他怎么生出来的时候，他非常茫然。他的骄傲不允许他在另一个孩子面前表现出一丝一毫的无知，他的手插在马裤口袋中，腿分得很开，头高高仰着，完全是一副不急着去作答的态度，但这模样实在是太滑稽了。最后，他耸了耸肩说：

“哎呀！我不记得了！那是太久之前的事情了！”

“人们都说，人间和活着的人很美好。”孩子评价道。

“是啊，不赖，”泰泰尔说，“有鸟，蛋糕，还有玩具……有些人什么都有，不过什么都没有的人可以看其他人的。”

这回答充分展现了我们的小朋友的性格。他很骄傲，还有点儿趾高气扬。但是他却从不嫉妒，他天生心胸开阔，因此能够欣赏他人的富足，安于自己的贫穷。

两个孩子又说了很多，但是要把他们说的话全都告诉你们需要花很长的时间，因为他们说的事情只是他们感兴趣的。过了一会儿，一直在远处看着他们的光匆匆地走了过来，她有一些焦急，因为泰泰尔哭了！大颗大颗的眼泪从他的脸颊上滚落下来，落到漂亮的外套上。她明白，他是谈到了他的奶奶，想到失去的爱，他便忍不住泪水了。他扭开头，想要掩饰自己的情绪，不过那个好奇的孩子却一直问他问题：

“奶奶们都会死吗？‘死’是什么意思？”

“有天晚上他们走了，就再也不会回来了。”

“你的奶奶走了吗？”

“是的，”泰泰尔说，“她过去对我特别好。”

说到这里，可怜的小家伙又哭了起来。

蓝衣孩子从来都没有见过人哭，因为他住在一个不存在悲伤的地方。他非常非常惊讶，大叫道：

“你的眼睛怎么了？……它们是在造珍珠吗？”

在他看来，眼泪是非常神奇的东西。

“不，这不是珍珠。”泰泰尔很羞怯地说。

“那它是什么？”

我们可怜的朋友不愿承认自己表现得脆弱，他尴尬地揉了揉眼睛，说这都是宫殿令人目眩的蓝光引起的。

迷惑的孩子继续追问：

“那落下来的是什么？”

“没什么，不过是点儿水。”泰泰尔说，他有些不耐烦，希望这解释尽量简短。

但那根本不可能。那个孩子非常固执，用他的手指去触碰泰泰尔的脸颊，还用好奇的语气问：

“这是从眼睛中流出来的吗？……”

“是的，有时候会流，当人哭的时候。”

“‘哭’是什么意思？”孩子问。

“我没有哭啊，”泰泰尔骄傲地说，“全都是这蓝色的错！……不过，要是我真哭了，流出来的也是这东西……”

“你们在人间经常哭吗？”

“小男孩不哭，小女孩经常哭……难道你们不哭吗？”

“不，我不知道该怎么哭……”

“好吧，你会学会的……”

这个时候，一阵猛烈的风吹来，他扭头望去，几步之外，有一个大机器。他之前光顾着和小孩说话了，没有注意到。那是一个非常巨大、非常华丽的东西，但是我没办法告诉你那东西的名字，因为在未来国度的发明出现在人间之前，人是不能给它命名的。我只能说，泰泰尔看着那东西，认为那在他眼前飞快挥动的巨大的蓝色翅膀，就像是他生活的世界中的风车，就算他找到了青鸟，青鸟的翅膀肯定也不会比这对翅膀更精致、更巧妙、更眩目。他心中满是钦佩，他问他新认识的朋友那是什么。

“那些？”孩子说，“那是我要在人间发明的东西。”

孩子看到泰泰尔的眼睛瞪得老大，又补充道：

“我到了人间的时候，会发明能给人带来幸福的东西……你想要看看吗？……就在那边，在两根柱子中间……”

泰泰尔扭头去看，但是所有的孩子都立刻冲到他面前，喊道：

“不，不，先来看我的！”

“不，我的更好些！”

“我的是一件了不起的发明！”

“我的是糖做的！”

“他的不好！”

“我会带来一种人们从来都没见过的光！”说着，最后的这个孩子用一种非常奇特的火焰将自己整个照亮了。

在一片欢乐的喧嚣中，泰泰尔和麦泰尔被拖到了蓝色工作坊边，小发明家们纷纷开动自己的机器，圆盘、滑轮、皮带、飞轮、驱动轮、齿轮以及其他各种各样的轮子都转了起来，立时间刮起了一阵蓝色的旋风，各种各样的机器都跑了出来，这些机器有的可以在地上行驶，有的可以在头顶上盘旋。其他孩子也都展开自己的图表和规划，或是打开沉重的书册，或是掀开蓝色雕像的幕布，或是拿出仿佛是由蓝宝石和绿松石做的巨大的花和硕大的水果。

我们的两位小朋友目瞪口呆地站着，手紧紧地握在一起，他们觉得自己就像是置身在天堂里。麦泰尔弯腰去看一朵巨大的花，开心地大笑着，花瓣遮住了她的头，仿佛给她戴了一顶蓝丝绸做成的帽子。一个长着黑头发和睿智的眼睛的漂亮孩子握着花茎，骄傲地说：

“等我到了人间，花都会长成这样。”

“那是什么时候呢？”泰泰尔问。

“五十三年四个月零九天后。”

接着，两个蓝衣孩子扛着一根杆子走了过来，那杆子非常重，压得他们都弯下了腰，杆子上挂着一大串葡萄，但是每一颗都比梨子还大。

“一大串梨！”泰泰尔叫道。

“不，这是葡萄，”孩子说，“等到我三十岁的时候，葡萄就都会长成这样子了，我已经发现了其中的秘密……”

泰泰尔很想尝尝那葡萄，不过这时，又来了一个孩子，这孩子的身体几乎被一个柳条篮子给挡住了，篮子是由一位个子很高的大人帮他提着的。孩子长着金色的头发，泛着玫瑰色红晕的小脸，透过柳条篮子上垂下来的叶子，露出了微笑。

“来看看呀！”他说，“看看我的苹果。”

“但这些是瓜啊！”泰泰尔说。

“不不，”孩子说，“这是我的苹果。等我出生之后，它们就都会长成这样了。我已经发现了这个转变过程……”

小读者们，如果要我向你们描述出现在我们的主人公面前所有神奇而不可思议的东西，那就没完没了了。不过，突然之间，一阵大笑响彻整个大厅。一个孩子说到了九大行星之王，泰泰尔非常困惑，一头雾水，四处张望。所有蓝衣孩子的脸上都带着笑容，他们的头都转向了一个泰泰尔看不到的位置，每人的手指都指向了同一个方向，但是我们的朋友却还是什么都看不到。他们在谈论一个国王啊！泰泰尔想找到那个王座，王座上应该坐着一个高大而威严的人，手握金色权杖。

“在那边……在那边……再低一些……就在你身后！”有一千个小小的声音异口同声地说。

“但是国王在哪里呢？”泰泰尔和麦泰尔又问道，他们都非常感兴趣。

突然，在众多孩子银铃般的声音中出现了一个更加洪亮、更加严肃的声音。

“我在这里！”他骄傲地说。

就在这时，泰泰尔发现了一个他一直都没有留意到的胖娃娃，因为这个孩子是所有孩子中最小的一个，一直都在人群外，以一种漫不经心的姿态坐在一根柱子下，似乎正在全神贯注地凝视着什么。小国王是唯一一个没有关注“活小孩儿们”的人，他那水汪汪的漂亮的眼睛，就像这个宫殿一样湛蓝，正在追寻着无尽的迷梦，他的右手撑着似乎因为思绪而沉重的头，他穿着短袍，带着肉窝的膝盖露在外面，金色的头发上戴着一顶金色的王冠。当他说“我在这里”的时候，他从坐着的台阶上站了起来，想要一大步跨上台阶，但是动作笨拙，失去了平衡，头朝下摔了下去。他立刻便以无比威严的仪态重新站起来，众人都不敢嘲笑他，这次，他索性手脚并用地爬上了台阶，然后双腿分开站定，从头到脚地打量着泰泰尔。

“你并不很大啊。”泰泰尔努力地压抑着自己的笑意。

“等我大了之后，会做出壮举的！”国王以一种不容置疑的语气反驳。

“到时候你会做什么？”泰泰尔问。

“我会建立太阳系行星总联盟。”国王用一种非常高傲的声音说。

我们的朋友实在太过震惊，简直无言以对。国王继续说：

“所有的行星都会属于这个联盟，只有天王星、土星和海王星例外，这三颗行星远得有些离谱。”

说完这话，他便摇摇晃晃地走下了台阶，恢复了最初的姿态，表示他要说的话都说完了。

泰泰尔任他继续沉思。泰泰尔非常渴望能去了解尽可能多的孩子。他结识了新太阳的发现者，要发明一种新娱乐的发明家，要扫平人间不公的英雄，以及要征服死亡的智者……实在是有太多太多孩子了，需要花很多天才能将他们一一介绍完。我们的朋友实在太累了，开始觉得无聊，不过这时，他突然听到一个孩子在叫他：“泰泰尔！泰泰尔！你好，泰泰尔，你好吗？”他的注意力陡然被唤了起来。

一个漂亮的蓝衣孩子从大厅后面跑了过来，一路挤过人群跑到前面。他皮肤白皙，个子高挑，眼睛明亮，和麦泰尔长得非常像。

“你怎么知道我的名字？”泰泰尔问。

“这并不奇怪。”蓝衣孩子说，“因为我将是你的弟弟呀。”

这一次，这两个活的小孩彻底惊呆了。这是多么不平常的会面啊！他们一回到家就要告诉妈妈这件事！爸爸妈妈该有多惊奇啊！

他们这么想的时候，那个孩子继续解释说：

“我明年就会到你们身边，就在棕枝全日(1)。”

然后，他向他的哥哥提了许多问题：家里舒服吗？吃得好吗？爸爸严厉吗？妈妈呢？

“哦，妈妈非常和气！”两个孩子说。

而他们也反问了他很多问题：他来到人间会做些什么呢？他会带来什么？

“我会带去三种疾病，”小弟弟说，“猩红热、百日咳和麻疹……”

“啊，就这些？”泰泰尔叫道。

他摇了摇头，面露失望，小弟弟继续说道：

“最后，我会离开你们！”

“那你去还有什么价值啊！”泰泰尔感觉十分沮丧。

“我们不能挑拣选择啊！”小弟弟有些烦躁地说。

不用等到去人间，他们可能就会爆发争吵，不过突然间一大群匆匆忙忙要去见某个人的孩子将他们分开了。就在这时，出现了一个巨大的声音，就好像走廊的尽头有千万扇看不见的门正在被同时打开。

“怎么了？”泰泰尔问。

“是时间来了，”一个蓝衣孩子说，“他要开门了。”

周围的人都越来越兴奋，孩子们丢下他们的机器，停下手里的工作，那些睡着的孩子也醒了过来，每双眼睛都充满渴望、紧张地投向了大厅后方的一扇蛋白石大门，众人异口同声地重复着一个名字。“时间！时间！”的喊声响彻大厅。洪亮而神秘的声音依然在继续。泰泰尔真的特别想弄清这是什么意思。最后，他拉住了一个孩子的衣袍下摆，向他询问。

“别拉着我，”孩子非常紧张地说，“我在赶时间，今天应该轮到我了……现在正是黎明时分。这是我们今天要降生的孩子去人间的时刻……你可以看到，时间正在拉开门闩……”

“谁是时间？”泰泰尔问。

“一个来召集去人间的孩子的老人，”另一个孩子说，“他人并不坏，不过他从来都不会听别人的请求。只要是没轮到的孩子，不管怎么恳求，他都会把那些试图过去的给赶回来……放开我！现在可能轮到我了！……”

光十分恐慌地向我们的小朋友们匆匆跑来。

“我正在找你们，”她说，“快点，绝对不能让时间发现你们。”

她说着，就将自己的金色斗篷围在了两个孩子身上，将他们拖到了大厅的一个角落，他们能从那里看到一切，但是别人却看不到他们。

泰泰尔很高兴能受到这样的保护。现在，他知道将要出现在他面前的是一个拥有非常强大力量的人，没有任何人类的力量能够与之抗衡。他既是神，也是妖，他能给予生命，也能吞噬生命。他瞬息之间就能走遍世界，你根本都来不及察觉，他不停地吞噬，任何他触碰的东西他都能带走。他已经带走了泰泰尔的爷爷奶奶，小弟弟们、小妹妹们，还有那只老黑鹂。他一点儿都不在乎自己带走的是什么：无论悲喜，无论冬夏，一切都如同进入他罗网里的鱼！

由于了解这一切，我们的朋友看到未来国度的每个人都飞快地跑去见他，真的非常惊讶。

“我猜，他并不吞噬这里的任何东西。”泰泰尔想。

他来了！大门的门轴缓缓转动，传来一阵隐约的乐声：那是来自人间的声音。一道红绿相间的光照入大厅，时间出现在门槛处。他是一个高高的、瘦削的老人，他是那么苍老，满是皱纹的脸一片灰白，就像尘土一样。白色的胡子一直垂到了膝盖。他一只手拿着一把巨大的镰刀，另一只手拿着一个沙漏。在他身后几步之遥，是一片晨曦色的海洋，海上漂着一艘挂着白帆的巨大的金船。

“那些轮到的人准备好了吗？”时间问。这个声音肃穆而低沉，如铜锣一样。听到这个声音，几千个活泼的孩子的声音便如同小银铃一般与之应和：

“我们准备好了！……我们准备好了！……我们准备好了！……”

瞬间，蓝衣孩子们就都围在了高个老人的身边，老人将他们都推了回去，用冷硬的声音说：

“一次一个！……一次一个，你们来的人可比需要的多！……你们可骗不了我。”

他一手挥舞着镰刀，另一只手撑开斗篷，挡住想要从他身边急匆匆溜过去的孩子。没有一个孩子能在可怕的老人那警惕的眼神下溜过去。

“还没有轮到你！”他对一个孩子说，“你应该明天出生！……你也不是，你还得等十年……第十三个牧羊人？……只需要十二个，不需要更多了……更多的医生？……已经有太多了，人间已经为此抱怨不停了……工程师在哪儿呢？……他们需要一个诚实的人，只要一个，一个了不起的人。”

这时，一个一直缩在后面的可怜孩子吮着大拇指羞怯地走上前来。他看上去脸色苍白，神情悲伤，脚步踉踉跄跄的，他的样子实在太惨了，甚至时间都产生了一瞬同情。

“就是你！”他宣布，“你看上去是一个非常可怜的人！”

他抬眼望望天，带着一种沮丧的神情，又说道：

“你会很短命。”

然后，一切又继续。被拒绝的孩子都情绪低落地回去做自己的事情了。被接受的孩子，都承受着其他人羡慕的目光。不过偶尔也会有意外，比如，注定要与不公正做斗争的那位英雄就拒绝降生。他拼命拉住自己的伙伴们，他的小伙伴们高声对时间喊：

“他不想去，先生！”

“是啊，我不想去，”小家伙哭着说，几乎用尽了所有的力气，“我宁愿不出生。”

“非常正确的决定！”泰泰尔想，他拥有很多常识，非常了解人间的生活是怎样的。

在人间，人们总是会无故地遭受打击。而当人们真正犯错时，惩罚则肯定会落在无辜的人身上。

“要是我，我也不想去过他的生活，”我们的朋友自言自语，“我宁愿去寻找青鸟，天天找都行。”

与此同时，与不公做斗争的小英雄几乎被时间先生吓掉了魂，抽泣着走了。

这是最令人激动的时刻。孩子们在大厅里跑来跑去，那些要离开的孩子忙着打包自己的发明，而留下来的则问个不停：

“你会给我写信吗？”

“他们说不能写。”

“噢，试试吧，就试一下吧。”

“把我的想法发布出来！”

“再见，吉恩……再见，皮埃尔！”

“有没有忘记带东西？”

“不要忘了你的想法！”

“如果好玩的话要想法子告诉我们啊！”

“够了，够了！”时间用洪亮的声音咆哮道，他摇晃着巨大的钥匙和可怕的镰刀，“够了！起锚了……”

孩子们爬上了扬着美丽的丝绸白帆的金船，向留下来的小朋友们挥着手，当看到远处的人间，他们都高兴地呐喊出来：

“人间！人间！……我看到了！……”

“多亮啊！”

“多大啊！”

就在这时，响起了一首歌，仿佛从深渊中传来的一般，那是一首从远方传来的饱含着喜悦和期待的歌。

光微笑着聆听着，看到泰泰尔脸上惊奇的神色，弯下腰对他说：

“这是迎接他们的妈妈的歌声。”

就在这时，刚刚关上门的时间看到了我们的朋友，他挥动着镰刀，愤怒地向他们冲了过来。

“快跑！”光说，“快跑！带上青鸟，泰泰尔，你和麦泰尔走在我前面。”

她将一只藏在斗篷下面的鸟塞到男孩怀里，然后整个人熠熠发光，伸开双臂，将她那绚丽的薄纱展开，保护着孩子们躲开时间的攻击。

他们就这样穿过了好几道绿松石和蓝宝石的走廊。那里真的非常漂亮，但是他们是在未来国度，时间是这里的主人，他们勇敢地面对了他的愤怒，也必须要逃离他的愤怒。

麦泰尔非常害怕，泰泰尔紧张地回头看向光。

“别害怕，”光说，“自从世界之始，我就是时间唯一尊敬的人，你们照顾好青鸟就行。它多漂亮啊！纯粹的青色啊！”

一想到青鸟男孩就狂喜不已。他感觉到这珍贵的鸟儿在自己怀中扑打着翅膀。他的手都不敢去按压它柔软而温暖的翅膀，他的心正贴着它的心一起跳动。这一次，他抓住了青鸟！什么也别想伤害它，因为这是光亲手给他的。等他回到家，这是多么盛大的凯旋啊！

他满心欢喜，都不知道自己该往哪里走。他的喜悦在他头脑中高声唱着凯歌，令他头晕目眩，他骄傲得几乎要疯了。唉，不幸的是，他因此失去了自己的冷静和理智！就在他们要跨出宫殿门槛的时候，一阵狂风席卷了门厅，吹起了光的纱巾，将两个孩子暴露在一直紧追在后的时间眼前。时间一声怒吼，将镰刀抛向了泰泰尔，泰泰尔吓得尖叫起来。光挡住了攻击，宫殿的大门在他们身后砰地关上，他们得救了！……但是，哎呀，泰泰尔刚才被吓到了，松开了手臂，透过泪水他看到未来国度的那只鸟儿在他们头顶高高地盘旋，它如梦的翅膀如此蔚蓝，如此轻盈、透明，和蔚蓝的天空融为一体，很快，泰泰尔就分辨不出来了……

————————————————————

(1) 指复活节前的星期天。

第六章　光的庙宇

泰泰尔在未来国度一直过得非常开心，他看到了很多神奇的东西，结识了千万个小伙伴，然后没有经历一点儿痛苦和麻烦便发现青鸟以最神奇的方式出现在了他的怀中。他从来都没有想过任何比它更加漂亮，颜色更青、更璀璨的小生命。他似乎依然能够感觉到它在他的胸前鼓翼，泰泰尔紧紧抱着胳膊，就像是青鸟还在他怀里。

唉，它已经如同幻梦一般消失了。

他和光手拉手走着，心中悲伤地想着这件令人失望的事情。他们回到光的庙宇，来到关着动物和物品的地窖。他们看到的是一幕什么样的景象啊！这些可怜虫一直吃吃喝喝，现在全都东倒西歪地醉倒在地板上。泰罗也失去了应有的体面，他在桌子底下翻来滚去，像一只海豚一样打着呼噜。他的直觉依然在，听到开门的声音仍支棱起了耳朵。他睁开了一只眼睛，不过他喝得太多，视线模糊，尽管看到了小主人，也没有认出来。他费了一番力气站起身，转了好几圈，然后又满足地咕噜了一声摔倒在地上睡着了。

面包和其他人的情形也同样糟糕。只有猫是个例外，她优雅地坐在一个大理石和黄金做成的长椅上，看上去十分清醒。她敏捷地跳到地上，笑着走向泰泰尔。

“我一直期待着能再见到你们呢，”她说，“在这些粗俗的人中间，我真的非常不开心。他们一上来就喝光了所有的酒，然后便开始大喊大叫、唱歌跳舞、吵架打斗，声音吵死了，最后他们终于醉得睡着了，我真是非常庆幸。”

孩子们热情地夸赞了她的良好表现。实际上，这并不是因为她有什么美德，只是因为她喝不了任何比牛奶烈的东西。但是我们很少会在我们该受到表扬时得到表扬，而在我们并不值得被表扬时，却会得到。

在亲热地吻了孩子们之后，泰莱特请光给她行一个方便。

“我太难受了，”她低声诉苦，“让我出去走走吧，让我自己待一会儿比较好。”

光丝毫没有怀疑，就表示了同意。猫立刻将斗篷披在身上，把帽子端正地戴好，将灰色的软皮靴子拉到膝盖上面，打开门，连跑带跳地进了森林。过一会儿，我们就知道狡诈的泰莱特这么开心是去了哪里，她在暗中谋划的又是多么可怕的阴谋。

就像几天前一样，孩子们和光在一间镶满了钻石的大房间内一同用餐。仆人们笑着在他们身边忙碌，端来了美味的饭菜和蛋糕。

吃过饭后，我们的小朋友就打起了哈欠。经历了这一番冒险之后，他们很早就困了。光非常慈爱、非常周到，让他们的生活就像是在人间的时候一样。为了不改变他们的习惯而影响到他们的健康，她将他们的小床安排在了庙宇的一个如同暗夜一般的黑暗的地方。

他们穿过了几个房间才到达他们的睡房。一路上，他们见到了所有人类知道的光和现在还不知道的光。

他们看到了很多间由大理石建造的大而奢华的房间，屋内的光白炽而强烈，孩子们都觉得目眩。

“这是富人之光，”光对泰泰尔说，“你看这有多危险，这样的光线没有给柔和的色调留一丝空间，在其中生活太久的话，就有失明的风险。”

她催促他们快些走，这样他们就可以到柔和的穷人之光中休息一下眼睛了。到了穷人之光中，孩子们突然觉得像是回到了他们父母的小屋中，那里一切都非常简朴而平和。微弱的光线纯粹而澄净，但总是摇曳不定，似乎一口气就能将其吹灭。

接着，他们来到了美丽的诗人之光的地界，他们真的无比喜欢这里，因为诗人之光色彩斑斓，如同彩虹，当你从光线中穿行的时候，你会看到可爱的图片、可爱的鲜花、可爱的玩具，但这些东西看得见，却无法抓住。两个孩子开心地笑闹着，追逐着飞鸟和蝴蝶，但是所有东西都一触即散。

“啊，我从来没有……”泰泰尔气喘吁吁地跑到光身边，“这简直令人无法相信！我不明白！”

“你以后会明白的，”光回答，“如果你能真正地明白了，你就会在看到青鸟的时候认出它来，只有极少数的人才能做到这一点。”

离开诗人之光的领域后，我们的朋友到了学者之光的地界，那里是已知之光和未知之光的交界处。

“咱们走吧，”泰泰尔说，“这里很无聊。”

说实话，他是有点儿害怕的，因为他们身处一长排冷硬而令人生畏的拱门之间，每时每刻，都有令人目眩的闪电在拱门上投下道道亮纹，每一次闪光，你都会看到还没有命名的奇特事物。

走过这些拱门，他们来到了人类未知之光的地界。尽管泰泰尔已经困得快要睁不开眼睛了，依然不由自主地欣赏着有紫罗兰色光柱的大厅和发散着红色光线的走廊。紫罗兰色的光柱是一种极深的紫色，而红色光线则是一种极浅的红色，两种光线都很难看清。

最后，他们来到了黑光的世界，这里有着柔和的黑色光线，人们将这种光称作黑暗，因为人类的眼睛没有办法看到这样的光线。在这里，孩子们很快便在两张软软的云床上陷入了梦乡。

第七章　墓园

孩子们没去探险的时候，便在光的辖界内玩耍，这对他们来说是最好的享受，因为庙宇周围的花园和乡野像金银建造的大厅和走廊一样奇妙。

有些植物的叶子宽大而结实，孩子们可以躺在上面，一阵微风吹过，叶片摇晃起来，他们就像是躺在吊床中一般。这里始终都是夏天，也没有一刻会被黑夜笼罩。但是随着时间变化，光线的色彩都是不同的，这里分为粉色时刻、白色时刻、蓝色时刻、紫色时刻、绿色时刻和黄色时刻。花儿、水果、小鸟、蝴蝶和各种气息会随着时间颜色的变化而变化，引得泰泰尔和麦泰尔连连惊奇。他们想要什么玩具，就能心想事成。玩累了之后，他们便伸展四肢躺在蜥蜴的背上，这里的蜥蜴的身体都又长又宽，仿佛小船一样，它们绕着花园小径飞奔，踩在如同糖一样又白又好吃的沙子上。孩子们渴了，水就会把她的头发甩入巨大的花朵当中，孩子们便从百合花、郁金香、牵牛花中喝水。如果饿了，他们就会摘下有光的味道的闪闪发亮的水果，那些水果甜美多汁，像阳光一样闪耀。

在灌木丛中，还有一个白色的大理石池塘，那个池塘拥有一种魔力，当人们望向它时，清澈的池水反映出来的，不是人的面孔，而是人的灵魂。

“这真是荒唐的发明。”猫说，她拒绝靠近那片池塘。

亲爱的小读者们，你们就像我一样了解她的想法，因此对她的这种抗拒丝毫都不会惊讶。同样，你们也非常理解为什么我们忠实的泰罗并不害怕去池塘喝水解渴，他无须害怕展示自己的思想，因为他是唯一一个灵魂从未发生变化的生灵。亲爱的小狗心里想的只有爱、善良和奉献。

泰泰尔弯身看向那面魔镜的时候，几乎总能看到一只美丽的青鸟，因为找到青鸟就是他的全部愿望。然后，他跑去找光，恳求道：

“请告诉我青鸟在哪里！……你什么都知道，请告诉我到哪里去找它。”

但是，光以一种非常神秘的语调回答：

“我什么也不能告诉你，你必须自己去寻找。”她吻了吻泰泰尔，又说道，“振作起来，每经历一次考验，你都离青鸟又近了一些。”

终于有一天，光对泰泰尔说：

“我收到了一条仙女贝丽露娜传来的消息，她说青鸟可能藏在墓园中……看起来，墓园中的一个死者将青鸟关在了自己的墓穴里……”

“我们该怎么办？”泰泰尔问。

“很简单，午夜时，你转动钻石，然后你就会看到那些死去的人从地下出来。”

听到这些话，牛奶、水、面包和糖都害怕地尖叫起来，他们都被吓得牙齿咯咯作响。

“别理会他们，”光悄声对泰泰尔说，“他们都害怕死人。”

“我不害怕！”火跳着说，“我曾经经常烧毁那些死人，那可比现在的日子有意思多了。”

“哦，我觉得我要晕倒了。”牛奶哀号着。

“我不害怕。”狗的四肢都在打颤，“但如果你要逃跑……我也会逃跑的……而且非常乐意……”

猫捋着她的胡须坐在一边。

“我知道那是怎么回事。”她用她惯常的神秘口吻说。

“安静，”光说，“仙女给了明确的指令。你们和我都要留在墓园大门那里，两个孩子自己进去。”

泰泰尔满心不快。他问道：

“你不和我们一起去吗？”

“是的，我不去，”光说，“我和你们同行的时间还未到。光不能够进入死者的地界。另外，那里也没有什么好怕的，我就在不远处，那些爱我的人和我爱的人总是能够再次找到我……”

她的话还没有说完，孩子们身边的一切都发生了变化。壮丽的庙宇、迷人的花朵、绚烂的花园全都消失不见了，化作了一个沐浴着柔和月光的凄凉的乡村墓地。在孩子们身边，有许多坟墓，长着青草的土包，木头十字架和墓碑。泰泰尔和麦泰尔的心一下子就被恐惧占领了，他们紧紧地拥抱住彼此。

“我害怕！”麦泰尔说。

“我从来都不害怕！”泰泰尔结结巴巴地说，他因为恐惧而颤抖，却不想承认。

“你说，”麦泰尔问，“死者邪恶吗？”

“不邪恶，”泰泰尔说，“他们不是活的……”

“你见过吗？”

“见过，见过一次，那是很久之前了，当时我还很小……”

“他是什么样的？”

“非常白，非常安静，非常冷漠，不说话……”

“我们要去见他们吗？”

听到这个问题，泰泰尔抖了一下，努力让自己的声音不发颤，但是并不成功，他答道：

“当然啦，光是这么说的啊！”

“死去的人在哪里？”麦泰尔问。

泰泰尔恐惧地打量了一下四周，两个孩子自从被独自留下之后就一步都没敢动过。

“那些死人就在这里，”他说，“在那些草下面，或是在那些大石头下面。”

“那些是他们房子的大门吗？”麦泰尔指着墓碑问道。

“是的。”

“天气好的时候他们会出来吗？”

“他们只在晚上出来。”

“为什么呀？”

“因为他们只穿着睡衣。”

“下雨的时候他们会出来吗？”

“下雨的时候他们会留在家里。”

“他们家里舒服吗？”

“据说非常狭窄。”

“他们中有小孩子吗？”

“啊，有，所有死去的人都在那里。”

“他们吃什么？”

泰泰尔没有立刻回答，而是停下来思考了一会儿。他觉得自己是麦泰尔的哥哥，便有责任什么都懂，但是麦泰尔的问题经常会难住他。这时，他意识到，由于死者是生活在地下的，那么他们就几乎吃不到任何地面上的东西，于是他十分肯定地回答：

“他们吃植物的根！”

麦泰尔得到了问题的答案，十分满意，然后又问出了那个占据她的小脑袋瓜的重大问题。

“我们会见到他们吗？”她问。

“当然啦，”泰泰尔说，“我转动这颗钻石后，我们就能看到一切。”

“那他们会说些什么呢？”

泰泰尔开始不耐烦了，答道：

“他们什么都不会说，因为他们不说话。”

“他们为什么不说话？”麦泰尔问。

“因为他们没什么要说的。”泰泰尔越来越烦躁，脑袋越来越乱。

“为什么他们没有什么要说的？”

这一次，哥哥失去了所有的耐心。他耸了耸肩，推了麦泰尔一下，生气地喊道：

“你真是个烦人精！”

麦泰尔十分难过，而且困惑不解。她吮了吮大拇指，决定再也不说一句话了，因为哥哥对她的态度实在太糟糕了。但是一阵风吹过，树叶沙沙作响，突然唤醒了孩子们的恐惧和孤寂。他们又紧紧地抱住彼此，开始说话，以打破那可怕的沉寂。

“你什么时候会转动钻石？”麦泰尔问。

“你也听到啦，光说我要等到午夜时分，因为那对死者造成的打扰最少，那个时候正是他们出来透风的时间……”

“还没到午夜吗？”

泰泰尔扭头看了看，看到了教堂的钟楼，他几乎没有力气回答，因为时钟的指针正指向午夜。

“听！”他结结巴巴地说，“听，就要鸣钟了……响了！你听到了吗？”

钟声响了。

这时，麦泰尔已经怕得难以自控了，开始跺着脚不停地叫喊：

“我想离开这里！……我想离开这里！……”

泰泰尔尽管也害怕得僵住了，但是还能说出这样的话：

“现在不行……我要转动钻石了……”

“不，不，不！”麦泰尔叫道，“我太害怕了，哥哥！……你别那么做！……我要离开这里！”

泰泰尔想要抬起手，但却根本没有办法触碰到钻石。麦泰尔紧紧地抓着他，把全部的重量都压在了哥哥的胳膊上，高声尖叫着：

“我不想见死人！……他们会很可怕的！……我不可能做到！……我太害怕了！”

可怜的泰泰尔其实和麦泰尔一样害怕，但是，每经历一次考验，他的意志力和勇气就会更强大一些，他在渐渐学会控制自己，什么都不能令他放弃自己的使命。第十一声钟声已经响起了。

“时间快过去了！”他叫道，“就是现在！”

他坚决地挣脱了麦泰尔的胳膊，转动了钻石……

接下来是一阵恐怖的静寂，然后两个孩子看到十字架晃动，坟丘张开了口，石板墓盖缓缓上升。

麦泰尔吓得把脸藏在泰泰尔的胸口。

“他们出来了！”她哭着说，“他们就在那里！……他们就在那里！”

恐惧已经超出了我们小勇士的承受能力。他闭上了眼睛，身子靠在旁边的一棵树上，这样才能坚持住不晕倒。他维持着那个姿势有一分钟，苦苦撑着，感觉那一分钟就像一个世纪那么漫长，他不敢动，不敢呼吸。然后他听到了鸟儿的叫声，一阵带着馨香的暖风吹拂着他的脸，他感到他的手上、脖子上都有着温煦的夏季艳阳带来的融融暖意。现在，他安下心来，但依然不敢相信这样的奇迹。他睁开眼睛，便立刻带着喜悦和赞美欢叫出声。

那些打开的坟墓中长出了千千万万绚丽的花朵，花儿四处蔓延，小径上，树上，草地上，都铺满了花；它们不停地向上长，向上长，似乎都触到了天空。那是完全绽放的玫瑰，展示着美丽的花心，神奇的金色的花心，散发出热烈、明亮的光线，把泰泰尔包裹在夏季的温暖之中。在玫瑰花周围，鸟儿欢唱，蜜蜂嗡鸣。

“我真不能相信！这不可能！”泰泰尔说，“那些坟墓和石头十字架呢？”

两个孩子惊叹不已，非常迷惑，他们手牵着手穿过墓园，其实这里已经看不到半点墓园的痕迹了，彻底变成了一个美丽的花园。经历过极度的恐惧之后看到这一切，他们真的非常高兴。他们曾经以为，会有丑陋的骷髅从土中出来追逐他们，露出狰狞的面孔，他们曾经想象了各种各样可怕的事情。而现在，真相就在眼前，他们发现，曾经听说的一切，都不过是彻头彻尾完全虚构的故事，死人并不存在这世上。他们也明白了一切并没有死亡，生命总是在继续，只是转换成了新的形式。凋谢的玫瑰洒落了花粉，促成了其他玫瑰的新生，零落的花瓣令空气也变得芬芳起来。当繁花落尽时，果实随之结出。丑陋的毛毛虫最终化作美丽的蝴蝶。一切都没有死亡，只是改变了模样……

美丽的鸟儿在泰泰尔和麦泰尔身边盘旋，其中并没有青鸟，不过两个孩子因为他们的新发现已经十分开心了，再无所求。他们怀着惊喜，不断地重复着：

“没有死亡！……没有死亡！”

第八章　森林

泰泰尔和麦泰尔一上床，光便吻了吻他们，然后立刻消失了，因为她不想她美丽的身体上射出的光线影响到他们的睡眠。

那时肯定是午夜前后，睡梦中的泰泰尔见到了蓝衣孩子们，这时，他感到有一个天鹅绒一样柔软的爪子轻抚着他的脸。他猛地一惊，有些害怕地坐起身，但是他很快便又安下心来，因为他看到的是他的朋友泰莱特的眼睛在黑暗中闪闪发光。

“嘘！”猫贴着他的耳朵说，“嘘！不要吵醒其他人。如果我们能偷偷溜出去，那今晚就能抓到青鸟。噢，我最亲爱的小主人，我冒着生命危险，制订了一个肯定能够实现愿望的计划！”

“但是，”男孩吻了吻泰莱特，“光很愿意帮助我们啊……另外，如果违背了她的意愿，我会很惭愧的。”

“如果你告诉她，”猫严厉地说，“那一切就都完蛋了，相信我，按照我说的做，今天是属于我们的。”

她这么说着，便开始急匆匆地给泰泰尔和麦泰尔穿衣服——麦泰尔是听到他们的声音醒来的，也要跟他们一起去。

“你不明白，”泰泰尔低声咕哝，“你还太小了，不知道我们在做的事情有多恶劣……”

但是奸诈的猫回应了他的话，说他之所以到现在还没有找到青鸟，全是光的错，因为她太亮了。如果孩子们自己去寻找，在黑暗中搜寻，很快就能找到所有能令人类幸福的青鸟。这个女骗子格外聪明，没多久，泰泰尔眼中原有的抗拒便消失了，变成了热切的渴望。泰莱特说的每一个字，都给他的行动提供了充足的借口，令他浮想联翩。他太容易受影响了，没有意志去对抗诡计，于是便被说服了，迈着坚定而雀跃的步子走出了光的庙宇。可怜的小家伙啊，如果他能够预见等待着他的可怕陷阱，那该有多好啊！

三个小伙伴出发了，他们要穿越沐浴在银白色月光下的田野。猫似乎非常兴奋，一路上说个不停，而且走得特别快，两个孩子几乎跟不上她。

“这一次，”她宣布，“我们要找到青鸟，我肯定能！我问过那片最古老的森林中的所有树了，他们都认识青鸟，因为它就躲藏在那些树中间。为了让大家都到那里，我还让兔子去村子里把重要的动物都召集来。”

不到一个小时，他们就到达了黑暗森林的边缘。然后，在路的一个拐弯处，他们看到远处有个人似乎正急匆匆地向他们走来。泰莱特弓起了背，她觉得这是她的宿敌。她因为愤怒而颤抖：他是不是又要来阻挠她的计划？他是不是猜到了她的秘密？他是不是会在最后一刻拯救孩子们的性命？

她向泰泰尔靠去，以她最甜蜜的声音低声对他说：

“那是我们忠实的朋友狗。但真的万分遗憾，因为他的出现会让我们无法实现目标。他和所有人的关系都不好，甚至和树木们都不和。一定要让他回去。”

“走开，你这个丑八怪！”泰泰尔向泰罗挥动着拳头。

亲爱的、诚实的老泰罗，之所以来到这里是因为他察觉到了猫的计划。听到这些话真的感到很受伤，他都要哭了。他一路跑来累得上气不接下气，什么回答都想不出来。

“走开，我跟你说，”泰泰尔说，“我们不想让你在这儿，就到这里吧……你这个讨厌鬼，走！……”

泰罗一直以来都温顺听话，如果是别的时候，他肯定就走了，但是他对主人的爱告诉他，这里发生的事情非常严重，他一动不动地站在那里。

“你能允许这样的违命吗？”猫对泰泰尔低语，“用你的手杖打他！”

泰泰尔听了猫的建议，打了狗。

“怎么样，这能让你学得更加听话！”泰泰尔说。

可怜的狗挨了打，哀号起来，但是他的自我牺牲精神非常强大，他勇敢地走到小主人身边，拉住他的胳膊，哭诉道：

“尽管你打了我，我也必须亲吻你。”

泰泰尔是个心地善良的小家伙，此时手足无措。猫咬着牙咒骂，就像只野兽一样。幸运的是，亲爱的小麦泰尔出面维护我们的朋友了。

“不，不，我想让他留下来，”她恳求道，“泰罗不在身边，我就感到害怕。”

时间很紧迫，他们必须做一个决定。

“我要找个别的办法来甩掉这个白痴！”猫心里想。然后，她以最礼貌的方式，扭头对狗说：“如果你能加入我们，我们真是太高兴了！”

他们走入大森林中，孩子们紧紧地贴在一起，猫和狗走在他们两侧。他们因为静寂和黑暗而心生敬畏，当听到猫说“我们到了！转动钻石！”时，他们都松了一口气。

这时，光开始在他们身边扩散，向他们展示出一幕奇景。他们正站在森林里一块面积很大的圆形空地中间，周围是非常非常古老的树木，高得似乎和天空连在了一起。宽宽的林荫路在暗绿色的森林中间勾勒出了一颗白色星星的形状。一切都平静、安宁，但是突然之间，树叶中传来一阵奇怪的颤动，树枝开始晃动伸展，就像人的胳膊一样。树根从覆盖着它们的泥土中拔出，聚拢到一起，形成了腿和脚的形状，站到了地面上。巨大的碎裂声划破长空。树木的树干都裂开了，释放出他们各自的灵魂，那些灵魂的外表都有些滑稽。

有的树魂缓缓地从他们的树干中走出来，还有的一下子蹦了出来，他们全都好奇地聚在我们的朋友身边。

健谈的杨树开始像个喜鹊一样叽叽喳喳地说：

“小人儿！我们能和他们说话！我们受够了沉寂了！……他们从哪里来的？……他们是谁？”

他就这么喋喋不休。

椴树是个快活的胖子，冷静地走上前来，嘴里叼着烟斗。打扮时髦、高傲自大的栗树推了推眼镜，盯着两个孩子。他穿着一件绿色的丝绸外套，上面绣着粉色和白色的花朵。他觉得这两个小家伙样子太寒酸了，嘲笑地扭开了头。

“他觉得自己是个大人物呢，因为他在城里住过！他看不起我们！”杨树很嫉妒他，嘴里冷嘲热讽。

“噢，天哪，噢，天哪！”柳树抽泣着说，他是个矮小的小可怜儿，脚上趿拉着一双对他来说有些过大的木鞋，“他们是来砍掉我的头和胳膊拿去当柴火的！”

泰泰尔不敢相信自己的眼睛。他一直不停地向猫询问：

“这是谁？……那又是谁？……”

泰莱特将树的灵魂一一介绍给他。

榆树是个喘气困难、大腹便便、脾气暴躁的矮子。山毛榉是个优雅而活泼的人。桦树那飘荡的白袍和透着不安的一举一动，让他看起来像是夜宫中的鬼魂。最高的一个是枞树，泰泰尔发现很难看清楚他瘦长身躯上方的面孔，但是他看起来非常温柔，也非常悲伤。而站在枞树旁边的柏树，穿着一袭黑衣，令泰泰尔非常害怕。

不过，到现在为止，还没有非常恐怖的事情发生。那些树很开心能够讲话，都聚在一起说个不停。我们的小朋友直接走过去问他们青鸟躲在哪里。就在这时，四周突然静了下来。所有的树都恭敬地弯身行礼，给一棵很老很老的橡树让路，这棵无比苍老的橡树身穿绣有苔藓和地衣的长袍。他一只手拄着一根手杖，另一只手搭在一棵年幼的橡树苗身上——这是他的向导，因为老橡树的眼睛已经瞎了。他长长的白胡子在风中飞扬。

“这是国王吧！”泰泰尔看到他戴着槲寄生做的王冠，自言自语道，“我要去问问他森林的秘密。”

他正要走上前去，却又停住了脚步，心中满是惊讶和狂喜：青鸟就在他面前呀，就栖息在老橡树的肩膀上。

“他有青鸟！”孩子欢叫，“快呀！快呀！把它给我！”

“别说话，闭嘴！”树们都吃了一惊，纷纷说道。

“脱帽行礼，泰泰尔，”猫说，“那可是橡树！”

可怜的孩子立刻笑着照办，他并不明白即将面临的危险。当橡树问他是不是樵夫泰尔的儿子时，他不假思索地回答说“是的，先生”。

听到这个回答，橡树愤怒得浑身发抖，开始了对泰尔爸爸的可怕控诉。

“就光说我的家族，”他说，“你父亲就杀死了我的六百个孩子、四百七十五个叔叔和阿姨、一千两百个表兄弟姐妹、三百八十个儿媳、一万两千个曾孙！”

他很恼怒，所以难免夸张，但是泰泰尔听着，丝毫也没有表示反对，只是非常礼貌地说：

“很抱歉打扰您，先生……猫对我说您能告诉我们青鸟在哪里。”

橡树年纪太大了，对人和动物的本性都已经非常了解了。他猜出这是猫设下的陷阱，胡子下面的脸露出了笑容，他非常高兴，他一直都期待着为整个森林复仇，因为人类一直都在奴役森林。

“这是为了仙女贝丽露娜的小女儿找的，她病得很厉害。”男孩接着说。

“够了！”老橡树打断了他的话，“我还没听动物的意见呢……他们在哪里？……这问题不仅关系到我们，也关系到他们……这么重大的事情，我们树族决不独自承担这个责任。”

“他们来了！”枞树说，他能越过所有树的树顶看出去，“兔子打头，别的动物跟着……我可以看到马、公牛、母牛、狼、绵羊、猪、山羊、熊……”

所有动物都到了，他们用后腿走路，穿着人类的衣服。他们在树的中间站成了一个圈子，非常严肃。只有不知轻重的山羊例外，他在林荫径上一蹦一跳地走着。还有猪想在刚刚离开土地的树根下面找些美味的松露吃。

“人都到齐了吗？”橡树问。

“母鸡不能丢下她的蛋，”兔子说，“大野兔出去玩了，公鹿犄角疼，还长了鸡眼，狐狸病了——这是医生的证明，鹅听不明白为什么要来这里，火鸡发起了脾气……”

“看啊！”泰泰尔对麦泰尔低语，“他们多好玩啊！他们就像是圣诞节的时候有钱孩子放在橱窗中的玩具。”

他们觉得最好笑的就是兔子了，他大大的耳朵上顶着一顶三角帽，身上穿着蓝色的绣花外套，身前挂着一面鼓。

这时，橡树开始向他的这些树兄弟以及动物朋友解释当前的情况。狡诈的泰莱特就是要利用他们对人类的仇恨。

“你们面前的这个孩子，”橡树说，“因为一个从大地之母那里偷来的法宝，有可能要抢占我们的青鸟，从而掌握我们自生命之初就保守的秘密……我们都非常了解人类，十分清楚一旦他们掌握了这个秘密，会怎么对待我们……此刻若有半分犹豫，都是愚蠢的，也是可耻的……这是性命攸关的时刻，在一切还来得及的时候，必须杀死这个孩子……”

“他在说什么？”泰泰尔说，他没有明白老橡树要干什么。

狗绕着橡树跑来跑去，露出他的獠牙。

“你看到我的牙齿了吗，你这个老瘸子？”他咆哮道。

“他在辱骂橡树！”山毛榉愤愤不平地说。

“把他赶走！”橡树恼怒地说，“他是个叛徒！”

“我跟你们说什么了？”猫轻声对泰泰尔说，“我会处理一切的……但是一定要把他赶走。”

“你走开！”泰泰尔对狗说。

“让我来撕破这个有痛风病的老乞丐的苔藓拖鞋！”泰罗乞求道。

泰泰尔想要阻止他，但是没有成功。泰罗明白当前的危险所在，简直怒不可遏，他本来可以成功拯救他的小主人，只可惜猫突然灵机一动，召唤一直站在旁边的常春藤来阻挡。狗像个疯子一样跳来跳去，咒骂所有人。他对着常春藤咆哮道：

“来啊，你敢不敢啊，你这团老乱麻，来啊！”

其他人都愤愤不平。橡树因为自己的权威遭到蔑视而气得脸都灰了。树木们和动物们也都十分生气，但他们都是胆小鬼，没有一个人敢出言反驳。如果狗继续下去，肯定能够把所有人都震住。只是泰泰尔严厉地威胁他，泰罗突然便臣服于自己顺从的天性，卧在了主人的脚下。因此，当我们不加区分的时候，美德会被当成错误对待。

从那时候开始，孩子们就处于不利的地位了。常春藤困住了可怜的狗，狗被带到了栗树的后面，捆在了他最大的根上。

“现在，”老橡树声如惊雷，“我们可以安静地讨论了……这是我们第一次有机会来审判人类！我觉得，在经历了我们遭遇的那些暴行和不公之后，对他的判决必然毫无争议……”

众人异口同声道：

“死刑！死刑！死刑！”

起初，可怜的孩子并不明白降临到他们身上的厄运，因为树木和动物们更习惯用他们自己的语言来交谈，他们说的话并不是那么明白易懂。另外，天真的孩子们从来都没有想象过这样的残酷局面！

“他们怎么了？”男孩问，“他们不高兴了吗？”

“别紧张，”猫说，“他们就是有点儿恼怒，因为春天来得迟了……”

她继续在泰泰尔耳边低语，想要分散他的注意力，让他无法关注正在发生的事情。

当这个轻信的小男孩听着她的谎言的时候，其他人则在讨论以哪种方式行刑是最实用、风险最小的。公牛建议用牛角重重一顶；山毛榉表示愿意提供自己最高的枝条将两个孩子吊死；而常春藤已经编出了一个套索！枞树愿意献出四块板材做棺材，柏树则同意提供一块永久的墓地。

“现在最简单的方法，”柳树轻声说，“就是将他们淹死在我旁边的一条河里。”

猪咬着牙哼哼着说：

“在我看来，最重要的事情应该是吃掉那个小女孩，她应该很鲜嫩……”

“安静！”橡树吼道，“我们必须决定，我们中的哪一个有荣幸发出第一击！”

“荣耀属于你，我们的国王！”枞树说。

“唉，我太老了！”老橡树回答，“我已经瞎了，站也站不稳了！而你，四季常青的兄弟，请接受荣耀，代替我，发出那决定性的一击，令我们获得自由！”

但是枞树托词说，他已准备享受埋葬两个死者的乐趣，不想引起过多的嫉妒，婉拒了这项荣誉。他推举山毛榉，因为他的枝条最硬。

“这可不行，”山毛榉说，“大家都知道的，我被虫子蛀了！还是问问榆树和柏树吧！”

听到这话，榆树开始呻吟起来，说昨晚有一只鼹鼠扭伤了他的大脚趾，他几乎都站不直身子。柏树也为自己找了理由，杨树说自己病了，烧得浑身颤抖。老橡树勃然大怒。

“你们全都害怕人类！”他指责说，“即便是这些无人保护、没有武装的小孩子，你们也害怕！……好吧，我自己上，我又老又盲，虚弱不堪，但我要对付我们的宿敌！……他在哪里呢？……”

他用手杖探索着路，向泰泰尔移动，一边走一边咆哮。

就在这几分钟中，我们的小朋友开始感到恐惧。猫突然离开了，说她想去安抚一下众人的激动情绪，然后就再也没有回来。麦泰尔靠着泰泰尔颤抖个不停。在这些可怕的人中间，他已经感受到了他们的愤怒，他觉得自己很孤单，很压抑。当他看到老橡树带着危险的气息向他靠近时，他拔出了小折刀，像个大人一样反抗。

“那个老家伙，拿着大棍子，是不是来对付我的啊？”他叫道。

一看到那把刀——人类不可抗拒的武器，所有的树木都吓得颤抖起来，匆匆地奔向老橡树，想把他拉回来。一番撕扯，老国王因年老体衰，丢下了手杖。

“真丢人啊！”他喊道，“我们可真是丢人啊！让动物们来解救我们吧！”

动物们一直在等这一刻！他们全都想要复仇。幸运的是，他们热切的渴望引发了一场混战，结果却拖延了对孩子们的这场谋杀。

麦泰尔放声尖叫。

“别害怕，”泰泰尔尽全力去保护着妹妹说，“我有刀。”

“小家伙还宁死不屈呢！”公鸡说。

“我要先吃那一个。”猪贪婪地看着麦泰尔。

“我对你们做过什么吗？”泰泰尔问。

“什么也没有，我的小人儿，”绵羊说，“不过是吃了我的一个小弟弟，两个姐妹，三个叔叔，还有阿姨，祖父，祖母……等你倒下，你就会发现我也是有牙齿的……”

羊和马都是非常怯懦的胆小鬼，他们全在等着两个孩子被打倒，然后再去分享胜利。

他们说着的时候，狼和熊已经阴险地从后方发动了攻击，扑向泰泰尔，将他推倒在地。这真是可怕的时刻。所有的动物，都盯着倒在地上的泰泰尔，想要抓住他。男孩支撑着单膝跪起，挥舞着刀子。麦泰尔痛苦地大叫着。而雪上加霜的是，突然间一切都被黑暗笼罩了。

泰泰尔疯狂地呼喊求助，“救命啊！救命啊！泰罗！泰罗！……来救救我们啊！……泰莱特在哪儿呢？……快来人啊！快来救命啊！……”

猫的声音从远方传来，她狡猾地躲到了大家都看不见的地方。

“我过不去！”她哀号着说，“我受伤了。”

这个时候，勇敢的小泰泰尔一直在奋力抵抗，但是他以一敌众，觉得自己就要死于非命了，于是用颤抖的声音又一次喊道：

“救命！……泰罗！泰罗！……我撑不住了！……他们人太多了！……熊！……猪！……狼！枞树！山毛榉！……泰罗！泰罗！……”

这时，狗冲了过来，他拖着被挣开的绳索，一路挤开树木和动物们，挡到了小主人的前面，他狂怒地维护着自己的主人。

“我来了，我的小上帝！不要怕！揍他们！我知道该如何运用我的牙齿！”

所有的树木和动物都高声咆哮起来：

“叛徒！……白痴！……背叛者！……恶棍！……傻子！……小人！……躲开！……他死定了！……你投降吧！……”

狗继续战斗。

“决不！决不！我一个人对抗你们所有人！……决不投降！决不投降！我要忠于我的上帝，忠于最好最伟大的人！……小心，我的小主人，熊过来了！……注意公牛啊！”狗说。

泰泰尔奋力自卫，但有些体力不支。

“我完了，泰罗！是榆树打的！我的手流血了！”他跌倒在地上，“不，我再也撑不住了。”

“他们来了！”狗说，“我听到有人来了！……我们得救了！是光！……得救了！得救了！……看啊，他们害怕了，他们撤退了！……得救了，我的小国王！……”

是的，光正向他们走来，随着她一步步靠近，晨光笼罩了森林，这里变得亮如白昼。

“怎么了？……发生什么事了？”她问道，看到孩子们和亲爱的泰罗身上满是伤口和瘀青，她十分吃惊，“哎呀，我可怜的孩子，你不知道吗？快点转动钻石啊！”

泰泰尔赶忙照办，一瞬间，所有树的灵魂都匆匆回到了树干里面，树干随之封闭。动物的灵魂全都消失不见了，只剩下远处一只牛和一只羊在安闲地吃草。森林又变得无害了，泰泰尔吃惊地看着四周。

“没事了，”泰泰尔说，“但要不是狗……要是我没有带着我的刀……”

光觉得泰泰尔已经受到了惩罚，没有再责怪他。另外她因为泰泰尔经历的恐怖危险也非常不安。

泰泰尔、麦泰尔和狗很开心能够再次平安，欣喜地吻着彼此。他们笑着数自己身上的伤口，那些伤口并不太严重。

只有泰莱特大惊小怪。

“狗弄伤了我的爪子！”她喵喵地叫着。

泰罗觉得自己应该狠狠咬她一口才对。

“别介意，”泰罗说，“又掉不了！”

“别惹她了，可以吗，你这个丑陋的小野兽！”麦泰尔说。

经历了这段冒险，我们的朋友返回光的神庙休息。泰泰尔很懊悔自己不听光的话擅自行动，没有勇气提他瞥到过的青鸟。光柔声对孩子们说：

“希望你们能从此记住这次教训，亲爱的孩子们，在这个世界上，人要单独地对抗一切。千万不要忘了。”

第九章　道别

自从孩子们踏上寻找青鸟的旅程，几个星期过去了，转眼几个月过去了。分别的时刻就在眼前。最近，光非常悲伤，她已经在伤心地数日子了，她没有对动物和物品说什么，他们都不知道即将降临到他们身上的不幸。

我们最后一次见到他们的那天，他们都在庙宇的花园里。光站在一个大理石露台上望着他们，泰泰尔和麦泰尔在她身边睡着。在过去的十二个月中发生了很多事情，但是动物和物品们智慧不足，不能够掌控生活，所以他们没有什么进步，反而倒退了。面包饱食终日，现在胖得都走不动路了。牛奶如同以往一样乐于助人，正吃力地推着坐在轮椅中的面包走动。火的暴脾气让他和每个人都发生过争吵，所以变得非常孤立，非常不开心。水自己没有什么主见，她屈服在糖的甜蜜攻势下，和糖结婚了。糖在婚后总是一副可怜兮兮的模样，这个可怜的家伙都瘦得没形了，一天天地在明显瘦下去，而且比从前更愚蠢了；而水在结婚后，失去了她最迷人的优点——单纯。猫一如既往，喜欢撒谎。我们亲爱的朋友泰罗则从没有停止过对猫的仇恨。

“可怜的东西！”光沉思着，叹了口气，“他们虽获得了生命，却没有收获什么。他们四处旅行，却丝毫没有看到我平和的庙宇中发生的那些奇迹。他们不是互相争吵，就是暴饮暴食，直到把自己吃病了。他们都太愚蠢了，都没有办法享受他们的幸福，不久，他们就会第一次认识到幸福是什么，但这已经是他们要失去幸福的时刻了……”

就在这个时候，一只十分漂亮的银翼鸽子落到了她的膝盖上。鸽子的脖子上套着一个祖母绿的项圈，扣环上拴着一张纸条。这只鸽子是仙女贝丽露娜的信使。光打开信，读到了下面的这些字：“记住这一年结束了。”

光站起身，挥动魔杖，一切都消失了。

几秒钟后，所有人都集合在了一道高墙之外，高墙上有一道小门。第一缕晨曦在树梢上闪耀。这时，泰泰尔和麦泰尔在光慈爱的怀抱中醒了过来，他们揉了揉眼睛，惊讶地看着周围。

“怎么了？”光问泰泰尔，“你不认识这道墙和这扇小门了吗？”

睡意蒙眬的男孩摇了摇头，他什么都不记得。光便帮助他回忆。

“这道墙，”她说，“环绕着一座房子，我们在一年前的这个晚上离开了那座房子……”

“就在一年前？……哎呀，那么……”泰泰尔欢快地拍着手，跑到门边，“妈妈肯定就在里面！……我想要立刻就亲亲她，立刻就亲，立刻！”

但是光拦住了他。她说现在还太早了，妈妈和爸爸还在睡着呢，泰泰尔肯定不想把他们吓醒了。

“另外，”她又说，“门只有到了时间才会开。”

“什么时间？”男孩问。

“分别的时间。”光悲伤地回答。

“什么？”泰泰尔非常沮丧，“你要离开我们了吗？”

“我必须走了，”光说，“这一年结束了。仙女会回来找你们要青鸟。”

“但是我没有找到青鸟。”泰泰尔叫道，“回忆之地的青鸟变成了漆黑色；未来国度的青鸟飞走了；夜宫的青鸟死掉了；墓园的鸟儿并不是青色的；而森林里面的青鸟，我没有抓住！仙女会生气吗？她会说什么呢？”

“没关系，亲爱的，”光说，“你已经尽力了，尽管你没有找到青鸟，但按照你表现出的善良、勇敢和胆量，你配得上找青鸟这个任务。”

光说这些话的时候，脸上闪耀着幸福的光芒，因为她知道，配得上找青鸟，和找到了青鸟，几乎是一样的，但是她不能够这么说，因为这是一个美丽的谜，泰泰尔必须自己去解开。她转头看向站在角落里啜泣的动物和物品们，让他们过来亲吻孩子。

面包立刻把鸟笼放在泰泰尔的脚下，开始发表演说：

“谨代表所有人，我渴望能有幸……”

“你可代表不了我！”火叫道。

“肃静！”水大声说。

“我们自己有舌头！”火咆哮。

“是啊！是啊！”糖尖叫，他知道自己的生命到了尽头，一直吻着水，在众人面前一点点地溶化。

可怜的面包想要大声说话，盖过这一片喧嚣，却徒劳无功。光不得不出面干预，让大家安静下来。这时，面包说出了他最后的话。

“我要离开你们了，”他抽泣着说，“我就要离开你们了，我亲爱的孩子们，你们不会再见到拥有生命的我了。你们的眼睛将再也看不到物品们内在的生命了。但是我一直都在，在面包烤盘中，在架子上，在桌子上，在汤旁边，如果允许的话，我得说，我是最忠实的伙伴，是人类最古老的朋友……”

“好吧，那我呢？”火吼道，他十分愤怒。

“肃静！”光说，“时间就要过去了……抓紧时间和孩子们道别……”

火匆匆向前，握住孩子们的手，挨个亲吻两个孩子，非常猛烈，两个孩子都痛苦地尖叫起来：

“啊！啊！……他烧着我了！……”

“啊！啊！……他把我鼻子烧焦了！……”

“让我来亲吻一下你们的伤口，帮你们治愈。”水温柔地走到了孩子们跟前。

火抓住机会挑拨。

“小心，”他说，“你们会被弄得浑身湿漉漉的。”

“我充满爱意，充满温柔，”水说，“我对人类非常友好……”

“那些被你淹死的人是怎么回事？”火问。

但是水假装没有听到。

“请爱护井水，倾听溪流的声音，”她说，“我一直都在。傍晚当你们坐在泉水边时，请注意聆听她们想要说的话……”

这时，她不得不停下来，因为她的眼泪又像瀑布一样从眼睛里涌了出来，在她身边四处泛滥。但她又继续说了下去：

“当你们看到水瓶的时候，就想到我……我就在水罐中，在水壶中，在水池中，在水龙头中……”

糖一瘸一拐地走上前来，他几乎都没有办法自己站着了。他用一种饱含深情的声音说了一些悲伤的话，然后停了下来，他说，眼泪不太适合他的本性。

“薄荷硬糖(1)！”面包叫道。

“糖渍李子！棒棒糖！太妃糖！”火叫道。

所有人都大笑起来，只有两个孩子依然非常悲伤。

“泰莱特和泰罗去了哪里？”我们的主人公问。

就在这个时候，猫跑了过来，样子狼狈极了：她的毛发都竖立着，乱蓬蓬的；她的衣服七零八落；她握着一块手帕遮着脸颊，好像正在犯牙疼一般。她发出刺耳的呻吟声。狗正紧紧地追在她身后，对她撕咬踢打。其他人跑过去将他们隔开，但是两个宿仇依然盯着对方，咒骂不停。猫指责狗拽她的尾巴，在她的食物里面放锡钉，还攻击她。狗只是咆哮着，倒是什么都没有否认。

“你尝到厉害了吧！”他不停地说，“你尝到厉害了吧，还没有完呢！”

但是，突然间，他住口了，开始亢奋地喘起了粗气。大家可以看到他的舌头变得非常白。因为光告诉他，去吻孩子们，这是最后一次了。

“最后一次？”可怜的泰罗结结巴巴地问，“我们要和这两个可怜的孩子分开了？”

他实在太悲伤了，几乎失去了理解事情的能力。

“是的，”光说，“你们知道，那个时刻就要到来了……我们都要回归沉寂了……”

狗突然意识到了自己的不幸命运，发出了痛彻心扉的绝望咆哮声，扑到孩子们身上，疯狂地亲吻他们。

“不要！不要！”他哭着说，“我不接受！……我不接受！……我要一直能讲话！……我会非常听话的……你们留着我吧，我可以学习怎么读书，怎么写字，怎么玩骨牌！……我会一直干干净净的……我再也不会从厨房偷东西了……”

他跪在两个孩子面前，抽泣着，恳求着。泰泰尔满眼都是泪水，什么都没有说。亲爱的泰罗想到了一个绝佳的主意：他跑到猫跟前，笑着去吻她。他本来想要微笑，但笑得龇牙咧嘴，有些狰狞。泰莱特可没有自我牺牲的精神，立刻向后一跳，躲到了麦泰尔的身边。麦泰尔天真地说：

“泰莱特，就差你一个还没有吻我们呢。”

猫装腔作势地说：

“孩子们，我当然爱着你们两个，因为你们也值得我爱。”

这时出现了一阵沉默。

“现在，”光说，“轮到我了，让我给你们最后一吻……”

她说着，展开了纱巾，罩住两个孩子，仿佛她要用光明的力量最后一次将孩子们包裹住一般。然后，她给了每个孩子一个长长的、充满爱意的吻。泰泰尔和麦泰尔恳求地紧紧拉住她不放手。

“不要，不要，不要，光！”他们哭着说，“请留下来陪着我们！……爸爸不会介意的……我们会告诉妈妈你人多好……你一个人要去哪里呢？……”

“不会多远的，我的孩子，”光说，“就在万物的沉默国度之中。”

“不，不，”泰泰尔说，“我不让你走……”

但光用一个充满慈爱的手势让他们安静了下来，对他们说了一些他们永远都不会忘记的话。很久之后，当泰泰尔和麦泰尔都已经苍老，成了别人的爷爷奶奶，他们都还记得那些话，并经常对他们的孙子孙女重复。

光那些打动人心的话是这样说的：

“听着，泰泰尔，不要忘记，孩子，在这个世界上你能够看到的一切，既没有开始，也没有结束。如果你心中始终记住这一点，在成长中始终不忘，那么，无论在什么情况下，你都会知道该说什么，做什么，期待什么。”

这时，我们的两个小朋友抽泣起来，光又用充满爱意的声音补充道：

“别哭，我亲爱的孩子……我没有像水一样的声音，我只有我的明亮，人类却无法理解这明亮……但是我会一直照耀着人，直到他生命的终点……千万不要忘了，每一束漫洒的月光，每一点闪烁的星光，每一次晨光，每一盏灯火，都是我在对你诉说，你灵魂中每一个善良光明的念头，也都有我的存在。”

就在这个时候，小木屋中祖父留下来的钟敲了八下。光沉默了一会儿，然后用突然间变得隐约的声音低语道：

“再见！……再见！……时间到了！……再见！”

她的纱巾渐渐褪去，她的笑容变得苍白，她的眼睛闭上了，她的身影慢慢消失了，透过泪水，孩子们的眼睛再也看不到别的东西，唯有他们脚下一缕正慢慢消失的淡淡的光。然后，他们转头去看其他人……但那些物品和元素也已经消失了……

————————————————————

(1) 原文humbug，语义双关，还有骗子之意。

第十章　醒来

在樵夫泰尔家的木屋中，祖父留下来的钟已经敲了八下。两个孩子——泰泰尔和麦泰尔，依然还睡在他们的小床中。泰尔妈妈站在床边看着他们，她两手叉腰，围裙卷了起来，笑着数落他们。

“我可不能让他们一直睡到中午呀，”她说，“快点，起来，你们这些小懒骨头！”

但是，不管是摇晃他们、亲吻他们，还是把他们的被子掀了，都没有什么用，他们不断地躺回枕头上，鼻子朝着天花板，嘴巴张得大大的，眼睛紧紧闭着，脸颊泛着粉红色。

最后，在肋骨上挨了温柔的一击之后，泰泰尔睁开了一只眼睛，嘟嘟囔囔地说：

“怎么了？……光？……你在哪里？……不，不，别走……”

“光！”泰尔妈妈大笑着叫道，“是呀，当然，当然有光啦！……天亮了很久了！……你是怎么了？……你看起来像瞎了一样……”

“妈妈！……妈妈！……”泰泰尔揉着眼睛，“是你呀！”

“哎呀，当然是我啦！……你为什么这么瞪着我？……我的鼻孔朝上长了？”

这时候，泰泰尔已经完全清醒了，所以并没有回答这个问题。他此刻能感到的只有高兴！他已经好久好久没有见到妈妈了，想要一直亲吻她，怎么都不满足。

泰尔妈妈不安起来。这到底是怎么回事？她的儿子疯了吗？他怎么突然间说起了什么漫长的旅途，还有仙女、水、牛奶、糖、火、面包和光陪着！他还相信他已经离开家一年了！……

“但你根本没离开过这个房间！”泰尔妈妈叫道，现在她几乎吓坏了，“我昨晚上把你放在床上的，今天早晨你还在床上啊！今天是圣诞节，你没听到村子里的钟声吗？……”

“当然，今天是圣诞节，”泰泰尔固执地说，“我是在一年前离开的，就在圣诞前夜啊！……你们没有生我气吧？……你觉得很伤心吧？……还有爸爸怎么说的呀？……”

“好啦，你还没有睡醒呢！”泰尔妈妈以此自我安慰道，“你还在做梦呢！……快点起床，穿上你的短裤和小夹克……”

“呃，我穿着我的衬衫呢！”泰泰尔说。

他猛地起身，然后跪在床上，开始穿衣服，他的妈妈一直盯着他看，脸上挂着担忧的表情。

小男孩继续嘟囔说：

“你要是不相信我，就问问麦泰尔……哦，我们经历了那么多的冒险啊！……我们见到了爷爷和奶奶……是的，是在回忆之地……那是在我们冒险的路上。他们都死了，但是他们都很好，是不是，麦泰尔？”

此刻，麦泰尔也醒了过来，和哥哥一起描述他们去拜访祖父母的旅程，还有他们和小弟弟、小妹妹们相处时的乐趣。

泰尔妈妈真的受不了了。她跑到小屋的门口，用尽全力地叫她的丈夫。泰尔爸爸现在正在森林边上干活。

“噢，亲爱的，噢，亲爱的！”她大叫道，“我要失去他们了，就像失去其他孩子一样！……回来吧！……快回来呀……”

泰尔爸爸很快便回到了小屋，手里还拎着斧子。他听着妻子的哭诉，两个孩子则又开始讲述他们的冒险故事，还问他过去这一年他都做了什么。

“你看，你看啊！”泰尔妈妈已经哭了，“他们都神志不清了，他们肯定是生病了，去找医生来……”

不过，樵夫爸爸可不是大惊小怪的人，他吻了吻孩子们，镇定地点燃烟斗，说他们看起来都很好，没必要着急。

这个时候，传来了一阵敲门声，邻居走了进来。这个邻居是一个小个子的老太太，手里拄着一根拐杖，很像仙女贝丽露娜。孩子们一下子扑上去搂住她的脖子，围着她手舞足蹈，高兴地大叫：

“这是仙女贝丽露娜！”

这个邻居有些耳背，没有留意他们的叫声，只是对泰尔妈妈说：

“我来借点火，好去做我的圣诞炖菜……今天早上可真是冷死了……早安，孩子们……”

这个时候，泰泰尔思考了一下。无疑，再次见到老仙女，他感到非常开心，但是如果她得知他没有找到青鸟，会说什么呢？但他下决心像个男子汉一样，于是大胆地走向前说：

“仙女贝丽露娜，我没有找到青鸟……”

“他在说什么呢？”邻居太太被吓了一大跳。

泰尔妈妈又担心起来：“行了，泰泰尔，你不认得柏林格特太太了吗？”

“哎呀，认得，当然，”泰泰尔上下打量着邻居，“这是仙女贝丽露娜。”

“贝……什么？”邻居问。

“贝丽露娜。”泰泰尔平静地回答道。

“柏林格特，”邻居说，“你是说柏林格特。”

泰泰尔被她肯定的语气说得有点儿不确定，他答道：

“贝丽露娜也好，柏林格特也好，随你高兴吧，夫人，但是我知道我要说的……”

泰尔爸爸已经有些受够了。

“我们必须到此为止了，”他说，“我们给他们两巴掌吧。”

“不要，”邻居说，“这不值得。不过是梦的影响而已，他们肯定是睡觉时照到月光了(1)……我那病重的小女儿，就经常会这样……”

泰尔妈妈暂时放下了自己的担心，开始问候柏林格特家的小女儿。

“她就那样子啦，”邻居摇着头说，“她起不来床，医生说她的神经有问题……不过，我知道什么能够令她痊愈。就在今天早上，她还跟我要呢，想当作她的圣诞礼物……”

她有些犹豫，叹着气看着泰泰尔，用一种沮丧的口气接着说：

“我能做什么呢？那只是她一厢情愿罢了……”

其他人都沉默地看着彼此，他们都知道邻居的这些话是什么意思。那个小女孩一直都说如果泰泰尔能把自己的鸽子送给她，她就会好起来的，但是泰泰尔太喜欢那鸽子了，不愿意和鸽子分开……

“呃，”泰尔妈妈对儿子说，“把你的鸟儿送给那个可怜的小东西不行吗？她盼望得到那只小鸽子都盼了那么久了！……”

“我的鸟儿！”泰泰尔拍了拍自己的额头，仿佛他们在说的是非常奇怪的事情，“我的鸟儿，”他重复说，“真是的，我都把它忘了！……还有鸟笼！……麦泰尔，你看到鸟笼了吗？……就是面包拎着的那一个……是啊，是啊，就是同一个鸟笼，在这里，在这里！”

泰泰尔简直不敢相信自己的眼睛。他拉过一把椅子，放在鸟笼下面，开心地爬上椅子，一边说：

“当然啦，我愿意送给她，我愿意！……”

然后，他惊讶地呆住了。

“天哪，它是青色的！”他说，“是我的鸽子，一模一样的，不过我不在的这段时间它变成青色的了！”

我们的主人公从椅子上跳下来，欢快地跳跃着说：

“它就是我们在寻找的青鸟！我们走了那么远，那么远，而它却一直都在这里！……它竟然在家里！……啊，多神奇啊！……麦泰尔，你看到那只鸟了吗？光会说什么呢？……给你，柏林格特太太，快点带去给你的小女儿吧……”

他这么说着时，泰尔妈妈扑到了丈夫的怀中，哭诉道：

“你看到了吗？……你看到了吗？……他又犯病了……他精神错乱了……”

这个时候，柏林格特太太的脸明媚起来，她将两只手握在一起，说着感谢的话。泰泰尔把鸟送给她的时候，她简直不敢相信自己的眼睛。她将小男孩抱在怀中，因喜悦和感激而泪水涟涟。

“你把它送给我了？”她不断问着，“你就这样给我了，不求回报？……天啊，她该有多高兴啊！……我得快点儿回去……我会回来告诉你她说了什么的……”

“是啊，是啊，快点儿回去吧，”泰泰尔说，“有些鸟儿会变色的！”

柏林格特太太跑出门去，泰泰尔跟在她后面将门关好。然后他站在门口，转身看着小屋的墙壁，看着周围的一切，似乎大吃一惊。

“爸爸，妈妈，你们对这房子做了什么呀？”他问，“虽然还是原来的样子，但是看起来漂亮多了。”

他的父母十分不解，面面相觑，小男孩继续说：

“啊，是啊，全都重新粉刷过了，看起来特别新。所有东西都干干净净的，亮闪闪的……看看窗外的森林！……多大、多美啊！……人们会觉得它好新啊！……在这里，我感到真是高兴啊，噢，我真是高兴啊！”

可敬的樵夫和他的妻子不明白他们的儿子到底是怎么了。但我亲爱的小读者们，你们跟随着泰泰尔和麦泰尔经历了美丽的梦境，能够猜出来到底是什么改变了我们年轻的小主人公眼中的一切。

在他的梦里，仙女给他的法宝帮助他睁开眼睛，那一切并非没有半点意义。他已经学会了去发现周围事物的美丽。他经历了考验，勇气得到了增长。在追寻青鸟——那只能给仙女贝丽露娜的小女儿带来幸福的青鸟——的过程中，他已经变得非常慷慨，非常善良，仅仅是将快乐带给其他人的念头，就能令他满心喜悦。而且经过那些无尽的、神奇的奇幻国度，他面对生活时的想法已经变得非常开放。

男孩认为一切都变得漂亮了，这是对的，因为随着他的理解力更加丰富，更加纯粹，周围的一切也必然会变得比过去更加美丽。

泰泰尔继续开心地巡视着小屋。他凑到面包烤盘那里，对面包友善地说话。他跑到睡在篮子中的泰罗身边，称赞他在森林之战中的出色表现。

麦泰尔弯腰爱抚在炉子边打盹的泰莱特，说：

“哎呀，泰莱特？……你认识我的，我看得出来，不过你再也不能说话了。”

泰泰尔把手放在前额。

“啊！”他叫道，“钻石不见了！……谁拿走了我绿色的小帽子？……没关系，我也不需要了！……啊，这是火！早上好，先生！他一直噼啪作响，惹水生气呢！”他跑到水龙头边，拧开水龙头，弯下腰靠近水，“早上好，水，早上好！……她在说什么？……她还在说话呢，不过我没有办法像原来那样听懂了……啊，我真高兴啊，我真的很高兴啊！”

“我也是啊，我也很高兴！”麦泰尔说。

我们的两个小朋友手拉着手，在厨房里面蹦蹦跳跳。

泰尔妈妈看到他们充满活力的样子，心稍微放宽了一些。泰尔爸爸非常平静镇定。他坐在桌边，吃他的粥，笑着说：

“你看，他们在玩开心生活的游戏呢！”

当然，这个可怜又可敬的人并不知道，那场神奇的梦并没有教会他的孩子们玩开心生活的游戏，而是教会了他们开心生活，这是最了不起而又最难的一课。

“所有人当中，我最喜欢光了，”泰泰尔踮着脚尖，站在窗边，对麦泰尔说，“你看她就在那边，穿过森林中的树木。今天晚上，她会在灯里。天哪，噢，天哪，这一切都多美好啊，我感到真高兴啊，我真高兴啊……”

他停下来，倾听着。所有人都在倾听着。他们听到了笑声，听到了欢乐的声音，那声音越来越近。

“那是光的声音！”泰泰尔叫道，“我去开门！”

实际上，站在门口的是一个小女孩，就是柏林格特家的小女儿，还有她的母亲柏林格特太太。

“看看她，”柏林格特太太简直喜不自胜，“她能跑、能跳，她简直要飞起来了！这真是个奇迹！她一看那只鸟儿，就跳起来了，就像这样……”

柏林格特太太单腿轮换着跳来跳去，不管是不是会跌倒，摔伤她长长的鹰钩鼻。

孩子们拍着手，每个人都在笑着。

小女孩穿着白色的长睡衣，站在厨房中间。在病了好几个月之后，现在能自己站起来，真的有点儿惊讶。她脸上带着微笑，将泰泰尔的鸽子抱在胸前。

泰泰尔先看了看那个孩子，然后又看向麦泰尔。

“你不觉得她很像是光吗？”他问。

“她小多了。”麦泰尔说。

“是啊，确实是！”泰泰尔说，“但她会长大的……”

三个孩子试着给小鸟喂了一些食物，他们的父母看着他们，感觉放松了很多，都露出了笑容。

泰泰尔容光焕发。我亲爱的小读者们，我不想瞒你们，鸽子是根本不会改变颜色的，是泰泰尔心中的喜悦和幸福，在他的眼睛里给那只鸟儿蒙上了一层瑰丽而明亮的青色。不过这有什么关系！泰泰尔并不知道这些，但他发现了光的伟大秘密，那就是：当我们想要与人分享幸福的时候，我们就离幸福近了一步。

而现在，不幸发生了。所有人都变得异常激动，孩子们尖叫起来，父母们举着胳膊，冲向开着的门那儿。因为鸟儿突然飞走了！很快就飞走了！

“我的鸟儿啊，我的鸟儿啊！”小女孩抽泣着说。

泰泰尔是第一个跑到台阶边的，但又兴致高昂地回来了。

“没关系的，”他说，“不要哭，它还在这屋子里面，我们会再次找到它的。”

他吻了小女孩一下。小女孩破涕为笑。

“你肯定能再抓到它，是不是？”她问。

“相信我，”我们的朋友自信地回答，“我知道它在哪里。”

而你们，我亲爱的小读者们，现在也知道了青鸟在哪里。亲爱的光什么都没有告诉樵夫的孩子们，但是她教会他们成为善良、和气、慷慨的人，向他们指明了通向幸福的路。

假如，在这个故事的一开始，她就对他们说：

“你们直接回家去吧，青鸟就在那里，在那简陋的小屋里，在一个柳条笼子里，和爱你们的父亲母亲在一起。”

孩子们是绝对不会相信的。

“什么？”泰泰尔会回答，“青鸟就是我的鸽子？别胡说了，我的鸽子是灰色的！……幸福，在小屋里面？和爸爸妈妈在一起？唉，哎呀！我家里可没有玩具，无聊得要命，我们想要去远方，面对无尽的冒险，享受各种乐趣……”

他肯定会这么说的，他和麦泰尔不会听光的建议，而是不顾一切出发去寻找，因为如果我们不亲身去经历，去体验，最确定的真理也一无是处。要将这个世界上所有的智慧都告诉给一个孩子，只需要很短的时间，但是要去理解那些智慧，整个生命都是不够的，因为我们自身的经验是我们唯一的光。

我们每个人都在寻找着自己的幸福，必须去经历无尽的痛苦，承受诸多残酷的失望，才能够明白：思想和心灵所能体会到的简单而纯粹的快乐，才会让人变得幸福。

————————————————————

(1) 西方传说月光会对人的心智有影响，尤其是满月的月光。

没有秘密的斯芬克斯[1]
——一幅蚀刻版画

一天下午，我正坐在和平咖啡馆外面，望着巴黎生活的光鲜与寒酸，一边喝着苦艾酒，一边对从我面前经过的这幅荣华与贫困交织的图景感到惊奇，这时我听到有人叫我的名字。我转过身，看到是默奇森勋爵。将近十年前，我们在一起上过大学。从那以来，我们没有见过面，所以我很高兴跟他再次相逢，我们热情握手。在牛津，我们曾经是要好的朋友。我当时非常喜欢他，他是那么潇洒漂亮、意气风发，那么值得尊敬。过去我们经常说，他要不是总说真话，就会是最出色的伙伴，但我觉得我们实际上格外佩服他的坦率。我发现他改变了好多。他一副焦虑困惑的样子，似乎对某件事儿疑神疑鬼。我觉得这不可能是现代的多疑癖，因为默奇森是最坚定的保守党人，对参议院的信仰就像对《摩西五经》[2]的信仰一样坚定。于是，我得出了结论，其原因在于一个女人，就问他结没结婚。

“我对女人还不够了解。”他答道。

“我亲爱的杰拉德，”我说，“女人是要被爱的，而不是要被了解的。”

“如果不能信任，我就没法去爱。”他答道。

“杰拉德，我相信你在生活中有一个秘密，”我大声说道，“告诉我是怎么回事。”

“我们坐车去兜风吧，”他回答说，“这里太挤了。不，不是黄车，其他任何颜色都可以——瞧，那辆深绿色的就行。”不一会儿，我们顺着林荫大道朝马德琳教堂方向一路驶去。

“我们要到哪里去？”我问。

“噢，你喜欢去哪里就去哪里！”他回答道，“去布洛涅森林[3]的餐厅。我们去那里吃饭，你要把自己所有的一切都告诉我。”

“我想先听听你的情况，”我说，“把你的秘密告诉我。”

他从口袋里掏出一只带有小银扣钩的摩洛哥羊皮盒子递给我。我打开盒子，里面有一张女人的照片。细高的身材，迷蒙的大眼，松散的头发，有一种奇异之美。她看上去仿佛有一双通灵般的眼睛，身上裹着昂贵的皮衣。

“你觉得那张脸怎么样？”他问，“它看上去坦诚吗？”

我仔细观察。在我看来，这是一个藏有秘密的人的脸，但那个秘密是好是坏，我却说不上来。它的美是一种由许多秘密塑造成的美——实际上，那种美是心理上的美，而不是造型上的美——嘴唇刚好浮起的淡淡微笑过于微妙，称不上真正的甜美。

“好吧，”他不耐烦地嚷道，“你以为如何？”

“她是身穿黑貂皮的乔孔达[4]，”我回答说，“告诉我有关她的所有情况。”

“不是现在，”他说，“晚饭后吧。”随后他就开始谈论其他事情。

当侍者给我们送来了咖啡和香烟的时候，我提醒杰拉德记住自己的诺言。他从座位上站起身，在房间里走了两三个来回，然后一屁股坐进扶手椅，给我讲了下面的故事：

“一天傍晚，”他说，“五点钟左右，我正沿着邦德街散步。当时，马车堵得要死，交通几乎瘫痪。靠近人行道停着一辆黄色小马车。出于这样或那样的原因，它吸引了我的注意。当我经过那里的时候，那张脸正从里往外看，就是今天下午我让你看的那张脸。它立刻就迷住了我。整个晚上，还有第二天整整一天，我都在不停地想着它。我徘徊在那条拥挤不堪的街上，窥视着每一辆马车，等待着那辆黄色马车。可是，我找不到我的陌生美人[5]。最后，我渐渐地觉得她只是一场梦。大约一个星期后，我要跟德·拉斯提尔夫人共进晚餐。晚餐定于八点钟。但到了八点半，我们还在客厅里等待着。最后，仆人猛地打开了门，宣布阿尔罗伊夫人驾到。这就是我一直在寻找的那个女人。她慢悠悠地走了进来，看上去犹如一道镶着灰色花边的月光，而且，让我欢天喜地的是，她请我带她进去吃饭。我们坐下来之后，我十分直率地说道：‘我想，不久前，我在邦德街瞥见过你，阿尔罗伊夫人。’她脸色煞白，用很低的声音对我说：‘请不要这么大声说话，也许会让别人听到。’我对自己开了个差劲的头而感觉糟糕，接着就自顾自地谈起了法国戏剧这个话题。她说话很少，总是以相同的低沉悦耳的声音说话，好像她是怕有人在听似的。我热烈而又愚蠢地堕入了情网，包围着她的神秘莫名的气氛引起了我最强烈的好奇心。晚饭后不久，当她要离开的时候，我问她，我可不可以去拜访她。她犹豫了一会儿，环顾四周，看有没有人在我们周围，然后说道：‘可以，明天四点四十五分。’我恳求德·拉斯提尔夫人告诉我有关她的情况，但我所能了解到的一切就是，她是一位寡妇，在公园路有一座漂亮的房子。某个无聊的家伙开始从科学的角度就寡妇这个话题发表一番长篇大论，举例论证婚姻中优胜劣汰、适者生存，于是我就告辞回家去了。

“第二天，我准时到达了公园路，但管家告诉我说，阿尔罗伊夫人刚刚出去了。我闷闷不乐，百思不解，去了俱乐部，经过一番考虑后给她写了一封信，询问我可不可以获准改天下午去试试运气。我好几天没有得到回复，但最后收到了一个小纸条，上面写着她星期天下午四点钟会在家里，还有一段奇怪的附言，‘请不要再往这里给我写信。我见到你的时候会解释的。’星期天，她接待了我，真是千娇百媚。而当我要离开的时候，她恳求我说，如果我有机会再次给她写信，就要‘由格林大街惠特克图书馆诺克斯太太转交’。‘我不能在自己的房子里收信是有原因的。’她说。

“那一季，我见了她很多次，而神秘的气氛从来没有离开过她。有时候，我觉得她是在某个人的控制下，但看上去她是那样难以接近，我无法确定。这真是很难让我下任何结论，因为她就像人们在博物馆里看到的一种奇异水晶，时而清晰，时而模糊。最终，我决定娶她做我的妻子：她对我的所有拜访和寄给她的几封信都一直保密，这些我都厌倦透了。我往她给的图书馆地址给她写信，问她下星期一晚上六点钟能不能见我。她的回答是肯定的，我开心极了。我对她心醉神迷：尽管她很神秘，但我当时还是想——离明了一切的那天不远了。不，我爱的是这个女人本身。她有一个秘密困扰着我，使我发疯。为什么碰巧要让我撞上呢？”

“这么说，是你发现了那个秘密？”我嚷道。

“恐怕是这样，”他回答说，“你可以自己判断。”

“星期一的时候，我跟我叔叔一起吃午饭，之后四点钟左右走到马里波恩路。你知道，我叔叔住在摄政公园。我想要去皮卡迪利大街，就穿过许多破旧的小街走了捷径。突然，我看到阿尔罗伊夫人出现在我面前，只见她戴着厚厚的面纱，走得很快。到达大街上的最后一座房子的时候，她走上台阶，掏出一把弹簧锁钥匙，自己走了进去。‘秘密就在这里。’我自言自语，匆匆往前，仔细察看了房子。这好像是一个出租房间的地方。门前的台阶上躺着她掉落的手帕。我把它捡起来，装进了口袋，随后开始考虑我应该做什么。我最后得出结论，我没有权利暗自监视她，就乘车去了俱乐部。到了六点钟，我去看望她。只见她躺在沙发上，身穿银色薄纱茶礼服，上面装饰着她喜欢的奇异月光石。她十分可爱。‘我很高兴见到你，’她说，‘我一整天都没出门。’我惊讶地盯着她，从口袋里掏出那块手帕，递给她。‘阿尔罗伊夫人，你今天下午把这个掉在了卡姆纳街上。’我平心静气地说。她恐惧地望着我，但没有接手帕。‘你当时在那里干什么？’我问。‘你有什么权利盘问我？’她反问道。‘是一个爱你的人的权利，’我回答说，‘我到这里是来请你做我的妻子的。’她把脸埋在双手里，泪如泉涌。‘你一定要告诉我。’我继续说道。她站起来，直视着我的脸，说道：‘默奇森勋爵，我没有什么可以告诉你的。’——‘你去会见某个人，’我嚷道，‘这就是你的秘密。’她脸色白得可怕，说道：‘我没有去会见任何人。’——‘难道你不能说实话吗？’我大声嚷道。‘我说的就是实话。’她答道。我发疯发狂，不知道当时说了什么，但我对她说了糟糕的话。最后，我冲出了那个房子。第二天，她给我写了一封信。我没有拆开就把信寄了回去，然后跟艾伦·科尔维尔启程前往挪威。一个月后，我返回巴黎，在《晨邮报》上看到的第一件事就是阿尔罗伊夫人的死讯。她在歌剧院受寒，五天后死于肺部充血。我把自己关起来，谁也不见。我曾经是如此爱她，我曾经那样疯狂地爱她。天哪！我曾经多么爱那个女人啊！”

“你后来又去那条街的房子了吗？”我问。

“去了。”他回答。

“有一天，我去了卡姆纳街。我没办法不去，疑问折磨着我。我敲了敲门，一位模样可敬的女士给我打开了门。我问她有没有房间出租。‘噢，先生，’她回答说，‘客厅应该可以出租。可是，我三个月都没有看到那位太太了，这房间都还欠着租金，不过你可以租。’——‘是这位太太吗？’我拿出照片说。‘毫无疑问，就是她，’她大声说道，‘她什么时候回来，先生？’‘这位太太死了。’我回答。‘噢，先生，真遗憾！’那个女人说，‘她是我最好的房客。她每星期付给我三几尼[6]，只是不时地在我的客厅里坐坐。’——‘她在这里见过什么人吗？’我问道。可是，那个女人向我保证说情况不是这样，她总是独自前来，没有见过什么人。‘她到底在这里做什么呢？’我嚷道。‘先生，她只是坐在客厅里，看看书，有时喝喝茶。’那个女人回答说。我不知道该说什么，于是给了她一金镑[7]就走了。现在，你认为这一切是什么意思？你难道不相信那个女人当时说的是真话吗？”

“我相信。”

“这么说，阿尔罗伊夫人为什么去那里？”

“我亲爱的杰拉德，”我回答说，“阿尔罗伊夫人只是一个热衷于营造神秘感的女人。她租这些房间，是为了戴着面纱来这里，想象自己是一个女主角。她对于神秘感无比狂热，但她自己不过是一个没有秘密的斯芬克斯。”

“你真这样想吗？”

“这一点我可以肯定。”我答道。

他掏出摩洛哥羊皮盒子，打开来，看着那张照片。“是这样吗？”他最后说道。

[1]斯芬克斯，在古希腊神话中是一个爱讲谜语的狮身女怪，说不出谜底的人就会被她吃掉。后来俄狄浦斯给出了正确答案，斯芬克斯跳崖而死（一说为俄狄浦斯所杀）。

[2]《摩西五经》，《希伯来圣经》最初的五部经典——《创世记》《出埃及记》《利未记》《民数记》《申命记》，是犹太教经典中最重要的部分，同时也是公元前六世纪以前唯一的希伯来法律汇编，曾作为犹大国的国家法律规范。

[3]布洛涅森林（Le bois de Boulogne），巴黎城西边的一片森林，跟巴黎东南的宛赛纳森林（Le bois de Vincennes）一起被视为巴黎吸收氧气的两扇“肺叶”。

[4]乔孔达，十六世纪艺术史家瓦萨里提出蒙娜丽莎是佛罗伦萨富商乔孔达的妻子，但这个观点没有引起人们太多兴趣。直到二〇〇五年，德国海德堡大学手稿研究专家阿明·施莱希特博士在图书馆找到了一本一五〇三年的古书。该书主人是达·芬奇的好友奥古斯蒂诺·韦斯普奇。韦斯普奇在书的空白处写道：“莱昂纳多·达·芬奇正在创作三幅画，其中一幅是格拉迪尼的画像——韦斯普奇。”这和十六世纪瓦萨里的说法不谋而合。他说的“富商乔孔达的妻子”就叫格拉迪尼，全名是丽莎·格拉迪尼·乔孔达。

[5]原文为法语：ma belle inconnue。

[6]1几尼=1.05英镑=21先令，最初是用几内亚的黄金铸造的，因此得名。

[7]金镑，英国等国本位货币“镑”的别称。

模范百万富翁
——一个惊叹号

一个人除非是富人，否则即便是一个迷人的家伙也白搭。浪漫是富人的特权，而不是穷人的行当。穷人应该务实平凡。收入稳定，胜过富有魅力。这些都是现代生活的伟大真理，休伊·厄斯金却从来没有意识到这些。可怜的休伊！从理智上来说，我们必须承认，他无足轻重。他一辈子从来没有说过生花妙语，也没有对谁恶语相向过。不过，他一头鬈曲的褐色头发、轮廓鲜明的五官和灰色的眼睛格外好看。他跟男人们在一起时像跟女人们在一起时一样受欢迎，除了赚钱，他样样在行。他的父亲留给了他一把马刀和一套十五卷的《半岛战争史》。休伊将马刀挂在穿衣镜上，把《半岛战争史》放在《拉夫指南》和《贝利杂志》之间的架子上，靠一位老姑妈给他的两百英镑年金生活。他什么工作都尝试过了。他曾经在证券交易所买卖过六个月股票。但是，一只蝴蝶在牛市和熊市之间能做什么呢？他当茶叶商的时间稍长些，但很快就厌倦了白毫茶[1]和小种茶[2]。之后，他曾试图出售干雪利酒，那酒却也不合人口味，味道有些太淡了。最终，他一事无成，成了一个讨人喜欢、没有出息的年轻人，模样精致，一无所有。

更糟糕的是，他还在谈情说爱。他爱的女孩劳拉·默顿是一位退休上校的女儿。上校在印度失去了绝好的脾气和胃口，从此再没找回来过。劳拉爱慕他，而他也情愿去吻她的鞋带。他们是伦敦最漂亮的情侣，却身无分文。上校非常喜欢休伊，但拒绝考虑任何订婚之事。

“我的孩子，当你有一万英镑的时候，再来找我，我们再考虑这件事。”他常常这么说。那些日子休伊一副闷闷不乐的样子，不得不去找劳拉寻求安慰。

一天早上，在前往默顿家所在的荷兰公园的途中，他顺便走访了自己的好友艾伦·特雷弗。特雷弗是一位画家。实际上，如今的人们不是画家的寥寥无几。不过，他也是一位艺术家，艺术家则相当罕见。他本人是一个奇怪粗暴的家伙，一脸雀斑，红髯蓬乱。然而，当拿起画笔的时候，他是一位真正的大师，他的画作受到人们的热烈追捧。一开始，他就十分喜欢休伊，我们必须承认这完全是因为他的个人魅力。“画家唯一应该认识的人，”他常说，“是愚蠢而又美丽的人，是看起来赏心悦目，谈起天来蠢笨无聊的人。花花公子和漂亮女人统治世界，至少他们应该这样做。”不过，渐渐地熟悉休伊之后，他也喜欢上了对方愉快活跃的性情和大方率真的本性，并允许他自由进出自己的画室。

休伊进来的时候，发现特雷弗正在给一幅乞丐肖像画画最后几笔。乞丐本人站在画室角落的一个高台上。这是一个干瘪的老头，脸像皱羊皮纸似的，一副可怜巴巴的表情，肩上搭着一件质地粗劣、破烂不堪的棕色外衣，厚靴子补丁摞补丁，一只手拄着一根粗糙的拐杖，另一只手伸出破帽子来请求施舍。

“一位令人震惊的模特！”休伊一边跟朋友握手，一边低声说道。

“令人震惊的模特？”特雷弗扯着嗓子嚷道，“我想的确如此！他这样的乞丐不是每天都会遇到的。一次意外的收获，亲爱的，[3]一幅活生生的媲美委拉斯开兹[4]的画！我的天哪！要是让伦勃朗来画他，他一定会做出一幅蚀刻版画！”

“可怜的老头儿！”休伊说，“看上去他是多么痛苦！不过，我想，对你们画家来说，他的脸所呈现的正是他的生活？”

“当然了，”特雷弗回答说，“你不可能指望一个乞丐面露喜色，对不对？”

“当一个模特让人画能挣多少钱？”休伊在一张舒服的长沙发上坐下来问道。

“一个小时一先令。”

“那你的画挣多少钱，艾伦？”

“噢，这个我挣两千！”

“英镑？”

“几尼。画家、诗人和医生得到的总是几尼。”

“嗯，我认为这些钱模特也应该分得一部分，”休伊笑着大声说道，“他们工作时像你一样努力。”

“胡说，胡说！啊，看看仅仅涂抹颜料有多么麻烦，还要一天到晚站在画架边！休伊，你说得很对，但你应该相信，有些时候艺术工作几乎应该得到和体力工作一样的尊敬。不过，你也不要喋喋不休，我很忙。抽一支烟，保持安静。”

过了一段时间，仆人进来，告诉特雷弗说画框制造商想和他说话。

“休伊，不要跑开，”他一边说，一边走了出去，“我去去就来。”

老乞丐趁特雷弗不在，便去他身后的木凳上休息。他看上去是那样无助又可怜，休伊不由得怜悯他，在口袋里摸了摸，看自己有多少钱。他所能找到的只有一枚金币和一些铜币。“可怜的老家伙，”他暗自想道，“他比我更需要钱，给他这些钱只不过意味着我两星期不坐马车罢了。”他穿过画室，然后把那枚金币轻轻地放在了乞丐的手里。

老人猛地一惊，干瘪的嘴唇掠过一丝淡淡的微笑。“谢谢你，先生，”他说，“谢谢你。”

随后，特雷弗赶到，休伊告辞，对自己做的事儿感到有些脸红。他跟劳拉一起待了一天，为自己的挥霍破费挨了一顿可爱的责骂，最后只好步行回家。

那天夜里十一点左右，他漫步至调色板俱乐部，发现特雷弗独自坐在抽烟室里喝着加了苏打水的白葡萄酒。

“好吧，艾伦，你那幅画画好了吗？”他一边说，一边点起了一支烟。

“画好了，也装上了框，我的伙计！”特雷弗回答，“还有，顺便说一下，你已经征服了那个人。你看到的那个老模特完全被你迷住了。我只好告诉他有关你的一切——你是谁，你住在哪里，你的收入是多少，你有什么前途——”

“我亲爱的艾伦，”休伊嚷道，“我回家的时候，可能会发现他在等着我。不过，当然，你只是在开玩笑。可怜的老家伙！我真希望我能为他做些什么。我认为，这种凄惨境况对于任何人都是可怕的。我家里有几堆旧衣服——你认为他会喜欢吗？唉，他的衣服都破成了烂布条。”

“不过，他穿上去很棒，”特雷弗说，“他如果穿着长礼服，我无论如何也不会画他。你称为破布的东西，我却称其为浪漫。在你看来等于贫困的东西，在我看来却是生动逼真的形象。不过，我会把你的提议告诉他的。”

“艾伦，”休伊严肃地说，“你们画家真是无情。”

“艺术家只有脑袋，没有良心，”特雷弗说，“再说，我们的职责是让我们看到的世界显得逼真，而不是改良我们了解的世界。每个人都有自己的职业。[5]现在告诉我劳拉怎么样了。老模特对她很感兴趣。”

“你不会对他谈起过她吧？”休伊说。

“我当然谈了。他对无情的上校、可爱的劳拉和一万英镑都了如指掌。”

“你把我所有的私事都告诉了老乞丐吗？”休伊气得满脸通红，大声嚷道。

“我亲爱的孩子，”特雷弗微笑着说，“你所称的那个老乞丐是欧洲最富有的人之一。他不用透支自己的账户，明天就可以买下整个伦敦。他在每个国家的首都都有一座房子，用金盘吃饭，他要是喜欢，还能阻止俄国开战呢。”

“你到底是什么意思？”休伊大声问道。

“我说的是，”特雷弗说，“你今天在画室看到的那个老头是豪斯伯格男爵。他是我的一位好朋友，几乎买下了我所有的画作，一个月前他给了我佣金，要我画一幅乞丐的画像。你会这么想吗？这是一个百万富翁的心血来潮！[6]我必须说，他穿着他的破衣烂衫，样子真是棒极了，或许我应该说穿着我的破衣烂衫，那是我在西班牙买的。”

“豪斯伯格男爵！”休伊嚷道，“天哪！我给了他一枚金币！”说完，他一屁股坐到扶手椅里，一副沮丧的样子。

“给了他一枚金币！”特雷弗突然哈哈大笑，大声嚷道，“我亲爱的伙计，你永远不会再看到它了。他拿别人的钱做生意。[7]”

“艾伦，我想你本应该告诉我，”休伊闷闷不乐地说，“不应该让我出这样的洋相。”

“噢，首先，休伊，”特雷弗说，“我从来没有想过，你会这样不假思索地到处施舍。你亲吻一个漂亮的模特我能理解，可你居然给一个丑陋的模特一枚金币——天哪，我不理解！此外，实际上，我今天真的没有准备接待任何人。你进来的时候，我不知道豪斯伯格愿不愿意让我提起他的名字。你知道他当时没有穿礼服。”

“他一定认为我是个笨蛋！”休伊说。

“一点也不。你离开后，他兴致再好不过了，不停地暗自发笑，来回搓着他布满皱纹的老手。我当时不明白为什么他那么有兴趣了解你的一切，可我现在全都明白了。休伊，他会用你的金币投资，每半年付给你一次利息，晚饭后也有一个精彩的故事可讲了。”

“我是个倒霉鬼，”休伊咆哮着说，“我能做得最好的事情就是去上床睡觉。还有，我亲爱的艾伦，你可千万不能告诉别人这件事，否则我就别想在这条街上见人了。”

“胡说！这件事说明了你心地仁慈，你应当引以为豪，休伊。不要跑掉。再来一根香烟，你可以再跟我多聊聊劳拉。”

然而，休伊不愿停留，而是感到闷闷不乐，走回了家，留下艾伦·特雷弗在身后发出一阵阵笑声。

第二天早上，他吃早餐的时候，仆人给他送来一张卡片，上面写着：古斯塔夫·诺丹先生，代表豪斯伯格男爵。“我想他是来要求我道歉的。”休伊自言自语地说。他吩咐仆人把来客领上来。

一位戴着金丝眼镜、头发花白的老先生走进房间，略带法国口音说道：“请问您是厄斯金先生吗？”

休伊点了点头。

“我是从豪斯伯格男爵那里来的，”他继续说道，“男爵——”

“先生，我恳求你给他带去我最诚挚的歉意。”休伊结结巴巴地说。

“男爵，”老先生面带微笑说，“委托我给你带来这封信。”说着，他递过来一个密封的信封。

信封外面写着：“一个老乞丐送给休·厄斯金和劳拉·默顿的结婚礼物。”里面还有一张一万英镑的支票。

他们结婚的时候，艾伦·特雷弗是伴郎，男爵在婚礼早餐上发表了祝词。

“百万富翁模特，”艾伦说，“真够罕见的。可是，天哪，模范百万富翁更罕见！”

[1]白毫茶，原名白毛茶，因其叶背长满白毫而得名，主产于广西百色凌云县四季云雾缭绕的岑王老山、青龙山一带。得天独厚的自然环境，使凌云白毫茶以色翠、毫多、香醇、味浓、耐泡五大特色成为中国名茶中的新秀。

[2]小种茶，小种红茶是福建省的特产，有正山小种和外山小种之分，正山小种产于政和或乡桐木关一带，也称桐水关小种或星村小种。坦洋、北岭、屏南、古田等地所产的仿照正山品质的小种红茶，质地较差，统称外山小种或人工小种。

[3]原文为法语：trouvaille，mon cher。

[4]委拉斯开兹（1599—1660），全名迭戈·罗德里格斯·德席尔瓦-委拉斯开兹，是文艺复兴后期西班牙最伟大的画家，对后来的画家影响深远。

[5]原文为法语：A chacun son métier。

[6]原文为法语：Que voulez-vous? La fantaisie d'un millionnaire。

[7]原文为法语：Son affaire c'est l'argent des autres。

亚瑟·萨维尔勋爵之罪
——一项责任的研究

第一章

这是复活节前温德米尔夫人的最后一次招待会，本廷克住宅甚至比平时更加拥挤。六位内阁部长佩戴勋章和缎带从众议院主席的招待会赶来，所有漂亮的女人都穿着最漂亮的礼服。卡尔斯鲁厄[1]的索菲娅公主站在画廊尽头，她是一位身体笨重、鞑靼人样的小姐，长着一双小黑眼睛，戴着美轮美奂的翡翠，扯开嗓门说着蹩脚的法语，无论对方说什么，她都纵声大笑。这肯定是一道奇妙的人群大杂烩。雍容华贵的贵夫人们和颜悦色地跟性情暴烈的激进分子聊了起来；受人欢迎的传教士们跟赫赫有名的怀疑论者擦着大衣后摆而行；一群主教一直跟着一位身材矮胖的女高音，从一个房间走到另一个房间；好几位皇家院士伪装成艺术家站在楼梯上。据说，晚餐室一度挤满了天才人物。实际上，这是温德米尔夫人家最棒的一个夜晚，后来公主一直逗留到将近十一点半才离开。

公主一走，温德米尔夫人就回到了画廊，那里一位大名鼎鼎的政治经济学家正在郑重其事地给一名看上去很气愤的匈牙利演奏家讲解音乐的科学理论，她开始跟佩斯利公爵夫人交谈起来。公爵夫人看上去美艳惊人，象牙白的高贵的颈项，一双勿忘我般的蓝眼睛，一头浓密的金色卷发。卷发是纯金色的——不是如今这种经常盗用金子雅号的暗淡的稻草黄，而是那种织入阳光或隐藏在奇异琥珀中的颜色。这种颜色给了她的脸几分圣人的模样，毫无罪魅之风。她是一位好奇的心理学研究者。早年，她已经发现了那个重要事实，就是再没有比纯真和轻率更为相似的东西了。通过一系列不顾一切的出轨行为——其中一半完全无害——她已经获得了名人的所有殊荣。她不止一次地换过丈夫，《德布雷特》[2]的确记载过她的三次婚姻。但是，她从来没有换过情人，这个世界早已不再谈论她的丑闻了。她现年四十岁，没有子女，而那种热衷享乐的激情成了她保持年轻的秘诀。

突然，温德米尔夫人急切地环顾房间，用清晰的女低音问道：“我的手相师在哪里？”

“你的什么，格拉迪斯？”公爵夫人突然不由自主地大声问道。

“我的手相师，公爵夫人。眼下没有他，我活不了。”

“亲爱的格拉迪斯！你总是这样与众不同。”公爵夫人一边喃喃说着，一边试图去想一个手相师（chiromantist）在现实生活中会是什么样子，希望他跟手足病大夫（chiropodist）不太一样。

“他每星期两次定期来看我的手，”温德米尔夫人接着说道，“而且对我的手极其关注。”

“天哪！”公爵夫人自言自语地说，“他真的是某种手足病大夫。真是可怕极了。我希望他至少是一个外国人，那就不会那么糟了。”

“我一定要把他介绍给你们。”

“介绍他！”公爵夫人嚷道，“你不是说他在这里吧？”她开始四处寻找她的小玳瑁扇子和那条破旧的花边披肩，以便准备好随时离去。

“当然，他在这里，没有他，我做梦也不会想要举行宴会。他告诉我说，我有一只纯净的通灵之手，如果我的拇指再短一点的话，我应该就是一个根深蒂固的悲观主义者，早已进了修道院。”

“噢，我明白了！”公爵夫人说，感到如释重负，“我想他会算好运吧？”

“也算厄运，”温德米尔夫人答道，“什么厄运都会算。比如，无论是陆路还是海路出行，明年我都有极大的危险，所以我得乘氢气球，每天晚上在篮子里吃晚餐。所有的一切都写在我的小拇指或手掌上，我忘记是哪一个了。”

“可这真是在考验上帝，格拉迪斯。”

“我亲爱的公爵夫人，上帝在这个时候肯定能经受住考验。我认为，每个人每个月都应该让人看一下手相，以便知道不能做什么。当然，人总会去做一些事，但得到提醒是一件非常令人愉快的事儿。现在，如果没有人马上去请伯杰斯先生，那我就亲自去了。”

“温德米尔夫人，让我去吧。”一个高大帅气的小伙子说道，只见他站在旁边，面带微笑地倾听着他们的谈话。

“非常感谢，亚瑟勋爵。可我怕你认不出他。”

“温德米尔夫人，如果他像你说的那样奇妙的话，我就完全不可能忽略他。告诉我，他什么模样，我会马上把他带到你身边。”

“啊，他一点也不像手相师。我是说，他看上去既不神秘难懂，也不风雅浪漫。他又矮又胖，秃顶而滑稽，戴着金边大眼镜，既像家庭医生又像乡村律师。我真的很抱歉，但这不是我的过错。这些人就是如此讨厌。我所有的钢琴师看起来都像诗人，而所有的诗人都像钢琴师。记得上个季节我请一个极其可怕的阴谋家吃饭，这个人曾炸死过好多人，总是穿着铠甲，衬衫的袖子里藏着一把匕首。你知道吗？他来的时候就像一个善良的老牧师，整个晚上都说着笑话。当然，他非常有趣，如此等等，但却让我大失所望。当我问他有关铠甲的问题的时候，他只是呵呵一笑，说英国冷死了，穿不了。啊，这就是伯杰斯先生！现在，伯杰斯先生，我想要你给佩斯利公爵夫人看一下手相。公爵夫人，你必须摘下手套。不，不是左手，是另一只手。”

“亲爱的格拉迪斯，我真的觉得这样不太好。”公爵夫人一边说着，一边有气无力地解开一只有些脏的小山羊皮白手套的扣子。

“没有什么总是有趣的东西。”温德米尔夫人说，“世道就是这样。[3]可我必须向你介绍。公爵夫人，这是我心爱的手相师伯杰斯先生。伯杰斯先生，这是佩斯利公爵夫人，如果你说她有比我更大的月亮丘[4]，我就再也不会相信你了。”

“格拉迪斯，我敢肯定我的手没有这种事儿。”公爵夫人神情严肃地说。

“夫人完全正确，”伯杰斯先生瞥了一眼那只长着又短又方的指头的手说，“月亮丘没有发育成熟。不过，生命线极好。请弯曲手腕。谢谢你。腕纹上有三条明显的线！公爵夫人，你会长寿，而且特别幸福。野心——非常克制，智慧线不突出，感情线……”

“伯杰斯先生，现在请放开来说。”温德米尔夫人嚷道。

“承蒙厚爱，”伯杰斯先生鞠躬说，“但我很抱歉地说，我看到了跟强烈的责任感相结合的伟大而又持久的感情。”

“请说下去，伯杰斯先生。”公爵夫人说，一副乐呵呵的样子。

“善于理财是夫人最大的美德。”伯杰斯先生接着说道，温德米尔夫人突然发出了一阵阵笑声。

“善于理财是一大好事，”公爵夫人得意地说，“当我嫁给佩斯利的时候，他有十一座城堡，而不是一座适合居住的房子。”

“而现在，他有十二座房子，却一座城堡也没有了。”温德米尔夫人嚷道。

“噢，亲爱的，”公爵夫人说，“我喜欢——”

“舒适，”伯杰斯先生说，“和现代化的改进设施，以及在每间卧室安装的热水系统。夫人完全正确。舒适是我们的文明能够给我们的唯一的东西。”

“伯杰斯先生，你出色地讲述了公爵夫人的性格，现在你必须讲一下弗洛拉夫人的性格。”一个身材高挑的姑娘从沙发后面笨手笨脚地走过来，向面带微笑的女主人点头回应，只见她一头淡茶色的苏格兰人的头发，高高的肩胛骨，伸出一只瘦骨嶙峋、竹片状指头的长手。

“啊，是一位钢琴家！我明白了，”伯杰斯先生说，“一位出色的钢琴家，但也许算不上音乐家。非常内敛，老老实实，而且十分喜爱动物。”

“确实如此！”公爵夫人转向温德米尔夫人大声嚷道，“绝对正确！弗洛拉在麦克罗斯基养了两打牧羊犬，如果她的父亲允许的话，她就会把我们的联排别墅变成动物园。”

“嗯，每个星期四晚上我的房子都是那样，”温德米尔夫人笑着大声说道，“只是我更喜欢狮子，不喜欢牧羊犬。”

“你这么说就不对了，温德米尔夫人。”伯杰斯先生夸张地鞠了一躬说。

“如果一个女人不能使她犯的错误变得迷人，那她就只是一个女性。”温德米尔夫人回答，“但你必须给我们多看看手相。来吧，托马斯爵士，让伯杰斯先生看看你的手。”一位模样和善，身穿白色背心的老先生走上前，伸出一只粗糙的厚手，中指很长。

“天性喜欢冒险。过去进行过四次漫长的航行，将来还要进行一次。曾经遇到过三次海难。不，只有两次，但下一次旅程会面临一次海难。是一个强硬的保守派，非常守时，十分热衷于收集古玩。十六到十八岁之间得过一次严重的疾病。三十岁时得到一笔遗产。十分讨厌猫和激进分子。”

“不同凡响！”托马斯爵士大声嚷道，“你一定也要实实在在地给我的妻子看看手相。”

“你的第二任妻子，”伯杰斯先生仍然把托马斯爵士的手放在他的手里，平静地说，“你的第二任妻子的手相。我会被迷住的。”但是，神情忧郁、长着棕色的头发和多情的睫毛的马弗尔太太完全拒绝把她的过去或将来暴露给别人。温德米尔夫人做的任何事情也都劝说不了俄罗斯大使德·科洛夫先生，即便只是摘下他的手套。实际上，许多人似乎不敢面对那个奇怪的小个子，只见他面带一成不变的微笑，戴着金丝眼镜，一双眼睛亮晶晶、圆溜溜的。他在大家面前直截了当地告诉可怜的弗莫尔太太，说她一点也不喜欢音乐，但特别喜欢音乐家，这时人们普遍感到手相学是一种极其危险的科学，而且是一种不应该得到鼓励的科学，只适合于一对一的私人场合。

然而，亚瑟·萨维尔勋爵对弗莫尔太太的不幸遭遇一无所知，一直在兴致勃勃地观察伯杰斯先生，充满了极大的好奇心，想让他给自己看看手相。他感觉有些害羞，不敢自己上前，就穿过房间，走到温德米尔夫人坐的地方，然后脸带迷人的红晕，问她认为伯杰斯先生会不会介意给他看手相。

“当然，他不会介意，”温德米尔夫人说，“这就是他此行的目的。亚瑟勋爵，我所有的狮子都是耍把戏的，无论我什么时候叫他们跳圈他们都得跳。可我必须事先警告你，我要把一切都告诉西比尔。她明天要来跟我一起吃午饭，谈论帽子，如果伯杰斯先生发现你有坏脾气，有痛风的倾向，或者有一个生活在贝斯沃特[5]的妻子，我就一定会让她知道所有的事情。”

亚瑟勋爵微微一笑，摇了摇头。“我不怕，”他回答说，“西比尔了解我，就像我了解她一样。”

“啊！听到你这么说，我有点儿遗憾。婚姻的良好基础是对彼此的误解。不，我一点儿也不愤世嫉俗，我只是经历了几乎与之相同的事儿而有了经验。伯杰斯先生，亚瑟·萨维尔勋爵期望有人给他看手相。不要告诉他说他跟伦敦最漂亮的一个女孩订婚了，因为《晨邮报》一个月前就刊登了这件事。”

“亲爱的温德米尔夫人，”杰德堡的侯爵夫人嚷道，“请让伯杰斯先生在这里再待一小会儿。他刚刚告诉我说我应该登台，我很感兴趣。”

“杰德堡夫人，如果他这样告诉你的话，我就一定要把他带走。伯杰斯先生，马上过来，给亚瑟勋爵看看手相。”

“好吧，”说着，杰德堡夫人从沙发上起身的时候稍微噘了噘嘴，“如果不准我登台，那就好歹也让我当一名观众。”

“当然可以，我们都是观众中的一员。”温德米尔夫人说，“现在，伯杰斯先生，务必告诉我们一件好事。亚瑟勋爵是我最爱的贵宾之一。”

但是，伯杰斯先生看到亚瑟勋爵的手，脸色变得出奇的惨白，一句话也没说。他似乎在全身发抖，浓浓的眉毛以奇怪、恼火的方式痉挛性地抽搐了一下，每当他迷惑不解的时候就是这样。随后，几颗大大的汗珠从他黄色的额头上冒出，就像有毒的露水一般，他的胖手指也变得又湿又冷。

亚瑟勋爵也察觉到了这些奇怪躁动的迹象，而且他自己有生以来第一次感到了恐惧。他想冲出房间，但他克制住了自己。无论如何，了解最坏的情况要比被留在这种可怕的悬疑中好。

“我在等待，伯杰斯先生。”他说。

“我们都在等待。”温德米尔夫人以快速而心急的口气嚷道，但手相师没有回答。

“我相信亚瑟要登台，”杰德堡夫人说，“而且，你责骂之后，伯杰斯先生不敢这样告诉他。”

突然，伯杰斯先生放下亚瑟勋爵的右手，一把抓住他的左手，腰弯得很低，仔细观察，眼镜的金边几乎擦到了亚瑟勋爵的手掌。一时间，他的脸变成了一副恐怖的白色面具，但他很快就恢复了镇静，抬头望着温德米尔夫人，勉强笑道：“这是一双迷人的小伙子的手。”

“当然是！”温德米尔夫人回答说，“但他会是一个迷人的丈夫吗？这就是我想知道的。”

“所有迷人的小伙子都是。”伯杰斯先生说。

“我认为丈夫不应该太迷人，”杰德堡夫人闷闷不乐地喃喃说道，“这很危险。”

“我亲爱的孩子，他们从来都不会太迷人，”温德米尔夫人嚷道，“但我想要的是细节。细节是唯一有趣的东西。亚瑟勋爵会发生什么事儿？”

“啊，在接下来的几个月里，亚瑟将进行一次航行——”

“噢，是的，当然是他的蜜月！”

“而且会失去一个亲戚。”

“我想不是他的妹妹吧？”杰德堡夫人用慈悲的语调问道。

“当然不是他的妹妹，”伯杰斯先生不以为然地挥了挥手答道，“只是一个远房亲戚。”

“唉，我失望极了，”温德米尔夫人说，“我明天绝对没有什么要告诉西比尔的。如今，没有人关心远亲。几年前他们就过时了。不过，我想她最好有一身黑色丝绸衣服，你知道黑色丝绸衣服在教堂总是有用的。现在让我们一起去吃晚饭吧。他们一定把大部分食物都吃掉了，但我们可能还会发现一些热汤。弗朗索瓦过去经常做得一手好汤，但他现在对政治非常焦虑，所以我对他不再有任何把握。我真希望布朗热将军[6]能保持安静。公爵夫人，我相信你累了吧？”

“一点也不累，亲爱的格拉迪斯，”公爵夫人一边回答，一边朝门口摇摇晃晃地走去，“我非常开心，手足病大夫，我是说手相师，有趣极了。弗洛拉，我的玳瑁扇子在哪里呢？噢，非常感谢，托马斯爵士。我的蕾丝披肩呢，弗洛拉？噢，谢谢你，托马斯爵士，你真是太好了。”说完，这个可敬的人儿终于设法到了楼下，中间也只把她的香水瓶子掉了两次。

这段时间亚瑟·萨维尔勋爵一直站在壁炉旁边，他身上的恐惧感依旧没有退去，还有对于不幸即将降临的胆战心惊。当他姐姐挽着普莱姆代尔勋爵的胳膊从他身边飘然走过的时候，他对姐姐苦笑了一下，只见她穿着粉红锦缎衣服，戴着珍珠，可爱极了。温德米尔夫人叫他跟着她的时候，他几乎没有听见。他想起了西比尔·默顿，想起了他们之间可能发生的一切，顿时泪眼模糊。

看着他，有人会说，涅墨西斯[7]窃取了帕拉斯[8]的盾牌之后，给他看了戈耳工[9]的头。他似乎变成了石头，忧郁的脸庞像是大理石做的一般。他生下来就过着一种富裕、精致和奢华的生活，这种生活摆脱了一切肮脏的想法，是一种美丽天真、无忧无虑的生活。现在他第一次感觉到了命运的不祥的神秘感，以及“末日”一词的可怕含义。

这一切看上去是多么疯狂和怪异啊！难道这种他自己看不懂、另一个人却能破解的写在他手上的符号，是某种罪恶的可怕秘密，或某种罪行的血红标志？难道没有逃脱的可能吗？我们是不是比被看不见的力量移动的棋子、依陶工的想象捏出的陶器更好呢？这一切是荣是辱？他的理性厌恶这一点，但他觉得某个悲剧正在围绕着他，使他必须得突然承受他无法承受的负担。演员们都非常幸运。他们可以选择他们愿不愿意出现在悲剧或喜剧里，他们愿不愿意受苦或作乐，欢笑或流泪。但在现实生活中，这是不一样的。大多数男人和女人被迫要扮演他们完全不胜任的角色。我们的吉尔登斯特恩[10]为我们扮演哈姆雷特，我们的哈姆雷特必须像哈尔王子一样会开玩笑。世界是一个舞台，但演员戏演得并不好。

突然，伯杰斯先生走进了房间。他看到亚瑟勋爵的时候吃了一惊，粗俗的胖脸变成了某种黄绿色。两个人目光相遇，一时间沉默了下来。

“亚瑟勋爵，公爵夫人把她的一只手套落在了这里，要求我把它带给她。”伯杰斯先生最后说道，“啊，我看到它在沙发上！晚安。”

“伯杰斯先生，我要问你一个问题，我一定要你给我一个直截了当的回答。”

“亚瑟勋爵，下一次吧，公爵夫人着急。恐怕我得走了。”

“你不能走。公爵夫人不急。”

“亚瑟勋爵，不应该让太太们一直等待，”伯杰斯先生苦笑着说，“女性容易急躁。”

亚瑟勋爵轮廓鲜明的嘴唇急躁而又不屑地噘起。可怜的公爵夫人似乎对他无足轻重。他穿过房间，走到伯杰斯先生站立的地方，伸出了一只手。

“告诉我，你在那里看到了什么，”他说，“告诉我真相。我必须知道这一点。我不是一个孩子了。”

伯杰斯先生的眼睛在金丝眼镜后面眨了眨，他不安地来回移动着两只脚，手指紧张地摆弄着一条闪光的表链。

“亚瑟勋爵，除了我说过的之外，是什么让你认为我从你手里还看到了别的东西？”

“我知道你看到了，我坚决要求你告诉我那是什么。我会付给你钱。我会给你一百英镑的支票。”

绿眼睛闪了一下，随后又暗了下去。

“几尼？”伯杰斯先生最后用低沉的声音问道。

“当然。我明天会送你一张支票。你的俱乐部在哪里？”

“我没有参加什么俱乐部。也就是说，只是目前没有。我的地址是——不过，还是让我把名片给你吧。”说着，伯杰斯先生从背心口袋里掏出一小张镶金边的卡片，深深地鞠了一躬后递给亚瑟勋爵。勋爵念着上面的字：

塞普蒂莫斯·R.伯杰斯先生

专业手相师

西月街1030号

“我的待客时间从十点钟到下午四点钟，”伯杰斯先生机械地说道，“家庭服务打折。”

“快。”亚瑟勋爵嚷道，脸色惨白，伸出一只手来。

伯杰斯先生紧张地看了看周围，拉上厚厚的门帘。

“亚瑟勋爵，这需要一点时间，你最好坐下来。”

“快，先生。”亚瑟勋爵在光滑的地板上愤怒地跺着脚，又一次嚷道。

伯杰斯先生微微一笑，从胸袋里掏出一只小小的放大镜，用手帕仔细地擦了擦。

“我完全准备好了。”他说。

第二章

十分钟后，亚瑟·萨维尔勋爵恐惧得脸色惨白，眼神狂乱而悲伤，从本廷克住宅冲了出来，一路闯过一群围站在大条纹遮阳篷四周的身穿皮衣的男仆，似乎什么都没有看到，什么都没有听到。夜晚严寒，广场四周的汽灯发出的光在凛冽的寒风中闪动摇曳着。但是，他手热发烫，额头火烧火燎。他继续走啊走，简直像是醉汉的步态。他走过去的时候，一名警察好奇地看着他；一个乞丐在拱门下面无精打采地乞讨，看到他比自己更加痛苦，越发害怕起来。有一次，他停在了一盏灯下面，看着自己的双手。他认为他可以察觉到血迹已经沾在了双手上，一阵微弱的叫声从他颤抖的嘴唇里迸发出来。

谋杀！这正是手相师在那里看到的。谋杀！那个夜晚似乎知道这一点，荒凉的风在他的耳朵里呼啸。连街道黑暗的角落都充满了这个字眼。它从房子的屋顶冲他龇牙狞笑着。

他首先来到海德公园，公园暗淡的林地似乎迷住了他。他疲惫地靠在栏杆上，眉头贴在湿漉漉的金属上降温，倾听着树木的颤抖着的沉默。“谋杀！谋杀！”他不停地重复着，好像重复可以使这个词不那么恐惧。他自己的声音使他不寒而栗，但他几乎希望回声能听到他的声音，将沉睡的城市从梦中唤醒。他觉得心里有一种疯狂的欲望，想拦住漫不经心的路人，并告诉他所有的一切。

随后，他漫步走过牛津街，走进一条条狭窄肮脏的小巷。他走过的时候，两个涂脂抹粉的女人嘲笑他。一个黑暗的院子里传来了一阵咒骂声和殴打声，随后传来了刺耳的尖叫声。他看到了那些穷人和老人们驼着背蜷缩在潮湿的门阶上，心里掠过了一阵莫名其妙的怜悯之情。这些身处罪恶和苦难中的孩子也注定要像他那样灭亡吗？他们像他一样仅仅是一出荒谬表演中的傀儡吗？

然而，击中他的不是苦难的神秘感，而是它的荒谬，是它彻底的无价值以及怪诞的意义缺失。一切都显得如此支离破碎！如此缺乏和谐！他对当时的肤浅乐观和实际事实之间的不一致惊讶不已。他还很年轻。

过了一段时间，他发现自己到了马里波恩教堂前面。沉默的道路看上去像一条长长的抛光银带，银带上面到处点缀着光影摇曳的暗色蔓藤花纹。闪烁着的汽灯排成一行，迤逦着伸向远方，带有围墙的小房子外面停着一辆孤零零的小马车，车夫睡在里面。他匆匆地朝波特兰广场方向走去，不时地环顾四周，好像担心自己被人跟踪似的。富街的拐角处站着两个男人，他们正在念巨幅广告牌上的一则小广告。一种古怪的好奇感打动了他，他走了过去。当他走近的时候，黑色字母印刷的“谋杀”一词映入了他的眼帘。他吃了一惊，随后脸颊通红。这是一则悬赏广告，悬赏捉拿一个中等个头的男子。这个男子年龄三四十岁，头戴小礼帽，上身穿黑色上衣，下身穿花格长裤，右脸颊上有一道伤疤。他念了一遍又一遍，想知道这个可怜的人会不会被逮住，会如何伤痕累累。也许有一天他自己的名字也会被张贴在伦敦的墙壁上。有一天说不定人们也会对他的脑袋进行悬赏。

这个想法吓得他直犯恶心。他转过身，匆匆地走进了夜幕。

他几乎不知道自己走到了哪里，模糊记得自己穿过了一片迷宫似的肮脏的房屋区。他发现自己最后到了皮卡迪利广场的时候，已经天光大亮。他朝贝尔格雷夫广场方向散步回家，在路上遇到了那些前往考文特花园的大马车。那些穿着白色工作服的车夫晒黑的脸庞喜气洋洋，头发卷曲蓬乱，大步跨进，毅然前行，鞭子甩得啪啪直响，不时地相互打声招呼。一匹高大的灰马领头，走在一个戴着铃铛的马队前面。一个胖乎乎的小男孩坐在灰马背上，破旧的帽子上插着一束报春花，小手紧紧地抓住马鬃，哈哈大笑着。大堆大堆的蔬菜看上去犹如一堆翡翠，朝着早晨的天空，被奇异的玫瑰那粉红色的花瓣包裹着。亚瑟勋爵觉得好奇，受到了影响，却说不清什么原因。黎明的精致之美似乎有一种让他说不出的伤感，让他想起了所有以美丽开局、以风暴结尾的日子。这些乡下人声音粗犷而愉快，对一切满不在乎，他们看到的是多么奇怪的伦敦！是一座摆脱了黑夜的罪恶和白昼的烟雾的伦敦，是一座死气沉沉的幽灵般的城市，是一座坟墓似的荒城！他不知道他们想的是什么，他们知不知道它的辉煌和耻辱，知不知道它火红色的极度欢乐，知不知道它可怕的饥饿，知不知道它从早到晚成就和毁灭的一切。这里对他们来说也许只是一个集市，他们把自己的水果带到这里来卖，他们至多在这里逗留几个小时，接着离开依旧沉默的街道，离开还在睡梦中的房子。他们走过去的时候，他望着他们，这给他带来了快乐。尽管他们粗鲁，穿着沉重的平头钉鞋，步态笨拙，但他们随身带来了一点儿阿卡迪亚[11]的味道。他觉得，他们跟大自然生活在一起，大自然教会了他们平和。他羡慕他们所不自知的一切。

他到达贝尔格雷夫广场的时候，天空呈淡蓝色，鸟儿们开始在花园里鸣啭起来。

第三章

亚瑟勋爵醒来的时候，已是十二点钟了，正午的阳光透过他房间的象牙丝绸窗帘溪水般流淌进来。他站起来，望着窗外。热气雾蒙蒙地笼罩在城市上空，房子的屋顶好似暗淡的白银。在下面广场忽隐忽现的绿色中，一些孩子像白蝴蝶一样飞来飞去，人行道上挤满了前往公园的人们。在他看来，生活似乎从来没有这样美好过，邪恶的东西似乎从来没有这样遥远过。

随后，他的仆人用托盘给他送来了一杯热巧克力。喝过后，他拉开桃红色的毛绒厚帘，走进了浴室。光线从屋顶轻轻溜过，穿过透明的玛瑙薄板，大理石浴池里的水像月光石一样一闪一闪的。他匆匆扑进去，让凉水浸湿他的脖颈和头发，然后把脑袋径直沉入水下，好像这样可以抹去某段可耻的回忆所留下的斑点。出来后，他差不多感到平和了。当下精致的物质条件已经主宰了他，就像火对于它的锻造之物，可以为之提纯，也可以毁灭它。

早饭过后，他倒在长沙发上，点了一根香烟。壁炉架上立着西比尔·默顿的大幅照片，照片四周镶着精美的旧式织锦，她还是像他第一次在诺埃尔太太的舞会上见到她时一样。形状优美的小脑袋微微垂向一边，好像细如芦苇的颈项简直难以承受这么多美丽的负担；双唇微启，似乎要唱出动听的曲调；梦幻般的眼睛向外散发出少女式的温柔与纯洁。她穿着柔软而紧身的双绉裙，手拿大叶扇子，看上去犹如一尊人们在塔纳格拉[12]附近的橄榄林里发现的精美小雕像一般。她的一举一动，无不显露出希腊时代的优雅。然而，她并不娇小。她简直拥有完美的身体比例——在当今时代是一件罕见之事，许多女人要么身材臃肿，要么单薄无力。

现在，亚瑟勋爵看着她，充满了因爱而生的怜惜。他觉得，在谋杀罪的厄运悬在头上的时候，娶她入门就像犹大的出卖行为一样，这是博尔吉亚家族[13]做梦也不曾想到的一种罪恶。当他随时可能奉召去执行写在他手上的那个可怕预言的时候，对他们来说还有什么幸福可言呢？命运的手里还握着这个可怕的预言的时候，他们的生活会是什么样子呢？婚期无论如何必须推迟。这一点他完全下定了决心。尽管他爱这个女孩，当他们坐在一起的时候，仅仅触碰一下她的手指，就能使他身体的每一根神经产生强烈的快感，但他依然清晰地认识到了他的职责所在，并充分意识到，他在谋杀发生之前没有权利结婚。这样做之后，他才能跟西比尔·默顿一起站在圣坛前，把他的一生交到她的手里，不再害怕出错。这样做之后，他才能把她抱在怀里，知道她永远不必为他脸红，不必在耻辱中低头。但是，必须首先做完这件事，而且对他们俩来说越早越好。

如果处在他的位置，许多男人会更喜欢得过且过的享乐之日，而不喜欢责任的陡峭高峰。但亚瑟勋爵却是一个本着良心做事的人，难以把快乐置于原则之上。他的爱超越纯粹的激情，对他来说，西比尔是一切美好与高贵的象征。他一度对自己受命做的一切有一种本能的抵触情绪，而这种抵触情绪很快就消失了。他的心告诉他说，这不是一种罪过，而是一种牺牲；他的理智提醒他，没有别的路可走。他必须得在为自己生活和为他人生活之间进行选择，毫无疑问，尽管压在他身上的任务十分艰巨，但他知道他不能让自私取代爱情。我们迟早都会受命对同样的问题做出决定——我们所有人都会被问到同样的问题。对于亚瑟勋爵来说，这个问题出现得更早些——在他的本性被中年的工于算计和玩世不恭破坏之前，或者说在他的心被我们时代的浅薄、普遍的自负腐蚀之前，他对履行自己的职责毫不犹豫。难得的是，他绝不仅仅是梦想家，也不是什么虚无的旁观者。如果是那样的话，他就会像哈姆雷特那样犹豫不决，让优柔寡断损耗自己的决心。不过，他本质上是一个注重实际的人。生活对他意味着行动，而不是思考。他具有最难得的东西——常识。

到这个时候，前一天夜里那些疯狂、混乱的感情已经完全消失了。他回想自己疯狂地走过一条条街道，回想自己强烈的痛苦，几乎有一种羞耻感。他的种种痛苦的确发自内心，使他现在觉得它们不真实。他不知道他为何会如此愚蠢，对无法改变的命运大喊大叫。唯一使他苦恼的问题似乎只是要杀死谁。因为他很清楚，谋杀这件事就像异教世界的宗教一样，既需要祭司，也需要祭品。他不是一个天才，因此没有敌人，实际上他也觉得现在不是发泄私愤的时候，他要履行的使命极其重大和庄严。因此，他在一张便签上列出了一份亲友的名单，经过深思熟虑之后，决定选中克莱门蒂娜·博尚太太。这是一位住在寇松街的可爱老太太，是他自己的远房表姐。他一向十分喜欢克莱门太太，人人都这样叫她，而且因为他成年之后已经继承了拉格比勋爵的所有财产，格外富有，所以她的死亡不会使他获得任何庸俗的金钱利益。实际上，他越考虑这件事，越觉得她似乎正是那个合适的人选，而且感到任何拖延对西比尔都是不公平的，因此决定立刻安排行动。

当然，要做的第一件事就是付清手相师的账务，所以他在窗口附近一张小谢拉顿[14]式样的写字台边开了一张一百零五英镑的支票，装入信封，吩咐仆人把它送到西月街支付赛普蒂默斯·伯杰斯先生的账单。随后，他给马厩打电话要小马车，穿好衣服就走出了门。他离开房间的时候，回头看了一眼西比尔·默顿的照片，并发誓说，无论如何，他绝不会让她知道他在为她做什么，会一直把自我牺牲这个秘密藏在心里。

在去白金汉俱乐部的途中，他在一家花店停下来，给西比尔送去了一篮漂亮的水仙花——可爱的白色花瓣，野雉眼般的鲜艳花冠。到达俱乐部之后，他直奔藏书室，按响了门铃，吩咐侍者给他端来一杯柠檬苏打水，并要找一本有关毒理学的书。他已经完全决定，使用毒药是应对这件棘手的事的最佳手段。对他来说，任何像个人暴力之类的事都令人讨厌至极，况且他绝不想以任何吸引公众注意的方式去杀死克莱门蒂娜太太，因为他讨厌在温德米尔夫人的宴会上被当成名流，也讨厌看到自己的名字出现在报纸庸俗的社会新闻中。他也不得不想到西比尔的父亲和母亲，因为他们是有些古板的人，听到什么丑闻的话，很可能会反对这门婚事。尽管他敢肯定，如果他告诉他们这个案件的全部事实，他们会是第一个欣赏他的动机的人。因此，他有充分的理由决定使用毒药。毒药安全可靠、悄无声息，排除了见到任何痛苦场景的可能性，他像大多数英国人一样，极力避免任何痛苦场景的出现。

然而，他对毒理学一无所知，侍者也似乎只从藏书室里找到了《拉夫指南》和《贝利杂志》。他亲自仔细查看了书架，终于无意中发现了一卷装帧漂亮的《药典》和一本厄斯金的《毒理学》。《毒理学》由马修·里德爵士编写，马修爵士是皇家医师学院院长，也是白金汉资历最老的成员之一，因被错当成别人而入选；一次意外就这样激怒了委员会，所以后来真人现身的时候，他们也一致反对他入选。亚瑟勋爵对这两本书中使用的术语百思不解，开始后悔他在牛津大学的时候没有更加重视经典，这时他在厄斯金的第二卷里发现了一段对乌头碱性质非常完整的叙述，是用相当明了的英文写的。在他看来，这正是他想要的毒药。这种药效果迅速——实际上，几乎是立竿见影——完全没有痛苦，如果服用马修爵士推荐的明胶胶囊，味道也绝不难吃。因此，他在衬衣袖口上记录下一个致命的剂量，把那些书放回原处，然后沿着圣詹姆斯街走到了著名药剂师佩斯特尔和哈姆贝的药店。佩斯特尔先生总是亲自服侍贵族，却对这个指令大为惊讶，毕恭毕敬地喃喃说了一些诊断书必不可少这样的话。但是，亚瑟勋爵对他解释了一番，说他不得不除掉一条大挪威獒，因为它露出了早期狂犬病的迹象，而且已经咬了赶车人的小腿两次。佩斯特尔先生随即点头称赞，说亚瑟勋爵具有了不起的毒理学知识，并马上按照处方配好了药。

亚瑟勋爵把胶囊放进了他在邦德街一个橱窗里看到的一只漂亮的小银糖果盒里，扔掉了佩斯特尔和哈姆贝药店难看的药丸盒，马上驱车赶到了克莱门蒂娜太太家里。

“噢，恶棍先生[15]，”他走进屋里的时候，老太太嚷道，“你怎么这么久都不来看看我呀？”

“我亲爱的克莱门太太，我从来没有一刻属于自己的时间。”亚瑟微笑着说。

“我想，你是说，你整天跟西比尔·默顿小姐四处闲逛，购买雪纺绸，胡说八道？我不明白为什么人们对结婚大惊小怪。在我那个时代，我们做梦也没有想过在公共场所卿卿我我，也不会在私下谈论这个问题。”

“我向你保证，我已经二十四小时没有见过西比尔了，克莱门太太。据我了解，她现在完全属于她的女帽商。”

“当然，这是你来看一个像我这样的丑老婆子的唯一原因。我纳闷你们这些男人为什么都不吸取教训。也曾有人对我痴狂[16]，我在这里是一个风湿病患者，可怜巴巴，戴着假面具，脾气也坏。啊，要不是因为亲爱的詹森太太，要不是她把那些所有她能找到的最蹩脚的法国小说送来给我，我认为自己将度日如年。除了让人缴费之外，医生们根本没用。他们甚至治不好我的心口痛。”

“克莱门太太，我已经给你带来了一个治愈这种病的良方，”亚瑟勋爵神情严肃地说，“这是一件由美国人发明的美妙东西。”

“我认为我不喜欢美国的发明，亚瑟。我敢肯定我不喜欢。我最近看了一些美国小说，它们写得相当荒谬。”

“噢，但这一个没得说，克莱门太太！我向你保证，这是一种完美的疗法。你一定要答应尝试一下。”说着，亚瑟勋爵从口袋里掏出了一个小盒子，递给她。

“嗯，这个盒子非常可爱，亚瑟。这真是一件礼物吗？你真好。这就是神奇的药吗？它看起来像是夹心糖。我要马上试试。”

“天哪！克莱门太太，”亚瑟勋爵一把抓住她的一只手大声说道，“你不能那样做。这是一种顺势疗法药物，如果你没有心口痛却吃了它，它就可能会对你有许多坏处。等你犯病的时候再吃吧。你会对结果大吃一惊。”

“我现在就想吃。”说着，克莱门蒂娜太太对着光线举起小透明胶囊，清澈的乌头碱浮起了泡沫，“我敢肯定它美味可口。事实上，尽管我讨厌医生，但我爱药丸。不过，我会留到下一次犯病的时候吃。”

“那将会是什么时候？”亚瑟勋爵急切地问道，“会很快吗？”

“我希望不是一个星期。我昨天上午就因犯病而不舒服。可谁也不知道。”

“那你月底前肯定会犯病吗，克莱门太太？”

“我害怕这样。可你今天是多么富有同情心，亚瑟！说真的，西比尔对你大有好处。现在你必须离开了，因为我要跟一些非常乏味的人吃饭，他们不愿谈论丑闻，而且我知道，如果现在得不到睡眠，我晚餐时就绝对无法保持清醒。亚瑟，再见，代问西比尔好，非常感谢你送给我美国药。”

“克莱门太太，你不会忘记吃的，对吗？”亚瑟从座位上站起来说。

“我当然不会，你这傻孩子。我觉得你能想到我，是再好不过了，我要是再想要的话，就会写信告诉你。”

亚瑟勋爵兴高采烈地离开了，有一种如释重负的感觉。

那天夜里，他会见了西比尔·默顿。他告诉她，他是如何被突然置于一种可怕的困境，荣誉和责任都不允许他从中退缩。他告诉她，婚期必须暂时推迟，因为直到摆脱可怕的纠葛，他才会成为一个自由人。他恳求她信任他，而不要对将来有任何疑虑。一切都不会有问题，但必须有耐心。

这个情景发生在海德公园默顿先生家的暖房里，亚瑟勋爵像平常一样在那里吃了饭。西比尔好像从来没有这样开心过。一时间，亚瑟勋爵禁不住要扮演起懦夫的角色，想给克莱门蒂娜太太写信要回那个药丸，并让婚姻继续下去，就像世界上没有伯杰斯先生这个人一样。然而，他人性里高尚善良的一面很快就显示了威力，甚至当西比尔扑在他怀里哭泣的时候，他都没有动摇。西比尔的美既撩动了他的感官，也触动了他的良知。他认为，为了几个月的愉快而破坏如此美好的生活，将是一种错误的做法。

他跟西比尔一直待到接近午夜，他安慰她，反过来她又安慰他。第二天一早，他给默顿先生写了一封措辞果决的信，谈了推迟婚姻的必要性之后，就启程去了威尼斯。

第四章

到了威尼斯，他遇到了他的哥哥瑟比顿勋爵，瑟比顿勋爵碰巧从科孚岛[17]坐游艇过来。两个年轻人一起度过了愉快的两个星期。早晨，他们在丽都岛骑马，或者乘坐长长的黑色平底船沿着绿色运河航行；下午，他们通常在游艇上款待游客；晚上，他们在弗洛莱恩餐馆吃饭，在广场享受数不尽的香烟。但不知何故，亚瑟勋爵却高兴不起来。他每天都研究《泰晤士报》上的讣告栏，期待看到克莱门蒂娜太太死亡的通告，但每天他都失望。他开始担心她发生什么意外，而且经常后悔，不应该在她十分渴望去尝试效果的时候阻止其服用乌头碱。尽管西比尔的信充满了爱、信任和柔情，但语气常常十分伤感，有时他总是认为他会跟她永别。

两个星期后，瑟比顿勋爵渐渐厌倦了威尼斯，决定前往拉文那[18]海岸，因为他听说松树园有一个盛大的猎野鸡活动。亚瑟勋爵起先一口拒绝，但他特别喜欢的瑟比顿最后说服他，如果他独自留在丹尼利的话，他将会闷死。于是，十五日早上，他们就出发了，东北风劲吹，大海有些波涛汹涌。这项运动很好，自由的户外生活使亚瑟勋爵的脸颊恢复了颜色，但大约到了二十二日，他渐渐地担心起了克莱门蒂娜太太，因此，尽管瑟比顿一再挽留，他还是乘火车返回了威尼斯。

当他走出平底船踏上旅馆台阶的时候，旅馆老板拿着一捆电报走上前迎接他。亚瑟勋爵一把从老板的手里夺走了电报一一撕开。一切都取得了成功。克莱门蒂娜太太已经在十七日的夜里突然死去了！

他首先想到的是找西比尔，就给她发了一份电报，告诉她自己将立即返回伦敦，随后吩咐贴身男仆给他收拾东西，赶晚上的邮车，付给船夫们的大约是正常费用的五倍，然后脚步轻快、心花怒放地跑到客厅。到了那里，他发现有三封信在等着他。一封是西比尔本人寄来的，充满了同情和慰问。另外两封是他的母亲和克莱门蒂娜太太的律师寄来的。看来当天晚上老太太曾跟公爵夫人共进晚餐，人人都为她的机智风趣而感到愉悦，但她抱怨心口痛，就早早回家去了。第二天早上，有人发现她死在了床上，显然没有遭受任何痛苦。马修·里德爵士立马应召前往，但想必也无能为力，二十二日她要在博尚夏科下葬。去世前几天，她就立下了遗嘱，除了她收藏的微缩型细密画要归她的妹妹玛格丽特·拉福德太太所有，她在寇松街的小房子，以及她所有的家具、个人物品和绘画作品都留给亚瑟勋爵，她的紫水晶项链则归西比尔·默顿。财产没有多大价值，但律师曼斯菲尔德先生十分期望亚瑟勋爵如有可能马上返回，因为还有大量票据需要支付，克莱门蒂娜太太从来不曾有过任何定期账户。

想起克莱门蒂娜太太的亲切关怀，亚瑟勋爵大为感动，觉得伯杰斯先生要大受惩罚。然而，他对西比尔的爱左右了其他所有情绪，那种尽职尽责的意识给了他平和与安慰。到达查令十字街的时候，他感到非常高兴。

默顿一家非常亲切地接待了他，西比尔让他保证，他再也不会让他们之间发生任何事儿，婚期定于六月七日。在他看来，生活似乎再次明媚了起来，过去所有的喜悦又回到了他身边。

然而，有一天，他跟克莱门蒂娜太太的律师和西比尔本人一起去寇松街的房子，焚烧一捆捆褪色的信件，清理一个个放满奇怪垃圾的抽屉时，女孩突然发出了一声小小的欢乐的叫声。

“你发现了什么，西比尔？”亚瑟勋爵从工作中抬起头来，面带微笑地说。

“这个可爱的小银糖果盒，亚瑟。是不是古雅精巧？请把它给我吧！我知道紫水晶不会适合我，得等到我八十多岁才戴。”

这是那个装乌头碱的盒子。

亚瑟勋爵吃了一惊，脸颊上泛起了淡淡的红晕。他几乎已经完全忘记他做了什么。在他看来，鬼使神差，是西比尔第一个提醒他这一点，为了西比尔他曾经历了所有这一切可怕的焦虑。

“当然，你可以拥有它，西比尔。是我亲自把它给了可怜的克莱门太太。”

“噢！谢谢你，亚瑟。夹心糖也是吗？我根本不知道克莱门蒂娜太太喜欢糖果。我还以为她智商多高呢。”

亚瑟勋爵脸色变得惨白，脑海里掠过了一个可怕的想法。

“夹心糖，西比尔？你是什么意思？”他以缓慢、沙哑的声音说。

“里面有一个，仅此而已。看上去已经放了一段时间，落满灰尘，我根本不想吃。这是怎么回事，亚瑟？你的脸色看上去一片惨白！”

亚瑟勋爵冲过房间，一把抓起那个盒子。里面是琥珀色胶囊，还冒着毒泡。克莱门蒂娜太太毕竟已经寿终正寝了！

发现这一点引起的震惊，简直让他难以承受。他把胶囊扔进了火里，绝望地叫了一声，一屁股坐在了沙发上。

第五章

默顿先生对第二次推迟婚期万分痛苦，朱莉娅太太已经为婚礼订购了婚纱，竭尽全力劝说西比尔中断婚约。然而，西比尔深爱她母亲的同时，也已经把自己的整个生命交到了亚瑟勋爵的手里，朱莉娅太太说什么都无法使她动摇信念。至于亚瑟勋爵本人，他花了几天时间才战胜了自己可怕的失望情绪，期间他一度心灰意冷。然而，他出色的常识很快就显示了威力，健全务实的心智没有让他踌躇不前。已经证明毒药完全失败后，炸药或某种其他形式的爆炸物显然也是可以尝试的。

于是，他又看了一遍那份亲友名单，经过慎重考虑后，决定炸掉他的叔叔——奇切斯特的教长。教长学识渊博，特别喜欢时钟，收藏了一批从十五世纪至今的奇妙钟表，在亚瑟勋爵看来，正是教长的这个嗜好给他提供了实施计划的绝佳机会。到哪里购买一个爆炸装置当然是件不容易的事。伦敦工商目录没有给他提供这方面的任何信息，他觉得去苏格兰场[19]也没有多大用处，因为他们似乎总要到爆炸发生后才能知道关于炸药的内情，甚至在那之后也所知寥寥。

突然，他想到了他的朋友鲁瓦洛夫。鲁瓦洛夫是一个具有强烈革命倾向的俄罗斯年轻人，他是冬天在温德米尔夫人的家里遇见这个年轻人的。鲁瓦洛夫伯爵被委派写一本关于彼得大帝生活的书，并已来到英格兰，目的是研究那位沙皇在这个国家做造船木匠时的住所的相关文件，但人们普遍怀疑他是一名无政府主义特工。毫无疑问的是，他出现在伦敦，俄罗斯大使馆对此并不看好。亚瑟勋爵觉得他正是自己要找的那个人，便选了一天早晨驱车前往他在布鲁姆斯伯里的住处，寻求他的建议和帮助。

“那么，你是要认真从事政治吗？”当亚瑟勋爵告诉他此行的目的之时，鲁瓦洛夫伯爵问道。但是，亚瑟勋爵讨厌任何形式的招摇自大，觉得他不得不对他承认自己对社会问题没有丝毫兴趣，只是因为纯粹的家庭问题想要爆炸装置，除了他自己之外，谁也不关心这个问题。

鲁瓦洛夫伯爵惊讶地看了他一会儿，然后看到他相当认真，就在一张纸上写了一个地址，签上自己名字的首写字母，隔着桌子递给了他。

“为了得到这个地址，苏格兰场会给一个大价钱，我亲爱的伙计。”

“他们不会得到的。”亚瑟勋爵朗声笑道。他热情地握过俄罗斯小伙子的手之后跑下楼，仔细查看了那张纸，然后吩咐车夫把车开到苏荷广场。

到了那里，他打发走了车夫，沿着希腊街走，直至一个叫贝尔院的地方。他穿过拱门，发现自己到了一个奇怪的死胡同。一家法国洗衣房显眼地盘踞在路的尽头，晾衣绳织成的紧密的网从房子的一边延伸至另一边，白色亚麻布在晨风中拂动着。他走到尽头，敲响了一间绿色小屋的房门。门一时没有开，院子里的窗口如同一个个模糊的窥探着什么的面孔。之后，一个模样有些粗野的外国人探出头来，用非常蹩脚的英语问他有何贵干。亚瑟勋爵把鲁瓦洛夫伯爵给他的那张纸递了过去。那个人看到那张纸的时候，鞠了一躬，邀请亚瑟勋爵进入一楼一个非常简陋的前厅等待。过了一会儿，那个在英国被称为温克尔科普夫先生的人匆匆走进房间，脖子上围着一块酒迹斑斑的餐巾，左手拿着叉子。

“鲁瓦洛夫伯爵向我介绍了你，”亚瑟勋爵鞠了一躬说，“我想和你就一件事聊几句。我的名字叫史密斯，罗伯特·史密斯先生，我想要你给我提供一座爆炸时钟。”

“亚瑟勋爵，很高兴见到你，”这个和颜悦色的矮个德国人笑着说道，“不要那么惊慌，了解大家是我的职责，我记得有一天晚上在温德米尔夫人的家里见过你。我希望夫人很好。你介意和我一起用早餐吗？有一种非常棒的肉酱，而且我的朋友都好心地说我的莱茵白葡萄酒比他们在德国大使馆得到的都好。”还没有从被认出的惊讶中回过神来，亚瑟勋爵就发现自己坐在了后屋里，正用标有帝国字母组合的淡黄色霍克杯呷着最美味的白葡萄酒，以尽可能最友好的方式跟那个有名的阴谋家聊着天。

“爆炸时钟，”温克尔科普夫先生说，“不是非常容易向外国出口的东西，因为即使成功通过海关，火车时刻表也没个准点，它们通常会在到达目的地之前发生爆炸。但如果你想要一个适合家庭使用的，我这里正好就有一个质量优良的爆炸时钟，保证你会对结果感到满意。我可以问一下这是针对谁的吗？如果是针对警察，或者任何一个跟苏格兰场有关的警察，恐怕我就不能为你做任何事儿了。英国警探的确是我们最好的朋友，拜他们的愚蠢所赐，我们总是可以想做什么就做什么。我可不想做任何针对他们的事儿。”

“我向你保证，”亚瑟勋爵说，“这跟警察没有任何关系。实际上，时钟是针对奇切斯特教长的。”

“天哪！我原来不知道你对宗教有如此强烈的感情，亚瑟勋爵。如今这样的年轻人寥寥无几。”

“温克尔科普夫先生，恐怕你高估我了，”亚瑟勋爵红着脸说，“事实上，我对神学一无所知。”

“那么，这是一件纯私人的事情吗？”

“是纯私人的。”

温克尔科普夫先生耸了耸肩，离开了房间，几分钟后带回来一颗一便士大小、圆蛋糕似的炸弹，是一座漂亮的法国小时钟，时钟顶端是自由女神镀金铜像，铜像脚下踩着象征独裁的九头蛇。

亚瑟勋爵看到它，脸上露出了笑容。“这正是我想要的东西，”他喊道，“现在告诉我它如何爆炸。”

“啊！这是我的秘密，”温克尔科普夫先生用一种理所当然的骄傲神情注视着他的发明答道，“告诉我，你希望它什么时候爆炸，我会将机器设置到那个时刻。”

“好吧，今天是星期二，如果你能马上寄出去——”

“那不可能，我手头上还有许多莫斯科朋友委托的重要工作。不过，也许我明天能把它寄出。”

“噢，如果明天夜里或星期四早上送到，时间就会绰绰有余！”亚瑟勋爵礼貌地说，“对于爆炸的那个时刻，定在星期五中午正好。教长总是那个时刻在家。”

“星期五中午。”温克尔科普夫先生重复道，壁炉旁边的书桌上放着一个大账簿，他把大意记了下来。

“现在，”亚瑟勋爵一边说，一边从座位上站了起来，“请告诉我该付你多少钱。”

“亚瑟勋爵，这样的区区小事，我本不愿收任何费用。炸药共计六先令七便士，时钟三英镑十先令，运费大约五先令。我非常高兴帮助鲁瓦洛夫伯爵的任何朋友。”

“可是，还有给你添的麻烦，温克尔科普夫先生？”

“噢，那没什么！这是我的荣幸。我不为金钱工作，完全是为自己的手艺而活。”

亚瑟勋爵在桌子上放下四英镑两先令六便士，对那位矮个子德国人的帮助表示感谢，成功地谢绝了下星期六在牛肉茶会上会见一些无政府主义者的邀请，离开后便去了海德公园。

随后的两天里，他处在一种极度亢奋的状态中。星期五中午十二点钟，他驱车前往白金汉俱乐部，等候消息传来。整个下午，那个缺乏热情的大厅门房不停地张贴着来自全国各地的电报，这些电报提供赛马结果、离婚诉讼判决、天气状况等等，而自动收报机嘀嘀嗒嗒地打印着一些乏味的琐事，说的是下议院的一次通宵会议，以及证券交易上的一次小小恐慌。下午四点钟，晚报送了进来，亚瑟勋爵拿着《蓓尔美尔公报》《圣詹姆斯公报》《环球报》和《回声报》钻进了藏书室。此举让古德柴尔德上校大为光火，上校想读那天上午他在市长大厦的演讲报告，演讲的主题是南非的传教工作，每个省安排黑人主教的可取性，以及出于某种原因对《新闻晚报》的严词抨击。然而，没有一家报纸提及奇切斯特，亚瑟勋爵觉得他的尝试一定是失败了。这对他是一个可怕的打击，一时间他十分气馁。第二天，温克尔科普夫先生去见他，心情复杂，充满歉意，并表示愿意提供给他另一座时钟，或者以成本价卖给他一盒硝基甘油炸弹。但是，他已经对炸药失去了所有信心。温克尔科普夫先生本人承认，如今的一切东西都十分伪劣，就连真正的炸药也几乎难以买到。然而，尽管那位矮个子德国人认为一定是机器出了问题，但他又不无希望地说着时钟仍有可能爆炸，举例说他曾给位于敖德萨的军事长官寄过气压表，尽管时间定在十天内爆炸，但差不多三个月都没有爆炸。的确，它真正爆炸的时候，只是成功地把一个女佣炸成了碎片，那个军事长官六个星期前就已经出城走了，但这至少表明，炸药作为一种破坏力量，在机械的控制下仍是一种有些不守时却又强大的力量。德国人的反省让亚瑟勋爵得到了一点儿安慰，但即便如此，他也是注定要失望的——两天后，就在他上楼时公爵夫人把他叫到了她的会客室，给他看了一封她刚收到的从教长宅邸寄来的信。

“简写的信非常迷人，”公爵夫人说，“你必须好好读读她的最后一封。这完全像穆迪寄给我们的小说一样出色。”

亚瑟勋爵一把从她的手里夺过那封信。信的内容如下：

最亲爱的姑妈：

非常感谢你为多加会[20]送来了法兰绒和多纹棉布。我完全同意你的看法，他们想穿漂亮的东西是无稽之谈，但如今每个人都如此激进，没有信仰，很难让他们明白他们不应该尝试穿得像上等人一样。我确信我不知道将来会发生什么。正如爸爸经常在他的布道里所说，我们生活在一个没有信仰的时代。

一个不明身份的仰慕者上星期四寄给爸爸一座时钟，我们开心极了。时钟是装在木箱里从伦敦寄来的，运费已付。爸爸觉得，这一定是读过他非凡的布道词《放纵是自由吗？》的某个人寄来的，因为时钟顶部是一个女人的雕像，爸爸说她的头上是自由之冠。我自己认为它很不合适，但爸爸说这具有历史意义，所以我想这没什么问题。帕克打开箱子，爸爸把它放在书房里的壁炉台上。星期五上午，我们都坐在那里，正当时钟敲响十二下的时候，我们听到了一阵呼呼声，只见一小股烟雾从雕像底座升起，自由女神雕像摔了下来，在炉围上摔断了鼻梁！玛丽亚相当惊慌，但看上去是如此可笑，我和詹姆斯都突然大笑了起来，连爸爸也被逗乐了。仔细查看之后，我们发现这是一座特别的闹钟。如果你将它设置到一个特定时间，放一些火药，在小锤子下面放上引信，你想要它什么时候响它就什么时候响。爸爸说不要把它留在书房，因为它发出了响声，雷吉就把它拿到了教室。它一整天都没什么响动，只有一阵阵小小的爆炸声。你觉得亚瑟会想要一个作为结婚礼物吗？我想这种闹钟在伦敦相当流行。爸爸说这种闹钟很棒，它表明自由不可能持久，而是一定会倒下。爸爸说自由是在法国大革命时期发明的。听起来是多么可怕！

我现在得去多加会，要在那里为她们读你那封极有启发性的信件。亲爱的姑妈，你的想法是如此明智，她们在那个阶层的生活中就应该穿些看上去不一样的衣服。我必须说，当今生和来世还有那么多更重要的事儿要做的时候，她们对着装的焦虑真是荒唐可笑。我很高兴收到你送来的花府绸衣服，看上去很合身，蕾丝也没有破。我穿着你星期三在主教家好心送给我的黄绸缎的衣服，觉得它看上去不错。你觉得再缝上蝴蝶结怎么样？詹宁斯说现在每个人都打蝴蝶结，衬裙应该饰有褶边。雷吉说闹钟刚刚又爆炸了一次，而爸爸已经吩咐他把它送到了马厩。我觉得爸爸不像当初那样喜欢它了，不过有人送给他这样一个漂亮精巧的玩具，他还是倍感荣幸。这表明人们读他的布道，并得益于此。

爸爸送上他的爱，詹姆斯、雷吉和玛丽亚也一同问好，希望塞西尔姑父的痛风好转，相信我，亲爱的姑妈。

永远爱你的侄女
简·珀西

附言：请告诉我有关蝴蝶结的情况。詹宁斯坚持认为它们是眼下的时尚。

奇切斯特教长宅邸
五月二十七日

亚瑟勋爵看信的时候表情非常严肃，怏怏不乐，公爵夫人哈哈大笑起来。

“我亲爱的亚瑟，”她大声说道，“我永远不会再给你看一个年轻太太的信了！可是，关于这种闹钟我想要说什么呢？我认为这是一个一流的发明，我自己也想要一个。”

“我可不太看好。”亚瑟勋爵苦笑着说。亲吻他的母亲后，他就离开了房间。

上楼后，他扑倒在沙发上，眼里充满了泪水。他已经尽力去实施这起谋杀，但两次都失败了，而且都不是他自己的过错。他曾试图尽职尽责，但好像命运自己变成了叛徒。好心好意，却竹篮打水一场空；试图完美，却徒劳无益，他感到压抑。或许，还是彻底取消婚约更好。诚然，西比尔将会痛苦，但痛苦并不能真正损伤她如此高贵的天性。至于他自己，那又有什么关系呢？总有某种可以让男人赴死的战争，某种可以让男人献身的事业，生命对他没有快乐可言，所以对于死亡他也没有任何恐惧。让命运女神解决他的厄运吧。他不会再主动帮她。

七点半钟，他穿好衣服，下楼去俱乐部。瑟比顿在那里跟一群小伙子聚会，他不得不跟他们一起吃饭。他们琐碎的谈话和无聊的玩笑没有引起他的兴趣。为了脱身，咖啡端上来时他就说有一个约会，借口离开了他们。当他走出俱乐部的时候，大厅门房递给他一封信。这是温克尔科普夫先生寄来的，请他第二天晚上过去看一把炸弹伞，那把伞一打开就会爆炸。这是最新的发明，刚刚从日内瓦发货抵达。他把信撕成了碎片。他已经打定了主意，不再尝试任何别的实验。随后，他散步到泰晤士河堤岸，在河边坐了几个小时。月亮从黄褐色的鬃毛似的云团间露出来，就像是狮子的眼睛，无数的星星在天空中闪耀，仿佛金粉洒在紫色的圆顶上。偶尔有一只驳船晃荡着驶过，进入浑浊的溪流，顺流漂去。鸣笛的火车奔过大桥后，铁路信号灯由绿色变成了猩红色。过了一段时间，十二点的钟声从威斯敏斯特高高的塔楼上隆隆传来，钟声每响一下，夜空似乎就颤抖一次。随后，铁路灯熄灭，留下一盏孤灯像一颗大红宝石在巨大的桅杆上闪闪发亮，城市的喧闹声变得越来越微弱。

到了两点钟，他站起来，朝黑衣修士桥走去。一切看上去都是如此虚幻！多么像一场奇怪的梦啊！河对岸的房子脱离了夜晚的黑暗。人们会说，银光和阴影已经重新塑造了世界。圣保罗教堂的巨大圆顶像气泡一样在朦胧的夜色中若隐若现。

他走近克娄巴特拉方尖碑[21]的时候，看到一个男人俯身在栏杆上面。他走得越来越近，那个男人抬起头，汽灯光完全照落在了他的脸上。

这是手相师伯杰斯先生！谁也不会认错那张肥胖松弛的脸庞、金丝眼镜、惨白的微笑和充满欲望的嘴唇。

亚瑟勋爵停住了脚步。一个绝妙的主意闪过他的脑海。他悄悄地绕到伯杰斯先生身后，一把抓住他的双腿，把他抛进了泰晤士河。这时传来了粗鲁的咒骂声和扑通的溅水声，随后万籁俱寂。亚瑟勋爵焦急地望过去，只见手相师的一顶高帽在月光下的水涡里打着转。过了一段时间，它也沉没了，再不见伯杰斯先生的一丝痕迹。他一度认为自己又看见了那个笨拙丑陋的巨大身影从大桥的楼梯处突然冒了出来，一种可怕的失败感向他袭来，但结果证明那原来仅仅是一道云影，当月亮从云后面钻出来的时候，它就消失了。最后，他似乎才意识到了命运的判决，如释重负地呼了口气，顺口说出了西比尔的名字。

“你扔下了什么东西，先生？”他身后一个声音突然说道。

他转过身，看到了一位手提靶心灯笼的警察。

“并不是什么重要的东西，警官。”他一边微笑着回答，一边招呼一辆路过的双座马车，然后跳了进去，吩咐车夫前往贝尔格雷夫广场。

接下来的几天，他时而充满希望，时而感到恐惧。有些时候，他简直盼望伯杰斯先生走进房间，但在其他时候，他觉得命运不能对他这么不公平。他两次前往位于西月街的手相师的办公室，都无法让自己按响门铃。他既渴望确定，又害怕确定。

最后，真相大白。他坐在俱乐部抽烟室一边喝茶，一边有些无聊地听着索比顿讲述欢乐剧院最近的滑稽歌曲，这时服务员拿着晚报走了进来。他拿起《圣詹姆斯公报》，无精打采地翻看起来，这时下面这个奇怪的标题引起了他的注意：

手相师的自杀

他兴奋得脸色苍白，开始看了起来。这段内容如下：

昨天早上七点钟，著名手相师塞普蒂默斯·R．伯杰斯先生的尸体被冲到了格林尼治镇的河岸上，就在航船酒店的前面。这位不幸的先生之前已经失踪了几天，手相界都为他的安全忧心忡忡。据推测，他是因积劳成疾在突发性精神错乱的影响下而自杀，验尸陪审团今天下午公布了裁定结果。伯杰斯先生刚刚完成了一篇关于手的主题详论，不久将会发表，到时一定将备受关注。死者六十五岁，似乎没有留下任何亲属。

亚瑟勋爵手里还拿着那张报纸就冲出了俱乐部，让大厅门房大为惊讶，门房试图拦住他，但没有拦住。亚瑟勋爵马上乘车去了公园小巷。西比尔从窗户看见了他，情况向她表明他带来了好消息。她跑下来迎接他，看到他的脸，她知道一切都很好。

“我亲爱的西比尔，”亚瑟勋爵嚷道，“我们明天结婚吧！”

“你这个傻小子！哎呀，连蛋糕都还没有订呢！”西比尔眼泪汪汪地笑道。

第六章

大约三个星期后，婚礼举行，圣彼得教堂挤满了上流人物。证婚词是由奇切斯特教长以极其感人的方式诵读的。人们都一致认为，他们从来没有见过一对比新郎新娘还要漂亮的夫妇。不过，他们不仅仅是漂亮——也非常幸福。亚瑟勋爵一刻也没有后悔过他为了西比尔而遭受的一切，而她，也献给了他一个女人可以给男人的最好的东西——爱慕、温柔以及爱情。对他们来说，浪漫并没有被现实扼杀。他们总是感到朝气蓬勃。

几年后，当两个漂亮的孩子生下来的时候，温德米尔夫人过来参观奥尔顿修道院——一个可爱的老地方，是公爵送给儿子的结婚礼物。一天下午，她跟亚瑟太太坐在花园里的欧椴树下，望着小男孩和小女孩像闪耀着的阳光般在玫瑰小路上追逐玩闹时，她突然握住了女主人的手，说道：“你幸福吗，西比尔？”

“亲爱的温德米尔夫人，我当然幸福。你不是吗？”

“我没有时间幸福，西比尔。我总是喜欢最后一个被介绍给我的人。不过，一般来说，一旦认识了他们，我又会渐渐感到厌倦。”

“你的狮子们满足不了你吗，温德米尔夫人？”

“哎呀，不！狮子们只在一个季节有好处。鬣毛一剪断，它们就是现存最迟钝的生物。此外，如果你真的对它们好的话，它们就会表现得非常糟糕。你还记得那个可怕的伯杰斯先生吗？他是一个可恶的骗子。当然，我根本不介意，甚至当他想借钱的时候，我都原谅了他，但我不能忍受他对我示爱。他真的已经使我讨厌手相术了。我现在爱好心灵感应。这有趣多了。”

“温德米尔夫人，你在这里千万不能提及反对手相术的话，这是亚瑟不喜欢人们打趣的唯一话题。我向你保证他对这件事非常认真。”

“你不是要说他相信手相术吧，西比尔？”

“温德米尔夫人，问他吧，他来了。”说着，亚瑟勋爵手里拿着一大束黄玫瑰，向花园走来，他的两个孩子正围着他跳舞。

“亚瑟勋爵？”

“是的，温德米尔夫人。”

“你不是说你相信手相术吧？”

“我当然相信。”年轻人微笑着说。

“可为什么？”

“因为我把一生所有的幸福都归功于它。”他喃喃说道，靠在了一把柳条椅上。

“我亲爱的亚瑟勋爵，你把什么归功于它呢？”

“西比尔。”他把玫瑰递给妻子，望着她紫罗兰色的眼睛答道。

“胡说什么！”温德米尔夫人嚷道，“我这辈子还从来没有听过这样的胡话呢。”

[1]卡尔斯鲁厄，德国西南部城市，属巴登-符腾堡州，位于黑林山麓，莱茵河东岸，有运河相通，是该州继斯图加特之后的第二大城市。

[2]《德布雷特》，全称是《德布雷特英国贵族年鉴》。

[3]原文为法语：on a fait le monde ainsi。

[4]月亮丘，靠手掌下半部分远离大拇指的那块区域。这块区域上的手纹会与旅行、创造力、想象力甚至某种幸运相关，有些平纹代表直觉、精神能力和康复的能量。月亮丘比较饱满的人会非常情绪化。

[5]贝斯沃特，威斯敏斯特市的主要住宅区，毗邻海德公园，有一个很大的国际社区，充满了历史趣味。

[6]布朗热（1837—1891），十九世纪八十年代法国著名军事家、政治家，十九世纪八十年代在法国掀起了民族沙文主义运动，后因失败而自杀。

[7]涅墨西斯，希腊神话中冷酷无情的复仇女神。

[8]帕拉斯，也称帕拉斯·雅典娜，是希腊神话中的奥林波斯十二神之一，是智慧女神、农业与园艺保护神、军事策略女神。

[9]戈耳工，蛇发女妖，在希腊神话中是三个长有尖牙、头生毒蛇的恐怖女妖，她们当中的代表就是最小的美杜莎。

[10]吉尔登斯特恩，莎士比亚《哈姆雷特》中的配角。

[11]阿卡迪亚，希腊南部地区，在诗歌和小说中常用来指代世外桃源。

[12]塔纳格拉，古希腊城市。

[13]博尔吉亚家族，中世纪西班牙的贵族，家族中著名人物有罗德里格（教皇亚历山大六世）、恺撒·博尔吉亚等。

[14]谢拉顿，英国乔治时代最后一位伟大的家具设计家和制作师。

[15]原文为法语：monsieur le mauvais sujet。

[16]原文为法语：On a fait des folies pour moi。

[17]科孚岛，位于希腊西部伊奥尼亚海中的岛屿，希腊语称克基拉岛，属希腊科孚州，隔海峡与阿尔巴尼亚相望，是伊奥尼亚群岛的第二大岛，也是群岛最闪亮的明珠。

[18]拉文那，意大利东北部港市。

[19]苏格兰场，英国首都伦敦警察厅的代称，位于大伦敦区的威斯敏斯特市，离上议院二百码左右，是英国首都大伦敦地区的警察机关。

[20]多加会，基督复临安息日会，是家庭聚会，又称余民教会，意指不依靠势力、组织、任何关系背景等，只依靠上帝的教会。耶稣在十字架上成就了旧约所有的礼仪律法，原则上所有过去的礼仪律法都没有实质意义。

[21]克娄巴特拉方尖碑，在英国首都伦敦风光旖旎的泰晤士河畔，矗立着一座又细又高的石碑，这座石碑高二十一米，底座宽约两米三，尖顶，碑身四周雕有精美的图案。这座重达二百吨的石碑是用整块花岗岩凿成的，跟美国纽约中央公园的那座石碑本是一对。

坎特维尔的幽灵
——一篇万物有灵浪漫传奇

第一章

当美国公使海勒姆·B．奥蒂斯先生买下坎特维尔猎场的时候，人人都对他说，他是在做一件愚不可及的事儿，因为毫无疑问这个地方闹鬼。实际上，坎特维尔勋爵本人是一个最一丝不苟的人，他已经感到自己有责任在洽谈条件的时候向奥蒂斯先生提及这个事实。

“自从我的姑婆博尔顿公爵老夫人受到惊吓并发生痉挛以来，我们自己都不愿住在这个地方。”坎特维尔勋爵说，“当时，她正在穿衣服准备吃饭，两只骷髅手搭在了她的肩上，她受到了惊吓，从此以后再没有恢复过来。奥蒂斯先生，我觉得必须告诉你，我好几个健在的家人都看见过那个幽灵，教区的牧师奥古斯都·丹皮尔也看见过，他是剑桥大学国王学院的研究员。公爵夫人发生那次不幸的意外之后，比较年轻的仆人们不再愿跟我们待在一起，坎特维尔夫人夜里常常睡不踏实，因为走廊和书房总是传来神秘的声音。”

“勋爵大人，”公使回答说，“我会给家具和幽灵估值。我来自一个现代化的国家，我们在那里拥有的一切，金钱都可以买到。我们所有朝气蓬勃的小伙子正把旧世界涂成红色，夺去你们最出色的女演员和女主角。我认为，如果欧洲有像幽灵这样的东西，我们得在家尽快见到它，要么把它带到我们国家的公立博物馆，要么带它做公路巡演。”

“我担心幽灵存在，”坎特维尔勋爵微笑着说，“不过它可能不会接受你富有魄力的剧团经理的提议。众所周知，从一五八四年以来，它已经闻名三百年了，实际上我的每个家庭成员在世时都见过它。”

“那么，家庭医生也是这样，坎特维尔勋爵。可是，先生，没有幽灵这样的东西，我猜自然规律是不会为英国贵族破例的。”

“你们在美国当然是非常自然的，”坎特维尔勋爵回答，没有完全明白奥蒂斯先生的最后一句话，“如果你不介意家里有鬼，那就没事儿。只是你必须记住我警告过你。”

这之后几个星期，这桩买卖最后完成，公使和他的家人在一季结束的时候迁去了坎特维尔猎场。奥蒂斯太太从前是第五十三街西的卢克丽霞·R．塔潘小姐，曾是纽约大名鼎鼎的美女，现在是一位非常标致的中年女人，眼睛漂亮，五官端正。许多美国太太离开故土的时候会化一种类似长期健康欠佳的妆容，认为这是一种欧洲的文雅，但奥蒂斯太太从来没有犯过这种错误。她有一副出色的体格，事实上充满令人惊奇的活力。实际上，在许多方面，她完全英国化，极好地证明了当今的我们除了语言外，与美国并无十分不同。他们的长子名叫华盛顿，这是他的父母亲一时爱国情绪高涨给他起的，一直让他愤恨不平。他是一个颇为英俊的金发小伙子，代表美国在纽波特娱乐场连续三个赛季领先德国人，即使在伦敦，他也因出色的舞技而赫赫有名。对栀子花和贵族爵位的痴迷是他唯一的不足，在其他方面他格外明智。弗吉尼娅·E．奥蒂斯小姐是一个十五岁的小姑娘，像小鹿一样轻盈可爱，蓝蓝的大眼睛漂亮直率。她是一个了不起的亚马孙女战士[1]，曾经骑着自己的小马跟老比尔顿勋爵比赛，绕着公园跑了两圈，在阿基里斯[2]雕像的前面，以一个半马身长的优势取胜；柴郡的年轻公爵大喜过望，当场向她求婚，却被他的监护人当天夜里送回伊顿公学，他顿时泪如泉涌。弗吉尼娅之后是双胞胎兄弟，他们通常被称为“星条旗”，因为他们总是被打得鼻青脸肿。他们是讨人喜欢的男孩，除了可敬的公使之外，他们是家里仅有的纯正共和党人。

因为坎特维尔猎场距离最近的火车站阿斯科特七英里，所以奥蒂斯先生就打电报要了一辆轻便马车来接他们，他们兴致勃勃地开始坐车兜风。这是一个宜人的七月黄昏，空气中弥漫着松木的清香。他们不时地听到林鸽静思默想时自己发出的悦耳的声音，或看到飒飒作响的蕨草深处野鸡光洁的胸脯。他们经过的时候，小松鼠在山毛榉树上凝视着他们；兔子翘着白尾巴穿过草丛，跃过长满青苔的圆丘，飞掠而去。然而，当他们进入坎特维尔猎场林荫道的时候，天空突然变得阴云密布，一种奇异的寂静托住了大气，一大群白嘴鸦静静地飞过他们的头顶，还没等他们到达房子，硕大的雨点就已经陆续落了下来。

站在台阶上迎接他们的是一位老太太，只见她身穿整洁的黑色绸衣，头戴白色帽子，腰系围裙。这是女管家乌姆妮太太，在坎特维尔夫人的殷切恳求下，奥蒂斯夫人已经同意继续保留她以前的职位。他们下车的时候，她对他们每人都行了屈膝礼，并以一种老派的方式说道：“我对你们莅临坎特维尔猎场表示欢迎。”他们跟着她穿过精美的都铎风格[3]的大厅，走进书房。那是一个狭长低矮的房间，墙上镶着黑橡木壁板，房间尽头是一个彩色玻璃大窗。在这里，茶已经为他们摆好，他们脱下外套后坐下来，开始环顾四周，这时乌姆妮太太伺候着他们。

突然，奥蒂斯太太看见了壁炉旁边地板上的一个暗红色斑点，但完全没有意识到那个斑点真正意味着什么，便对乌姆妮太太说：“恐怕是什么东西溅在了那里。”

“是的，夫人，”老管家用低沉的声音回答说，“血溅在了那块地方。”

“真讨厌，”奥蒂斯夫人嚷道，“我根本不关心客厅里的血迹。必须马上除去。”

老太太微微一笑，以同样低沉而神秘的声音回答说：“这是艾莉诺·德·坎特维尔夫人的血，一五七五年她正是在那个地方被自己的丈夫西蒙·德·坎特维尔爵士谋杀了。西蒙爵士比她多活了九年，然后在非常神秘的情况下突然消失了。他的尸体一直没有找到，但他罪恶的灵魂依旧在猎场出没。那些血迹备受游客及其他客人的赞美，而且也难以除掉。”

“胡说，”华盛顿·奥蒂斯嚷道，“平克顿出品的冠军牌去污剂和完美牌洗涤剂能立刻把它除掉。”还没等吓坏了的女管家阻拦，他就已经跪到了地上，用看上去像黑色化妆品的小棒飞快地擦起了地板。不一会儿，血迹就不见了踪影。

“我就知道平克顿能做到这一点。”他环顾着啧啧称赞的家人扬扬得意地大声说道，但他刚说完这些话，一道可怕的闪电瞬时照亮了昏暗的房间，一声吓人的炸雷惊得他们都跳了起来，乌姆妮太太晕倒在地。

“多么怪异的气候！”美国公使点起方头长雪茄平静地说，“我想这个古老国家的人口太多了，这样没法让人人都有个像样的天气。我一直认为向外移民是英格兰唯一的出路。”

“我亲爱的海勒姆，”奥蒂斯夫人叫道，“我们能为一个晕倒的女人做些什么呢？”

“收她损失赔偿费，”公使回答说，“之后她就不会晕倒了。”不一会儿，乌姆妮太太的确醒了过来。然而，毫无疑问，她特别难过，却仍旧固执地正告着奥蒂斯先生要提防房子会遇到的麻烦。

“先生，我亲眼见到过一些东西，”她说，“那能使任何一个基督徒都头发倒竖，这里发生的那些可怕的事情，让我好多好多个夜晚都合不上眼。”但是，奥蒂斯先生和他的妻子友好地向这个实诚的人保证说他们不怕鬼，接着，在祈求上帝保佑新主人夫妇，并达成涨工资的协议之后，老管家就蹒跚着去了她自己的房间。

第二章

狂风暴雨肆虐了整整一夜，但没有发生特别值得注意的事儿。然而，次日早上他们下来吃早饭的时候，发现可怕的血迹又一次出现在了地板上。“我认为，这不可能是完美牌洗涤剂的过错，”华盛顿说，“因为我曾经用它擦净过所有的东西。那一定是幽灵干的。”接着，他第二次擦掉了血迹，第二天早上血迹却再次出现。尽管书房夜里由奥蒂斯先生本人锁上，钥匙也被拿上了楼，但第三天早晨它还是在那里。全家人现在对此都非常感兴趣；奥蒂斯先生开始怀疑他曾经在否定幽灵存在这个问题上过于武断，奥蒂斯太太表示有加入通灵会的打算，华盛顿准备了一封给迈尔斯和波德莫尔先生的长信，主题是跟犯罪有关的血迹永久性这个问题。那天夜里，所有对幽灵是否客观存在的疑虑永远消除了。

这一天和煦温暖。在凉爽的夜晚，全家人坐车出去兜风。他们直到九点钟才回家，吃了一顿简便的晚饭。常常，人们在看到通灵现象之前都会表现出一种接受此种现象的期待，而今晚的谈话根本没有涉及幽灵，所以连产生这种期待的基本条件都没有。后来，我从奥蒂斯先生那里了解到，他们当晚讨论的话题仅仅是有修养的上层美国人的普通对话：比如范妮·达文波特小姐比莎拉·伯恩哈特演得好多了，比如即使在英国最好的人家也难以得到嫩玉米、荞麦饼和玉米粥，比如波士顿对培养世界精神的重要性，比如铁路旅行中行李检查系统的优点，比如跟伦敦拉长的音调相比纽约口音更加甜美。根本没有提到超自然现象，也没有任何一个字与西蒙·德·坎特维尔爵士有所关联。十一点钟，家人都去睡觉了，到十一点半所有的灯都熄灭了。过了一段时间后，奥蒂斯先生被走廊里的一个奇怪的声音惊醒了。听上去像是金属的叮当声，而且似乎越来越近。他立刻起床，划亮一根火柴，看了看时间。正是一点钟。他相当平静，摸了摸自己的脉搏，根本没有发烧的迹象。奇怪的声音还在继续，而且伴随着奇怪的声音，他清晰地听到了脚步声。他穿上拖鞋，从梳妆盒里拿出一个长方体小药瓶，打开了门。就在他的面前，在暗淡的月光下，他看到了一位相貌可怕的老人。老人的眼睛像火红的燃煤一般，灰色的长发乱蓬蓬打着卷儿披在肩上，衣服款式古老，又脏又破，手腕和脚踝上戴着沉重而又锈迹斑斑的手铐和脚镣。

“我亲爱的先生，”奥蒂斯先生说，“我真的必须得让你给那些枷锁上点油了，为此给你带来了一小瓶坦慕尼旭日牌润滑油。据说，这东西用一次就会完全起效，包装纸上有好几条这样的客户评价，都是出自我们当地一些最著名的牧师。我将把它留给你，放在这卧室的蜡烛旁边，你要是需要，我非常乐意提供更多给你。”说完这些话，美国公使把瓶子放在一张大理石桌子上，关上门，就去休息了。

一时间，坎特维尔的幽灵站在那里一动不动，自然是怒不可遏。随后，他狠狠地把瓶子摔在锃亮的地板上，顺着走廊逃去，嘴里发出空洞的呻吟声，眼睛里闪出一道瘆人的可怕绿光。然而，就在他逃到橡木大楼梯顶部的时候，一扇门猛地被推开了，只见两个白袍小人出现了，一只大枕头从他的头边飕地飞过！显然刻不容缓，因此他匆匆采用四维空间作为逃生途径，穿过护墙板不见了踪影，房子完全静了下来。

他逃到左侧的一间小密室的时候，倚着一道月光，喘了口气，开始思考自己的处境。在三百年间从未中断的辉煌生涯中，他从来没有受到过如此严重的侮辱。他想起了公爵老夫人，她穿着蕾丝衣服、戴着钻石站在镜子前面的时候，他已经把她吓得发生了痉挛；他想起了四个女佣，当他仅仅透过其中一间备用卧室的窗帘朝她们咧开嘴笑的时候，她们突然歇斯底里地发作了起来；他想起了教区牧师，一天深夜，牧师从书房出来的时候吹灭了蜡烛，从那以后他便只能由威廉爵士照看，因为他已经完全成了一个神经紊乱的牺牲品；他还想起了特雷莫伊拉克老夫人，她一天早晨醒来的时候看到一个骷髅坐在炉边的扶手椅里看她的日记，就脑膜炎发作，在床上躺了六个星期，康复后皈依了教会，断绝了她与臭名昭著的怀疑论者伏尔泰[4]先生的来往。他记得那个可怕的夜晚，有人发现邪恶的坎特维尔勋爵在更衣室里窒息，半张方块J卡在了他的喉咙中间，而且就在死之前，坎特维尔承认，他就是通过这张牌在克罗克福德家里骗了查尔斯·詹姆斯·福克斯五万英镑，并发誓说那个幽灵逼迫他吞下了那张牌。他所有的伟大成就又回到了他的脑海里。男管家之所以在食品储藏室开枪自杀，是因为他看到了一只绿手在敲窗玻璃；对美丽的斯塔特菲尔德夫人来说，为了隐藏烙在白皙皮肤上的五个手指印，她总是不得不围着黑色天鹅绒带子，最后在国王步道尽头的鲤鱼塘里淹死了自己。他带着真正艺术家的热情与自负，一一回顾着自己最著名的表演，回想起自己最后一次扮演“红色鲁宾，即被勒死的宝贝”，回想起他初次登台演出“贝克斯利沼地的吸血鬼冈特·基比恩”，回想起六月的一个可爱的傍晚他只是用自己的骨头在草坪网球场地上玩九柱戏[5]就引起的轰动场面，他不由得暗自苦笑了一下。经过这一切之后，一些卑鄙的现代美国人居然要送给他旭日牌润滑油，还要拿枕头砸向他的脑袋！这是完全难以忍受的。此外，历史上没有任何幽灵曾被这样对待过。因此，他决心报仇雪恨，直到天亮都保持着一个不变的陷入沉思的姿势。

第三章

第二天早上，奥蒂斯一家吃早餐时见面的时候，对于幽灵这个话题进行了详细的讨论。美国公使发现自己的礼物没有被接受自然有点儿恼火。“我并不希望，”他说，“去对那个幽灵进行任何人身伤害。我必须说，他在家里待的时间并不长，我认为朝他扔枕头是根本不礼貌的。”——尽管这话说得非常公正，但我很抱歉地说，这对双胞胎兄弟却爆发出了一阵阵大笑。“另一方面，”他继续说道，“如果他真的拒绝使用旭日牌润滑油，我们就不得不去掉他身上的铁链。卧室外面发出那么大的噪音，是完全不可能睡觉的。”

然而，在一个星期剩下的时间里，他们没有受到干扰，引起注意的唯一的东西就是书房地板上不断更新的血迹。这当然非常奇怪，因为夜里房门总是由奥蒂斯先生锁上的，窗户也已经被严严实实地插好。另外，血迹变色龙般的色彩也引起了纷纷议论。有些早晨，血迹是暗红色的（几乎是印度红），接着是朱红色，之后是浓紫色；有一次，按照自由美国归正圣公会教堂的简单仪式，他们下楼进行家庭祈祷，发现血迹是鲜艳的翠绿色。这万花筒似的种种变化自然让一家人兴致勃勃，每天晚上都要对这一主题频频下赌。唯一没有参与这个游戏的人是小弗吉尼娅，由于某种无法解释的原因，她一见到血迹就痛苦万分，血迹呈翠绿色的早晨她差点儿痛哭起来。

幽灵第二次出现是在星期天夜里。他们上床睡觉后不久，突然被大厅里一阵可怕的撞击声吓得惊慌失措。他们冲下楼来，发现一件大盔甲已经从支架上脱离开来，掉在了石地板上，与此同时，坎特维尔的幽灵坐在高背椅上，表情极其痛苦地揉着自己的膝盖。双胞胎随身带着自己的玩具枪，马上朝他开了两枪，打得很准，这只有通过长期细致地瞄准写作老师进行训练才能做到，而美国公使则用左轮手枪瞄准了他，按照加州的规矩，要求他举起双手！幽灵发出了一声疯狂而愤怒的尖叫，跳将起来，像雾一般扫过他们，路过的时候刮灭了华盛顿·奥蒂斯的蜡烛，因此把他们都留在了一片黑暗当中。到达楼梯顶部的时候，他恢复了过来，决定发出他赫赫有名的恶魔般的笑声。这一招，他用过不止一次，发现特别有用。据说，这笑声曾经一夜之间把雷克尔勋爵的假发变成了灰色，使坎特维尔夫人的三位法国女教师不到一个月就纷纷果断提出了辞职。因此，他发出了最恐怖的笑声，直使老拱形屋顶发出一次次轰鸣，但还没等可怕的回声消失，门就突然洞开，只见身穿淡蓝色睡衣的奥蒂斯夫人走了出来。“我担心你身体不好，”她说，“就给你带来了一瓶多贝尔医生的酊剂。如果是消化不良，你就会发现这是一服极其有效的药。”幽灵愤怒地瞪着她，随即准备把自己变成一只大黑狗，他这一手名不虚传，家庭医生总是把坎特维尔勋爵的叔叔托马斯·霍顿阁下的永久性痴呆归结于这一手。然而，越来越近的脚步声使他在自己毁灭性的意图上举棋不定，所以他自我满足般地变成了微弱的磷光，就在双胞胎赶到他身边之时，发出了一声低沉的哀叹，销声匿迹。

到达自己房间的时候，他完全崩溃了，被最强烈的焦虑不安的情绪所折磨。双胞胎的粗俗无礼和奥蒂斯太太的唯利是图自然特别让人恼火，但真正让他最痛苦的是，他未能穿上盔甲。他希望，即使是现代美国人，看到穿盔甲的幽灵也会不寒而栗，要是没有更合理的理由，至少出于对他们本国诗人朗费罗的尊重，也应该这样。坎特维尔一家待在城里的时候，他就在朗费罗优雅迷人的诗歌上打发了许多无聊的时光。此外，这是他自己的盔甲。他曾穿着这身盔甲在凯尼尔沃思擂台赛上大获成功，受到了童贞女王[6]本人的高度称赞。然而，他穿上去的时候，已经完全不堪巨大胸甲和钢盔的重负，沉重地倒在了石砌路面上，两只膝盖严重脱皮，还擦伤了右手指关节。

此后几天，他病得特别厉害，除了正常维护血迹之外，几乎足不出户。然而，通过悉心照料自己，他恢复了过来，并决心第三次尝试吓唬美国公使和他的家人。他选择了八月十七日星期五现身，那天大部分时间他都在仔细查看自己的衣柜，最终决定挑选一顶带有一根红色羽毛的大宽边软帽，一条在腕部和颈部饰有褶边的裹尸布，还有一把生锈的匕首。傍晚时分，一场猛烈的暴雨突然袭来，风很大，老房子的所有门窗都震得嘎嘎作响。实际上，这正是他喜爱的天气。他的行动计划是这样的：他要悄悄地走进华盛顿·奥蒂斯的房间，站在床脚对他胡言乱语，并伴着缓慢的音乐，在自己的喉咙上连刺三下。他对华盛顿怀有一种特别的怨恨，因为他完全清楚，正是这个人习惯使用平克顿出品的完美牌洗涤剂，除去远近闻名的坎特维尔的血迹。等这个鲁莽蛮干的年轻人进入一种绝望的恐惧状态之后，他就会进入美国公使夫妇占据的房间，到了那里把一只湿冷的手放在奥蒂斯夫人的额头上，同时冲她瑟瑟颤抖的丈夫的耳朵咝咝有声地说出尸骨存放所的可怕秘密。对于小弗吉尼娅，他还没有完全打定主意。她漂亮温柔，从来没有以任何方式侮辱过他。他认为，从衣柜里发出几声空洞的呻吟就够了，如果那样叫不醒她，他可能会用麻痹抽搐的手指朝着床罩摸索几下。至于双胞胎，他下定决心要教训他们一顿。当然，要做的第一件事就是坐在他们的胸上，以使他们产生噩梦般的窒息感。随后，因为他们的床彼此挨得相当近，所以他要以冰冷的绿色尸体的样子站在他们之间，直到把他们吓瘫。最后他要脱掉裹尸布，露出白森森的骨头和一只圆溜溜的眼珠在房间里爬来爬去，扮演“哑巴丹尼尔，即自杀者的骷髅”，凭借这个角色，他不止一次产生过极大影响，而且他认为，这完全可以跟他扮演的著名角色“疯子马丁，即蒙面神秘人”相媲美。

十点半，他听到这家人上床睡觉了。有一段时间，他受到了双胞胎尖声狂笑的打搅，显然，他们带着学童那样的轻松愉快，在休息之前正自得其乐，但到了十一点一刻，一切都静了下来，当午夜钟声响起的时候，他开始动身了。猫头鹰反复拍打着窗玻璃，乌鸦在老紫杉树上呱呱叫着，风呜咽着像丢了魂似的绕房徘徊；但是，奥蒂斯一家却正睡着，没有意识到自己的厄运。穿过降雨声和风暴声，他能听到美国公使持续不断的打鼾声高声传来。他偷偷地走出护墙板，布满皱纹的残忍的嘴角上浮起了邪恶的笑容。护墙上有一扇大凸肚窗，窗上装饰有他自己和他被害妻子的天蓝色和金色的纹章。当他偷偷地经过那里的时候，月亮把脸躲在了一朵云里。他像邪恶的影子似的不停地滑行，他经过的时候，黑暗也似乎对他深恶痛绝。有一次，他认为自己听到什么东西在叫喊，就停下了脚步，不过那只是从红色农场传来的狗叫声。于是，他继续向前走，喃喃自语着十六世纪的奇怪咒语，在午夜的空中不时地挥舞着生锈的匕首。最后，他到达了通向倒霉的华盛顿房间的通道拐角处。他在那里停顿了一会儿，头上的灰发被风吹拂着，古怪地打着卷儿，就像死人身上的裹尸布，有种无法形容的恐怖。接着，钟敲响了十二点一刻，他觉得时候到了，于是独自轻声笑了起来，转过了拐角。但是，刚转过那个拐角，他就发出了一声恐怖可怜的哀号，连连后退，把惨白的脸藏在了瘦长的双手里。只见在他面前正站着一个可怕的幽灵，犹如一尊雕像般一动不动，像疯子的梦一样骇人听闻！它的头光秃锃亮，它的脸圆胖惨白，狞笑似乎已经把它的五官扭曲定形，眼里冒出一道道深红色的光线，嘴巴张得像一口宽宽的火井，泰坦巨人般的身躯上裹着一件极其可怕的服装，就像他自己身上的这件一样，悄无声息地掉着雪片般的碎渣。它的胸部是一个标语牌，上面是用古老的字符写成的奇怪文字，看上去像是某种耻辱名册、野蛮犯罪记录、可怕的犯罪日程表。它的右手还高举着一把寒光闪闪的钢刀。

他以前从来没有见过幽灵，自然怕得要死，匆匆地瞥了一眼那个可怕的幽灵之后，便往自己的房间逃。他顺着走廊飞奔的时候，还绊倒在了长长的裹尸布上，并把那把生锈的匕首掉在了公使的长筒靴里。第二天早晨，男管家在那里发现了那把匕首。一回到自己的密室，他就扑倒在一张简陋的小床上，把脸隐藏在衣服下面。但是，过了一段时间，老坎特维尔的勇敢精神占了上风，于是他决定天一亮就去找另一个幽灵聊聊。因此，正当曙光给层层山峦染上一道道银色的时候，他赶回了他第一次看到那个可怕的幽灵的地方，他心里想，两个幽灵毕竟比一个好，而且，凭借新朋友的帮助，说不定还能稳妥地跟双胞胎搏斗。然而，到达现场后，他看到了一个可怕的景象。那个幽灵显然出了什么状况，因为光已经完全从它空洞的眼里消逝了，寒光闪闪的弯刀从它的手里掉落下来，它正以一种紧张不适的姿态靠在墙上。他冲上前，一把将它抱在怀里，这时让他恐惧的是，幽灵的脑袋滑下，滚落在地板上，身体呈斜倚的姿势。他发现自己紧抱着一条白色凸花条纹的布床帏，一把扫帚、一把厨房切肉刀和一只空心萝卜躺在他的脚边！他无法理解这种奇怪的转变，就心急火燎地抓紧标语牌，在灰色的晨光中读到了这些可怕的话：

奥蒂斯幽灵

唯一正宗真鬼
如有雷同
实属仿效

整个事情闪过他的脑海。他上当受骗，被涮了一把！他的眼里又闪现出过去那个坎特维尔的神情；他把失去牙齿的牙床咬在一起，干瘪的双手高举过头顶，以旧时学院派的独特措辞发誓说，雄鸡两次鸣唱，血腥之事酝酿，杀戮悄然蔓延。

他刚说完这个可怕的誓言，一只公鸡就在遥远宅地的红瓦屋顶上啼鸣起来。他发出了一阵悠长低沉的苦笑，等待着。他等了一个小时又一个小时，但由于某种莫名其妙的原因，公鸡没再啼鸣。最后，到了七点半钟，女佣们的到来使他放弃了可怕的守夜，他大步回到自己的房间，想着自己徒劳的誓言和夭折的计划。在那里，他查阅了自己特别喜欢的几本古典骑士传奇后发现，主人公每一次发出誓言，公鸡总是啼鸣两遍。“让那只不听话的公鸡毁灭，”他喃喃地说，“我总有一天要用结实的长矛刺穿它的喉咙，让它为我啼鸣，就是死也要啼鸣！”说完，他就退入了一具舒适的铅棺里，在那里一直待到了晚上。

第四章

第二天，幽灵有气无力、疲惫不堪。过去四个星期的可怕刺激开始有了效果。他的神经被彻底弄垮了，最轻微的声音都会让他猛地一惊。他在房间里待了五天，最后打定主意不再关注书房地板上的血迹。如果奥蒂斯的家人不想要它，那他们显然就不应该得到它。显而易见，他们是在低级物质层面存在的人，完全欣赏不了审美现象的象征性价值。显灵的问题和魂灵的演变当然完全是另一回事，真的不在他的控制之下。每星期出现在走廊里一次，每月的第一个和第三个星期三在大凸肚窗边喋喋不休，这些都是他庄严的责任，他不明白怎么才能体面地从自己的义务中逃脱。他的生活十分邪恶，这千真万确，但另一方面，他对与超自然现象相关的所有东西都尽心尽责。因此，接下来的三个星期六，他还是像往常一样，在午夜到凌晨三点之间穿过走廊，采取各种可能的预防措施，以免让人听到或看到。他脱下靴子，尽可能轻地踩在虫蛀的地板上，穿上宽大的黑天鹅绒外衣，认真使用旭日牌润滑剂给他的锁链上油。我必须承认，他的确用了九牛二虎之力才让自己采取了这最后的保护模式。虽然勉强，但一天夜里，当那家人在吃饭的时候，他还是溜进了奥蒂斯先生的卧室，拿走了那只瓶子。他起先感到有点儿羞愧，但后来足够明智地看到，这个发明可以说有极大的好处，而且在一定程度上，对他的计划有所帮助。然而，尽管他做了这所有一切，但依然不是毫无困扰。他顺着走廊走时得一直拉着链子，在黑暗中常常被绊倒；有一次，双胞胎兄弟给挂毯房间的入口到橡木楼梯的顶部之间的地板涂了一层黄油，他打扮成“黑以撒，即霍格莱林地猎手”，踩在了上面，重重地摔了一跤。这最后的侮辱就这样激怒了他，他决定做最后一次努力，以维护自己的尊严和社会地位，打算第二天夜里扮成大名鼎鼎的“鲁莽的鲁珀特，即无头伯爵”，去探望那两个粗野无礼的伊顿学童。

他已经七十多年没有以这种装扮现身了，尽管他曾经借此吓唬过漂亮的芭芭拉·莫迪什夫人。当时芭芭拉突然跟现在的坎特维尔勋爵的祖父解除了婚约，跟英俊的杰克·格雷卡斯尔顿私奔去了格雷特纳格林镇，宣称这世界上任何东西都诱使不了她嫁入这个家庭，因为这个家庭居然允许一个如此可怕的幽灵黄昏时分沿着平台走来走去。后事，可怜的杰克在旺兹沃思[7]公有地的一次决斗中被坎特维尔勋爵枪杀。那一年还没有过完，芭芭拉夫人就因心碎而死在了坦布里奇韦尔斯市，因此可以说，他在各个方面都取得了巨大的成功。然而，这是一次难度极高的“装扮”，如果我可以用“装扮”这样一个剧场用语来表达与超自然——采用更科学的术语，是高级的自然世界——最大谜团之一相关的现象的话，这整整花费了他三个小时的时间进行准备。最后，一切就绪，他对自己的外表格外满意。跟衣服搭配的大皮马靴对他来说只是有点儿大，两把马上用的手枪他只能找到一把，但总的来说他十分满意。一点一刻，他滑出了护墙板，沿着走廊悄悄前行。他走到双胞胎占据的房间——我应该提一下，这个房间因悬挂的帷幔的颜色而被称为蓝卧室——发现房门只是半掩着。他想做出一些惊悚的效果，就猛地一把推开房门，这时一罐沉甸甸的水正好泼在他的身上，令他浑身上下湿了个透，而且罐子差两英寸就砸中了他的左肩。与此同时，他听到从四柱床那里传来的压抑的尖笑声。这对他的神经系统冲击如此巨大，他尽了最大努力逃回自己的房间，第二天因重感冒而卧病在床。整个事件中唯一安慰他的就是他没有带去自己的脑袋，因为如果他这样做，后果可能会非常严重。

他现在放弃了吓唬这个粗鲁的美国家庭的所有希望，通常只满足于自己穿着拖鞋在走廊里悄悄地来回走动，脖子上围着厚厚的红围巾，生怕有穿堂风，还带着一支小小的火绳枪，以防受到双胞胎兄弟的攻击。他受到的最后一击，发生在九月十九日。他下楼去宽大的门厅，感觉至少在那里完全不会受到骚扰，并借对美国公使夫妇在萨罗尼摄制的巨幅照片的冷嘲热讽自娱自乐，这些照片现在已经取代了坎特维尔家族的肖像画。他穿着虽朴素却整洁的长寿衣，上面带着墓地的霉斑，用黄麻布条绑住下巴，一只手提着一盏小灯笼，另一只手拎着一把教堂司事的铁锹。实际上，他扮的是“无墓乔纳斯，即彻特西谷仓夺尸鬼”这个角色，这是他最出色的扮相之一，也是坎特维尔家族有充分理由记住的扮相之一，因为这是他们跟邻居拉福德勋爵争吵的真正由来。当时是深夜两点一刻左右，而且，就他所能查明的情况来看，没有人在走动。然而，当他朝书房信步走去，看看有没有留下什么血迹的时候，突然从黑暗的角落里跳出两个身影扑向了他，只见那两个身影在头顶疯狂地挥舞着他们的胳膊，冲他的耳朵“噗！”地尖叫着。

在这种情况下，惊慌失措是最自然不过的事儿，他冲向楼梯，却发现华盛顿·奥蒂斯正拿着花园大洒水器在那里等着他。如此一来，他被敌人四面包围，几乎走投无路，只好钻进了大铁炉子。对他来说，幸运的是炉子没有生火，他只好从烟道和烟囱爬行回家，以一种肮脏、混乱和绝望的可怕状态到达了自己的房间。

之后，再也没有见到他进行任何夜间探险。双胞胎埋伏着等待了他好几次，让他们的父母和仆人大为烦恼的是，每天夜里他们用坚果壳撒满了那些走廊，但依然无济于事。显而易见，他的感情受到了如此的伤害，再也不愿现身了。因此，奥蒂斯先生重又写起了他那本有关民主党历史的伟大著作，这本书他已经专心致志地写了几年时间；奥蒂斯太太举办了一次精彩的蛤蜊烘烤宴，这让全郡人都叹为观止；男孩们开始打曲棍球，玩尤克牌[8]和扑克，以及其他美国游戏；在柴郡的年轻公爵的陪同下，弗吉尼娅骑着小马在路上四处走动，这位公爵是来坎特维尔猎场度过自己假期的最后一个星期的。人们普遍认为，幽灵已经走了。而且，实际上，奥蒂斯先生给坎特维尔勋爵写了一封信，告诉了他这件事情。坎特维尔勋爵回信表示，听到这个消息他非常高兴，并向公使可敬的妻子送去了最美好的祝贺。

然而，奥蒂斯一家受到了蒙骗，因为幽灵还在房子里，尽管现在几乎成了残废，但他绝不愿善罢甘休，尤其是听说客人们当中有柴郡的年轻公爵的时候。那位公爵的伯祖父弗朗西斯·斯蒂尔顿勋爵曾经跟卡伯里上校赌了一百几尼，说他要跟坎特维尔的幽灵玩骰子。第二天早上，人们发现斯蒂尔顿勋爵处在一种十分无助的瘫痪状态，躺在牌室的地板上，尽管他一直活到了高寿，但他再也说不出“双六”之外的任何事情了。当然，尽管出于对两个贵族家庭感情的尊重，大家想方设法隐瞒这件事，但这个故事当时还是家喻户晓，后来人们发现坦特尔勋爵的《回忆摄政王及其朋友们》第三卷中也有与这件事有关的所有情况的详尽叙述。那么，幽灵自然迫不及待地想要证明他没有失去对斯蒂尔顿一家的影响力。其实，他跟斯蒂尔顿一家是远亲，因为自己的堂妹再婚嫁给了德·巴尔克利先生，每个人都知道，柴郡的公爵们是巴尔克利先生的直系后裔。因此，他安排停当，打算以“吸血幽灵修士，即没有血色的本笃会[9]修士”的著名扮相出现在弗吉尼娅的小情人面前。这个表演可怕极了，一七六四年那个致命的除夕，斯塔尔普老太太看到这一情景，突然发出了最刺耳的尖叫声。这次尖叫以严重的中风而告终。不到三天，她就撒手而去了。临终前，她剥夺了自己最近的亲属坎特维尔一家的继承权，把她所有的钱都留给了她的伦敦药剂师。然而，在最后时刻，对双胞胎兄弟的恐惧使他没敢离开自己的房间。公爵安睡在皇家寝宫硕大的羽毛华盖下面，还梦到了弗吉尼娅。

第五章

之后过了几天，弗吉尼娅和她的鬈发骑士出门，前往布洛克雷牧场骑马。到了那里，在穿过一道树篱的时候，她挂坏了骑装，所以他们回家后，她打定主意从后楼梯上去，以免被人看见。她跑过挂毯屋的时候，门正好开着，她看见里面好像有人，认为那是她母亲的侍女，侍女有时会把活计带到那里做，所以她就朝里面看了看，想请侍女给她修补一下骑装。然而，让她无比惊讶的是，那居然是坎特维尔的幽灵！只见他正坐在窗边，望着金黄色的落叶飘过空中，红叶沿着长长的林荫道狂舞。他的头倚在一只手上，整个姿态看上去极度消沉。实际上，小弗吉尼娅看到他的第一个想法就是逃走，然后把自己锁在房间里，但她又感到了怜悯，决心去设法安慰他。她的脚步是那么轻，他的忧郁是那么深，直到她对他说话，他才意识到她的存在。

“真是抱歉，”她说，“但我的两个弟弟明天将返回伊顿公学，之后，如果你行为规矩的话，就没有人会打扰你。”

“要求我行为规矩，真是荒唐，”他一边回答，一边惊讶地回头望着这个斗胆跟他说话的漂亮小女孩，“真是可笑极了。我必须把锁链晃得叮当乱响，透过锁孔发出呻吟，夜里走来走去，你指的是这些吗？这是我存在的唯一理由。”

“这根本不是存在的理由，你知道你一向邪恶透顶。我们来到这里的第一天，乌姆妮太太告诉我们说，你杀了自己的妻子。”

“好吧，我完全承认这一点，”幽灵气急败坏地说，“但那纯粹是一个家庭问题，跟别人无关。”

“杀死任何一个人，都是非常错误的。”弗吉尼娅说，她不时地表现出一种可爱的清教徒般的严肃神情，这种严肃源自某个古老的新英格兰祖先。

“噢，我讨厌抽象道德的假正经！我的妻子相貌平平，从来没有浆好过我的衣领，而且对烹饪一无所知。哎呀，有一次我在霍格莱树林打死了一只公鹿，那是一只非常壮硕的两岁公鹿，你知道她是怎么把它送上餐桌的吗？不管怎样，现在都无关紧要了，因为一切都过去了，尽管的确是我杀了她，但我认为，她的兄弟们把我饿死也不是很地道。”

“把你饿死？噢，幽灵先生，我是说西蒙先生，你饿了吗？我的盒子里有一块三明治。你喜欢吃吗？”

“不，谢谢你，我现在从来不吃任何东西。不过，你还是有情有义，比你那些可怕、粗鲁、庸俗而又不诚实的家人好多了。”

“住口！”弗吉尼娅跺着脚嚷道，“可怕、粗鲁、庸俗的是你，至于不诚实，你自己清楚，你从我的盒子里偷走了我的颜料，试图保持书房里那块荒唐可笑的血迹。首先，你拿走了我所有的红色，包括朱红色，结果任何落日我都画不成了，接着你拿走了翠绿色和铬黄色，最后我只剩下了靛蓝和中国白，只能画月光下的场景，可那景象总是令人沮丧，也根本不容易画。尽管我气得不行，但我从来没有告发过你，整个事情真是荒唐极了，谁曾经听说过翠绿色的血液呢？”

“噢，真的吗？”幽灵颇为温顺地说，“我该怎么办？如今很难搞到真正的血了，况且，你的兄弟一开始就用完美牌洗涤剂挑起事端，我当然看不出有什么理由不拿你的颜料。至于颜色，这始终是一个品位的问题。比如，坎特维尔家族具有贵族血统——英国最高贵的血统；可是，我知道你们美国人不关心这样的事儿。”

“你对此一无所知，而你能做得最好的事儿就是移居国外，长长见识。我的父亲会十分乐意给你自由通行权，尽管那里各种烈酒都有重税，但海关方面不会有任何困难，因为那些官员都是民主党人。一旦到了纽约，你就一定能大获成功。我知道，那里好多人愿意出十万美元获得一个爷爷，而对于一个家族幽灵出价会高得多。”

“我认为我不会喜欢美国。”

“我想是因为我们没有废墟，也没有古玩。”弗吉尼娅讥讽地说。

“不要废墟！不要古玩！”幽灵回答说，“还有你们的海军和美式礼仪。”

“再见，我要去请求爸爸再给这对双胞胎一个星期假。”

“请不要走，弗吉尼娅小姐，”他喊道，“我很孤独，也很不开心，我真不知道该怎么办。我想去睡觉，却又睡不着。”

“这相当荒唐！你只需上床，吹灭蜡烛就行了。有时保持清醒很难，尤其是在教堂，但睡觉根本不难。哎呀，就是婴儿也知道该怎么做，而他们并不是很聪明。”

“我已经三百年没有睡过觉了，”他伤心地说，弗吉尼娅美丽的蓝眼睛惊奇地睁大，“三百年来我都没有睡过觉了，我好累呀。”

弗吉尼娅变得相当严肃，小小的嘴唇像玫瑰花叶一样颤抖。她向他走来，在他的身边跪下来，抬起头，望着他苍老干瘪的脸庞。

“可怜巴巴的幽灵，”她喃喃地说，“你没有可以睡觉的地方吗？”

“在很远的松林那边，”他用梦幻般的声音低沉地答道，“有一座小花园。那里的草长得又高又深，那里有又大又白的星形的铁杉花，那里的夜莺彻夜鸣唱。它彻夜鸣唱，水晶般的寒月俯瞰下方，紫杉树展开巨大的手臂撑在沉睡者的上方。”

弗吉尼娅渐渐地泪眼模糊，把脸藏在了自己的双手里。

“你是说死亡花园吧。”她低声说道。

“是的，是死亡。死亡一定非常美丽。躺在柔软的褐色泥土里，青草在头顶晃动，倾听寂静的声音。没有昨天，也没有明天。要忘却时间，要原谅生活，要安宁。你可以帮助我。你可以为我打开死亡之屋的门，因为爱跟你永在，爱比死亡更强大。”

弗吉尼娅一哆嗦，浑身打了个冷战，有片刻的沉默。她觉得自己仿佛是在一个可怕的梦里。

这时，幽灵又说起了话，他的声音听上去就像是风的叹息。

“你读过书房窗户上的那段古老预言吗？”

“噢，经常读，”小女孩抬起头大声说道，“我一清二楚。那是用古怪的黑色字母涂写的，读起来很难。只有六行：

当可人的女孩能从罪恶之口，
赢得一次次祈祷，
当荒芜的巴旦木有果实结出，
小孩子流下一颗颗泪珠，
这时整个房子一片静悄悄，
坎特维尔的安宁就会来到。

但我不知道这是什么意思。”

“这些话是说，”他伤心地说，“你必须跟我一起为我的罪恶哭泣，因为我没有眼泪；跟我一起为我的灵魂祈祷，因为我没有信仰；接下来，如果你始终甜美、善良和温柔，死亡天使就会怜悯我。你会在黑暗中看到形形色色可怕的身影，各种各样邪恶的声音会在你的耳边低语，但它们伤害不了你，因为地狱的力量对小孩子的纯真发挥不了作用。”

弗吉尼娅没有回答，幽灵一边俯视着她低垂的金发脑袋，一边十分绝望地绞着双手。突然，她站起来，脸色煞白，眼里有一种异样的光芒。“我不害怕，”她坚定地说，“我会请天使怜悯你的。”

他发出了一声轻微的欢呼，从座位上站起身，拉住她的手，以古老优雅的方式弯下腰，吻了吻。他的手指像冰一样冷，嘴唇像火一样烫。但当他领着弗吉尼娅穿过昏暗的房间的时候，她没有动摇。淡绿色的挂毯上绣着一些小猎人。这些小猎人吹着流苏号角，挥动着小手让她回去。“回去！小弗吉尼娅，”他们喊道，“回去吧！”然而，幽灵把她的手抓得更紧了。于是，她闭上了眼睛，不再看那些小猎手。一些带有蜥蜴尾巴的可怕动物从雕刻的壁炉架上对她眨着金鱼眼睛，喃喃地说：“当心！小弗吉尼娅，当心！我们可能再也见不到你了。”但是，幽灵向前滑行得更快了，弗吉尼娅听而不闻。当他们走到房间尽头的时候，他停下来，喃喃地说了一些她听不懂的话。她睁开眼睛，看到墙像雾一样慢慢地消失，一个巨大的黑色洞穴出现在她面前。一阵刺骨的寒风从他们身边扫过，她感觉有什么东西拽着她的衣服。“快，快，”幽灵喊道，“否则就来不及了。”护墙板立刻就在他们身后合拢了，挂毯屋空空如也。

第六章

大约十分钟后，下午茶的铃声响了，弗吉尼娅没有下来，奥蒂斯太太就派一个男仆上去告诉她。过了一小会儿，男仆回来说，哪里都找不到弗吉尼娅小姐。她每天晚上都习惯到花园里为餐桌采花，奥蒂斯太太起初毫不惊慌，但当六点的钟声敲响，弗吉尼娅还是没有出现的时候，她才真正焦虑不安起来，打发男孩子们出去寻找，她自己和奥蒂斯先生则搜寻了家里的每个房间。到了六点半钟，男孩子们回来说，他们哪里都没有发现妹妹的踪影。他们现在都处在最紧张的状态，不知道该怎么办，这时奥蒂斯先生突然想起，几天前他曾经允许一伙吉卜赛人在公园里扎营。于是，他立刻动身前往布莱克菲尔洼地，他知道他们在那里，他的大儿子和两个农场仆人也陪同前往。柴郡的年轻公爵急得完全像发了疯似的，苦苦哀求允许他也一起去，但奥蒂斯先生不准他去，因为他担心会有一场混战。然而，到达现场后，他发现吉卜赛人已经走了，而且显而易见，他们的离开有些突然，因为火还在燃烧，一些盘子躺在草地上。打发华盛顿和两个男仆彻底搜索了这个地区之后，他跑回家，给郡里的所有警督发了电报，让他们留心一个被流浪汉或吉卜赛人绑架的小女孩。然后，他吩咐人牵来他的马，坚决要求他的妻子和三个男孩子坐下来吃完饭后，就带着一个马夫沿着阿斯科特路策马飞奔。然而，他刚跑了两英里，就听到在他后面有人骑马追来。他回过头，看到是年轻的公爵骑着小马追来，只见他满脸通红，没戴帽子。“非常抱歉，奥蒂斯先生，”男孩子气喘吁吁地说，“但只要弗吉尼娅还没有找到，我就吃不下饭。请不要生我的气。如果去年你让我们订婚的话，就绝不会有这一切麻烦了。你不要送我回去，好吗？我不能走！我不愿回去！”

公使禁不住对这个年轻英俊的纨绔少年露出了微笑，并为他对弗吉尼娅的一心一意而深受感动。于是他从马上俯下身来，亲切地拍了拍他的肩膀，说：“好吧，塞西尔，如果你不愿回去，我想你就必须跟我走，但到了阿斯科特，我必须给你买一顶帽子。”

“噢，不要操心我的帽子了！我想要弗吉尼娅！”年轻的公爵笑着嚷道。于是，他们向火车站疾驰而去。到了那里，奥蒂斯先生询问站长，有没有在月台上见过跟弗吉尼娅的相貌特征符合的人，但没能得到她的任何消息。不过，站长给沿线车站去了电报，并向他保证，他们会密切注意她。奥蒂斯先生从一个正要打烊的亚麻布料商那里为公爵买了一顶帽子后，骑马赶往大约四英里远的贝克斯利村，有人告诉他说，这是一个远近闻名的吉卜赛人经常聚会的地方，因为旁边有一大块公有地。在这里，他们叫醒了村里的一个警察，但从他那里没能得到任何信息，接着，骑马找遍了那块公有地之后，他们掉转马头回家，十一点左右到达了猎场，筋疲力尽，几乎伤心欲绝。林荫道黑黢黢的，他们发现华盛顿和双胞胎兄弟提着灯笼在门房口等着他们，没有发现弗吉尼娅的一丝痕迹。尽管人们在布洛克雷牧场抓住了那些吉卜赛人，但她没有跟他们在一起。他们解释说，他们之所以突然离开，是因为他们搞错了乔顿集市的日期，于是匆匆离开，唯恐迟到。实际上，听到弗吉尼娅失踪的消息，他们都万分痛苦，非常感激奥蒂斯先生允许他们在公园里扎营，于是留下了其中四个人来帮助寻找。鲤鱼塘已经被打捞了一遍，整个猎场都彻底搜过了一遍，但没有任何结果。显而易见，那天夜里他们无论如何也找不到弗吉尼娅了。奥蒂斯先生和孩子们走向房子，沮丧到了极点，马夫牵着两匹马和那匹小马跟在后面。到了大厅，他们看到了一群惊慌失措的仆人，躺在书房沙发上的是可怜的奥蒂斯太太，她因恐惧和焦虑而几乎失去了理智，老管家往她的额头上抹了些科隆香水。奥蒂斯先生马上督促她吃些东西，并吩咐给全体人员上晚饭。这顿晚饭吃得闷闷不乐，因为几乎没有任何人说话，就连双胞胎兄弟也诚惶诚恐、服服帖帖，因为他们非常喜欢自己的姐姐。他们吃完饭后，奥蒂斯先生不顾年轻公爵的苦苦哀求，命令他们都统统睡觉，说那天夜里什么也做不了了，他第二天早上会给苏格兰场发电报，让他们马上派一些侦探来。就在他们走出餐厅的时候，钟楼传来了午夜的钟声，而当最后一声响过之后，他们听到了碰撞声和一声凄厉的尖叫；一阵可怕的炸雷声震撼了整个房子，一串奇异神秘的音乐旋律飘过了空中，楼梯顶部的面板随着一声巨响飞落，只见弗吉尼娅脸色惨白，一只手拿着一个小盒子，走到了外面的楼梯平台上。他们都立刻冲到了她身边。奥蒂斯太太热情地把她紧抱在怀里，公爵的吻让她几乎透不过气来，双胞胎绕着他们跳起了疯狂的战舞。

“天哪！孩子，你到哪里去了？”奥蒂斯先生有些生气地说，以为她一直在跟他们玩某个愚蠢的把戏，“我和塞西尔骑着马一直在到处找你，你的母亲吓得要死。你千万不要再搞这些恶作剧了。”

“只对幽灵搞！只对幽灵搞！”双胞胎雀跃着，尖叫着。

“我的心肝宝贝，感谢上帝，总算找到你了，你千万不要再离开我的身边了。”奥蒂斯太太一边喃喃地说，一边吻着浑身颤抖的孩子，捋了捋她乱蓬蓬的金发。

“爸爸，”弗吉尼娅平静地说，“我刚才跟幽灵在一起。他死了，你一定要来看看他。他曾经十分邪恶，但他也为自己所做的一切感到抱歉。去世前，他把这盒美丽的珠宝送给了我。”

全家人默然无声，惊讶地凝视着她，但她非常严肃和认真。她转过身，带领他们沿着一条狭窄的秘密走廊穿过护墙板的缺口，华盛顿从桌子上抓起一支点燃的蜡烛跟在后面。最后，他们来到了一个高大的橡木门边，门上钉着生锈的钉子。弗吉尼娅碰了一下门，门就绕着沉重的门枢转了过去，一下子打开了，他们发现自己到了一个低矮的房间，房间带有拱形天花板和一个小小的格子窗。嵌在墙里的是一个巨大的铁环，拴在铁环上的是一具枯瘦的骷髅，骷髅在石头地面上全身伸展开来，似乎是想尽力用没有血肉的瘦长手指去抓住一套老式的木盘和水罐，木盘和水罐正好放在他够不到的地方。水罐显然曾经装满了水，因为里面覆盖了一层绿霉。木盘上只有一堆灰尘。弗吉尼娅在骷髅旁边跪下来，小手合在一起，开始默默祈祷。其他人惊奇地看着这可怕的场景，此刻秘密终于在他们面前揭晓了。

“喂！”双胞胎中的一个突然大叫，他一直望着窗外，想设法发现这个房间位于房子的哪一侧。“喂！那棵枯萎的老杏树已经开花了。我在月光下能清清楚楚地看到那些花。”

“上帝已经原谅了他。”弗吉尼娅严肃地说着，站起身来，一道美丽的光芒似乎照亮了她的脸庞。

“你是多么美丽的天使啊！”年轻的公爵叫道，然后伸出一条胳膊搂住了她的脖子，亲吻了她。

第七章

这些离奇的事件发生后又过了四天，夜里十一点左右，一场葬礼在坎特维尔猎场举行。灵车由八匹黑马拉着，每匹马的头上都戴着一大绺低垂的鸵鸟羽毛，铅棺覆盖着浓紫色棺罩，棺罩上面用金线绣着坎特维尔家族的纹章。手持火把的仆人们走在灵车和马车的侧面，整个队伍引人瞩目。坎特维尔勋爵是丧主，特地从威尔士赶来参加葬礼，跟小弗吉尼娅坐在第一辆马车里。随后是美国公使夫妇，接着是华盛顿和三个男孩子，最后一辆马车里是乌姆妮夫人。人们普遍感到，她在一生中曾经被幽灵惊吓了五十多年，有权利看到他最后的结局。教堂墓地的一角已经挖了一个深深的墓穴，就在老紫杉树下面，奥古斯塔斯·丹皮尔牧师以最感人的方式宣读了祭文。仪式结束后，按照坎特维尔家族遵守的古老习俗，仆人们熄灭了火把，在棺材被下到坟墓的时候，弗吉尼娅走上前，把一个由白色和粉红色杏花做成的大十字架放在上面。在她这样做的时候，月亮从一朵云后面钻了出来，默默地把银光洒到了小小的教堂墓地，一只夜莺在远处的一个小灌木林里开始鸣唱。她想起了幽灵对死亡花园的描述，顿时泪眼模糊，坐车回家期间几乎一言不发。

第二天早上，在坎特维尔勋爵上城里之前，奥蒂斯先生跟他会面讨论幽灵送给弗吉尼娅珠宝的问题。这些珠宝完美瑰丽，尤其是一条嵌有古威尼斯背景的红宝石项链，这的确是十六世纪精湛工艺的标本，其价值如此巨大，所以对是否允许女儿接受，奥蒂斯先生顾虑重重。

“亲爱的勋爵，”他说，“我知道，在这个国家，永久管业规定既适用于土地，也适用于饰品。我心知肚明，这些珠宝是，或者说应该是你们的传家宝。因此，我必须请求你随身把它们带到伦敦，仅仅把它们看成是在某种奇怪条件下归还给你的一部分财产。至于我的女儿，她还只是个孩子，我很高兴地说，到现在为止，她对这种奢侈品没有多大兴趣。奥蒂斯太太还告诉我说——她少女时代有幸在波士顿待过好几个冬天，可以说是响当当的艺术行家——这些宝石非常值钱，如果拿去卖的话，一定会卖个高价。坎特维尔勋爵，在这种情况下，我确信你会认识到，对我来说，允许它们留在我的家人手里将是多么难以忍受。而且，实际上，所有这些华而不实的玩物，对英国贵族的体面而言，是多么的适宜和必要，但对那些在严格的——而且我相信是不朽的——共和党的朴素原则下成长的人，却完全格格不入。也许我应该提到，弗吉尼娅非常希望你能允许她保留那个盒子，作为对你那位命运多舛并又误入歧途的祖先的一种纪念。因为盒子特别旧，大概也修不好，所以也许你会认为可以答应她的要求。就我个人而言，我承认，对我的一个孩子居然会带着中世纪精神来展现她的同情心，我感到十分意外。这只能以一个事实做出解释，那就是奥蒂斯太太雅典之行回来后不久，弗吉尼娅出生在了你们伦敦的一个郊区。”

坎特维尔勋爵神情非常严肃地听着可敬的公使讲话，不时地捋捋灰色胡子，掩饰着不由自主的微笑。奥蒂斯先生说完之后，坎特维尔勋爵亲切地握了握他的手，说道：“我亲爱的先生，你的迷人而可爱的小女儿给了我那位倒霉的祖先——西蒙爵士——一个至关重要的帮助，我和我的家人都十分感激她惊人的勇气和胆量。现在珠宝显然是她的，而且，天哪，我相信，如果我足够狠心把它们从她那里拿走的话，那个邪恶的老家伙不出两个星期就会从坟墓里爬出来，让我去过一种魔鬼般的生活。至于他们现有的传家宝，遗嘱或法律文件没有提及的东西不算是传家宝，我们完全不知道这些珠宝的存在。我向你保证，我并不比你的男管家有更多的索要的权力，而当弗吉尼娅小姐长大成人的时候，我敢说她一定会乐意有漂亮的东西穿戴。况且，奥蒂斯先生，你忘了，你对家具和幽灵都估了价，属于幽灵的任何东西随即都归你所有，因此无论西蒙爵士夜里在走廊搞些什么活动，就法律而言，他的确死了，你通过购买获得了他的财产。”

奥蒂斯先生对坎特维尔勋爵的拒绝万分痛苦，恳求他再考虑一下他的决定，但这个心地善良的贵族义无反顾，最终说服了公使，允许他的女儿保留幽灵送给她的礼物。于是，一八九〇年春天，当年轻的柴郡公爵夫人结婚那天，在女王的第一次觐见名媛会上亮相时，她的珠宝得到了大家的一致赞美。因为弗吉尼娅收到了宝冠，这是所有美国好少女都梦想的奖赏，并在自己的情郎一到法定年龄就嫁给了他。他们俩是那么迷人、相亲相爱，每个人都为这桩婚配感到高兴，除了邓布尔顿的老侯爵夫人，她曾经设法抓住公爵，要配给她七个未婚女儿中的一个，并为此举办过不少于三次的昂贵晚宴。还有，说来也怪，就是奥蒂斯先生本人。奥蒂斯先生特别喜欢年轻的公爵本人，但从理论上说，他反对贵族头衔，而且用他自己的话说：“就是不免忧惧，在贵族寻欢作乐、令人萎靡的影响中，共和党朴素精神的真正原则会被忘到脑后。”然而，他的反对意见被完全驳回，我相信，当他让女儿挽着他的胳膊走上汉诺威广场圣乔治教堂过道的时候，整个英格兰再也没有比他更自豪的男人了。

蜜月结束后，公爵夫妇去了坎特维尔猎场，并在抵达后的第二天下午走到了松林边的那个孤独的墓园。起初，他们曾经为西蒙爵士的墓碑碑文绞尽脑汁，但最后决定只简单地刻上老先生姓名的首字母和书房窗户上的那段诗文。公爵夫人随身带来了一些可爱的玫瑰花撒在坟墓上。他们在坟墓边站了一段时间后，漫步走进了老修道院废弃的圣坛。到了那里，公爵夫人在一根倒下的柱子上坐下来，而她的丈夫则躺在她的脚边一边抽烟，一边抬头望着她美丽的大眼睛。突然，他扔掉香烟，握住她的手，对她说道：“弗吉尼娅，妻子不应该对丈夫有任何秘密。”

“亲爱的塞西尔！我对你没有什么秘密啊。”

“有，你有，”他微笑着答道，“你从来没有告诉过我，你跟那个幽灵关在一起的时候发生了什么事情呢。”

“塞西尔，我还从来没有告诉过任何一个人。”弗吉尼娅神情严肃地说。

“这我知道，但你可以告诉我吧。”

“塞西尔，请不要问我，我不能告诉你。可怜的西蒙爵士！我非常感激他。是的，不要笑，塞西尔，我真的非常感激他。他使我明白了人生是什么，死亡意味着什么，为什么爱比这二者都强大。”

公爵站起来，含情脉脉地吻了吻妻子。

“只要我拥有你的心，你就可以拥有自己的秘密。”他喁喁细语。

“你始终都拥有那颗心，塞西尔。”

“而且有朝一日你会告诉我们的孩子们，不是吗？”

弗吉尼娅顿时脸色羞红。

[1]亚马孙女战士，古希腊神话中一个全部由女战士构成的民族，占据着小亚细亚、佛里及亚、色雷斯和叙利亚的许多地方。

[2]阿基里斯，也译为阿喀琉斯，荷马史诗《伊利亚特》中参加特洛伊战争的一个半神英雄，希腊联军第一勇士。

[3]都铎风格，室内爱用深色木材做护墙板，板上做浅浮雕。顶棚则用浅色抹灰，做曲线和直线结合的格子，格心中央垂一个钟乳状装饰。一些重要大厅用华丽锤式屋架。这是一种富有装饰性的木屋架，由两侧向中央逐级挑出，逐级升高，每级下面有一个弧形撑托和一个雕镂精致的下垂装饰物。这是中世纪向文艺复兴的过渡时期的建筑风格，得名“都铎风格”，因为当时正是英国都铎王朝（1485—1603）。

[4]伏尔泰（1694—1778），本名弗朗索瓦-马利·阿鲁埃，法国启蒙时期的思想家、文学家、哲学家。伏尔泰是十八世纪法国资产阶级启蒙运动的领袖和导师，被誉为“法兰西思想之王”“法兰西最优秀的诗人”和“欧洲的良心”。代表作有《哲学通信》《路易十四时代》《老实人》等。

[5]九柱戏，现在称“地滚球”，也称“保龄球”，起源于德国，是一种在木板球道上用球滚击木瓶的室内体育运动，流行于欧美、大洋洲和亚洲一些国家。

[6]童贞女王，伊丽莎白一世（1533—1603），于一五五八年十一月十七日至一六〇三年三月二十四日任英格兰和爱尔兰女王，是都铎王朝的第五位也是最后一位君主。她终身未嫁，因此被称为“童贞女王”。

[7]旺兹沃思，英国英格兰大伦敦内伦敦的自治市。

[8]尤克牌，一种起源于德国的牌类游戏，也是十九世纪末美国最流行的家庭牌战游戏。纸牌有四种花色，每种花色八张，共三十二张。各花色牌按高低排列为：A、K、Q、J、10、9、8、7。其中，王牌花色的J为最大王牌，称右王牌；同一颜色另一种花色的J为次王牌，称左王牌。

[9]本笃会，天主教隐修会之一，五二九年由贵族出身的意大利人本笃所创。本笃会所订会规规定会士不可婚娶，不可有私财，一切服从长上，称此为“发三愿”。本笃会会士每日必须按时进经堂诵经，咏唱“大日课”，余暇时从事各种劳动。会规要求祈祷不忘工作，视游手好闲为罪恶。后来该会规成为天主教修会制度的范本。

W.H.先生的画像

第一章

有一次，我在鸟笼道厄斯金的漂亮小房子里跟他一起吃饭，后来我们坐进了书房，一边喝咖啡，一边抽烟，这时文学伪造的问题碰巧出现在了谈话当中。我现在记不起是怎么开的头了，那个时候我们突然就想起了这个有些奇怪的话题，但我知道我们就麦克弗森、爱尔兰和查特顿[1]谈论了很久。对于查特顿，我坚持认为他所谓的伪造仅仅是艺术渴望完美表现的产物；我们没有权利指责艺术家选择的展示其作品的那些方式；在某种程度上，所有艺术都是一种表演模式，是一种超越时势约束和现实生活局限，在某个想象层面实现自己个性的尝试，指责艺术家伪造就是混淆道德问题和美学问题。

厄斯金比我年龄大得多，带着四十岁男人有趣的顺从姿态一直在听我说话。他突然把一只手搭在我的肩上，对我说道：“如果一个年轻人对某件艺术品有一种奇怪的理论，他相信自己的理论，并为了证明这个理论而进行伪造，你怎么看？”

“啊！那完全是另一回事。”我回答说。

厄斯金望着香烟袅袅升起的一缕缕灰蒙蒙的细线，沉默了一会儿。“是的，”停顿过后，他说，“完全是另一回事。”

他的语气中有一种什么东西，似乎是一丝轻微的痛苦，这激起了我的好奇心。“你知道那个作假的人？”我嚷道。

“知道，”他一边回答，一边把香烟扔进火里——“是我的一位好友西里尔·格雷厄姆。他既非常迷人，又非常愚蠢，没心没肺。不过，我有生以来得到的唯一一份遗产就是他留给我的。”

“那是什么？”我惊叹道。厄斯金从座位上站起身来，走到立在两个窗户之间的一个高大的嵌花橱柜前，打开柜锁，然后回到我坐的地方，只见他手里拿着一幅小小的嵌板画，那幅画镶嵌在一个略显灰暗的伊丽莎白一世时代的旧画框里。

这是一幅全身画像，只见画上的年轻人穿着十六世纪末的服装，站在一张桌子旁边，右手放在一本打开的书上。他看上去十七岁左右，相貌十分英俊，不过显得有些缺乏阳刚之气。实际上，要不是因为穿着礼服、留着平头，人们会说这张有着梦幻而伤感的眼睛和精巧红唇的脸庞是女孩的。在技法上，尤其是在对双手的处理上，这幅画使人想起了弗朗索瓦·克卢埃[2]的晚期作品。黑天鹅绒紧身上衣配有别致的镀金圆点，孔雀蓝的底色将它衬托得赏心悦目，因此让它获得了明亮的色彩，颇具克卢埃的风格。大理石底座上规整地挂着两副分别代表悲剧和喜剧的面具，格调是那样刻板而严肃——跟意大利画家的温和优雅截然不同——即使是在法国的宫廷，那位伟大的佛兰德大师也永远不会完全失去这种格调，这种格调一向是北方性情的一个特点。

“这是一幅迷人的画，”我叫道，“艺术如此幸运地为我们保存了他的美貌，但这个令人惊叹的年轻人是谁呢？”

“这是W.H.先生的肖像。”厄斯金面带苦笑说。可能是光线碰巧产生的效果，我看到他的眼里闪着泪光。

“W.H.先生！”我大声嚷道，“W.H.先生是谁？”

“你不记得了吗？”他反问道，“看看他那只手正按着的那本书。”

“我看到那里有一些笔迹，但我看不清是什么。”我答道。

“拿这个放大镜试试看。”厄斯金嘴角仍然泛着苦笑说。

我接过放大镜，把灯又移近了一点，开始拼出潦草的十六世纪的笔迹。“献给下列这些十四行诗的唯一促成者……”“天哪！”我叫道，“这就是莎士比亚的那个W.H.先生？”

“西里尔·格雷厄姆过去经常这样说。”厄斯金咕哝道。

“可他一点也不像彭布罗克勋爵，”我回答说，“我对彭斯赫斯特的画像非常熟悉。几个星期前，我就待在那附近。”

“这么说，你真的相信那些十四行诗是写给彭布罗克勋爵的？”他问。

“我敢肯定这一点，”我答道，“彭布罗克、莎士比亚和玛丽·菲顿夫人是那些十四行诗的三个主要人物，这一点毫无疑问。”

“好吧，我同意你的观点，”厄斯金说，“但我并不总是这么认为。我过去一直相信——嗯，我想我过去一直相信西里尔·格雷厄姆和他的理论。”

“那是什么？”我看着这幅令人赞叹的画像问，在我看来，它已经开始产生一种奇异的魅力。

“说来话长，”说着，厄斯金从我手里拿走了那幅画像——当时我觉得有些突然——“说来话长啊。不过，如果你愿意听的话，我就告诉你。”

“我对有关十四行诗的理论兴趣浓厚，”我大声说道，“但我认为我不可能转而相信任何新的理论。这个问题对任何人都不再是一个谜了。实际上，我想这从来就不是一个谜。”

“我不再相信这个理论，所以也不可能让你去相信它，”厄斯金笑着说道，“但它可能会使你感兴趣。”

“当然，那就告诉我吧，”我回答说，“如果它有那幅画的一半赏心悦目，我就会十分满意。”

“好吧，”说着，厄斯金点了一支香烟，“我必须先给你讲一下西里尔·格雷厄姆本人的情况。我和他在伊顿公学时住在同一个房子里。我比他大一两岁，但我们是非常要好的朋友，一起学习和玩乐。当然，玩乐的时间要比学习的时间多得多，但我从未为此感到后悔。接受良好的商科教育并不总是有好处，我在伊顿公学的运动场上学到的东西完全像我在剑桥学到的一样有用。我应该告诉你，西里尔的父亲和母亲都去世了。他们是在离开怀特岛的一次可怕的游艇事故中淹死的。他的父亲曾在外交部门工作，娶了老克雷迪顿勋爵的女儿——唯一的女儿。他的父母亲去世后，老克雷迪顿勋爵就成了西里尔的监护人。我认为克雷迪顿勋爵并不算十分关心西里尔。他一直没有真正原谅自己的女儿嫁给了一个没有贵族头衔的男人。他是一位与众不同的老贵族，像蔬果小贩那样骂人，而且一举一动都像一个农民。我记得在演讲日那天见过他一次。他对我咆哮，给我一枚金币，告诉我不要像我的父亲那样长成‘该死的激进分子’。西里尔对他没有多少感情，大部分假日反倒十分乐意和我们在苏格兰度过。他们从来没有真正在一起相处过。西里尔认为他野蛮愚蠢，而他则认为西里尔柔弱无力。尽管西里尔是非常出色的骑手和一流的击剑手，但我想他在某些事情上确实十分柔弱。实际上，在离开伊顿公学前，他就开始练剑了。可是，他行事懒散，对自己的俊俏外表自命不凡，而且强烈反感足球。真正给他带来快乐的两件事情就是诗歌和表演。在伊顿公学，他总是饰演莎士比亚戏剧中的角色，吟诵莎士比亚的作品，去读三一学院后，第一学期就成了业余戏剧俱乐部的一员。我还记得我总是非常嫉妒他的演技。我对他的关注到了荒唐的程度，我想，这是因为我们在某些事情上截然不同。我是一个笨手笨脚、虚弱无力的小伙子，满脸都是可怕的雀斑，还有一双大脚。雀斑在苏格兰家庭就像痛风在英格兰家庭一样流行。西里尔过去常说，两者中他更喜欢痛风。他高度重视个人形象，几乎到了荒唐的地步。有一次他在我们辩论团前念了一篇论文，证明人心好不如相貌好。他的确英俊帅气。不喜欢他的人、平庸之辈和大学教师，还有为了进教会而读书的年轻人过去常说，他不过是徒有其表罢了。然而，那张脸不光是英俊，内涵要比这丰富得多。我认为，他是我见过的最出色的人，他的举止优雅而富有魅力，无人能及。他迷住了所有值得迷住的人，也迷住了许许多多不值得迷住的人。他十分任性，而且脾气暴躁，而我过去也认为他过于虚伪。我想这主要是因为他对于享乐从无节制。可怜的西里尔！有一次，我说他只是满足于一些非常廉价的胜利，而他也只是哈哈一笑。令人感到可怕的是，他被宠坏了。我想，所有迷人的人都是被宠坏的人。这正是他们吸引人的秘密之所在。

“不过，我必须给你讲一下西里尔表演方面的事儿。你知道，女演员不被允许在业余戏剧俱乐部演出，至少在我那个时代不行。我不知道现在是怎么回事。嗯，当然，西里尔总是扮演女角。当《皆大欢喜》[3]演出的时候，他扮演罗莎琳德。这是一次了不起的表演。实际上，西里尔·格雷厄姆是我见过的唯一完美的罗莎琳德。他所扮演的角色美丽、精致而优雅，完全难以描述。这在当时引起了巨大的轰动，剧场极小，每天晚上都挤得水泄不通。即使现在看这个剧本，我也会情不自禁地想起西里尔。这个剧本或许正是为他写的。到了下一学期，他拿到了学位，来到伦敦攻读外交学。可是，他从来没做过任何功课，白天读莎士比亚的十四行诗，晚上泡在剧院里。当然，他发疯似的想登台表演。我和克雷迪顿勋爵所能做的就是阻止他。如果他当初成了演员，也许现在还会活着。劝告始终是一个愚蠢之举，而良言相劝绝对能致人死命。我希望你永远不要犯那种错误。如果那样做了，你将会为此感到后悔。

“好了，言归正传。有一天，我收到了西里尔的一封信，请我当晚到他的住所去。他在皮卡迪利大街租了一套能俯瞰格林公园[4]的很棒的住所。当时我每天都去看他，因此对他特意写信邀请感到非常惊讶。当然，我还是去了。到达后，我发现他处于一种万分激动的状态。他告诉我说，他终于发现了《莎士比亚十四行诗集》的真正奥秘，所有的学者和评论家都完全走错了路，而他纯粹通过内文证据，第一个发现了W.H.先生究竟是谁。他欣喜若狂，迟迟不愿给我讲他的理论。最后，他拿出一捆笔记，从壁炉架上取下他那本《莎士比亚十四行诗集》，坐下来给我滔滔不绝地讲起了整个论题。

“他首先指出，既然莎士比亚给这个年轻人写了这些不可思议、充满激情的诗歌，那么这个年轻人一定曾是他戏剧艺术生涯里一个至关重要的人，这个人既不是彭布罗克勋爵，也不是南安普敦勋爵。事实上，不管他是谁，他都不可能是出身高贵的人，因为第二十五首十四行诗非常清楚地说明了这一点。在这首诗里，莎士比亚把自己跟那些‘大公的宠臣’进行对比，说得相当坦率：

就让那些吉星高照的人们，
夸耀公众荣誉和得意称号，
命运拒绝给我胜利的欢欣，
而我却最崇尚意外的开心。

他自得并热爱这一卑微的身份，并以下列诗句收尾：

那么，爱与被爱，我都很幸福，
我在此既不愿迁升也不会被黜。

西里尔宣称，如果我们设想这首十四行诗是写给彭布罗克伯爵或南安普敦伯爵的，这就会让人百思不解，因为两人在英格兰都是地位崇高的人，完全有资格被称为‘大公’。在佐证自己观点的时候，他给我念了第一百二十四首和第一百二十五首十四行诗。在这些诗里，莎士比亚告诉我们，他的爱不是‘权势的子孙’，‘并未在微笑的浮华中遭罪’，而是‘绝非产生于偶然’。我兴致勃勃地倾听着，因为我认为这一点以前从来没有人提起过。可是，随之而来的更加稀奇，关于诗中对象是彭布罗克勋爵的论断几乎被完全驳倒了。我们从米尔斯那里知道，莎士比亚的十四行诗是一五九八年前写的，第一百零四首十四行诗告诉我们，莎士比亚同W.H.先生的友谊已经存在三年了。而出生于一五八〇年的彭布罗克勋爵，直到十八岁才来到伦敦，也就是到一五九八年。莎士比亚与W.H.先生的相识一定开始于一五九四年，或者最晚在一五九五年。因此，莎士比亚与彭布罗克勋爵相识，必然是写完这些十四行诗后的事情。

“西里尔还指出，彭布罗克的父亲直到一六〇一年才去世，而从这行诗，

你有过父亲，让你儿子这样说，

显而易见，在一五九八年，W.H.先生的父亲已死。此外，卷首语出自出版商之手，我们绝不能荒唐地想象，有哪个出版商敢于把彭布罗克的伯爵威廉赫·伯特称为W.H.先生。巴克赫斯特勋爵被说成萨克维尔先生的例子其实不能与之相提并论，因为巴克赫斯特勋爵不是贵族，而仅仅是贵族的小儿子，勋爵对于他是礼节上的尊称，尽管《英格兰诗坛》的文章如此提到了他，但那并不是庄严正式的献词，仅仅是随意提及。到目前为止，就在我惊讶地坐在一旁时，彭布罗克勋爵可能是W.H.先生的种种假设，都被西里尔轻而易举地一一驳倒了。至于南安普敦勋爵，西里尔论证的困难就更少了。南安普敦年纪轻轻就成了伊丽莎白·弗农的情人，所以不用别人来劝他结婚。他不漂亮，不像自己的母亲，W.H.先生则像：

你是母亲的镜子，她在你身上
唤回了风华正茂时的四月芬芳；[5]

而且，最重要的是，南安普敦的教名是‘亨利’，而那两首一语双关的十四行诗（第一百三十五首和第一百四十三首）表明，莎士比亚那位朋友的教名跟他本人的一样——也是‘威尔’。

“至于一些倒霉的评论者的其他看法——‘W.H.先生’被误印成了‘W.S.先生’，‘W.S.先生’的意思就是‘威廉·莎士比亚’（William Shakespeare）先生；‘W.H. all先生’应该读为‘W. Hall先生’; ‘W.H.先生’就是‘威廉·哈撒韦（William Hathaway）先生’；句号应该放在“wisheth”这个词后面，‘W.H.先生’应该是作者，而不应该是献词的对象——西里尔眨眼间就否定了它们。他的理由不必提，不过我还记得，他当时给我念了一位名叫巴恩斯托夫的德国评论者的文章节选，引得我一阵大笑，我很庆幸自己听到的不是德语原文。巴恩斯托夫坚持认为，W.H.先生不是别人，正是‘威廉先生自己（Mr. William Himself）’。他也绝不相信，莎士比亚的十四行诗仅仅是针对德雷顿[6]和赫里福德的约翰·戴维斯的作品的讽刺诗集。在他看来，其实我也这样看，十四行诗是具有严肃的悲剧含义的诗歌，是从莎士比亚的心里榨出的苦汁，并因他的嘴唇之蜜而变得甜美。他更不愿承认它们仅仅是一种哲学寓言，也不愿承认莎士比亚是针对理想自我、理想男性、美的精神、理性、神圣理法或天主教会而写下这一切。他所感到的，我认为我们事实上都有同感，莎士比亚的十四行诗是为个人写的——是为某个人格魅力似乎已经以极度的喜悦和极度的绝望充满了莎士比亚的灵魂的年轻人而写的。

“可以说，西里尔以这种方式扫清了道路，让我从脑海里排除了我对这个问题抱有的其他看法，不偏不倚地倾听着他自己的理论。他指出，问题是莎士比亚时代的那个年轻人是谁。他没有高贵的出身，甚至没有高贵的本性，莎士比亚却因他而激情澎湃，我们只能对这种莫名的崇拜感到惊奇，几乎不敢去转动打开诗人心灵之谜的钥匙。他的身体是如此之美，居然成了莎士比亚的艺术基石、灵感之源、梦想的化身。他到底是谁呢？如果把他仅仅看成情诗对象，就会错失这些诗的全部意义：莎士比亚在十四行诗里所谈论的艺术并不是十四行诗本身。实际上，十四行诗对他来说不过是秘不可宣的雕虫小技——他始终暗指的都是剧作家的艺术，莎士比亚对他说道：

你就是我所有的一切的艺术，
把我的愚笨升到学问的高度，[7]

他对那个年轻人许下了不朽之名，

气息最旺处其实在人们嘴里，[8]

这肯定不是别人，正是那个小演员，莎士比亚为他创作了维奥拉和伊莫金、朱丽叶和罗莎琳德、波西娅和苔丝狄蒙娜，以及克娄巴特拉。这就是西里尔·格雷厄姆的理论，你明白，纯粹是从那些十四行诗本身推断出来的，它是否被人接受，不大依靠显而易见的证明或正式的证据，而是依靠一种精神和艺术的感受。他声称，只有通过这种感受，才能领悟这些诗的真正意义。我还记得他当时给我念了那首优美的十四行诗——

我的诗神怎能缺乏创作主题？
你还呼吸时，把甜美的论点
倾入我的诗，那是多么精彩，
每一个俗笔都难以这样复述。
噢，如果我的诗里有何东西，
值得你细看，那要感谢自己；
你自己主动献出了创作灵感，
谁会那么笨，不去写诗给你？
你是第十位诗神，比前九位，
你的价值要更重十倍还多；
谁要向你呼吁，就让他写出，
流传久远的一行行不朽诗篇[9]……

并指出这首诗如何完全证实了他的理论。而实际上，他仔细查看了所有的十四行诗，以此表明或自以为表明，根据他对诗意的新解，一些曾经显得晦涩、邪恶或夸张的东西变得清晰而具有理性，富有极高的艺术内涵，阐明了莎士比亚关于演员的艺术和剧作家的艺术之间真正关系的理念。

“当然，显而易见，莎士比亚的剧团里一定有一个倾国倾城的绝妙小演员，莎士比亚托付他来表演自己创作的那些高贵的女主角，因为莎士比亚不仅是一个富有想象力的诗人，还是一位注重实际的剧院经理。西里尔·格雷厄姆实际上已经发现了小演员的名字。他就是威尔，或者像他喜欢叫的那样——威利·休斯。当然，这个教名是他在一语双关的第一百三十五首和第一百四十三首十四行诗里发现的。按照他的说法，姓氏藏在第二十首十四行诗的第七行，莎士比亚在这里把W.H.先生描述为：

绝色（hew)男子，所有美色（Hews）由他掌控。[10]

“在《莎士比亚十四行诗集》的原版中，‘Hews’用大写字母和斜体印刷，他声称，这一点清楚地表明作者是在有意地进行文字游戏，他的观点从那些十四行诗中得到了大量佐证，因为在这些诗中，‘use’和‘usury’[11]使用了古怪的双关语。当然，我马上接受了这个观点。在我看来，威利·休斯成了像莎士比亚一样真实的人。我对这个理论提出的唯一反对意见就是，第一批开本印刷的时候，威利·休斯的名字并没有出现在莎士比亚剧团的演员名单当中。不过，西里尔指出，威利·休斯的名字不在这个名单里，恰恰证实了这个理论，因为第八十六首十四行诗清楚地表明，威利·休斯已经放弃了莎士比亚的剧团，到了一家竞争对手的剧团，大概是要在查普曼[12]的某部戏剧中演出。关于这一点，莎士比亚在针对查普曼的伟大十四行诗中对威利·休斯说道：

但当你的面容充满他的诗行，
我就会缺乏灵感，羸弱而心慌[13]……

‘当你的面容充满他的诗行’这种诗句显然是指年轻演员的美貌给查普曼的诗句赋予了生命和真实，并为其增添了魅力，同样的思想也在第七十九首十四行诗里提出——

当我独自恳求你援助之际，
我的诗独享你所有的妩媚；
但现在我的雅致渐渐衰退，
我的病诗神得给他人让位；[14]

在紧接前面的那首十四行诗里，莎士比亚说：

每支陌生的笔采用我的手法，
在你名下把他们的诗歌播撒，[15]

文字游戏当然一目了然，而那句‘在你名下把他们的诗歌播撒’，意思是：‘通过你这个演员的协助，才能把戏剧展示在众人面前。’

“这是一个美妙的夜晚，我们一遍又一遍地诵读《莎士比亚十四行诗集》，差不多熬到了天亮。然而，过了一段时间，我开始明白，在将这个理论以真正完美的形式展示在世人面前之前，有必要得到这位年轻演员威利·休斯存在的某个独立证据。这个论点一旦成立，无疑可以说他就是W.H.先生了；如若不然，这个理论必将落空。我措辞激烈地向西里尔提出了这一点，他认为我思想庸俗并且大为恼火，语气有些尖刻。不过，我还是让他保证，为了自己的利益，他要让整个事情没有任何疑问，才能把自己的发现公之于众。我们周复一周地查究市里各个教堂的登记簿，德威公学的阿莱恩手稿，档案局、宫务大臣的文件——实际上，我们认为有可能提及威利·休斯的一切材料。当然，我们什么也没有发现，在我看来，关于威利·休斯存在的事实性，似乎每天都有越来越多的疑问。西里尔处于一种可怕的状态，常常日复一日地仔细检查整个问题，恳求我相信；但是，我看到了这个理论当中的一个缺陷，所以就不再心悦诚服，除非能确凿无疑地证明伊丽莎白一世时期确实真的存在威利·休斯这个小演员。

“有一天西里尔离城，我当时以为他去跟他的外祖父待在一起，但我后来听克雷迪顿勋爵说情况并非如此。大约两个星期之后，我收到了他从沃里克发来的一份电报，请我一定要在当天晚上八点钟过去跟他一起吃饭。我到达后，他对我说道：‘唯一不该得到证明的使徒是圣·托马斯，圣·托马斯却又是唯一得到证明的使徒。’我问他此话何意。他回答说，他不仅能够证明十六世纪确实有一个名叫威利·休斯的小演员，而且能通过最确凿的证据证明他就是十四行诗里的W.H.先生。他当时不愿再多告诉我什么，但晚饭后，他郑重其事地拿出了那幅我让你看过的画像，告诉我说，他完全是碰巧发现的，他在沃里克郡的一个农家买了一口旧箱子，那幅画像就钉在箱子的侧面。箱子本身是伊丽莎白女王一世时期精湛工艺的典范，他当然随身带着箱子，正面箱板中央确定无疑地刻着首字母W.H.。吸引他注意的正是这个组合字母，他告诉我说，直到买了这口箱子好几天后，他才想起仔细检查一下箱子里面。然而，一天早上，他看到箱子的一侧比另一侧厚得多，就更加仔细地查看，发现较厚的一侧钉着一幅带框的木板画。他把画取了出来，就是现在躺在沙发上的那幅画。那幅画脏兮兮的，霉迹斑斑，但他还是设法把它擦干净了，而且让他大为高兴的是，他歪打正着地发现了自己一直在寻找的东西。这就是W.H.先生的正宗画像，W.H.先生的一只手按在《莎士比亚十四行诗集》献词的页面上，框架上依稀可见用黑色安色尔字体在褪色的金色背景上写的那个年轻人的名字——“威尔·休斯先生”。

“好吧，我该怎么说呢？我从来没有想过西里尔·格雷厄姆是在捉弄我，也从来没有想到他会设法通过伪造来证明他的理论。”

“可它是伪造的吗？”我问。

“当然是，”厄斯金说，“这是一个以假乱真的伪造品，不过终究还是一个伪造品。我当时认为西里尔对整个事情表现得颇为平静，我还记得他不止一次对我说，他自己不需要这类证据，他认为没有这类证据这个理论也是完整的。我嘲笑他，并告诉他说，没有这类证据，这个理论就会落空，我热烈祝贺他有了这个惊人的发现。然后，我们协商决定，要把这幅画蚀刻或临摹，并作为西里尔版《十四行诗集》的卷首插画。连续三个月，我们都在一行一行地仔细检查每一首诗，直到我们解决了文本或诗意的每一处难点。一个晦气的日子，我在霍尔本的一家印刷店看到柜台上摆着一些极其漂亮的银笔素描。它们是那样吸引我，我就买了下来。店主是一个名叫罗林斯的人，他告诉我说，这些画是一个名叫爱德华·默顿的年轻画家画的，这个年轻画家聪明过人，但一贫如洗。我从版画商那里要来了默顿的地址，几天后就去拜见了他。他是一个脸色苍白、饶有风趣的年轻人，他的妻子长相颇为普通——我后来得知那是他的模特。我告诉他我是多么欣赏他的画，他对此显得非常高兴。我问他愿不愿意给我看一下他的其他一些作品。于是，我们就翻看起了一个作品集，里面的确都是非常好看的东西——因为默顿的笔法精致完臻、赏心悦目——这时，我突然瞥见了一幅W.H.先生的画像素描。这一点毫无疑问，几乎是一个摹本——唯一的区别是，那两个代表悲剧与喜剧的面具不是画像里那样从大理石桌上悬挂下来，而是躺在这个年轻人脚边的地板上。‘你是从哪里弄来这个的？’我问。他变得有些困惑，说道：‘噢，那没什么。我不知道它在这个集子里。这是一件没有任何价值的东西。’‘这是你为西里尔·格雷厄姆画的啊，’他的妻子大声说道，‘这位先生想买，就让他买走吧。’‘为西里尔·格雷厄姆先生画的？’我又问道，‘是你画的W.H.先生的画像？’‘我不明白你是什么意思。’他脸色通红地回答说。唉，整个事情糟透了。他的妻子把这一切都给抖了出来。我临走的时候给了她五英镑。我当时怒不可遏，现在想起这件事还是受不了。我马上去了西里尔的住处，在那里等了三个小时，那个可怕的谎言一直盯着我的脸。他回来后，我告诉他我已经发现了他的伪造品。他的脸色一下子变得煞白，说道：‘我这样做，纯粹是为你着想。任何别的方式，你都不会信服。它不影响这个理论的真实性。’‘理论的真实性！’我大声嚷道，‘这我们还是少说为好。连你自己都从来没有相信过这一点。如果你相信的话，就不会弄虚作假来证明了。’我们之间争论激烈，发生了一场可怕的争吵。我当时说话大概有失公允。第二天早晨，他就死了。”

“死了！”我叫道。

“是的，他用左轮手枪射杀了自己。一些血飞溅到了画框上，正好落在了那个写有名字的地方。他的仆人马上派人来叫我，而等我赶到的时候，警察已经到了现场。他留给了我一封信，显然是在最烦乱、最痛苦的状态下写的。”

“信里写的是什么？”我问。

“噢，说他绝对相信威利·休斯，说伪造画像仅仅是对我做出的一种让步，丝毫无损这个理论的真实性。而且，为了向我表明他对整个事情的信念是多么坚定不移、完美无瑕，他要把自己的生命作为祭品，献给《莎士比亚十四行诗集》的这一秘密。这是一封愚蠢又疯狂的信。我还记得，他在信尾说，他把威利·休斯理论托付给我，让我把它呈现给世人，揭开莎士比亚内心之谜。”

“这是一个极其悲惨的故事，”我讲道，“但你为什么没有履行他的意愿？”

厄斯金耸了耸肩。“因为它从始到终都是一种完全站不住脚的理论。”他回答说。

“我亲爱的厄斯金，”我从座位上站起来说，“你在整个事情上完全错了。它是开启《莎士比亚十四行诗集》的唯一完美的钥匙。它每一个细节都完整。我相信威利·休斯的存在。”

“不要那样说，”厄斯金神情严肃地说，“我相信这个理念有一些极其错误的东西，没有丝毫理性。我曾经探究过整个事情，而且可以向你保证这个理论是完全靠不住的。它在某种程度上貌似有理，然后就此打住。看在上帝的分上，我亲爱的孩子，不要研究威利·休斯这个话题了。你会为此伤心的。”

“厄斯金，”我回答说，“把这个理论推向世界，是你的职责。如果你不这样做，我就会去做。如果你隐瞒，你就会辱没西里尔·格雷厄姆的英名，他是文学的所有殉道者中最年轻、最出色的一位。我恳求公正地对待他。他是为这件事而死的——不要让他白死啊。”

厄斯金惊讶地看着我。“你被这个故事冲昏了头脑，”他说，“你忘了一个人为一件事而死，这件事未必就是真实的。我过去对西里尔·格雷厄姆忠心耿耿。他的死对我是一个可怕的打击。我好几年都没有恢复过来。我认为我永远都恢复不过来。可是，威利·休斯呢？威利·休斯的理念一文不值。没有这样的人曾经存在过。至于把整个事情摆在世人面前——世人会认为西里尔·格雷厄姆是意外射杀了自己。他自杀的唯一证据是给我的那封信，而公众从未听说过这封信。直到今天，克雷迪顿勋爵都认为整个事情是一次意外。”

“西里尔·格雷厄姆把自己的生命献给了一个伟大的思想，”我回答说，“如果你不愿讲述他的殉道，那就至少讲述一下他的信念。”

“他的信念，”厄斯金说，“植根于一件虚假的东西，植根于一件靠不住的东西，植根于一件所有莎士比亚学者都丝毫不愿接受的东西。这个理论将会被嘲笑。不要让自己出丑，走一条行不通的小路。你一开始就假设那个人的存在，而那个人的存在却是有待证明的事情。此外，每个人都知道这些十四行诗是写给彭布罗克勋爵的。这件事已经有定论了。”

“这件事没有定论！”我大声叫道，“我会从西里尔·格雷厄姆遗留的这个理论开始研究，还会向世人证明他是对的。”

“傻孩子！”厄斯金说，“回家吧，都两点多钟了，不要再想威利·休斯了。很抱歉，我对你说了这件事，真正抱歉的是我竟然使你相信了我都不相信的事情。”

“你已经送给了我打开现代文学最伟大的奥秘的钥匙，”我回答说，“不让你认可，让大家都认可西里尔·格雷厄姆是我们时代最敏锐的莎士比亚批评家，我不会善罢甘休。”

当我穿过圣·詹姆斯公园走回家的时候，伦敦上空刚刚破晓。白天鹅在澄亮的湖面上睡觉，荒凉的宫殿在淡绿色天空的映衬下呈现出紫色。我想起了西里尔·格雷厄姆，眼里顿时涌满了泪水。

第二章

我醒来的时候已经过了中午十二点，太阳光像长长的，裹挟着尘土的金柱，透过窗帘，照进我的房间。我对仆人说，我在家里不会见任何人。喝了一杯巧克力、吃了一个早餐面包[16]后，我从书架上拿下我那本《莎士比亚十四行诗集》，开始仔细审阅起来。在我看来，每一首诗似乎都能证实西里尔·格雷厄姆的理论。我觉得好像我把一只手放在了莎士比亚的心上，并在数着激情的每一次悸动和脉跳。我想起了那个令人赞叹的小演员，在每一行诗句里都看到了他的脸庞。

我还记得，有两首十四行诗给我留下了特别深刻的印象：它们是第五十三首和第六十七首。在前一首里，莎士比亚称赞威利·休斯全面的演技，称赞他从罗莎琳德到朱丽叶，从比阿特丽斯到奥菲莉亚，扮演了范围宽广的角色，对他说道：

你的本质是什么，你由何构成，
无数奇异的影子纷纷把你推崇？
人人都是这样，每人有一个影，
除了一个影，你还能增各种影[17]……

如果这首诗不是写给演员的，这些诗行就会难以理解，因为在莎士比亚时代，“影子”这个词有跟舞台相关的一种专门含义。“这种戏里最好的就是影子。”忒修斯这样评说《仲夏夜之梦》里的演员，而且同时代的文学作品中也有许多类似的比喻。这些十四行诗显然属于这类，莎士比亚在诗句中讨论了演员的艺术本质，以及完美的舞台演员必不可少的那种奇异而罕见的气质。“你是怎么，”莎士比亚对威利·休斯说，“拥有这么多个性的呢？”随后，他接着指出，休斯的美如此出众，似乎把想象的各种形式和阶段都变成了现实，将充满创造性想象力的每一个梦具象化——这种理念在紧接着的那首十四行诗里得到了进一步扩展，它以如此美好的思想开始：

噢，真实要是赋予了甜美装潢，
美似乎就会增光添彩，美上加美！[18]

莎士比亚请我们注意演技的真实、舞台上有形展示的真实是如何增加诗的神奇，让诗的魅力赋有生命，让理想形式赋有真正的现实感。然而，在第六十七首十四行诗中，莎士比亚呼吁威利·休斯放弃舞台，放弃舞台的矫揉造作，放弃涂脂抹粉的面容和模仿的服装构成的虚假生活，放弃不道德的影响和暗示，放弃它同行为高贵、话语真诚的真实世界的疏离。

啊，为什么他活在这腐败社会，
用他的仪态来为亵渎增光添彩，
罪恶行径也依靠他来攫取利益，
以他的陪伴刻意装点美化自己？
为什么虚假脂粉仿造他的容颜，
从他逼真的色彩窃取呆板外观？
既然玫瑰是真，可怜的美何以，
还要弯来绕去寻找玫瑰的影子？[19]

像莎士比亚这么伟大的戏剧家，在戏剧创作和舞台表演的理想平面上，作为艺术家，实现了自己的完美；作为人，实现了人性。他居然以这样的术语来写戏剧，这看起来可能奇怪。但是，我们必须记住，在第一百一十首和第一百一十一首十四行诗里，莎士比亚向我们表明，他也厌倦了这个木偶的世界，对使自己成为“公众的小丑”充满了羞耻。第一百一十一首尤其苦涩：

噢，为了我，你斥责命运女神，
我的有害行为都怪这有罪女神，
除了我逢人便去卖弄当众谋生，
没有人会为我的生活好好供应。
因而，我的名字便把烙印招领，
我的本性由此便这样俯首听命，
就像染工之手，屈从工作环境：
那就可怜我，希望我获得新生[20]……

其他地方还有许多这种情绪的标志，所有真正研究莎士比亚的学者都熟悉这些标志。

我读《莎士比亚十四行诗集》的时候，有一点百思不解。几天后，我才突然明白它真正的诠释，好像西里尔·格雷厄姆本人也没有明白它的意义。我不明白莎士比亚为什么对朋友结婚期望值那么高。他自己年纪轻轻就结了婚，结果却非常不幸，他不太可能让威利·休斯犯同样的错误。扮演罗莎琳德的小演员从婚姻中和现实生活的激情中什么也得不到。在我看来，那些带有关于结婚生子的奇怪恳求的早期十四行诗，是一个不和谐的音符。神秘的解释突然产生，对我来说非常意外，我是在古怪的献词里发现的。人们一定会记住献词，内容如下：

献给下列这些十四行诗的
唯一促成者
W.H.先生。像我
不朽诗人[21]允诺的那样
万事如意幸福永久
良好祝愿
冒昧付梓者。

T.T.[22]

有些学者推断，这个献词里的“促成者”仅仅是指为出版商托马斯·索普获得《十四行诗集》的人。但是，这种观点现在被普遍摈弃了，最高权威都一致地认为这个词应该理解为“激发灵感者”，这个比喻是从物质生活的类比得来的。现在我明白了，莎士比亚本人在创作诗歌时一直使用同样的比喻，这使我走上了正路。最后，我有了重大发现。莎士比亚提议威利·休斯结婚是“与他的诗神结婚”，第八十二首诗里明确地这样表达了。他为那个小演员创作了最伟大的角色，小演员之美的确给了那些角色启发，而小演员却背叛了他，他对此内心苦涩，一开头就诉苦说：

我承认你没有嫁给我的诗神。[23]

他请求休斯生出的不是有血有肉的孩子们，而是更加永恒的孩子们，也就是不朽之名。诗集开头整个一组十四行诗[24]仅仅是莎士比亚邀请威利·休斯登上舞台，成为一名演员。他说，如果你的美丽派不上用场，那会是一件多么沉闷无趣、毫无裨益的事情：

当四十个冬天围攻你的前额，
在你美的田地挖下深深沟壑，
你的青春华服如今引人瞩目，
有朝一日会像败草不值一提：
有人到时问你的美躺在何处，
哪是你所有风华正茂的宝藏，
在你自己那双深陷的眼睛里，
是饕餮的耻辱和无益的赞扬[25]。

你必须在艺术中有所创造：我的诗“是你的，因你而生”[26]；只要听我说，我就会“写出一行行流传久远的不朽诗篇”，你则会用自己的形象在舞台上演绎想象世界中的形形色色的人。他继续说道，你的这些孩子就不会像凡人的孩子们那样消亡，你会活在他们身上，活在我的戏里：只要你：

为了我，在孩子身上复制自己，
那种美仍可活在你或孩子体内！[27]

我收集了所有在我看来能证实这个观点的篇章，它们给我留下了强烈的印象，并向我说明了西里尔·格雷厄姆的理论的确是多么完整。我也看到，莎士比亚有些诗行是在谈论十四行诗本身，有些是在谈论他的伟大戏剧作品，要区分那些诗行相当容易。在西里尔·格雷厄姆出现那天前，这是一个被所有批评者完全忽视的问题。然而，这是整个系列诗歌里最重要的一点。对于十四行诗，莎士比亚或多或少有些淡漠。他不希望自己的名声停留在这些十四行诗上面。对他来说，十四行诗是他所谓的“卑微的诗神”，因为米尔斯也告诉我们，十四行诗只有寥寥几个朋友私下传阅而已。另一方面，他特别在意自己的戏剧作品的巨大的艺术价值，并对自己的戏剧天分流露出了一种高贵的自恃。当他对威利·休斯说起：

但是，你的长夏不会黯淡无光，
也不会失去你靓丽优美的形象；
死神夸口你在他的阴影里游荡，
当你在永恒的诗行与时间成长：
只要人类能呼吸，眼睛能眺望，
永世长存，赐给你生命的光芒；[28]——

“永恒的诗行”这个措辞显然是暗指他当时送给休斯的其中一部戏剧，同样，最后两句表明他相信自己的戏剧有可能经久不衰地演下去。在他写给戏剧缪斯（第一百首和第一百零一首）的十四行诗中，我们发现了同样的情绪。

诗神啊，你在哪里，久久忘记，
去说起佳人赋予你的所有力量？
你在毫无价值的歌上浪掷诗意，
屈尊你的力量给卑微主题借光？[29]

他大声叫喊，然后继续责备悲剧和喜剧的情人，责备她“疏忽浸染于美好的纯真[30]”，说道：

他不需要赞美，你就装聋作哑？
别为沉默找借口，你有能力啊，
使他比镀金的坟墓活得更久长，
会受到世世代代一致纷纷赞扬。
诗神尽你的职责，我教你怎样，
使他从此像现在这样一如既往[31]。

然而，也许在第五十五首十四行诗里，莎士比亚才对这个理念进行了最充分的表述。如果想象第二行的“雄浑韵律”指的是十四行诗本身，那就完全误解了莎士比亚的意思。在我看来，从十四行诗的共性来看，“雄浑韵律”极有可能是指一部特定的戏剧，这部戏剧不是别的，正是《罗密欧与朱丽叶》。

无论大理石还是王公的镀金碑，
都活不过这种雄浑博大的韵律；
但你将永远闪耀在这些诗篇里，
胜过那些懒惰时光涂脏的石头。
当挥霍的战争将要去推翻铜像，
战火也会连根拔起铁壁和铜墙，
无论是战神利剑还是战争烈焰，
都烧不掉你记忆里的鲜活记录。
面对死亡和湮没这一切的怨仇，
你阔步向前；即使在后世的眼里，
你的赞美也将会找到一席之地，
耗尽这个世界，直到最后末日。
所以直到最后审判你自己站起，
你活在诗里，住在恋人的眼里。

这同样特别发人深省，注意这里和其他地方一样，莎士比亚向威利·休斯承诺的不朽是一种引人注目的形式——也就是说，是一种引人入胜的形式，是一种供人观看的戏剧。

连续两个星期，我努力研读十四行诗，几乎足不出户，谢绝了所有邀请。我似乎每天都能发现新东西，威利·休斯对我来说成了一种精神存在，一种永远占主导地位的人格魅力。我几乎可以在想象中看到他站在我房间的阴影里，莎士比亚把他描绘得是那么出色：他一头金发，花朵般温柔优雅，梦幻般的深眼窝，柔和灵动的四肢，还有白百合般的双手。就连他的名字都让我心醉神迷。威利·休斯！威利·休斯！它是多么悦耳动听啊！是的，除了他，还有谁可能成为莎士比亚最衷爱的“情妇”，[32]成为他臣服的爱情上帝，[33]成为快乐的柔弱宠臣，[34]成为全世界的玫瑰，[35]成为春天的信使[36]，身穿青春华服[37]，成为那个倾听甜美音乐的可爱男孩[38]，他的美就是莎士比亚心灵的衣裳，[39]因为这是他的戏剧力量的基石。现在由他的背叛和羞耻产生的整个悲剧似乎是那么苦涩！——仅仅通过他个性的魔力，他把耻辱变得甜美可爱[40]，但这毕竟还是耻辱。然而，莎士比亚原谅了他，我们不也应该原谅他吗？我不喜欢窥探他罪恶的秘密。他对莎士比亚剧院的背叛是另一回事，我极其详细地调查了这一点。最后，我得出结论，西里尔·格雷厄姆错误地认为第八十首十四行诗的剧坛对手是查普曼。这首诗显然暗指的是马洛[41]。在写作这些十四行诗的这段时间里，“他雄浑的诗行的傲然扬帆”[42]这样的表达不可能适用于查普曼的作品，无论它可能多么适用于他后来在詹姆斯一世时期的戏剧风格。不，莎士比亚以如此赞美的措辞谈论的剧坛对手显然是马洛，而且：

那个和蔼可亲的幽灵，
每天夜里用机智骗他，[43]

指的是他的《浮士德博士》里的梅菲斯特。毫无疑问，马洛被这个小演员的美丽与风度迷住了，并引诱他离开了黑衣修士剧院，这样小演员可能在他的《爱德华二世》中扮演了盖文斯顿。显然，从第八十七首十四行诗来看，莎士比亚有合法的权利把威利·休斯留在自己的剧团，他说：

再见！你金贵我高攀不起，
你充分地知道自己的价值：
你的价值赋予你特权自由；
我对你的盟约都已经终止。
没有你的恩准我如何留你？
我哪有福分得到那种宝藏？
我没有理由接受公平礼物，
我的专利权还是物归原主。
你不知自己宝贵以身相许，
否则你就错看了受赐的我；
因此你的厚礼是出于误会，
经过明断，就要重新还归。
我曾拥有你，像一场美梦，
梦里权称王，醒来万事无。

但是，用爱留不住的人，他也不愿用武力留住。威利·休斯成为彭布罗克剧团的一员，而且有可能在红牛酒馆的露天场地扮演了爱德华国王的幸臣这一角色。马洛去世后，休斯似乎又回到了莎士比亚身边，不管合作伙伴对这件事可能有什么想法，莎士比亚马上就原谅了这个年轻演员的任性与背叛。

此外，莎士比亚对舞台演员的气质刻画得是多么出色！威利·休斯是其中之一。

他们不去做自己最爱做的事，
他们感动别人自己却如磐石。[44]

他可以演绎爱情，却感觉不到爱情；可以模仿激情，却意识不到激情。

许多人虚情假意的种种经历，
露在蹙眉皱纹的莫名情绪里。[45]

但是，威利·休斯并不是这样。“上苍，”莎士比亚在一首洋溢着疯狂的偶像崇拜的十四行诗里说：

上苍在创造你之时便已注定，
甜爱要永远地留在你的脸上；
无论思想还是心里如何嬗变，
你的容貌从此只会诉说甜美。[46]

从他的“见异思迁”和“虚情假意”中，不难看出伪善和背叛，不知何故，似乎这跟艺术本质密不可分，因为他喜欢得到赞扬，渴望马上得到认可，表现出了所有演员的特征。然而，威利·休斯在这方面比其他演员更幸运，他了解不朽的东西。他跟莎士比亚的戏剧密不可分，所以会活在其中。

你的名字从此将会永垂不朽，
一旦离去，我定会隔绝人世：
大地只能给我一座普通坟墓，
你将会埋葬在人们的眼睛里。
我的温柔诗行将是你的丰碑，
当所有世人都纷纷撒手而去，
未来的眼睛一定会前后通读，
未来的舌头也会把你来传递。[47]

此外，莎士比亚无数次地提到了威利·休斯征服观众的威力——莎士比亚称观众们为“仰慕者”。但是，也许关于休斯对戏剧艺术的精通最完美的描述莫过于《情女怨》[48]。在这首诗里，莎士比亚是这样叙说他的：

他心里有许多巧妙招数，
千姿又百态故弄又玄虚，
脸红如火，或泪水长流，
苍白眩晕；他得手就走，
骗人天衣无缝得心应手，
听粗话脸红闻不幸哭泣，
见惨景脸色煞白倒在地。[49]
因此，在他如簧的舌尖上，
各种各样争论和深刻问题，
所有随即应答和有力推断，
无论醒来睡着都对他有利，
能让哭者笑，能让笑者哭。
各种行话和技巧应有尽有，
他随心所欲虏获所有激情。[50]

有一次，我认为，我真的已经在伊丽莎白一世时代的文献里找到了威利·休斯。在对埃塞克斯郡大伯爵最后日子的精彩生动的叙述里，他的私人牧师托马斯·奈尔告诉我们说，伯爵去世前一天晚上，“他吩咐乐师威廉·休斯一边弹奏维金纳琴[51]一边歌唱。‘威尔·休斯，’他说，‘弹我那首歌，我要唱给自己听。’于是，他兴高采烈地唱了起来，不像是依然低头悲鸣末日来临的天鹅，而像是一只歌声悦耳的云雀，只见他举起双手，抬眼望着上帝，就这样升上了水晶般透明的天空，并跟他不倦的舌头一样到达了最高的天顶。”当然，那个对西德尼之星的垂死父亲弹维金纳琴的男孩不是别人，正是莎士比亚题献十四行诗的威尔·休斯。莎士比亚告诉我们说，休斯本身听起来就是甜美的音乐。然而，埃塞克斯勋爵一五七六年去世，当时莎士比亚本人才十二岁。他的乐师不可能是《莎士比亚十四行诗集》里的W.H.先生。莎士比亚的年轻朋友可能会是维金纳琴师的儿子吗？这至少已经发现威尔·休斯是伊丽莎白一世时期的一个名字。实际上，“休斯”这个名字似乎曾经跟音乐和舞台密切相关。英国第一个女演员是可爱的玛格丽特·休斯，鲁珀特王子如此疯狂地爱上了她。在她和埃塞克斯勋爵的乐师之间出现了那个表演莎士比亚戏剧的小演员，这有什么不可能的呢？但是，那些证据、那些环节——它们在哪里呢？唉！我找不到它们。在我看来，我总是处在完全确认的边缘，却从来没有真正到达过那里。

从威利·休斯的生活，我很快就想到了他的死亡。我过去常常想知道他是什么样的结局。

也许他曾经跟那些英国演员一起，于一六〇四年漂洋过海前往德国，在不伦瑞克[52]的亨利·尤里乌斯[53]大公面前表演，大公本人也是一位非常出色的剧作家。他们还在勃兰登堡那个奇怪的选帝侯宫演出，这个选帝侯非常迷恋美人，据说他曾经用相当于他体重的琥珀买下了希腊客商的小儿子；为了表彰他的奴仆，还在一六〇六到一六〇七那个可怕的饥荒年举行了一些盛会，这时他的子民纷纷饿死在城市的大街上，因为七个月都没有下一滴雨。我们知道，不管怎样，一六一三年《罗密欧与朱丽叶》《哈姆雷特》和《李尔王》一起在德累斯顿上演；一六一五年，经英国大使的一位随员之手，把莎士比亚的遗容面模带去交给的肯定不是别人，正是威利·休斯，这是逝去的伟大诗人深爱他的凭证。实际上，一定会有特别符合这种观点的一些东西：这个小演员的美是莎士比亚艺术的现实主义和浪漫情怀中至关重要的元素，应该是他第一个把新文化的种子带到了德国，并以自己的方式成为十八世纪启蒙运动[54]的先驱，尽管那次辉煌的运动是由莱辛[55]和赫尔德[56]开创的，并由歌德推向了充分而又完美的顶点，同时也得到了另一位演员——弗里德里希·施罗德[57]——的大力帮助。弗里德里希·施罗德唤醒了大众意识，并通过舞台上的假装激情和模仿手段表现生活与文学之间亲密无间、至关重要的联系。如果是这样——当然还没有任何反对的证据——威利·休斯是那些英国喜剧演员之一（古代编年史称他们是来自英国的演员[58]），这不是没有可能。那些英国喜剧演员在纽伦堡的一次突发的人民起义中被杀，一些年轻人把他们秘密地埋在了城外的一个小葡萄园；“这些年轻人在他们的表演中发现了乐趣，其中一些曾试图得到有关新艺术奥秘的指导。”当然，再没有什么地方比城墙外的这个小葡萄园更适合威尔·休斯了，莎士比亚曾经对他说过：“你是我所有的艺术。”难道悲剧不是源于狄奥尼索斯[59]的种种悲伤吗？难道带着无忧无虑的快乐和随机应答的喜剧的轻松笑声，不是首先从西西里葡萄园丁的嘴里听到的吗？不仅如此，而且人们脸上和四肢上留下的葡萄酒泡沫的紫红印迹，不是也首先暗示了伪装的种种魅力——对自我隐藏的欲望，对客观现实的价值感——从而自动地呈现在了艺术的原始开端之中吗？不管怎样，无论他躺在哪里——无论是在哥特城门口的小葡萄园，还是在我们大城市伦敦喧嚣忙乱中的某个昏暗墓地——都没有壮丽的丰碑标明他的安身之处。正如莎士比亚预见的那样，他真正的墓地是诗人的诗行，他真正的纪念碑是戏剧的永恒魅力。其他人也曾如此，这些人以自身的美给予了他的时代一个崭新的、创造性的推动。那个俾泰尼亚奴仆[60]象牙般的躯体在尼罗河的绿色软泥中腐烂，那个雅典青年[61]的骨灰撒落在克拉美库斯[62]的黄色山丘上。但是，安提诺乌斯[63]活在雕塑里，卡尔米德[64]则活在哲学里。

第三章

三个星期后，我决心向厄斯金强烈呼吁：要公正地纪念西里尔·格雷厄姆，并向世人公布他对《莎士比亚十四行诗集》的精彩解读——唯一一个对这个问题进行了全面说明的解读。我给厄斯金写了一封信。我遗憾地说，我没有我那封信的任何副本，也没有能拿到原件。但是，我还记得我当时把整个问题回顾了一遍，在满满几页纸上充满热情地重述了我研究得来的那些论点和证据。在我看来，我不仅仅是要把西里尔·格雷厄姆恢复到他在文学史上应有的地位，而且是要挽救莎士比亚本人的荣誉，以免人们以为那些十四行诗只是单调乏味地回忆一段司空见惯的私情。我把所有的热情都投入了这封信。我把所有的信念都投入了这封信。

其实，我刚把这封信寄走，一种奇异的感应就向我袭来。在我看来，我已经放弃了我对《莎士比亚十四行诗集》威利·休斯理论的所有信念，好像什么东西已经离我而去，所以我对整个主题都完全无动于衷。到底发生了什么事呢？这很难说。也许通过寻找完美地宣泄激情的方式，我已经用尽了激情本身。情感的力量，就像物质生活的力量一样，有其确定的局限性。也许原因在于，仅仅通过努力使任何一个人转而相信一种理论，就意味着劝说者要在某种程度上放弃相信的能力。也许我完全厌倦了整个事情，而且我的热情已经燃尽了，我的理性只能依赖其自身的冷静判断。无论发生怎样的变化，我都无法妄加解释，威利·休斯对我来说突然变成了一个纯粹的神话、一场无聊的梦想，变成了一个年轻人幼稚的幻想，这个年轻人像大多数热情的人一样，更渴望说服别人，而不是说服自己。

因为我在信里说了一些对厄斯金很不公平的刻薄话，所以我马上决定去看看他，为自己的行为向他道歉。于是，第二天早上，我坐车去了鸟笼道，发现厄斯金坐在他的书房里，威利·休斯的伪造肖像立在他面前。

“我亲爱的厄斯金！”我叫道，“我是来向你道歉的。”

“向我道歉？”他问，“为什么道歉？”

“为我的信道歉。”我答道。

“你在信里没有什么可道歉的，”他说，“恰恰相反，你在力所能及的范围内帮了我一个最大的忙。你已经向我表明，西里尔·格雷厄姆的理论是完全合理的。”

“你不是说你相信威利·休斯吧？”我大声问道。

“为什么不相信呢？”他答道，“你已经向我证明了那件事。你以为我判断不了证据的价值吗？”

“可是，根本没有任何证据。”我一屁股坐在椅子上抱怨道，“我给你写信的时候，是受到了愚蠢透顶的热情的影响。我已经被西里尔·格雷厄姆去世的故事打动了，被他的浪漫理论陶醉了，被整个理念的新奇迷住了。我现在明白，那个理论是基于一种错觉。威利·休斯存在的唯一证据就是你面前的那幅肖像，而且肖像是伪造的。在这件事上不要被纯粹的感情冲昏了头脑。无论浪漫情怀对有关威利·休斯的理论有多么新奇的感受，理性都是坚决反对的。”

“我不明白你的意思。”厄斯金惊讶地看着我说，“哎呀，是你自己通过那封信已经使我确信威利·休斯是绝对真实的。你为什么改变了主意？要么说，你之前对我说的所有一切，只是一个玩笑？”

“我无法给你解释，”我回应说，“但我现在明白西里尔·格雷厄姆所做出的解读实在没有什么可赞同的。《莎士比亚十四行诗集》是写给彭布罗克勋爵的。看在上帝的分上，不要浪费时间犯傻去试图发现伊丽莎白一世时期一个从不存在的年轻演员，让一个幽灵木偶成为《莎士比亚十四行诗集》伟大诗篇的中心。”

“我看你不明白那个理论。”他答道。

“我亲爱的厄斯金，”我喊道，“不明白！啊，我感觉它好像是我无中生有的。当然，我的信向你表明，我不仅研究了整件事，而且提供了各种证据。这种理论的一个缺陷是，它预先假定那个人的存在，而这个人的存在正是争议的话题。如果我们承认莎士比亚的剧团有一个名叫威利·休斯的年轻演员，就不难使他成为那些十四行诗的对象。可是，因为我们知道环球剧院[65]里没有这个名字的演员，所以进一步调查是无聊的。”

“不过，这正是我们不知道的，”厄斯金说，“千真万确，他的名字没有出现在第一对开本的演员名单上。然而，正如西里尔指出的那样，如果我们还记得他为了一个剧坛对手而背弃过莎士比亚的话，这就会相当有利地证明威利·休斯的存在，而不是否定。”

我们就这件事争论了几个小时，但无论我说什么，都不能使厄斯金放弃他对西里尔·格雷厄姆理论的信念。他告诉我说，他打算奉献自己的一生来证明这个理论，并下定决心以还其公正的方式来纪念西里尔·格雷厄姆。我恳求他，嘲笑他，央求他，但都无济于事。最后，我们就此分手，并不完全是满腔怒火，但我们之间肯定留下了一道阴影。他认为我浅薄，我觉得他愚蠢。当我再次拜访他的时候，仆人告诉我他已经去了德国。

两年后，我正要走进俱乐部，门房递给我一封盖有外国邮戳的信。这是厄斯金寄来的，是在戛纳的英格兰酒店写的。看过信后，尽管我不太相信他会如此疯狂地下定决心付诸行动，但我心里还是充满了恐惧。那封信的要点是，他想尽了各种办法去证实威利·休斯理论，都一一失败了，而且，由于西里尔·格雷厄姆为这个理论献出了自己的生命，因此他本人已经决定也为同样的事业献出自己的生命。信的结尾是这样写的：“我仍然相信威利·休斯。当你收到这封信的时候，我应该早已为威利·休斯亲手结束了自己的生命：既为了他，也为了西里尔·格雷厄姆。是我通过浅薄的怀疑主义和无知的信仰缺失逼死了西里尔·格雷厄姆。事实真相一度透露给你，而你却一口否定了。这件事沾有两条生命的鲜血，现在来到了你身边——不要避开。”

这是一个可怕的时刻。我因痛苦而感到恶心，但我却无法相信这一点。为某个人的神学信仰而死，是一个人对自己的生命最糟糕的利用，况且是为一个文学理论而死！这似乎说不过去。

我看了看日期。这封信是一个星期前写的。不巧的是，我好几天都没有来俱乐部，否则的话，也许我就能及时地收到信去救他。也许还不太晚。我坐车赶回自己的房间，收拾好东西，然后从查令十字车站乘夜班邮车启程。旅途难以忍受。我想自己再也到不了了。

一到站，我就驱车赶到了英格兰酒店。他们告诉我说，两天前厄斯金已经被埋葬在了英国人的墓地。整个悲剧有一种可怕而又怪诞的气氛。我说了各种各样的疯话，大厅里的人都好奇地看着我。

突然，厄斯金夫人满面哀伤，穿过前庭。看到我后，她向我走来，低声说了几句关于她可怜的儿子的话，就放声大哭。我把她领进起居室。一位上了年纪的先生在那里等着她。他是个英国医生。

我们谈了很多有关厄斯金的情况，但我对他自杀的动机只字未提。显而易见，他没有告诉他的母亲，是什么原因逼迫他做出如此致命、如此疯狂的行为。最后，厄斯金夫人起身说道：“乔治给你留下了一件东西作为纪念。这是他非常珍视的一件东西。我去给你拿来。”

她一离开房间，我就转身对医生说道：“这对厄斯金夫人一定是一个非常可怕的打击！我对她居然这么能忍受感到惊讶。”

“噢，她几个月前就知道会是这样。”他答道。

“几个月前就知道！”我嚷道，“可她为什么不阻止他呢？她为什么不让人看着他呢？他一定是疯了。”

医生盯着我。“我不明白你是什么意思。”他说。

“噢，”我喊道，“如果母亲知道她的儿子要自杀——”

“自杀！”他回答说，“可怜的厄斯金没有自杀。他死于肺病。他来这里就是等死的。看到他的那一刻，我就知道没有希望了。一只肺几乎没有了，另一只肺也受到了非常严重的感染。去世前三天，他问我还有没有什么希望。我对他坦言没有什么希望了，他只有几天活头了。他写了几封信，完全听天由命，直到最后都能保持清醒。”

正在此刻，厄斯金夫人手里拿着威利·休斯那幅致命的画像，走进了房间。“临终前，乔治求我把这个给你。”她说。当我从她的手里接过画像的时候，她的眼泪扑簌簌地落在了我的手上。

那幅画像目前挂在我的书房里，我那些从事艺术的朋友都赞不绝口。他们已经确定那不是克卢埃的手笔，而是乌德里的。我从来都不喜欢把它真正的来历告诉他们。但有时，我看着它的时候，觉得关于《莎士比亚十四行诗集》的威利·休斯理论真的有好多话可说。

[1]麦克弗森（1736—1796），苏格兰诗人。他曾声称发现了古代作家奥西安用盖尔语写作的系列史诗，并将其译成英文发表，在当时产生了很大的影响。后来人们普遍认为，这些作品大部分是麦克弗森自己的创作。爱尔兰（1775—1835），英格兰作家。曾伪造大量莎士比亚“佚作”，蒙骗了许多人，后来被揭穿。查特顿，全名托马斯·查特顿（1752—1770），英国天才诗人，擅长模仿，他虽然运用的是十五世纪的英语词汇，但他的诗歌节奏和观点却十分前卫，被看作英国浪漫主义诗人的先驱者之一。他的代表作有《歌手之歌》《布里斯托尔悲剧》（又名《查尔斯·波丁爵士之死》）、《一首极好的慈善歌谣》等。

[2]弗朗索瓦·克卢埃（1510—1572），法国文艺复兴时期肖像画代表画家。他的艺术达到了法国文艺复兴现实主义肖像画的至高水平，为法国文艺复兴奠定了现实主义基础。除肖像以外，他也画神话题材，并有少量细密画传世。

[3]《皆大欢喜》，莎士比亚的四大喜剧之一。

[4]格林公园，英国伦敦的一座皇家园林，介于海德公园和圣詹姆斯公园之间。连同肯辛顿公园和白金汉宫的花园，这些公园构成一个从白厅、维多利亚车站绵延至肯辛顿和诺丁山的一连串几乎不中断的开阔地带。

[5]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第三首第九行、第十行。

[6]德雷顿，全名迈克尔·德雷顿（1563—1631），英国著名诗人，出生于沃里克郡。代表作有《多福之国》《阿金库尔歌》。

[7]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第七十八首第十三行到第十四行。

[8]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第八十一首第十四行。

[9]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第三十八首第一行到第十二行。

[10]hew=hue，Hews跟Hughes发音一样。

[11]use和usury跟Hughes的发音相近。

[12]查普曼，全名乔治·查普曼（1559—1634），英国诗人、剧作家和翻译家，因翻译荷马的《伊利亚特》和《奥德赛》而出名。

[13]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第八十六首第十三行到第十四行。

[14]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第七十九首第一行到第四行。

[15]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第七十八首第三行、第四行。

[16]原文为法语：petit-pain。

[17]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第五十三首第一行到第四行。

[18]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第五十四首第一行、第二行。

[19]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第六十七首第一行到第八行。

[20]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第一百一十一首第一行到第八行。

[21]我们的不朽诗人，指莎士比亚。

[22]T.T.，全名Thomas Thorpe（托马斯·索普），伦敦出版商，一六〇九年出版《十四行诗集》第一个四开本（The First Quarto）时在卷首加了这段献词。

[23]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第八十二首第一行。

[24]诗集开头整个一组十四行诗，是指第一首到第十七首。

[25]出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第二首第一行到第八行。

[26]出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第七十八首第十行。

[27]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第十首第十三行、第十四行。

[28]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第十八首第九行到第十四行。

[29]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第一百首第一行到第四行。

[30]出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第一百零一首第二行。

[31]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第一百零一首第九行到第十四行。

[32]作者注：第二十首第二行。

[33]作者注：第二十六首第一行。

[34]作者注：第一百二十六首第九行。

[35]作者注：第一百零九首第十四行。

[36]作者注：第一首第十行。

[37]作者注：第二首第三行。

[38]作者注：第八首第一行。

[39]作者注：第二十二首第六行。

[40]作者注：第九十五首第一行。

[41]马洛（1564—1593），全名克里斯托弗·马洛，英国诗人、剧作家。在伦敦期间，马洛曾与探险家兼政治活动家罗利、剧作家查普曼、数学家哈里奥特等怀疑宗教者结成团体，人称黑夜派和无神论者。马洛革新了中世纪戏剧，在舞台上创造了反映时代精神的巨人性格和“雄浑诗行”，为莎士比亚的创作铺平了道路。

[42]该句出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第八十六首第一行。

[43]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第八十六首第九行、第十行。

[44]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第九十四首第二行、第三行。

[45]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第九十三首第七行、第八行。

[46]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第九十三首第九行到第十二行。

[47]以上出自《莎士比亚十四行诗集》第八十一首第五行到第十二行。

[48]《情女怨》，莎士比亚的一首叙事长诗，最早出版于一六〇九年，与莎士比亚的十四行诗合为一集。本诗通篇用王韵（Rhyme Royal），每小节七行，五音步抑扬格，韵式为ababbcc，共四十七节。

[49]以上出自《情女怨》第四十四节。

[50]以上出自《情女怨》第十八节。

[51]十六、十七世纪的一种英国古钢琴类乐器。

[52]不伦瑞克，德国中北部城市，属下萨克森州。

[53]亨利·尤里乌斯（1597—1606），不伦瑞克—吕讷堡公爵。

[54]启蒙运动，是发生在十七、十八世纪欧洲的一场反封建、反教会的思想文化解放运动，是继文艺复兴运动之后欧洲近代第二次思想解放运动。

[55]莱辛（1729—1781），德国戏剧家、戏剧理论家，代表作是《年轻学者》《拉奥孔》。

[56]赫尔德（1744—1803），德国哲学家、诗人、路德派神学家，其作品《论语言的起源》成为狂飙运动的基础。

[57]弗里德里希·施罗德（1744—1816），德国演员、导演。受莱辛美学思想影响，早期曾组织流动剧团，创办并主持汉堡剧院。导演和表演过德国狂飙突进运动剧作家及莎士比亚的剧作，以表演《一仆二主》中的特鲁法尔金诺著称。第一个把莎士比亚戏剧搬上德国舞台，并写有多部戏剧。对十八世纪欧洲共济会的历史有过重要研究。

[58]拉丁语，mimae quidam ex Britannia。

[59]狄奥尼索斯，十二主神之一，古希腊色雷斯人信奉的葡萄酒之神，他不仅握有葡萄酒醉人的力量，还以布施欢乐与慈爱在当时成为极有感召力的神，他推动了古代社会的文明并确立了法则，维护着世界的和平。此外，他还护佑着希腊的农业与戏剧文化。

[60]俾泰尼亚奴仆，指安提诺乌斯。

[61]雅典青年，指卡尔米德。

[62]克拉美库斯，指雅典的一个地区。

[63]安提诺乌斯，罗马皇帝哈德良（117—138在位）的同性恋爱人。传说他是为了哈德良皇帝而拿自己的生命做献祭。

[64]卡尔米德，古希腊哲学家柏拉图在《卡尔米德篇》提到的年轻人。

[65]环球剧院（Globe Theatre）位于伦敦，一五九九年由莎士比亚所在的宫内大臣剧团建造，一九一三年六月二十九日毁于火灾。

小兔彼得的故事

从前，有四只小兔子，他们的名字分别是：噗噗、篷篷、棉花尾巴和彼得。他们和母亲一起住在一个沙坝上一棵非常大的枞树根底下。

一天清晨，兔子太太说：“听我说，宝贝儿们，你们可以去田野里或是小路上玩，不过，不要到麦克格雷格先生的菜园里去。你们的父亲就是在那里出的事，他被麦克格雷格太太做成了馅饼。现在去玩吧！不要调皮捣蛋。我要出门了。”

然后，兔子太太就拎着一个篮子，带着她的伞，去了森林里的面包店。她买了一条黑面包和五个加了葡萄干的小圆面包。

噗噗、篷篷和棉花尾巴都是乖乖的小兔子，一起到小路上摘黑莓去了，而彼得却是个淘气的家伙，直接跑到麦克格雷格先生家的菜园里去了。然后，他从门下面的缝隙中挤了进去！

他先吃了一些生菜，又吃了一些菜豆，后来又吃了一些小萝卜。然后，他觉得有些不舒服，便去找芹菜吃。但是，刚绕过一片黄瓜架，他就和麦克格雷格先生碰了个面对面！

麦克格雷格先生当时正趴在地上移栽卷心菜的秧苗，他一跃而起，就来追彼得。他手里挥舞着一个耙子，喊道：“站住，小偷！”

彼得简直害怕得要命，他在菜园中慌张地乱窜，因为他已经忘记通往大门的路了。他在卷心菜地中丢了一只鞋，然后在马铃薯菜地中掉了另一只鞋。鞋子丢了之后，他四脚着地，可以跑得更快了。我猜按照那速度，他本可以逃脱的，可他不走运，一头撞进了醋栗树丛交织成的网里，他外套上的大纽扣都被醋栗网给挂住了。彼得穿的是一件有黄铜纽扣的蓝色外套，非常新呢。

彼得认为自己无处可逃，一定会被抓住的，眼泪便大颗大颗地滚了下来。他的抽泣声被几只好心的麻雀听到了，他们焦急地飞过来，鼓励他不要放弃。

麦克格雷格先生拿着一个筛子走了过来，他想用筛子扣住彼得，但好在彼得及时地从网中挣脱了，只把外套甩在了那里。他迅速跑进工具棚，跳进了一个水壶中。那真是一个绝妙的藏身之处——只是里面装了很多水。

麦克格雷格先生十分确信彼得就躲在工具棚里，他觉得彼得可能就藏在了某个花盆的下面。所以，他把花盆一个个地翻过来，仔细地检查。

就在这时，彼得打了个喷嚏：“阿嚏！”麦克格雷格先生立刻就向他冲去，抬脚想踩彼得，而彼得从一扇窗户跳了出去，这一跳带翻了三个花盆。那窗户很小，麦克格雷格先生过不去，而且，他追彼得追得已经有些累了，所以他便回去继续干活了。

彼得坐下来歇了一会儿，他已经快喘不过气来了，因为害怕，浑身都在发抖，他根本不知道该怎么出去。而且，因为刚才藏在水壶里，他现在浑身都湿漉漉的。过了一会儿，他开始在菜园中漫无目的地走动，一跳一跳地，速度并不快，一边跳一边四处查看。他在墙上发现了一扇门，不过门却是锁着的，下面的缝隙太小了，根本没有办法让一只胖乎乎的小兔子挤过去。

有一只年迈的老鼠在石头台阶上跑来跑去，把豌豆和菜豆运到森林的家中。彼得向她打听大门的方向，但是老鼠的嘴里塞着一颗大豌豆，没有办法说话。她只是朝彼得摇了摇头。彼得又哭了起来。

然后，他想直接穿过菜园，但越走越迷糊。不一会儿，他走到了一个池塘边，麦克格雷格先生就是在这里给水壶灌水的。此刻，有一只白猫正在池塘边，盯着池塘里的金鱼，她非常非常安静地坐着，一动也不动，只是她的尾巴尖儿时不时地会抖一下，仿佛那尾巴尖儿是活的一样。彼得觉得最好直接走开不要打扰她，他曾经听自己的表哥——小兔本杰明——说过关于猫的事情。

他又回头向工具棚走，突然，在离他很近的地方传来了一阵锄头锄地的声音：嚓嚓，咔咔，咔咔，嚓嚓。彼得赶紧钻到灌木丛下面躲了起来。又过了一会儿，什么事情也没有发生，他又出来了，爬上一辆独轮手推车，偷偷地打量四周。第一眼，他就看到了麦克格雷格先生正在洋葱地里面锄地。他背对着彼得，而越过他便是大门。

彼得悄悄地从独轮车上下来，用自己最快的速度顺着黑醋栗丛后面的一条直直的小路拼命地跑。

他拐弯的时候被麦克格雷格先生看到了，但彼得已经顾不得了。他直接从大门下面的缝隙钻了出去，终于离开了菜园，安全地到了树林里。

麦克格雷格先生把彼得的小外套和鞋子挂在一根杆子上，当作稻草人，来吓唬乌鸫。

彼得头也不回地一路跑回到大枞树下的家里。他累坏了，直接扑倒在兔子洞中柔软舒服的沙土地上，闭上了眼睛。兔子妈妈正在忙着做饭，她很好奇彼得的外套和鞋丢到哪里去了。要知道，这是半个月内彼得弄丢的第二件外套和第二双鞋了！

那天晚上，彼得不是很舒服。

妈妈把彼得放进床里，然后泡了一些甘菊茶给他喝。

“睡前喝一勺。”妈妈说。

不过，那天晚上，噗噗、篷篷和棉花尾巴的晚餐可是面包、牛奶和黑莓呢。

松鼠坚果金的故事

这是一个关于一条尾巴的故事——这条尾巴属于一只红色的小松鼠，他的名字叫作坚果金。他有一个兄弟，名字叫闪闪莓，另外他还有许多堂兄弟和表兄弟。他们都住在湖边的一个树林里。

在湖的中央，有一个小岛，岛上长满了树和结坚果的灌木，在那些树中，有一棵空心的橡树，那是一只名叫老灰灰的猫头鹰的家。

有一年秋天，坚果都成熟了，榛树的叶子有的金灿灿的，有的绿油油的——坚果金和闪闪莓以及其他所有小松鼠都走出树林，来到湖边。

他们用小树枝做成木筏子，划向猫头鹰岛去采坚果。每只小松鼠都带了一个小口袋，手握一根大桨，将尾巴撑起并展开作为船帆。他们还带了三只肥肥的老鼠，作为送给老灰灰的礼物，他们将老鼠放在了老灰灰家门前的台阶上。

闪闪莓和其他的小松鼠都深深地鞠躬，很有礼貌地说：

“灰灰老先生，您能慷慨地允许我们在您的岛上采坚果吗？”

但是坚果金却格外鲁莽无礼。他上蹿下跳，像颗小红樱桃一样，同时还唱着：

猜谜啦，猜谜啦，啰哒哟！
一个小小人，穿着红红袄！
手里拿权杖，喉咙卡石头；
要是你猜到，给你四便士。

这个谜语像山一样古老，而灰先生却根本没有理会坚果金。他只是自顾自地闭着眼睛，睡他的觉。

松鼠们在他们的小口袋里面装满了坚果，傍晚时划着筏子回家了。

第二天一早，他们又都来到了猫头鹰岛，闪闪莓和其他松鼠带来了一只肥美的鼹鼠，将它放在老灰灰家门口的石头上，说：

“灰先生，您能好心允许我们再采些坚果吗？”

但是坚果金没有表现出一点儿敬意，他开始手舞足蹈，上下乱跳，他手里握着一根荨麻逗弄灰灰老先生，同时唱道：

灰老先生啊！来猜谜呀！
墙里长着尖尖刺，
墙外长着尖尖刺，
要是你敢碰碰刺，
尖尖刺儿咬死你！

灰先生突然间醒了过来，将鼹鼠带到了自己的房子里。他当着坚果金的面关上了门，很快，柴火点燃了，从树顶上冒出了一缕青烟。坚果金透过钥匙孔向内窥探，他又唱道：

屋也满，洞也满！
你却收不齐一碗！

松鼠们在整个岛上四处寻找坚果，填满他们的小口袋。而坚果金却收集了一些橡果——有黄色的，也有深红色的——他坐在一个山毛榉树的树桩上，将橡果当作弹珠玩，一边玩一边盯着灰灰老先生的家门口。

第三天，松鼠们很早就起床了，然后就去钓鱼，他们钓到了七条肥硕硕的米诺鱼，作为送给老灰灰的礼物。他们划着筏子过湖，在一棵长得弯曲的栗子树下登上猫头鹰岛。

闪闪莓和另外六只小松鼠各拿着一只肥肥的米诺鱼。而坚果金则表现得更没有礼貌了，根本没有带礼物。他却跑在最前面，边跑边唱：

荒野里的那人来问我：
“海里长了多少草莓果？”
我细细想过才开口说：
“和林里红鲱鱼一样多。”

但是老灰灰先生对谜语不感兴趣，即便把答案告诉他，他也不感兴趣。

第四天，松鼠们给老灰灰带了六只肥肥的甲虫作为礼物，这对老灰灰来说，就像是李子布丁里面的李子一样好。每只甲虫都被包在一片阔叶草的草叶中，还用松针封了口。

而坚果金像以往一样粗野地唱着：

老灰先生！来跟我猜个谜！
英格兰的面粉，西班牙的水果，
在一场小雨中相遇成了一国；
把它们装进口袋里，再系上绳子，
你要是能告诉我谜底，我就给你一枚戒指。

坚果金这么说实在很可笑，因为他根本没有什么戒指可以送给老灰灰。

其他的松鼠在坚果灌木中钻来钻去地采坚果，但是坚果金却从石楠丛中找到了知更鸟的插针垫，在上面插满了松针。

第五天，松鼠们带了野蜂蜜作为礼物，那蜜又甜又黏，他们把蜜放下之后，都舔起了自己的手指。这蜜是他们从山顶上一个大黄蜂的蜂巢中偷来的。

而坚果金上蹿下跳地唱着：

哼哼嘣！嗡嗡嗡！哼嘣嗡！
我翻过那三叉山，
遇到一群美丽的猪；
有的黄脖子，有的黄脊背，
他们是三叉山上面
最最美丽的小猪！

面对坚果金的粗鲁无礼，老灰灰嫌弃地转过脸不看他。不过他倒是把蜜吃光了。

松鼠们把他们的小口袋里装满了坚果。

而坚果金却坐在一块大而平的石头上，用一颗沙果和一些青青的枞树球果玩起了保龄球游戏。

第六天是一个星期六，松鼠们最后一次来到猫头鹰岛，他们用一个灯芯草笼子装了一颗新下的鸡蛋，作为送给老灰灰的最后的告别礼物。

但是坚果金跑在最前面，一边大笑，一边大叫：

矮胖子躺在河中央，
脖子上缠着白床罩，
四十个医生和四十个工匠，
也没法子把矮胖子扶起来！

老灰灰对鸡蛋很感兴趣，他睁开了一只眼睛，然后又闭上了。但他一直没有说话。

坚果金却越来越粗鲁：

老灰先生！老灰先生！
马笼头，马缰绳，
挂在国王厨房门上；
国王全部的马，
国王全部的人，
也没法子把马笼头和马缰绳，
从国王厨房的门上取走！

坚果金像一束阳光一样跳来跳去，但老灰灰还是什么都没有说。

坚果金又开始唱道：

波尔的亚瑟挣断了链，
一路咆哮着上了岸！
苏格兰国王用尽了力，
也没法把亚瑟赶回去！

坚果金发出呼呼的叫声，好像风声一样，他助跑了一段，然后一跃而起，跳上了老灰灰的头。立刻，传来一阵翅膀的扑打声，接着便是一场厮打，还传来了一声很大声的“吱”！

其他松鼠全都四散奔逃，躲进了灌木丛中。等他们蹑手蹑脚地回来时，从大树后面偷看，只看到老灰灰坐在自家门前的台阶上，眼睛闭着，仿佛什么事都没有发生过，而坚果金此时却在老灰灰的马甲口袋里。

这似乎就是故事的结局了，不过还不是。

老灰灰把坚果金带到了自己的屋子里，提住他的尾巴，要把他的皮剥下来。但坚果金奋力挣扎，以致挣断了尾巴，他猛地冲上楼梯，从阁楼的窗子跳出去逃跑了。

直到今天，你要是在树上看到坚果金，请他猜个谜语，他准会向你扔树枝，并跺着脚大喊：

咯——咯——咯——咔——啦——啦——咯——咔——咔！

格洛斯特的裁缝

很久以前，有一段时期，人们都佩带宝剑，头戴假发，穿着有印花垂饰的连身外套。那时候的绅士们都穿着带褶皱花边的衣服，或用棱纹丝和塔夫绸做成的镶金色花边的马甲。就在那时，在格洛斯特住着一个裁缝。

他的店铺在西门街上，他每天都坐在店铺窗户前，双腿盘坐在工作台上，从早到晚地缝制衣服。

只要白日的光线充足，他就不停地又裁又缝，拼接缎子、花纹布、亮光绸。那些布料都有着奇怪的名字，在格洛斯特裁缝生活的时代，它们都是很昂贵的。

尽管裁缝为他的邻居们缝制上等丝绸的衣服，但是他自己却非常非常穷——他是一个戴着眼镜的小老头儿，脸上满是皱纹，双手苍老得变了形，身上总穿着已经磨破了边的旧衣服。

他裁剪衣服的时候从来都不浪费，总是将绣花布料物尽其用。在他的桌子上放着很多小布头和小碎片。“实在太零碎了，什么也做不了——只能给老鼠们做马甲了。”裁缝说。

在临近圣诞节的一个寒冷冬日，裁缝开始为格洛斯特的市长做一件外套。这件外套要用樱桃红色的灯芯绸制成，绣很多紫罗兰和玫瑰花，另外还要配上一件奶白色的缎子马甲，马甲要镶上薄纱和绿色精纺纱的花边。

裁缝不停地忙碌着，还不断地自言自语。他量完了绸缎的尺寸，然后又将绸缎翻过来又翻过去，用他的大剪刀将布料裁成需要的形状，桌子上留下了很多樱桃红色的布头。

“根本不够宽啊，只能斜着裁开，根本不够宽，只能给老鼠做披肩了！给那些小坏家伙做缎带喽！给老鼠！”格洛斯特的裁缝说。

雪花飘落，落在小小的铅制窗框上，光线越来越弱，裁缝结束了一天的工作，所有裁好的丝绸和缎子都摊放在桌子上。

桌上有做外套用的十二片布料和做马甲用的四片布料，另外还有口袋布、袖口和纽扣，全都放得井然有序。外套的衬里用的是上好的黄色塔夫绸，而马甲的扣眼则需要用樱桃红的丝线锁边。所有的东西都准备就绪，明天一早便能够将它们缝在一起，该量的都量好了，要用的也都充足——不过，里面还缺少一团用来锁边的樱桃红色的捻丝线。

天黑下来后，裁缝离开了他的店铺，他晚上不睡在这里。他关好了窗户，锁好门，装好钥匙走了。夜里，这里什么人都没有，只有一群棕色的小老鼠，他们进出根本不需要什么钥匙！

在格洛斯特，所有老房子的木头护墙板后面，都有小老鼠们的楼梯和秘密活板门，老鼠们通过窄窄的通道从一座房子到另一座房子，他们不用走街道就可以跑遍全镇。

裁缝离开店铺，冒着雪艰难地回到了自己的家。他住的地方离学院巷很近，就在学院草地门口的旁边。尽管那并不是一所多大的房子，但是裁缝太穷了，他也只租得起那里的厨房。

他和他的猫住在那里，他的猫叫辛普金。由于白天裁缝都在店铺工作，所以白天的时候辛普金独自在家，他也很喜欢老鼠，只是他从来不给他们做缎子外套！

“喵？”裁缝打开门的时候猫叫道，“喵？”

裁缝回答说：“辛普金，我们要发财了，不过我现在可真是要累散架了。拿着这枚四便士的硬币，这可是我们最后的四便士了，带上一个小瓷罐，去买一便士的面包、一便士的牛奶和一便士的香肠。噢，辛普金，用我们四便士中的最后一便士，给我买一卷樱桃红色的捻丝线。千万不要把最后一便士弄丢了呀，辛普金，不然我就真要完蛋了，那样我就没有丝线锁边了。”

然后辛普金又“喵”了一声，便带着钱和小罐子，走进了黑暗之中。

裁缝累极了，累得都要生病了。他坐在炉火旁边，自言自语地说着那件精美绝伦的外套。

“我会发财的——这儿要斜着裁——格洛斯特的市长会在圣诞节当天的上午结婚，他定做了一件外套和一件绣花的马甲——要用黄色塔夫绸做衬里——塔夫绸是足够用了，可剩下来的布头只够给老鼠做些披肩——”

就在这时，裁缝猛地一惊，因为突然间，从厨房另一头的橱柜里传来了一阵簌簌的响声，打断了他的思绪，那声音听起来是这样子的：

“踢嗒！”“踢嗒！”“踢嗒踢！”

“那是什么声音？”格洛斯特的裁缝说着从椅子上跳了起来，橱柜上摆满了各种罐子、柳叶花纹的盘子、茶杯和大杯子。

裁缝穿过厨房，然后一动不动地站在橱柜旁边，透过眼镜仔细观察着。从一个茶杯下面又传来了细细的声音：

“踢嗒！”“踢嗒！”“踢嗒踢！”

“这可真古怪。”格洛斯特的裁缝说着，就将倒扣着的茶杯拿了起来。从里面走出了一个小小的老鼠女士，她向裁缝行了个屈膝礼，然后便跳下橱柜，跑进了护墙板下面。

裁缝又坐回到火边，烤着自己冰冷的双手，又自顾自地嘀咕起来：

“马甲要用桃红色缎子裁出来——用漂亮、华丽的丝线绣出玫瑰花蕾！我把最后的四便士给了辛普金真的明智吗？可还有二十一个扣眼需要樱桃红色的丝线锁边啊！”

而就在这时，从橱柜里又传来了一阵小小的响动：

“踢嗒！”“踢嗒！”“踢嗒踢！”

“这可是太不同寻常了！”格洛斯特的裁缝说着，便将另一个倒扣着的茶杯翻了过来。这次走出来一只老鼠先生，他对着裁缝鞠了一躬。

然后，从整个橱柜中传来了一阵“踢嗒踢嗒”的合唱，声音全都一起响起，彼此相互应和，就好像一扇被蛀空的旧百叶窗中的蠹虫一般合唱着——

“踢嗒！”“踢嗒！”“踢嗒踢！”

从茶杯下面，从碗下面，从盆子下面，走出越来越多的小老鼠，他们都跳下橱柜，跑进护墙板的下面去了。

裁缝坐回炉火边，靠近炉火，叹息着：“有二十一个扣眼需要樱桃红色的丝线锁边啊！要在星期六的中午前完成，而现在已经是星期二晚上了。到底该不该把那些老鼠放走呢？他们肯定都是被辛普金抓起来的。唉唉，我要完了，我没有丝线锁边了。”

小老鼠们又出来了，听着裁缝的话，他们回忆着那件外套的式样，低声讨论着塔夫绸的衬里和小小的老鼠披肩。

然后，在一瞬间，他们全都跑到了护墙板后的通道中，吱吱叫着，呼唤着伙伴，从一座房子跑到另一座房子。等到辛普金提着一罐子牛奶回来的时候，裁缝的厨房中已经一只老鼠都没有了。

辛普金打开门，一跃而入，恼怒地叫了一声：“呼——呼——喵！”猫在恼怒的时候就会这么叫。辛普金很讨厌下雪，他的耳朵里和脖子后面的衣领下都钻进雪了。他把面包和香肠放到了橱柜上，用力吸着鼻子，使劲嗅着。

“辛普金，”裁缝说，“我的丝线呢？”

而辛普金只是把牛奶罐放在橱柜上，狐疑地看着茶杯。他还想着要把肥肥的小老鼠做晚餐呢！

“辛普金，”裁缝说，“我的丝线呢？”

但是辛普金把一个小包偷偷地藏到了茶壶里，然后冲着裁缝又吐口水又咆哮，如果辛普金可以说话的话，那他肯定是在问：“我的老鼠呢？”

“唉唉，我真完蛋了。”格洛斯特的裁缝说着，悲伤地爬到了床上。

一整夜，辛普金都在厨房里四处寻觅、搜索，检查橱柜，寻找护墙板下面，还探入他藏锁边丝线的茶壶中寻找，但是一只老鼠都没有找到！

裁缝只要在睡梦中嘟囔低语，辛普金便会发出“喵——呜——噢——”的声音，制造出奇怪而恐怖的噪音，猫在夜里总是会这么做。

可怜的老裁缝发起了高烧，躺在他的四柱床上辗转反侧，在睡梦中还嘟囔着：“没有丝线了！没有丝线了！”

他病了一整天，第二天也没有起来，第三天也是。那件樱桃红色的外套到底会怎么样呢？在西门街上的裁缝店里，裁好的绣花丝绸和缎子就摆在桌上，上面还有二十一个扣眼，可是店铺的窗户紧闭，门也被牢牢锁住，有谁能来缝起它们呢？但是这可拦不住棕色的小老鼠们，他们不需要任何钥匙，便能够在格洛斯特所有的老房子中进进出出，行走无碍。

在街上，赶集的人们为了烘焙他们的圣诞馅饼，顶风冒雪地去买鹅和火鸡，但是辛普金和可怜的老裁缝却没有圣诞大餐。

裁缝病着在床上躺了三天三夜，然后便到了圣诞节前夜。夜越来越深了，月亮爬过屋顶，爬上烟囱，俯视着通向学院巷的巷道。窗户里面没有灯，房子里面也都没有声音，整个格洛斯特市都在白雪的覆盖下陷入了沉睡之中。而辛普金依然想要他的老鼠，他站在四柱床旁边喵喵地叫着。

据古老的故事说，在圣诞节前夜到圣诞节早晨之间的深夜中，所有的动物都能讲话，只是很少有人能听到，或是明白那些动物说的什么。

当大教堂的钟声敲响了十二点的时候，答案揭晓了，就如同是钟声的回声一般。辛普金听到了那个声音，他走出裁缝家的门，在雪中徘徊。

从格洛斯特城所有的屋顶、山墙和老旧的木头屋子传来了一千个愉快的声音，唱着古老的圣诞歌曲——包括所有我曾经听过的老歌，还有一些我不知道的歌曲，就像是“惠廷顿的钟声”。

最初发声的，也是声音最响亮的，是公鸡们的歌声：“夫人，起床了，需要烤馅饼了！”

“噢，真好，真好，真好，真好！”辛普金叹息着。

一个阁楼上亮着灯光，并传来了跳舞的声音，猫们从那个方向过来。

“嘿呀，扭吧，扭吧，有猫还有小提琴！格洛斯特所有的猫都参加了——除了我。”辛普金说。

在木屋檐下面，八哥和麻雀唱着圣诞馅饼之歌；大教堂塔楼中的寒鸦醒了过来；尽管已经是午夜时分了，画眉鸟和知更鸟都在唱歌；空气中充满了微微呢喃的旋律。

但是这一切令可怜而饥饿的辛普金更加恼怒。

特别是一个木头隔板后面传来的微弱的尖细叫声令他格外烦躁。我觉得那后面的是蝙蝠，因为他们的嗓音总是非常微小，尤其是在严寒的黑暗中，他们就像格洛斯特的裁缝一样，会在睡梦中说话。他们说着一些神秘的事情，就像这样的东西：

蓝蝇嗡嗡嗡，
蜜蜂哼哼哼，
他们嗡又哼，
我们也一样！

辛普金走开了，他晃了晃耳朵，就像是有一只蜜蜂飞进了无边帽里。

从西门街上的裁缝店里透出一丝光亮。辛普金蹑足悄悄靠过去，透过窗户向里面窥望，窗户内点满了蜡烛。里面传来剪刀的咔嚓声、丝线的窸窣声，以及小老鼠们大声而欢快的歌声：

二十四个裁缝呀，
齐去抓蜗牛，
最厉害的那个呀，
怕碰蜗牛尾；
蜗牛伸出触角，
就像长角小母牛，
快跑啊，裁缝们，快点跑！
不然她会把你们都吃掉！

没有停顿，小老鼠们又接着唱道：

筛了太太的燕麦，
磨了太太的面粉，
放入栗子壳中，
等上一个小时。

“喵！喵！”辛普金打断了他们，他用爪子挠着门。但是钥匙放在裁缝的枕头下面，他没有办法进去。

小老鼠们一阵大笑，然后又唱起了另一首歌：

三只小老鼠，坐下来纺纱。
小猫经过了，偷偷看过来。
你们在干吗，我的好伙计？
我们做衣服，给绅士们穿。
让我进去吧，帮你们咬线头儿？
哦，不用了，猫小姐，你会咬断我们的头！

“喵！喵！”辛普金叫道，“嘿嘿摇一摇？”小老鼠们回应道：

嘿嘿摇一摇，乖乖小宠物！
伦敦的商人穿红衣，
领子用丝绸，镶边是金子，
商人们走路喜洋洋！

小老鼠们敲着顶针打节拍，不过这些歌辛普金都不喜欢，他在店铺的门口嗅来嗅去，喵喵叫着。

然后我买了，
一个瓦罐和一个水罐，
一个纸罐和一个废水罐，
总共只花了一个子儿——

“就放在厨房的橱柜上。”粗鲁的小老鼠们又加了一句。

“喵！嚓！嚓！”辛普金挠着窗台，屋内的小老鼠们都站了起来，一齐用低低的呢喃声喊道：“没有丝线了！没有丝线了！”他们关上了百叶窗，把辛普金彻底关在了外面。

但是通过百叶窗的缝隙，他依然能够听到屋内顶针的碰击声，还有小老鼠们的歌声：

“没有丝线了！没有丝线了！”

辛普金离开店铺，回了家，一路上都在沉思。回到家后他发现可怜的老裁缝已经退烧了，正安详地睡着。然后，辛普金踮着脚走到橱柜边，从茶壶中拿出了那一小卷丝线，借着月光看着它。想到那些善良的小老鼠，他为自己做过的坏事感到很愧疚。

第二天一早，裁缝醒了过来，他看到的第一样东西，就在他那碎布缝成的被子上面，是一卷樱桃红色的捻丝线，而忏悔的辛普金就站在他的床边。

“哎呀，我真是累坏了呀，”格洛斯特的裁缝说，“不过我有了丝线呀！”

裁缝起床穿好衣服，走到街上，辛普金跑在他前面。这时候阳光灿烂，照耀着雪地。

八哥们在烟囱上面吹着口哨，画眉鸟和知更鸟在唱着歌，不过他们用的是他们特有的语言，不再像夜里那样唱出歌词了。

“哎呀，”裁缝说，“我有了锁边线了，可是我没有力气呀，也没有时间，顶多能够锁好一个扣眼，现在已经是圣诞节当天早晨了！格洛斯特的市长中午就要举行婚礼了——可他的樱桃红外套在哪里呢？”

他打开了西门街上的小店铺的门，辛普金跑了进去，就像是在期待着什么。但是里面没有一个人！甚至连一只棕色的小老鼠都没有。

工作台都被打扫清理过了，线头和丝绸的碎片全都被清走了，地面上也没有什么东西。不过就在桌子上面——噢，真让人惊喜！裁缝发出一声惊呼——就在那里，在他放着裁剪好的丝绸的地方——现在那里放着一件最美丽的外套和一件绣花的缎子马甲，格洛斯特的任何一任市长都没有穿过这么精致、美丽的衣服。在外套的前襟上有玫瑰和紫罗兰的绣花，而马甲上面则绣着罂粟花和矢车菊。除了还有一个扣眼需要锁上樱桃红色的丝线锁边以外，其他的一切工作都完成了。那个扣眼上别着一张小纸片，上面用极小极细的字写着：

没有丝线了。

从此以后，格洛斯特的裁缝的好运来了，他变得身体强壮，又非常富有。他做最好的马甲，为格洛斯特所有有钱的商人和全国各地所有体面的绅士服务。

从来都没有人见过那么好看的褶边或是绣花那么精美的袖口和衣襟。不过，最引人注目的是他锁的那些扣眼。那些扣眼针脚如此整齐——真是太整齐了，所以我都怀疑一个戴着眼镜、指关节变形，还戴着顶针的老人怎么可能缝出这样的针脚。那些扣眼的针脚是那么细小——实在太细小了，看上去就像是小老鼠缝出来的一样。

小兔本杰明的故事

一天早晨，一只小兔坐在河岸边，他支棱着耳朵，听着一匹小马“嘚嘚嘚嘚”的马蹄声。

一辆双轮马车顺着路而来，赶车的人是麦克格雷格先生，在他旁边坐着麦克格雷格太太，麦克格雷格太太戴着她最好的一顶帽子。

他们刚从路上过去，小兔本杰明就溜到路上，一蹦一跳地出发了，他要去拜访住在树林中的亲戚，那树林就在麦克格雷格先生的菜园后面。

那片树林中满是兔子洞，其中最整洁、沙子最多的一个洞中住着本杰明的姨妈和他的表兄妹们——噗噗、篷篷、棉花尾巴和彼得。

老兔子太太是一个寡妇，她靠着织兔毛手套和围巾来赚钱养家（我曾经还在一个市场中买到过一套）。她还卖药草、迷迭香茶和兔子烟草（就是我们称作薰衣草的东西）。

小兔本杰明并不太想去探望姨妈。他绕到枞树的后面，差点儿被他的表弟彼得绊倒。彼得正独自坐在那里，看起来十分可怜，身上裹着一条红色的棉布手帕。

“彼得，”小兔本杰明叫了他一声，声音非常轻，“你的衣服被谁拿走了？”

彼得回答说：“是麦克格雷格先生菜园里的稻草人。”然后他描述了自己如何被追得满菜园跑，如何丢了鞋子和外套的经历。

小兔本杰明坐在表弟旁边，告诉他麦克格雷格先生已经赶着马车出门了，麦克格雷格太太也跟着出去了，肯定一整天都不会回来，因为她戴着她最好的帽子。

彼得说要是下雨就好了。

这时，老兔子太太的声音从兔子洞中传出来，她喊道：“棉花尾巴！棉花尾巴！给我再拿点甘菊来！”

彼得说，如果可以出去散散步的话，他想他会感觉好点的。于是，彼得和本杰明手拉着手，走到了森林尽头的围墙顶上。从那里，他们能够俯瞰麦克格雷格先生的菜园。他们看得一清二楚，彼得的外套和鞋子都在稻草人身上，稻草人头上还戴着一顶麦克格雷格先生的旧苏格兰圆扁帽。

小兔本杰明说：“从门底下钻进去会把衣服弄坏的，最好能顺着那棵梨树爬下去。”

彼得头朝下栽了下去，不过倒没什么大问题，因为下面的菜地刚刚犁过，十分松软。那里已经种了生菜。他们在整片菜地里都留下了奇怪的小脚印，特别是小兔本杰明，他的脚上穿着木底鞋。

小兔本杰明说首要大事是要拿回彼得的衣服，一会儿可能需要用到彼得现在围着的手帕。他们把衣服从稻草人身上脱了下来。夜里下了雨，鞋子里面有水，外套也有些缩水了。

本杰明试了试苏格兰圆扁帽，但是那帽子对他来说太大了。然后，他建议说，他们应该用手帕包满洋葱，作为送给他姨妈的小礼物。

彼得似乎并不开心，他似乎总是听到许多声音。而本杰明则完全相反，他自得其乐地吃了一片生菜叶子。他说他过去经常跟着他爸爸到菜园里，摘生菜做星期天的大餐。

（小本杰明的爸爸是兔子先生老本杰明。）

生菜当然非常好吃。

彼得什么都没有吃，他说他想要回家了。一会儿工夫，他就丢了一半的洋葱。小本杰明说带着这么多菜，他们没有办法爬上梨树原路返回了。他大胆地领头走向了菜园的另一头。他们在木板小径上走了一段，那小径就在洒满阳光的红砖墙下面。

老鼠们坐在家门口的台阶上，砸着樱桃核。他们冲着小兔彼得和小兔本杰明挤眉弄眼。

彼得不一会儿又把手帕包松开了。他们走在花盆、木架和水桶中间，彼得听到的噪音比刚才还要大，他的眼睛瞪得像棒棒糖一样大！他走在他表哥前面一两步远处，走着走着突然停了下来。

就在墙的拐角那里，两只小兔子看到了令他们大惊失色的东西——一只猫！

小兔本杰明只看了一眼，便立刻带着彼得和洋葱躲进了一个倒扣的大篮子下面。

那只猫站起身来，伸展了一下身体，走过来，嗅了嗅那个篮子。也许她喜欢洋葱的气味。反正，她坐到了篮子的顶上。而且，她在那里一直坐了五个小时。

我没有办法给你们画出彼得和本杰明躲在篮子下面的画面，因为那里太黑了，而洋葱的气味太可怕了，把小兔彼得和小兔本杰明都熏哭了。

太阳落到了树林后面，已经快到傍晚了，那只猫依然坐在篮子上面。后来，从墙上传来一阵“啪嗒”“啪嗒”的声音，还落下来了一些灰泥。猫抬头望去，看到老本杰明先生正昂首阔步地走在上面的围墙顶上。他抽着一个装着兔子烟草的烟斗，手中还拿着一根小树枝。他正在找自己的儿子。

老本杰明先生一点儿都没把那只猫放在眼里。他猛地一跃，从墙上跳下来，跳向那只猫，把它从篮子上打了下去，然后将它踢到了温室里，还从它身上抓下了一把毛。那只猫吓了一大跳，都没有反抗。

老本杰明先生把猫赶入温室后，便锁上了温室的门。然后他走回篮子边，揪着他的儿子小本杰明的耳朵，将他拉了出来，用手中的小细枝抽了他一顿。然后他又将他的外甥彼得也拉了出来。接着他又拉出了包着洋葱的手帕，阔步走出了菜园。

半个小时后，麦克格雷格先生回来了，他注意到很多令他困惑的事情。似乎有个穿着木鞋的人在整个菜园里走了个遍——只是那脚印出奇的小。他也搞不明白那只猫是怎么把自己关进了温室里，又是怎么把外面的门锁给锁上的。

彼得回到家，得到了妈妈的谅解，因为她很高兴看到彼得找回了自己的鞋子和外套。棉花尾巴和彼得将手帕叠起来，而老本杰明先生则把洋葱穿起来，跟一束束的草药和兔子烟草一起挂在了厨房的屋顶上。

两只坏老鼠的故事

从前，有一座非常漂亮的玩偶房，红色的砖墙，白色的窗子，上面还挂着真正的平纹细布做的帘子，房子上有一个前门和一个烟囱。

这座房子是属于两个洋娃娃的，她们分别叫作露辛达和简，更确切地说，露辛达是这里的女主人，不过她从来都不吩咐厨娘做饭。简是厨娘，但是她从来都不做饭，因为玩偶房买来的时候饭已经做好了，就装在一个有很多锯末的盒子中。里面有两只红红的龙虾、一根火腿、一条鱼、一个布丁，另外还有几个梨和橙子。这些东西没办法从盘子上拿下来，不过它们都非常漂亮。

一天早上，露辛达和简坐在娃娃车中出去兜风了。育儿室中没有一个人，非常安静。而就在这时，从壁炉旁边的角落，传来了一阵窸窣的声音，在那里壁脚板的下面有一个洞。

大拇指汤姆把头探出来待了一会儿，然后又缩了回去。大拇指汤姆是一只老鼠。

一分钟之后，他的妻子汉卡曼卡也把头探了出来，她发现育儿室中没有人，便大胆地走到了煤箱下面的油布上。

玩偶房在壁炉的另一边，大拇指汤姆和汉卡曼卡小心翼翼地穿过壁炉前的地毯。他们推了推玩偶房的前门——门并没有闩上。

大拇指汤姆和汉卡曼卡到了玩偶房的楼上，向餐厅望去，然后他们高兴地吱吱叫了起来！

那边桌子上摆的菜肴是多么丰盛可口啊！桌上还摆了锡质的小勺子、铅质的刀叉，桌边还有两个娃娃坐的椅子——一切都太方便了。

大拇指汤姆立刻开始拿刀切火腿。那火腿色泽诱人，黄中透红。但是他手中的刀却卷了刃，还伤到了他，他把手指放在嘴里吮吸说：“这东西没煮熟，太硬了，你来试试，汉卡曼卡。”

汉卡曼卡站在椅子上，拿起另一把铅质的刀去剁火腿。

“这简直和干酪店里的火腿一样硬。”汉卡曼卡说。她非常用力，搞得火腿从盘子中飞了出去，滚到了桌子底下。

“别管它了，”大拇指汤姆说，“递给我些鱼，汉卡曼卡。”

汉卡曼卡挨个拿起桌上的小勺试着去盛鱼。那鱼是粘在盘子上的。然后大拇指汤姆发火了，他把火腿放到屋子中间，拿起火钳子和煤铲子狠狠地砸下去——乓，乓，砰，砰！火腿变成了碎片，因为在闪亮的彩绘外表里面，火腿是石膏做的。

大拇指汤姆和汉卡曼卡的愤怒和失望并没有因此结束。他们又打烂了布丁、龙虾、梨子和橙子。由于鱼没有办法从盘子中弄出来，他们把鱼连同盘子一齐放到了厨房的炉火中，那火是用皱纹纸做的，看上去又红又热，但是鱼却没有点着。大拇指汤姆顺着厨房的烟囱爬了上去，钻出来看了看烟囱顶，那里没有一点儿烟灰。

大拇指汤姆爬上烟囱的时候，汉卡曼卡又发现了另一桩令她失望的事。她看到橱柜中有一些小罐子，上面贴着标签，写着大米、咖啡、西米等字样，但是当她把罐子翻转过来时，里面掉出来的只有一些红色和蓝色的珠子，没有别的。

然后两只老鼠开始了全力大破坏——特别是大拇指汤姆！他把简卧室里抽屉柜中的衣服拿出来，从顶层的窗户扔了下去。

而汉卡曼卡则发扬了勤俭持家的作风，在把露辛达的羽毛靠枕抖落出来一半之后，她突然想起自己正缺一个羽毛床垫，于是在大拇指汤姆的帮助下，她搬着那个靠枕下了楼，拖过炉前的地毯。要把那靠枕塞进老鼠洞可真不容易，但是他们最后还是塞进去了。

然后，汉卡曼卡又回去拿了一把椅子、一个书柜、一个鸟笼和好多其他的小东西。书柜和鸟笼都进不了老鼠洞。汉卡曼卡便将这些东西丢到了煤箱子后面，又去拿了一个摇篮。

汉卡曼卡带着另一把椅子返回来的时候，楼梯平台那边突然传来了一阵说话声。两只老鼠匆匆地回到了他们的洞中，这时娃娃们回到了育儿室。

眼前的景象实在令简和露辛达大吃一惊！

露辛达坐在翻倒的炉子上，看着这一切，简靠着厨房的橱柜，脸上带着微笑——但是她们俩谁都没有对此发表什么评论。

书柜和鸟笼被从煤箱子那儿寻了回来，但是汉卡曼卡已经拿走了摇篮，还拿走了好几件露辛达的衣服。她还拿走了一些有用的壶和锅以及其他几样东西。

拥有这个玩偶房的小女孩说：“我要买一个穿警察衣服的洋娃娃！”

但是她的保姆说：“我要设个老鼠夹子。”

这就是两只坏老鼠的故事了，但其实他们并没有特别特别坏啦，因为大拇指汤姆为他破坏的一切支付了赔偿费。他在炉前地毯的下面捡到了一个变形的六便士的硬币。在圣诞节前夜，他和汉卡曼卡把这个硬币放到了露辛达和简的一只袜子里面。

而每天一大早，所有人都还没有醒来的时候，汉卡曼卡则会带着簸箕和扫把，来打扫那个玩偶房。

碰碰螺太太的故事

从前，有一个叫露西的小女孩，她住在一个叫作“小镇”的农场上。她是一个乖巧的小姑娘——不过她总是把她的手帕弄丢。

有一天，小露西大叫着来到农场的院子中——噢，她是这么叫的：“我丢了我的手帕！三条手帕还有一件围裙！你看到了没有，花斑小猫？”

小猫仍然继续清理着自己的白爪子，所以露西又去问一只芦花母鸡：

“小母鸡萨利，你看到过三条手帕吗？”

但是芦花母鸡跑进了一个谷仓里，嘴里咯咯咯地叫着：

“我光着脚呢，光着脚呢，光着脚啊！”

然后，露西去问栖息在树枝上的雄知更鸟。雄知更鸟用他闪亮的黑眼睛斜了露西一眼，然后掠过矮土墙，飞走了。

露西爬上矮土墙，眺望着小镇后面的那座山——那座山好高，好高，直入云霄，高得好像没有顶。她觉得自己看见山腰的草地上有些白色的东西摊着，就在很远很高的地方。

露西以她的小短腿能达到的最快速度向山上爬，她沿着那条陡峭的山间小径向上跑，一直向上，一直向上，直到小镇被她远远地抛在了下面，她甚至可以把一颗石头直接丢到烟囱里面去。

没一会儿，她来到了一眼泉水旁边，泉水汩汩地从山腰流出。有人把一个罐子放在了泉水边的石头上接水，但是水都溢了出来，因为那罐子只有鸡蛋杯那么大。小径的沙子是湿的，那上面有许多非常小的脚印。

露西继续跑啊跑。

小径的尽头在一块大石头的下面。那里的草很矮，但是很绿，那里有欧洲蕨的茎做的晾衣杆，中间的绳子则是编织成辫子状的灯芯草，上面挂着小小的衣服夹子——但是没有手帕。不过那里还有别的东西——那是一扇门！直接通向山里面，在门内有人正唱着歌：

纯白无瑕又干净，哦！
小小饰边平又整，哦！
光滑滑，热乎乎，
红红的锈斑呀，从来都没有，哦！

露西敲了一下门，然后又敲了一下，打断了这歌声。一个有点儿受惊的声音问道：“是谁啊？”

露西打开门，你们猜露西在里面看到了什么？——那里有一间整洁可爱的厨房，石板铺的地面，木头的梁柱，就和普通农场里的厨房一样。只是屋顶实在很矮很矮，露西的头几乎就顶着房顶了，厨房里面的水壶和锅也都很小，屋里所有的东西都很小。

屋子里有一股好闻而又热乎乎的焦味儿，有一个矮矮胖胖的人，手里拿着一个熨斗，正紧张地望着露西。她身上穿的印花长袍被卷了起来，在她的条纹衬裙外面是一条大围裙。小小的黑鼻头抽抽，又嗅嗅，她的眼睛不停地眨呀眨。而在她帽子的下面——露西长着黄色的鬈发——这个小人儿却长着刺。

“你是谁？”露西问，“你看到我的手帕了吗？”

这个小人儿行了一个屈膝礼说：“噢，是的，如果你愿意的话，可以叫我碰碰螺太太。噢，对，你相信吗，我可是一个优秀的浆洗工。”然后，她从洗衣篮里面拿出了一样东西，然后摊开，铺在了熨衣毯上。

“那是什么？”露西问，“那不是我的手帕吗？”

“噢，不是的，抱歉，这件小小的红色马甲是雄知更鸟的。”

然后她熨了那件马甲，叠好放在一边。接着她又从衣架上拿下了什么。

“那不是我的围裙吗？”露西说。

“噢，不是的，抱歉，这是鹪鹩珍妮的缎子桌布。看看这一大片酒渍！非常难洗。”碰碰螺太太说。

碰碰螺太太的鼻子抽了抽，又抽了抽，然后又大声地抽了一下，她的眼睛眨了眨，又眨了眨。然后她从火上拿下了另一个热烫的熨斗。

“那是我的一块手帕！”露西叫道，“那是我的围裙。”

碰碰螺太太将围裙熨好，压出褶皱，抖开荷叶边。

“噢，真是太好了！”露西说，“那些有着手套一样分指的长长的黄东西是什么呀？”

“噢，那是小母鸡萨利的长筒袜——看看呀，她整天刨地，脚后跟儿都破了。用不了多久她就得光着脚了。”碰碰螺太太说。

“哎呀，还有一块手帕——不过不是我的，这条是红色的吧？”

“噢，不是你的，抱歉，这是老兔子太太的，上面一股洋葱味！我洗它的时候是单独洗的，怎么也洗不掉那股气味。”

“那是我的另一块手帕。”露西说，“那些好玩的白色的小东西是什么呀？”

“那是小花斑猫的露指手套。我只需要熨烫它们，因为是她自己洗的。”

“那是我的最后一块手帕！”露西说，“你放到水淀粉盆子里面的是什么？”

“这是小老鼠汤姆的小衬衫前襟——他讲究得过分！”碰碰螺太太说，“我已经熨完了。现在得把一些衣服晾一晾。”

“那些可爱的、软软的、毛茸茸的东西是什么？”露西问。

“噢，这些是斯凯高尔的小羊们的羊毛外套。”

“他们的外套能脱下来吗？”露西问。

“噢，是的，来看看肩膀上的这些羊的记号。有一个是盖茨盖斯的记号，还有三个是小镇的。他们总是在这些要洗的东西上做标记。”碰碰螺太太说。

然后，她把各种各样、大大小小的衣物挂了起来，里面有老鼠们的棕色小外套；还有一件软软的黑色鼹鼠皮马甲；松鼠坚果金的一件红色无尾燕尾服；小兔彼得的一件缩水严重的蓝色夹克；还有一件衬裙，上面没有标记，应该是在洗涤的过程中掉了——最后，篮子终于空了。

接着，碰碰螺太太去泡了茶，一杯给自己，一杯给露西。她们坐在壁炉前的一条长凳上，侧脸看着彼此。碰碰螺太太端着茶杯的手是极深的棕色，皱皱的，上面还挂着肥皂泡，她的长袍和帽子上都是刺到外面的“发针”，所以，露西并不想坐得离她太近。

她们喝完茶后，把衣服包进包袱里。露西的手帕都被叠起来放到了干净的围裙里，然后用一根银别针固定好。然后，她们往火里添了些泥炭，便出了门，锁好门后，把钥匙藏在了门缝下面。露西和碰碰螺太太带着一大包衣服。一路飞快地走下了山。

下山的路上，时不时就会有小动物从草丛中出来迎接她们，她们最先见到的是小兔彼得和小兔本杰明。碰碰螺太太把干净、整洁的衣服给了他们，所有的小动物和小鸟都对碰碰螺太太非常感激。等她们到了山脚，来到了矮土墙边时，她们手上已经只剩下露西的小包袱了。

露西拿着小包袱爬上了矮土墙，然后转身向这位洗衣妇道晚安并表示谢意。但是真奇怪啊！碰碰螺太太既没有等着她道谢，也没有要洗衣费，而是一路跑啊跑啊跑，跑上山——她的荷叶边小白帽怎么不见了呢？她的围巾呢？她的袍子呢？还有她的衬裙呢？

哎呀，她可真小啊——颜色是非常深的棕色——而且还长满了刺！

哎呀！碰碰螺太太原来就是一只刺猬。

有些人说小露西是在矮土墙上面睡着了——但她又是怎么找到三条干净的手帕和一件围裙，而且还用安全别针固定在一起的呢？

另外，我曾经见过通向那座叫作“猫铃山”后山中的门，另外我和亲爱的碰碰螺太太可是很熟的！

馅饼和馅饼模子的故事

从前，有一只叫瑞比的小猫，她邀请一只叫公爵夫人的小狗来吃茶点。

“尽早过来，我亲爱的公爵夫人，”瑞比的信中这么写道，“我们会享用一些非常非常好的东西。我正在用一个带粉色花边的馅饼盘烘烤它哦。你从来都没吃过这么好吃的东西！你会把它全都吃掉的。而我会吃松饼，亲爱的公爵夫人。”

公爵夫人读了这封信，并写了回信：“我非常开心受到邀请，我会在四点一刻拜访。但是，真是巧了，我本来是正要邀请你来我这里吃晚饭的，我亲爱的瑞比，我想请你吃一些最最美味的东西。”

“我会准时到达的，我亲爱的瑞比，”公爵夫人写道。在信的结尾，她又加了一句，“我希望不是老鼠肉吧？”不过，她又觉得这样写似乎显得不太礼貌，所以，她便把“不是老鼠肉吧”给划掉了，改成了“我希望天气会很好”，然后将信交给了邮差。但是，她一直在琢磨瑞比的馅饼，所以，便将瑞比的信读了一遍又一遍。

“我真担心死了，万一是老鼠肉呢！”公爵夫人自言自语道，“我真的真的吃不下老鼠肉馅饼。而我却不得不吃，因为这是一次聚会。我本来要烤牛肉和火腿馅饼的。一个粉边的白色馅饼盘子！我的盘子也是这样的，和瑞比的一样，都是在塔比莎·特迟特的店里买的。”

公爵夫人走进她的食品储藏室，从架子上拿下馅饼，看了又看，说道：“一切都准备好了，就差放进烤箱里了。多么可爱的馅饼脆皮啊，我把原料放在了一个小的馅饼模子里面，这样就能保持脆皮的形状，我还用叉子在馅饼中间戳了一个洞，以便排出蒸汽——啊，我真希望能够吃我自己的馅饼啊，而不是用老鼠肉做的馅饼。”

公爵夫人思来想去，于是又把瑞比的信读了一遍：

“一个带粉边的白色馅饼盘——你会把它整个吃光的。‘你’是指我——那么，瑞比自己是不会尝那个馅饼了？一个粉边的白色馅饼盘！瑞比肯定会去外面买松饼……啊，真是个好主意！为什么我不趁瑞比不在的时候赶过去，把我的馅饼放进瑞比的烤箱里面呢？”公爵夫人非常满意自己的聪明。

同时，瑞比接到了公爵夫人的回信，一得知小狗能来赴约，她便把她的馅饼放到了烤箱里。她有两个烤箱，摞在一起，一个上，一个下。她的烤箱上有些把手和手柄都是装饰性的，并不能打开烤箱。瑞比把馅饼放到了下面的那个烤箱里，那个烤箱的门很难开。

“上面的这个烤箱烤东西时火太急了。”瑞比对自己说，“这是一个用最细嫩的老鼠肉混合培根做成的馅饼，我把所有骨头都去掉了，上一次我宴请公爵夫人的时候，她差一点儿被鱼骨头给卡得窒息了。她吃东西有点儿快——又总是大口大口地吃。但她是一只非常有教养又文雅的小狗，如果选朋友，她相比于塔比莎·特迟特表姐来说，简直是好得太多了。”

瑞比又加了一些煤，并清理了炉边。然后她带着一个水罐到了井边打水，灌满水壶。接着，她开始整理房间——这个房间既用作客厅也用作厨房。她在前门把垫子抖了抖，又放平整，炉前地毯是一块兔皮的。她擦拭了时钟和壁炉台上的摆设，又把桌椅都擦得光可鉴人。

然后，她又铺开一张干净的白色桌布，从壁炉旁的壁橱中拿出了她最好的一套瓷器摆好。那茶杯是白色的，上面有粉色玫瑰的花纹，而餐盘则是蓝白相间的。

瑞比摆放好桌子之后，便带上一个罐子和一个蓝白相间的盘子，穿过田野，去附近的农场，取牛奶和黄油。回来之后，她看了看下面的烤箱，里面的馅饼看上去非常不错。

瑞比围上围巾，戴上小帽，提上篮子，又出门了，她要去村子里的商店买一包茶叶、一磅方糖和一瓶果酱。

而就在这时，公爵夫人离开了她在村子另一头的家。

瑞比在街上碰到了公爵夫人，看到她也提着篮子，上面盖着一块布。她们彼此弓身致意，但没有说话，因为她们就要聚会了。

公爵夫人一走过街角，离开瑞比的视线，便跑了起来——直奔瑞比的家！

瑞比去了商店，买了需要的东西，和塔比莎·特迟特表姐开心地闲聊了几句，然后才离开。

后来，塔比莎表姐提起这件事时，非常不屑。

“请一只小狗！就好像索里这一带没有猫一样！居然准备了一个馅饼在下午茶时吃！真想得出来！”塔比莎·特迟特表姐说。

瑞比又去了蒂莫西面包房买了松饼，然后才回家。就在她从前门进去的时候，后面的走廊传来了窸窸窣窣的声音。

“我相信这不是喜鹊捣的乱，而且勺子也都锁起来了。”瑞比说。不过，没发现有人在那儿。瑞比用了些力气打开下面的烤箱门，把馅饼翻了一面。已经开始闻到烤鼠肉散发出的阵阵诱人的香气了。

而就在这时，公爵夫人从后门溜了出去。“真奇怪，我把我的馅饼放到烤箱里时，并没有看到瑞比的馅饼呀。四处都找不到，我可是把整个房子都找了一遍了。我把馅饼放到了上面那个漂亮的热烤箱里。但转不动其他的把手，那些应该都是样子货。”公爵夫人说，“但我真希望能够拿走那个用老鼠肉做的馅饼！真不知道瑞比到底把它放哪儿去了，我听到瑞比回来了，不得不从后门跑出来。”

公爵夫人回到家，把她美丽的黑色皮毛梳了好几遍，然后从自家的花园里面采了一束花，作为送给瑞比的礼物，时间就这么过去了，时钟敲了四下，已是四点钟了。

瑞比把自己的家仔细检查了一遍，确认不论是壁橱里还是食品储藏室里面都没有藏着任何人，然后便上楼去换了一条裙子。她穿上一件淡紫色的丝绸长裙，围上一件绣花的平纹细布围裙和一条披肩。

“真奇怪，”瑞比说，“我不记得自己把抽屉打开了，是有人想要试我的连指手套吗？”她又下楼去，泡了茶，然后把茶壶放在炉架上。接着她又看了看下面的烤箱，馅饼现在已经变成了诱人的焦黄色，热气腾腾的。

她坐在壁炉前面，等候小狗的来访。“还好我用了下面的那个烤箱。”瑞比说，“上面那个肯定太热了。真奇怪，壁橱的门怎么是开着的呀？难道家里真的有人进来过？”

四点整，公爵夫人出发去参加聚会。她以自己最快的速度穿过了村子，结果到瑞比家的时候太早了，所以就站在通向瑞比家的小巷子里等了一会儿。

“瑞比有没有把我的馅饼从烤箱里拿出来呢？”公爵夫人说，“另一个用老鼠做的馅饼到底哪儿去了？”

四点一刻，准时响起了一声最最文雅的轻轻的敲门声。“瑞比斯通太太在家吗？”公爵夫人站在门廊上问道。

“快请进！你好吗，我亲爱的公爵夫人？”瑞比叫道，“希望你一切都好啊！”

“非常好，谢谢，你呢，我亲爱的瑞比？”公爵夫人说，“我给你带了些花来，好香的馅饼味啊！”

“啊，这花真漂亮啊！对，馅饼是老鼠肉和培根馅的。”

“先别谈吃的，我亲爱的瑞比，”公爵夫人说，“好漂亮的茶巾啊！……那馅饼翻过面了吗？还在烤箱里吗？”

“我觉得还需要五分钟才能熟。”瑞比说，“再等一小会儿就行。趁着这工夫，我来倒茶吧！你需要加糖吗，亲爱的公爵夫人？”

“噢，加，谢谢！我亲爱的瑞比，我能拿一块放在我的鼻子上吗？”

“当然可以，亲爱的公爵夫人，你的请求实在太有礼貌了！你真是太可爱太可亲了！”

公爵夫人把糖放在自己的鼻子上，嗅了嗅，说：“馅饼的味道闻起来真好啊！我真喜欢牛肉和火腿——我是说老鼠肉和培根——”慌乱之中，她把糖弄掉了，不得不钻到茶几下面去寻找，所以她并没有看到瑞比拿馅饼的时候打开的是哪一个烤箱。

瑞比把馅饼放在了桌子上，那馅饼散发的香味真能让人口水都流下来。

公爵夫人嚼着糖从桌布下面钻了出来，在一把椅子上坐好。

“我先替你切馅饼，我要吃些松饼和果酱。”瑞比说。

“你真的更喜欢松饼吗？小心那馅饼模子！”

“抱歉，你说什么？”瑞比说。

“要我把果酱递给你吗？”公爵夫人匆忙掩饰说。

馅饼十分可口，松饼绵软热乎，都很快被一扫而光，特别是馅饼！

公爵夫人心里想，“我觉得如果我自己拿馅饼的话会更好，尽管瑞比在切的时候似乎并没有注意到什么。这馅饼被烘烤得成了这么细的小块儿！我真不记得我把肉馅切得这么碎。我猜，这个烤箱比我自己的那个要加热快。”

“公爵夫人吃得可真快！”瑞比一边给自己的第五块松饼涂黄油一边想。

馅饼盘子很快就空了！公爵夫人已经吃了四块馅饼，正用勺子探索着什么。

“再来点儿培根吧，亲爱的公爵夫人？”瑞比说。

“谢谢了，亲爱的瑞比，我只是想找馅饼模子。”

“馅饼模子？亲爱的公爵夫人，你说什么？”

“就是让馅饼外皮保持形状的馅饼模子。”公爵夫人黑色皮毛下的脸红了。

“噢，我没用馅饼模子，亲爱的公爵夫人，”瑞比说，“我觉得做老鼠肉馅饼没必要用馅饼模子。”

公爵夫人仍在用勺子搜寻着。“我找不到了。”她焦急地说。

“没有馅饼模子。”瑞比看起来十分困惑。

“是啊，真的，亲爱的瑞比，它跑哪儿去了呢？”公爵夫人说。

“肯定没有，亲爱的公爵夫人。我不喜欢在布丁和馅饼里放铁皮做的东西，太不方便了——尤其是有人狼吞虎咽的时候。”瑞比又低声补充说。

公爵夫人看起来惊慌不已，继续在馅饼盘里面挖。

“我姑婆斯奎提娜，也就是塔比莎·特迟特表姐的祖母，就因为在圣诞节的时候，吃李子布丁吃到了一个顶针给噎死了。我从来都不在我的布丁和馅饼里面放金属做的东西。”

公爵夫人大吃一惊，把馅饼盘翻了过来。

“我只有四个馅饼模子，现在都在壁橱里面呢。”

公爵夫人发出一阵哀号。

“我要死了！我要死了！我吞了一个馅饼模子！啊，亲爱的瑞比，我觉得不舒服极了。”

“不可能，亲爱的公爵夫人，根本没有什么馅饼模子。”

公爵夫人呻吟着，哀号着，身子摇来摇去。

“我觉得很难受，我肯定吞了一个馅饼模子。”

“馅饼里面什么都没有。”瑞比很郑重地说。

“有的，有的，亲爱的瑞比，我肯定吞下去了。”

“我拿个枕头给你靠着吧，亲爱的公爵夫人，你觉得那馅饼模子在哪儿？”

“啊，我觉得我浑身都难受，亲爱的瑞比，我肯定吞了一个大个儿的馅饼模子，还有着尖锐的扇贝状的边儿。”

“需要我去请医生吗？我把勺子锁起来就行。”

“噢，需要，需要！快去请玛戈蒂医生，亲爱的瑞比，他就姓馅饼，是只喜鹊[1]，他肯定能理解我的。”

瑞比将公爵夫人安顿在壁炉前的扶手椅里面，便匆匆忙忙地出门去请村子里的医生。她在铁匠铺找到了医生。医生正在忙着把生锈的钉子放到一个墨水瓶里面，墨水瓶是他在邮局得到的。

“熏猪腿？哈？哈？”他说话的时候头侧向一边。

瑞比解释说自己的客人吞下了一个馅饼模子。

“菠菜？哈？哈？”他说着，动作迅速地走到了瑞比身边。

他跳着向前走，速度非常快，瑞比不得不跑着才能跟上。这简直太引人注目了。整个村子的人都看到瑞比请来了医生。

“我就知道她们肯定会吃撑了的！”塔比莎表姐说。

就在瑞比找医生时，公爵夫人遇到了一件怪事儿。她独自坐在壁炉前面，呻吟着，觉得非常不开心。

“我怎么会吞下去呢！馅饼模子那么大的东西！”

她站起身，走到桌边，又用勺子在馅饼盘里面找馅饼模子。

“没有，这里没有，我肯定放了一个进去的，除了我也没有人吃馅饼，我肯定是把它吞下去了！”

她又坐下来，满怀悲伤地盯着壁炉架。火噼噼啪啪地烧着，火苗舞动着，这个时候，有什么东西发出了嗞嗞的声音。

公爵夫人吃了一惊！她打开了上层烤箱的门，从里面冒出了浓郁的牛肉和火腿的香气，里面是一个诱人的棕色馅饼。而通过脆皮上面的那个小孔，可以看到里面有一个小小的金属做的馅饼模子。

公爵夫人长长地吸了一口气。“那么，我肯定是吃了老鼠肉了！……难怪我觉得难受呢！……不过如果我吞了馅饼模子，应该会更难受吧。”公爵夫人回想着，“这要跟瑞比解释，可真是尴尬死了！我想我还是把我的馅饼放到后院，什么都不说的好。等我回家的时候，可以绕到后面把它拿走。”她把馅饼放到了后门外面，又在火炉边坐好，闭上眼睛。等瑞比带着医生来到的时候，她似乎已经睡熟了。

“熏猪腿，哈，哈？”医生说。

“我觉得好多了。”公爵夫人一下子醒了过来。

“听到这消息我真的非常开心。他给你带来了药，亲爱的公爵夫人！”

“我觉得，他光给我把把脉就够了。”公爵夫人后退一步，离嘴里含着东西悄悄走进的喜鹊远了一些。

“这只是个面包药丸，你最好吃了它，然后再喝点牛奶，亲爱的公爵夫人。”

“熏猪腿？熏猪腿？”医生说，这时公爵夫人咳嗽起来，甚至有点儿透不过气。

“别说了！”瑞比控制不住自己的脾气了，“给，拿上这块果酱面包，立刻出去，到院子里去！”

“熏猪腿和菠菜！哈哈哈！”后门外传来玛戈蒂医生欢欣雀跃的喊叫声。

“我觉得好多了，亲爱的瑞比，”公爵夫人说，“你说，我是不是最好在天黑之前回家呢？”

“也许的确是这样的，亲爱的公爵夫人，我给你找条又漂亮又暖和的披肩，你可以挽着我的胳膊，我送你回去。”

“无论如何我都不该再麻烦你了，我真的觉得好多了。玛戈蒂医生的一颗药——”

“如果它把你吞的馅饼模子给治好了，那的确是很神奇啊！明天吃过早饭之后我会去拜访你，看看你睡得怎么样。”

瑞比和公爵夫人热情地道别，公爵夫人便启程回家。走到巷子一半的地方，她停了下来，转身看了看，瑞比已经回屋关上了门。公爵夫人偷偷地翻过栅栏，绕到瑞比房子的后面，向院子里望。

猪圈的顶上，玛戈蒂医生和三只寒鸦正落在那里。寒鸦们正在吃着馅饼的脆皮，而喜鹊医生正在喝着馅饼模子里面的肉汤。

“熏猪腿，哈，哈！”看到公爵夫人的小黑鼻子从拐角处露出来的时候，他叫道。

公爵夫人一路跑回了家，感觉自己简直蠢透了！

当瑞比出来准备打一桶水回去洗茶具的时候，看到院子中间有一个打碎了的粉边白底的馅饼盘。馅饼模子就在水泵下面，是玛戈蒂医生故意留在那里的。

瑞比吃惊地盯着它：“谁遇到过这样的事情呢！那么真的是有一个馅饼模子？而我的馅饼模子都在厨房的壁橱里面。好吧，我从来都没有用过。下一次我要是再办聚会——还是邀请塔比莎表姐吧。”

[1]喜鹊的英文和馅饼的英文都是pie。

渔夫杰瑞米先生的故事

从前，有一只青蛙，名字叫渔夫杰瑞米先生，他住在池塘边金凤花丛中一座潮湿的小房子里。

他的食品储藏室和后面的过道里四处都是水，湿漉漉的，非常容易滑倒。但是杰瑞米先生就喜欢把脚弄湿，没有人因此而数落过他，他也没有因此感冒过。

当他向屋外看去，看到大滴大滴的雨点溅落在池塘上的时候，非常开心。

“我应该弄些虫子去钓鱼，钓一盘子米诺鱼当晚餐。”渔夫杰瑞米先生说，“如果我能够抓到五条以上的鱼，我就请我的朋友乌龟奥尔德曼·托勒密先生和艾萨克·牛顿爵士来吃饭。只是奥尔德曼先生吃生菜。”

杰瑞米先生穿上了他的雨衣和雨鞋，拿上鱼竿和篮子，便大步跳着前往他停放小船的地方。

小船是圆圆的，绿色的，很像一片荷叶，被绑在池塘中央的一株水生植物上。杰瑞米先生用一根芦苇做篙，将船推向了开阔的水域。“我知道一个钓米诺鱼的好地方。”渔夫杰瑞米先生说。

杰瑞米先生把芦苇篙插入泥中，然后将船拴在上面固定。之后他便盘腿坐好，开始收拾他的钓鱼用具。他的红色小浮标非常可爱，他的鱼竿是一根坚韧的草茎，他的鱼线是一根细长的白色马尾毛，他在鱼线尾端绑上了一个扭来扭去的小虫子。

雨点敲打着他的后背，将近一个小时，他一直盯着浮标。

“这有点儿无聊，我觉得我应该吃些午餐。”渔夫杰瑞米先生说。

他撑船回到原来的地方，从篮子里面拿了一些午餐出来。

“我要吃一个蝴蝶三明治，然后等雨停了再钓。”渔夫杰瑞米先生说。

一只大个儿的水甲虫在荷叶船下面，用力拉他一只雨鞋的鞋尖。

杰瑞米先生把腿又盘了盘，这下水甲虫够不到了，他继续吃午餐。

在池塘的边上，偶尔会有东西移动，发出一阵“沙沙”或是“啪啪”的声音。

“我敢肯定那不是老鼠。”渔夫杰瑞米先生说，“我觉得我最好还是离开这里。”

杰瑞米先生又将船向外划了一小段距离，将鱼饵放入水中，几乎立刻就有东西咬了钩，浮标猛烈地上下晃动。

“一条米诺鱼！一条米诺鱼！我钩住他的鼻子了！”渔夫杰瑞米先生叫着，一边用力地拉鱼竿。但真是个可怕的意外啊！杰瑞米先生钓上来的并不是一条滑溜肥美的米诺鱼，而是棘鱼小杰克·夏普，他身上可是长满了刺！小棘鱼在船上拼命挣扎，四处乱刺乱咬，直到最后快喘不过气来了。然后他又跳回了水里面。一群其他种类的小鱼把头探出水面，嘲笑渔夫杰瑞米先生。

而杰瑞米先生则哭丧着脸坐在他的小船边——吮吸着他疼痛的手指，盯着水面——然后，更加糟糕的事情发生了。我是说，如果杰瑞米先生没有穿雨衣的话，那可真会是一件极端可怕的事情了。

一只超级巨大的鳟鱼游了过来——噗噗噗噗——伴随着一阵水花声，他一口咬住了杰瑞米先生。“哦！哦！哦！”然后转身潜入了池塘底部。但是鳟鱼非常不喜欢雨衣的味道，没过半分钟就把杰瑞米先生吐了出去，只是他把杰瑞米先生的雨鞋吞下去了。

杰瑞米先生弹回到水面上，就像是一个软木塞或是汽水瓶中的气泡一般。然后他用尽全力游向了池塘的岸边。一触到岸，他就挣扎着爬出水面，然后穿过草地一路跳回了家。他的雨衣已经都碎了。

“幸好那不是一条梭鱼！”渔夫杰瑞米先生说，“我把鱼竿和篮子给丢了，不过这不重要，因为我肯定我绝对不敢再去钓鱼了。”他在手指上缠了一些胶布。他的两个朋友都来他家吃晚饭，但是他没有鱼招待他们了。不过他的食品储藏室里面还有其他食物。

艾萨克·牛顿爵士穿着他的黑色和金色相间的马甲。奥尔德曼·托勒密先生用网兜提了一棵生菜过来。

他们没有享用到美味的米诺鱼，但是却吃了配瓢虫酱的烤蚂蚱，青蛙们都觉得这是一道佳肴。但我觉得味道肯定很糟糕！

小猫汤姆的故事

从前，有三只小猫，他们的名字分别是：咪咪、汤姆和娃娃。他们都有一身可爱的软皮毛，喜欢在门前的台阶上打滚，喜欢在尘土中玩耍。

但是有一天，他们的妈妈——塔比莎·特迟特太太——要招待朋友们来喝茶，所以，她在客人到来之前，把小猫们拎到了屋中，给他们洗澡，换上新衣服。她先是擦洗了他们的脸（先是娃娃）。接着她梳顺了他们的毛（接着是咪咪）。然后她梳了他们的尾巴和胡子（最后是汤姆）。汤姆非常淘气，他不断乱抓。

塔比莎太太给娃娃和咪咪穿上了干净的围裙和领巾，然后她从一个抽屉中拿出了各式各样优雅却不舒服的衣服，来打扮她的儿子汤姆。小猫汤姆很胖，而且他个子很高，有好几颗扣子都绷掉了。他妈妈只好把扣子再缝上去。

三只小猫都被收拾整齐后，塔比莎太太很不明智地让他们去了花园里，以免他们在她烤黄油吐司的时候碍事。

“不要弄脏衣服，孩子们！你们必须直立着用后腿走路。离脏兮兮的灰坑远点儿，离母鸡萨利远些，别靠近猪圈和泥潭鸭。”

娃娃和咪咪摇摇晃晃地走在花园的小路上。没多久，她们就踩到了围裙，摔了个嘴啃泥。等她们再站起来的时候，衣服上已经有了好几块绿色的污渍。

“咱们去爬假山吧，坐到花园围墙上去。”娃娃说。

她们把围裙前后调换了一下，让后面朝前，然后便蹦蹦跳跳地出发了。娃娃的白色领巾掉落到了地上。

小猫汤姆的后腿上穿着裤子，没有办法跳跃，只能一点一点地爬上假山，他弄断了些蕨草，衣服上的扣子掉得东一个西一个。等到他爬上围墙的时候，身上的衣服已经七零八落了。娃娃和咪咪合力将他拉了上来，他的帽子掉了下去，其余的扣子全都绷开了。

就在小猫们身陷麻烦的时候，传来了一阵“啪啦”“啪嗒”的声音，原来有三只泥潭鸭顺着坚硬的大路走了过来，他们排成一列，迈着方步——“啪啦！”“啪嗒！”“啪啦！”“啪嗒！”

他们停下脚步，站成一排，盯着小猫们。泥潭鸭们的眼睛很小，看上去很吃惊。然后，其中两只鸭子——瑞贝卡和杰迈玛——捡起了地上的帽子和领巾，戴到了自己身上。

咪咪不禁哈哈大笑，笑得从墙上跌了下去。娃娃和汤姆跟在她后面也下去了，在下去的过程中，娃娃和咪咪的围裙以及汤姆剩下的衣服都掉了下来。

“过来！泥潭鸭德雷克先生，”娃娃说，“过来帮我们给他穿上衣服！过来给他扣扣子！”

泥潭鸭德雷克先生慢悠悠地侧着身子走了过去，捡起地上散落的那些衣服。但是他把衣服都穿在了自己的身上。那些衣服穿在他身上非常不合适，比在小猫汤姆身上还不合适。

“真是个晴朗的早晨啊！”泥潭鸭德雷克先生说。然后他和杰迈玛、瑞贝卡继续迈着方步前行——“啪啦！”“啪嗒！”“啪啦！”“啪嗒！”

这时，塔比莎·特迟特来到花园，看到她的小猫们都在墙上，身上的衣服却都不见了。她把他们从墙上拉下来，狠狠地揍了一顿，然后把他们带回了家中。

“我的朋友们马上就要来了。你们几个不能被人看见，真是快被你们气死了！”塔比莎·特迟特太太说。她把他们赶去了楼上，很遗憾，她对朋友们说小猫们生了麻疹卧病在床，当然，这并不是真的。相反，他们没在床上，根本没有。

不知怎么，就在茶会举行的时候，楼上总是传来阵阵噪音，打扰了茶会优雅安静的氛围。

我想，有一天，我会再写一本书，很大的一本，告诉你们关于小猫汤姆的更多故事。

至于泥潭鸭，他们去了一个水塘里。那些衣服立刻就都掉下去了，因为衣服上都没有纽扣。从那之后，德雷克、杰迈玛和瑞贝卡一直在寻找那些衣服。

泥潭鸭杰迈玛的故事

要是你看到一群新出壳的小鸭子和一只母鸡在一起的画面，你肯定会觉得非常有意思——下面来听听泥潭鸭杰迈玛的故事，因为农夫的妻子不让她自己孵蛋，她气坏了。

她的嫂子，泥潭鸭瑞贝卡太太却非常乐意把孵化工作交给其他人来完成——“我可没有耐心在一个窝里趴上二十八天。你也不会有的，杰迈玛。你会让那些蛋变冷，你知道你会的。”

“我希望能够孵化我自己的蛋，我愿意自己孵化它们！”杰迈玛嘎嘎叫着。她想把自己的蛋藏起来，不过总是会被农夫找到并拿走。

杰迈玛越来越绝望，最后决定在远离农场的地方做个窝。在一个明媚的春日午后，她沿着那条通往山里的马车道出发了。出发时，她披上一条披肩，戴着一顶阔边女帽。到达山顶的时候，她看到不远处有一片树林。她觉得那里是个非常安全而且安静的地方。

杰迈玛并不太习惯飞行。她向山下助跑了一段距离，她的披肩噗啦啦翻飞，然后她跃向了空中。她开始得很好，便飞得很漂亮。她从树顶上掠过，直到看到树林中有一片开阔地带，那里没有树木，也没有灌木。

杰迈玛降落得非常笨拙，然后便开始四处溜达，想要选一个方便而干燥的地点做窝。她很喜欢一个在高高的毛地黄丛中的树桩。但是，她惊讶地发现，有一个穿着非常优雅的绅士正坐在那个树桩上看报纸。他长着黑色的尖耳朵，还有浅棕色的胡须。

“嘎？”杰迈玛把头和头上的小帽子侧向一边，“嘎？”

那位绅士把视线从报纸上移开，好奇地看着杰迈玛。

“夫人，您迷路了吗？”他说。他有一条浓密的尾巴，他就坐在尾巴上面，因为那个树桩有些潮湿。

杰迈玛觉得他很文雅，也很英俊，便解释说自己并没有迷路，只是想找一个方便而干燥的地点搭窝。

“啊！是这样？真的吗？”那位长着浅棕色胡须的绅士说，还好奇地看着杰迈玛。他把报纸折起来放到了自己大衣后摆的口袋中。

杰迈玛正在抱怨那只多管闲事的母鸡。

“真的？真有意思。我真希望自己能见一见那只家禽，我很愿意教会她管好自己的事情就够了。至于做窝嘛——这没有什么难的。我的小木屋里有很多羽毛。不，亲爱的夫人，您不会打扰任何人了，只要您高兴，您愿意在那里待多久都可以。”长着毛茸茸长尾巴的绅士说。他领着杰迈玛来到了毛地黄丛中一座看上去废弃了很久、很破旧的房子。

这房子是用木柴和草皮盖的，两个摞在一起的破桶充作烟囱。

“这里是我避暑的地方，您会觉得我的洞穴——也就是我冬季的住所——没有这里这么方便。”好客的绅士说。

在房子后部，有一个几乎快塌了的棚子，那是用旧的肥皂箱子搭成的。绅士打开了门，领着杰迈玛进了屋。那棚子里面，四处都是羽毛——多得几乎让人喘不过气来，但是真的非常舒适而且柔软。

杰迈玛看到这么多羽毛，非常吃惊。但是这里实在太舒服了，她毫不费力地就做好了一个窝。

当杰迈玛出来的时候，那位长着浅棕色胡须的绅士正坐在一根原木上读报纸——至少他是把报纸摊开的，只是眼睛却从报纸的上方向外瞄着。

他太有礼了，似乎因为让杰迈玛回家过夜而非常抱歉。他承诺说一定会用心照顾她的窝，直到她第二天再回来。

他说他喜欢蛋和小鸭子，看到一个这么漂亮的窝出现在他的小棚子里他会非常骄傲。杰迈玛每个下午都过来，她在窝中一共产下了九颗蛋，全都是青白色的，个头非常大。那位迷人的绅士对它们极力赞美，他总是在杰迈玛不在的时候翻动那些蛋，一遍遍地数它们的个数。

最后，杰迈玛对他说，她决定要从第二天开始孵蛋了。“我要带一口袋玉米过来，这样我就不用离开我的窝，可以一直到这些蛋都被孵化出来，不然它们会变冷的。”认真的杰迈玛说道。

“夫人，我请您不要那么麻烦地把口袋带来，我可以给您提供燕麦。但是在您开始无聊的孵蛋工作前，我想要款待您一次。咱们办一个餐会吧，就咱们两个。我能请您从农场的菜园带些香草过来吗？这样才能做出美味的煎蛋饼。鼠尾草、百里香、薄荷，再带两个洋葱和一些香芹。我能提供做填料的猪油——做煎蛋饼的猪油。”浅棕色胡须的好客绅士说。

杰迈玛头脑简单，鼠尾草、洋葱这些东西都没有引起她的怀疑。她去了农场的菜园，用嘴一点点地啃了各种香草——而这些香草正是做烤鸭时填在鸭腹中的填料。然后，她又摇摇晃晃地走进厨房，从篮子里面弄到了两个洋葱。

就在她离开厨房时牧羊犬凯普看到了她。“你拿洋葱做什么？你每天下午都一个人跑去哪里了，杰迈玛？”

杰迈玛对牧羊犬很敬畏，于是便将事情的前因后果都告诉了他。

牧羊犬听着，他聪明的脑袋便开始思考，当杰迈玛描述说那位礼貌的绅士长着浅棕色的胡须时，牧羊犬咧嘴笑了。他问了几个关于树林的问题，问清了那房子和小棚子的确切位置。然后他走出农场，跑到村子里，找到了和屠夫一起出门的两只小猎狐犬。

这可能是杰迈玛这辈子最后一次走上那条马车道了，这是一个阳光灿烂的午后，她身上背着好几把香草，包里装了两个洋葱，走起来很费劲。她飞过树林，落到了长着毛茸茸长尾巴的绅士的房子对面。

绅士正坐在原木上，嗅着空气，时不时还不安地环顾一下树林。杰迈玛降落的时候，他猛地一惊，跳了起来，说道：

“等你看完你的蛋，就来屋里。把那些煎蛋饼用的香草给我。利落点！”

他说话很无礼，杰迈玛从来都没有听他这么说过话。她很吃惊，而且很不舒服。

杰迈玛在小棚子里的时候，听到小棚子后传来了一阵脚步声。有一个长着黑鼻子的家伙透过门底下的缝嗅了嗅，然后锁上了门。杰迈玛立刻害怕起来。

过了一阵儿，传来了一些非常可怕的声音——有吼叫声，犬吠声，咆哮声，哀号声，尖叫声和呻吟声。那位长着迷人胡须的绅士不见了踪影。

不一会儿，凯普打开了小棚子的门，将杰迈玛放了出来。不幸的是，两只小狗在凯普还没来得及阻拦的时候，就冲了进来，把杰迈玛的蛋都给吃掉了。凯普的耳朵被咬伤了，两只小狗都一瘸一拐的。

杰迈玛在他们的护送下回了家，一路上都在为她的那些蛋哭个不停。六月的时候，她又生了一些蛋，这次被允许自己留着孵化，但是只有四只被孵了出来。

杰迈玛说，这全是因为她紧张。但是，其实她一直都不是个好的孵化者。

络腮胡塞缪尔的故事

从前，有一只老猫，名叫塔比莎·特迟特太太，她是个很焦虑的母亲。她经常找不到自己的小猫，而且只要他们跑丢了，就总会遇到危险。

在烘焙日那天，她决定把小猫们关进一个橱柜中。她抓住了娃娃和咪咪，却没有找到汤姆。

塔比莎太太将房子上上下下找了一个遍，喵喵地叫着汤姆的名字。她查看了楼梯下面的餐具室，又找了那间一直闲置的卧室，里面的东西全都盖着防尘罩。她上了楼梯，检查了阁楼，但就是怎么也找不到汤姆。

这是一栋很老、很老的房子，里面到处都是壁橱和走廊。有些墙壁有四英尺厚，里面经常会传出奇怪的声音，好像里面有一道小小的秘密楼梯。当然，在护墙板上的确有一些小小的、锯齿状的门洞，而且夜里经常会有东西失踪——特别是奶酪和培根。

塔比莎太太越来越焦虑，一直担心地叫着。

就在猫妈妈搜索房子的时候，娃娃和咪咪又遇到危险了。橱柜的门没有锁，所以她们推开了门，从里面出来了。她们直接走向放置在炉火前的一个发酵着的面团，那块面团被放在一个平底锅里。她们用小小的柔软的爪子拍着面团——“我们要不要做点可爱的小松饼？”咪咪对娃娃说。但就在这时，有人敲门，娃娃一惊之下跳到了面粉桶里。咪咪则跑进了奶制品室里，躲进了一个放奶锅的石头架子上的空罐子里。

来访者是他们的邻居，瑞比太太。她是过来借酵母的。

塔比莎太太从楼上下来，还在担心地喵喵叫着——“进来，瑞比表妹，进来，坐下。我遇到大麻烦了，瑞比表妹。”塔比莎太太说着流出了泪水，“我把我亲爱的儿子汤马斯[1]给弄丢了。我担心老鼠们把他抓走了。”她用围裙抹着眼泪说。

“他是只淘气的小猫，塔比莎表姐，上次我过来喝茶的时候他用我最好的帽子翻绳儿玩。你到什么地方找过他了？”

“整个房子都找了！老鼠们实在太多了！家里有这些不听话的家伙真是麻烦啊！”塔比莎·特迟特太太说。

“我倒是不怕老鼠，我来帮你找找他，然后再揍他一顿！火炉围栏里面怎么那么多煤灰？”

“烟囱需要清扫了——噢，天啊，瑞比表妹——现在娃娃和咪咪也都不见了！她们从橱柜里跑出去了。”

瑞比和塔比莎又开始把房子彻底找了个遍。她们用瑞比的伞捅到床下面一点一点地探查，翻箱倒柜地又彻底检查了一遍。她们甚至点了一根蜡烛，检查了一个阁楼中的衣箱里有什么。但是她们什么都没有找到，而就在这时，她们听到了门“砰”的一声响，像是有人跑到了楼下。

“是啊，这里的老鼠太多了。”塔比莎含着眼泪说，“我从后厨房的一个洞里抓到过七只小老鼠，上个星期六当晚饭吃掉了。还有一次，我看到了那只老鼠爸爸——那可真是一只体型巨大的老鼠啊，瑞比表妹。我刚要跳起来扑向他，他居然向我露出他的大黄牙，然后立刻缩回洞里不见了。”

“那些老鼠真是让我神经紧张啊，瑞比表妹。”塔比莎说。

瑞比和塔比莎四处找啊找啊，她们都听到了从阁楼地板下传来骨碌碌、骨碌碌的奇怪声音，但什么都找不到。

她们回到厨房。“至少找到了你的一只小猫！”瑞比说着，从面粉桶中将娃娃拽了出来。

她们使劲摇晃她，把她身上的面粉抖掉，然后将她放在厨房的地板上。她看上去像是被吓坏了。

“噢！妈妈！妈妈！”娃娃说，“厨房里面有一只很老的母老鼠！她偷了一些面团！”

瑞比和塔比莎赶紧跑去察看面团，果然，上面有小小的爪子抓过的痕迹，一大块面团不见了。

“她往哪个方向跑了，娃娃？”

但是娃娃当时太害怕了，没敢从面粉桶里向外看。

瑞比和塔比莎将她带在身边，确保在继续寻找的时候，她安全地在她们的视线之内。

她们走进了奶品室。最先找到的便是藏在空奶罐里的咪咪。她们把奶罐推倒，让她爬了出来。

“噢！妈妈！妈妈！”咪咪说，“噢！妈妈！妈妈！有一只很老的公老鼠在奶品室里——一只超级巨大的大老鼠，妈妈！他偷了一块黄油，还有擀面杖！”

瑞比和塔比莎面面相觑。

“黄油和擀面杖！唉，我可怜的儿子汤马斯啊！”塔比莎一边哭号一边绞着自己的爪子。

“擀面杖？”瑞比说，“我们在阁楼里面检查那个箱子的时候，不是听到了骨碌碌、骨碌碌的声音了吗？”

瑞比和塔比莎急匆匆跑回楼上去，能很清楚地听到那骨碌碌的声音在阁楼的地板下面响动。

“这件事情可严重了，塔比莎表姐，”瑞比说，“我们得立刻找木匠约翰过来，让他带着锯子来。”

接下来，我们来说说小猫汤姆到底遭遇了什么。看起来爬进一座老房子的烟囱里面真的很不明智，在里面很容易迷路，而且那里面有很多体型硕大的老鼠。

小猫汤姆不愿意被关在橱柜里面，所以，看到妈妈准备烘焙，他就决定躲起来。他想找一个方便又舒服的地方藏起来，最后他选定了烟囱作为他的藏身处。

火刚刚生起来，烟囱里面还不热，不过从青色的木柴上冒出了一团呛人的白烟。小猫汤姆爬过围栏，查看了一下。这是一个老式的大壁炉。

烟囱里面很宽，足够一个人站直了身子行走。所以，对于小小猫汤姆来说，空间非常充足。他直接跳进了壁炉里，在挂水壶的铁架子上稳住身子。然后汤姆又用力一跳，跳离铁架，落到烟囱里面高处的一个壁架上。他碰落了一些煤灰，正掉在火炉围栏里。

小猫汤姆被烟呛到了，咳嗽了起来，他听到木柴在下面的壁炉里噼啪作响地烧着。他决定一直向上爬，从上面的石板那儿出去，然后试着抓些麻雀。

“我不能回去了。如果我打滑，可能会掉到火里面，我漂亮的尾巴和我的蓝色小夹克都会被烧焦的！”

这烟囱是一个非常大的老式烟囱。建这个烟囱的时候，人们在炉膛里面烧的还是整块的木头呢。屋顶上烟囱露出来的部分，就如同一座小小的石塔，日光从上面照射下来，照到了防雨的倾斜石板下面。

小猫汤姆越来越害怕！他向上爬啊爬，爬啊爬。他侧着身子穿过好几寸厚的烟灰。他就像个扫烟囱的小人儿。

在黑暗里根本就分不清方向。烟道一个连着一个。现在烟少了很多，不过汤姆感觉自己迷路了。他向上爬啊爬啊，但是他没有到达烟囱的顶部，而是来到了一个地方，那里烟囱壁上的一块石头被抽掉了，里面放着一些羊骨头。

“这倒真是奇怪，”汤姆说，“谁会在烟囱里面啃骨头呢？我真希望自己从来没来过这里。这到底是什么味儿啊！好像是老鼠，只不过气味格外强烈！呛得我想打喷嚏。”

他挤进墙里的一个洞中，硬是穿过了一段非常不舒服的狭窄的通道，那里几乎没有光。他小心翼翼地向前摸索着走了几码远，来到了阁楼的护墙板后面。

黑暗中，他突然头朝下栽进了一个洞里，落到了一堆非常脏的碎布上面。汤姆重新站起来的时候，环顾四周，他发现自己是在一个从来都没有见过的地方，尽管他从出生就住在这所房子里。

这是一个非常狭小的、散发着阵阵霉味的闷热房间，里面到处都是木板、椽子、蜘蛛网、板条和墙上的灰泥。正对着他——在离他远远的地方——坐着一只硕大的老鼠。

“你浑身脏兮兮地在我的床上滚，到底打算做什么？”老鼠说，他的牙咯咯作响。

“抱歉，先生，这烟囱需要清理了。”可怜的小猫汤姆说。

“安娜·玛丽亚！安娜·玛丽亚！”老鼠喊道。随着一阵“啪嗒”“啪嗒”的声音，一只母老鼠从椽子后面探出头来。

她立刻就冲向了小猫汤姆，汤姆完全还没有反应过来是怎么回事，他的衣服就被扒下来了，他被捆成了一团，捆他的绳子被打了个很结实的死结。

捆他的就是安娜·玛丽亚。另外那只老鼠一边看着，还一边嗅着鼻烟。她将汤姆捆好后，两只老鼠就都坐在一边，张着嘴巴盯着汤姆。

“安娜·玛丽亚，”公老鼠络腮胡塞缪尔说，“安娜·玛丽亚，给我做一个小猫馅卷布丁作晚餐吧。”

“那需要面团和黄油，还得用擀面杖。”安娜·玛丽亚说，她侧着脑袋想着该如何料理小猫汤姆。

“不，”络腮胡塞缪尔说，“有什么材料就用什么做，用面包屑裹上就行，安娜·玛丽亚。”

“胡扯！必须用黄油和面团！”安娜·玛丽亚回答。

两只老鼠为此讨论了一会儿，然后便分头走了。

络腮胡塞缪尔穿过护墙板上的一个洞，壮着胆子直接顺着前面的楼梯下去，到奶品室去拿黄油。他一路什么人都没有碰上。然后他又跑了第二趟，去拿擀面杖。他用爪子推着擀面杖，就像是一个酿酒人推着啤酒桶那样。他能听到瑞比和塔比莎说话，但是她们在忙着点蜡烛检查箱子里面，谁都没有发现他。

安娜·玛丽亚顺着踢脚板下楼，从一扇百叶窗进了厨房，偷了面团。她拿了一个小碟子，用爪子抠出面团来放到碟子里。她没有看到娃娃。

汤姆被单独留在阁楼地板下，他不断挣扎，想要喵喵叫着求救。但是他的嘴里满是煤灰和蜘蛛网，被捆得非常结实，他没有办法让别人听到他求救的声音。

只有一只蜘蛛从屋顶的裂缝中爬出来，站在安全的距离外，以评判的目光审视了一下绳结。这只蜘蛛是绳结方面的权威，因为他经常把不幸的丽蝇捆起来。他并没有给汤姆提供帮助。

小猫汤姆扭动着身子挣来挣去，到最后一点儿力气都没有了。不一会儿，老鼠们回来了，开始动手把他包成布丁。他们先用黄油涂抹小猫汤姆的身体，然后将他卷进了面团里面。

“那绳子是不是很难消化啊，安娜·玛丽亚？”络腮胡塞缪尔问。

安娜·玛丽亚说她觉得那没有什么，但是她希望小猫汤姆的脑袋能够保持静止不动，因为动的话很容易弄坏面皮。她抓住了汤姆的耳朵。

小猫汤姆又是张嘴乱咬，又是吐口水，喵喵叫着扭来扭去，擀面杖骨碌碌地滚来滚去。两只老鼠分别握着擀面杖的两端。

“他的尾巴还露在外面！你拿来的面团不够用，安娜·玛丽亚。”

“我实在拿不了太多了。”安娜·玛丽亚回答。

“我不这么觉得。”络腮胡塞缪尔说。他暂停下来看了看小猫汤姆，“我不觉得这会是一个好吃的布丁，闻起来有一股煤灰味儿。”

安娜·玛丽亚正要和他争论，但就在这时，他们头上传来了别的声音——那是锯子拉来拉去的声音，还有小狗又抓又挠和兴奋地吠叫的声音。

两只老鼠丢下擀面杖，紧张地听着。

“我们被发现了，没法再做我们要做的事了，安娜·玛丽亚。咱们收拾一下咱们的财物——当然还有别人的，赶紧离开。恐怕咱们不得不留下这个布丁了。但是我相信那些绳结会很难消化，不管你怎么反对。”

“立刻过来，帮我把这些羊骨头用床单包起来，”安娜·玛丽亚说，“我还在烟囱里面放了半块熏火腿。”

因此，等到木匠约翰把板子锯开时，地板下面就只剩下擀面杖和一个被包在很脏的面皮里的小猫汤姆了。但是，那里有很强烈的老鼠的气息，接下来一整个上午，木匠约翰都在嗅来嗅去，叫个不停，他摇着尾巴，跑来跑去，不停地把头探进那个洞里面，就像个木钻一样。然后他又把板子钉好，把工具收进自己的包里，下了楼。

小猫一家已经恢复如常了。他们邀请约翰留下来吃饭。面皮已经从小猫汤姆身上剥了下来，被做成了一个大布丁，里面还塞了葡萄干，以掩盖它里面的煤烟味。他们不得不给汤姆洗了个热水澡，好把他身上的黄油洗掉。

木匠约翰闻了闻布丁的味道，很遗憾自己没有时间留下来吃饭了，他刚给波特小姐[2]做了一个独轮车，但她又预定了两个鸡窝。

傍晚，我去邮局的时候，在拐角处向那条巷子看了看，看到了逃亡中的络腮胡塞缪尔先生和他的太太，他们用一个小独轮车推着几个大包袱，那独轮车看起来很像是我的。他们正拐进农场主马铃薯家的谷仓门里。

络腮胡塞缪尔气喘吁吁的。安娜·玛丽亚依然在用尖锐的声调和他争执着。她似乎认识路，似乎有很多行李。

但我可以肯定，我从来都没有允许她借用我的独轮车。

他们进了谷仓，然后用一段绳子把包袱拖到了干草堆顶上。那之后很长一段时间，塔比莎·特迟特太太家中都没有再出现过老鼠。

而至于农场主马铃薯，他几乎被逼疯了，他的谷仓里四处都是老鼠，老鼠，老鼠！他们还吃光了鸡食，偷走了燕麦和谷糠，在面粉袋上咬出了很多洞。他们都是络腮胡塞缪尔夫妇的后代，是他们的儿子、孙子和曾孙玄孙。真是没个完了。

娃娃和咪咪长大后成了非常好的捕鼠能手。她们去村子里抓老鼠，有很多人找她们工作。她们收费很高，赚了很多钱，生活富足。她们把老鼠的尾巴在谷仓门口挂成一排，以展示她们抓了多少只老鼠——有好几十只呢！但是小猫汤姆却一直害怕大老鼠，他至多只敢面对小老鼠。

[1]汤姆的大名。

[2]本文的作者毕翠克丝·波特。

噗噗家的小兔子的故事

据说，多吃生菜会产生催眠效果。

我在吃了生菜之后可从来都没有觉得困倦过，当然，因为我并不是兔子。生菜对噗噗家的小兔子肯定有非常强的催眠效果。

小兔本杰明长大之后，和他的表姐噗噗结了婚。他们生了一大窝孩子，这一家子都没有什么远忧，日子过得非常开心。我不记得他们的孩子各自叫什么了，他们被统称为噗噗家的小兔子。

由于他们总是没有足够的食物吃，本杰明经常从噗噗的弟弟彼得那里借洋白菜——彼得有一个苗圃。有时候彼得也没有多余的洋白菜。这时候，噗噗家的小兔子们就穿过田野，到麦克格雷格先生的菜园外面的垃圾堆里去找食物，那个垃圾堆在一个阴沟里。

麦克格雷格先生的垃圾堆是个大杂烩，里面有果酱罐、纸袋子，有割草机割下来的堆成山一样的草（吃起来总是油腻腻的），一些腐烂了的西葫芦和一两只靴子。有一天——天啊，真让人开心——那里有很多长老了的生菜，那些生菜都长得太过，开花了。

噗噗家的小兔子吃生菜都吃撑了。最后，他们一个接一个地都被睡眠给征服了，全躺在了割下来的草上。

本杰明受到的影响并没有他的孩子们那么厉害。在睡着前，他还足够清醒地在头上罩了一个纸袋，以防止苍蝇骚扰。

噗噗家的小兔子们在温暖的阳光下舒服地睡着。从花园那边的草地上隐约传来了割草机隆隆的声音。丽蝇在墙头嗡嗡地飞着，一只上了年纪的小个子老鼠在果酱罐中翻找着。（我可以告诉你她的名字，她是小小鼠托玛西娜，是一只长着长长尾巴的林鼠。）她爬过本杰明头上的纸袋子，簌簌作响，吵醒了本杰明。老鼠一再表示歉意，并且说自己认识彼得。

她和本杰明就在墙边聊天，这时，他们听到一阵沉重的脚步声在头顶响起。麦克格雷格先生将一口袋割下来的草直接倒到了噗噗家的小兔子身上。本杰明缩进了他的纸袋子里，而老鼠也藏到了果酱罐里。在如雨般落下来的草中，小兔子们依然在睡梦中甜美地笑着，他们并没有醒过来，因为生菜的催眠效果太强了。他们都梦到了妈妈将他们裹进了一床干草做成的铺盖中。

麦克格雷格先生在倒空了口袋后向下面看了看，他看到从草堆中露出来的小小的棕色的耳朵尖儿。他盯着看了一会儿。就在这时，一只苍蝇落在了其中一只耳朵上，然后那只耳朵动了动。

麦克格雷格先生下来，凑到垃圾堆上。

“一，二，三，四！五！六！六只小兔子！”他说着，抓起他们并丢进了自己的口袋中。

噗噗家的小兔子们梦到了妈妈帮他们在床上翻了个身。他们动了动，但还是没有醒过来。

麦克格雷格先生把口袋扎好，然后就放在墙上，去收拾割草机了。他走了之后，兔子噗噗太太（她本来是留在家中的）穿过田地走了过来。她充满疑惑地看着那个口袋，想知道大家都去哪里了。这时，老鼠从果酱罐里面出来了，本杰明也拿下了他头上的纸袋子，他们讲述了刚才发生的悲惨的故事。

本杰明和噗噗非常绝望，因为他们都解不开扎口袋的绳子。但是小小鼠太太是一个很有办法的人，她在袋子底部的角落咬了一个洞出来。小兔子们被拽了出来，被又掐又捏地弄醒了。他们的父母把三个烂了的西葫芦、一个旧的鞋油刷子、两个烂了的萝卜放到了口袋里。然后他们躲进了一片灌木中，等待着麦克格雷格先生。

麦克格雷格先生回来后，拿起口袋便走了。从他拎着口袋的样子看，口袋似乎很重。噗噗家的兔子们在后面远远地跟着。他们看到麦克格雷格先生回到了自己的房子里。然后他们偷偷溜到窗户边偷听。

麦克格雷格先生将口袋扔到石头地板上，如果噗噗家的小兔子还在口袋里面的话，那种扔法肯定会让他们很疼的。他们听到麦克格雷格先生在石板地上拖动椅子，边走边咯咯笑。

“一，二，三，四，五，六，六只小兔子！”麦克格雷格先生说。

“呃？那是什么？他们又糟蹋什么了？”麦克格雷格太太问道。

“一，二，三，四，五，六，六只肥肥的小兔子！”麦克格雷格先生重复道，他扳着自己的指头数着，“一，二，三——”

“别傻了，你到底什么意思，你这个老糊涂？”

“在这个口袋里！一，二，三，四，五，六！”麦克格雷格先生又重复说。

（噗噗家最小的那只小兔子爬到了窗台上。）

麦克格雷格太太拎过袋子来摸了摸。她说她能够摸出来是六只，但肯定是六只老兔子，因为都很硬，而且形状都不一样。

“不适合吃，但是皮毛肯定很合适给我的旧斗篷镶边。”

“给你的旧斗篷镶边？”麦克格雷格先生大叫道，“我要卖了他们，给我自己买烟草。兔子烟草！我得剥下他们的皮，把他们的脑袋处理掉。”

麦克格雷格太太解开口袋，探手进去。她摸到了蔬菜，然后非常非常生气。她说麦克格雷格先生是“故意”的。麦克格雷格先生也非常生气。其中一个烂了的西葫芦被他从厨房的窗户丢了出来，砸到了噗噗家最小的兔子身上。真是疼死了！

本杰明和噗噗觉得他们该回家了。

所以，麦克格雷格先生没有得到烟草，麦克格雷格太太也没有得到兔皮。

但是在圣诞节时，小小鼠托玛西娜收到了一件礼物——很多的兔毛，足够她给自己做一件斗篷、一个兜帽、一个漂亮的暖手筒，还有一副暖和的连指手套。

姜和腌菜的故事

从前，在一个村子里有一家店铺，窗户上的店名是“姜和腌菜”。那是一家很小的店，大小只适合玩偶们——露辛达和厨娘简总是来这家店买食物和杂货。店里面柜台的高度对兔子们来说倒是很适合。姜和腌菜出售带红点的手帕，一便士三法寻[1]一条。他们还出售糖、鼻烟和雨靴。实际上，尽管这是一家很小的店铺，但它几乎什么都卖——除非是一些特别急需的东西——比方说鞋带、发卡和羊排。

姜和腌菜是开店的人的名字。姜是一只黄色的公猫，腌菜是一只猎犬。兔子们始终有点儿害怕腌菜。店里面也有老鼠来光顾——只是老鼠们都有点儿害怕姜。姜总是让腌菜招待老鼠，因为他说老鼠会让他流口水。

“我受不了，”他说，“我没办法看着他们带着小包袱出门去。”

“我对老鼠也有相同的感觉。”腌菜回答说，“但是我们绝对不能吃我们的顾客，不然他们会不再光顾这里，改去塔比莎·特迟特的店了。”

“不，他们谁的店都去不了了。”姜闷闷不乐地回答。

塔比莎·特迟特开着村子里的另外一家店，村子里面只有这两家店。塔比莎从来都不赊账。

姜和腌菜是允许无限制地赊账的。

赊账的意思就是：当客人买了一块肥皂，她没有拿出钱包付款，而是说下次再给钱。腌菜会深深鞠一躬，说：“当然可以，夫人。”然后便将账目记录在一个本子上。

顾客会一次又一次光顾店里，买很多东西，尽管他们还是害怕姜和腌菜。但是所谓的“钱柜”里面却一直都没有钱。

每天，顾客们都一批批地来，买很多东西，特别是太妃糖。但是总是见不到钱，哪怕只买一便士的薄荷糖，那些顾客也从来没有付过钱。但是店里的销售量巨大，是塔比莎·特迟特店的十倍。

由于总是收不到钱，姜和腌菜不得不吃自己的货物。腌菜吃饼干，姜吃鳕鱼干。他们在小店关门后，点着蜡烛吃这些东西。到了元旦的时候，他们依然没有钱，腌菜没办法去买狗证。

“真是让人难过，我很担心警察。”腌菜说。

“身为一只猎犬是你的错，我就不需要证件，牧羊犬凯普也不需要。”

“这真让人不安，我觉得自己会被法院传召。我试了去邮局赊账办理证件，可是没成功，”腌菜说，“这里四处都是警察，回家的路上我就碰上了一个。”

“咱们再给络腮胡塞缪尔寄一次账单吧，姜，他买腌肉欠了我们二十二先令九便士。”

“我相信他根本就没打算还。”姜说。

“而且我觉得安娜·玛丽亚在偷东西——那些奶油饼干都到哪儿去了？”

“你自己把它们都吃了。”姜回答。

姜和腌菜回到了后厅。他们算了算账目，加了一笔又一笔。

“络腮胡塞缪尔欠的账单有他的尾巴那么长了。自从十月份到现在，他已经买了一又四分之三盎司的鼻烟了。还用一先令三便士的价格买了七磅黄油，还有一条封蜡和四盒火柴，这该是多少？”

“给每个人都再寄一遍账单明细吧。”姜说。

过了一会儿，他们听到店铺那边传来一些响动，好像是有人从门口那里塞进来了什么。他们从后厅出来，发现柜台上有一个信封，一个警察正在笔记本上写着什么。

腌菜火冒三丈，他不停地叫啊叫啊，还跑来跑去。

“去咬他，腌菜！去咬他！”姜躲在一个糖桶后面，气急败坏地说，“他不过是个德国娃娃。”

那个警察继续在自己的本子上写着，他有两次把铅笔放进了嘴里，有一次把笔蘸进了糖浆里。

腌菜一直叫着，直到他的嗓子都哑了。但是那个警察依然没有理会。那警察有一双豆子眼，头盔是缝在头上的。终于，在最后一次跑过去看的时候，腌菜终于发现店里面没人了，那个警察不见了。不过那个信封还在那里。

“你觉得他是去叫一个真正的警察了吗？我担心那是张传票。”腌菜说。

“不是，”姜回答，他打开了信封，“是税单，需要交三英镑十九先令十一便士三法寻。”

“这是压死我们的最后一根稻草了。”腌菜说，“咱们把店关了吧。”

他们关上了门板，然后离开了。但是他们没有搬离这一片社区。实际上，有些人希望他们能够搬得远一些。

姜住在兔子洞中，我不知道他找到了什么工作，不过他看上去很强壮，日子过得很舒心。

腌菜现在是个猎场看守。

他们的店铺关门造成了很大的不便。塔比莎·特迟特立刻就把所有东西的价格提高了半个便士，她依然拒绝赊账。

当然，也有一些商人赶着马车过来——有屠夫、渔夫，还有面包商蒂莫西。但是，没有人能只依靠“芝麻发糕”、松糕和黄油小圆面包生活呀——哪怕那松糕做得像蒂莫西家做的那么美味！

过了一段日子，睡鼠约翰先生和他的女儿开始卖薄荷糖和蜡烛。但是他们没有调整蜡烛的长短，一根七英寸长的蜡烛，需要五只老鼠才能搬动。另外——他们卖的蜡烛在温暖的天气就会奇怪地起反应。睡鼠小姐拒绝回收那些投诉的顾客所带来的蜡烛头儿。

而当睡鼠约翰先生接待那些投诉的顾客时，他就躺在床上，除了说“很舒服啊”，其他的什么也不说。这可不是运营零售业的正确方法。

所以，当大家看到小母鸡萨利贴出一张印刷的海报说自己要重开那家店铺的时候，都十分开心。“母鸡家开业大促销！大酬宾大让利！超低价！快来买，快来试，快来买呀！”海报真的非常吸引人。

在开业那天，店里的人太多了。店铺里面挤满了顾客，饼干罐上站着一群一群的老鼠。小母鸡萨利手忙脚乱地给顾客找零钱，但是她坚持顾客必须付现金，不过她没什么恶意。而且，她店里有很多很多的特价商品。

在这里，每个人都能找到满意的东西。

[1]法寻（farthing）：英国旧硬币，值四分之一旧便士。

小小鼠太太的故事

从前，有一只林鼠，名叫小小鼠太太，她住在树篱下面的一道土垄里。她的房子非常有意思。她在沙子中挖了长长的通道，通向储藏室、坚果地窖和种子地窖，这些全在树篱的根部。这房子里面还有厨房、客厅、餐具室和食品储藏室。另外，还有小小鼠太太的卧室，她睡在一张小小的箱子形状的床里。

小小鼠太太是个格外爱整洁的小老鼠，她总是打扫软软的沙子地板。

有时候，会有一只甲虫在走廊里迷路。

“走开！走开！小脏脚！”小小鼠太太会敲着她的簸箕说。

一天，一个穿着红色波点斗篷的老妇人在小小鼠太太家爬上爬下。

“你家房子着火啦，瓢虫妈妈！快点飞回家找你的孩子去吧。”

另一天，一只很大很肥的蜘蛛来到这里躲雨。

“抱歉，这难道不是玛菲小姐的家吗？”

“一边儿去，你这个胆大包天的坏蜘蛛！你把我干净整洁的房子弄得到处都是蜘蛛网！”

她把蜘蛛赶出了窗户。

蜘蛛拉了一条长长的、细细的丝，顺着丝滑下树篱。

小小鼠太太继续向前走，去一个比较偏的储藏室，取樱桃核和蓟花种子好准备饭菜。她一边走，一边不停地嗅来嗅去，眼睛盯着地板。

“我闻到了蜂蜜的味儿，是外面树篱里的樱草花吗？我敢肯定我看到的就是那些小脏脚丫留下的脚印。”

绕过一个拐角，她突然就看到了大黄蜂芭比蒂，大黄蜂正嗡嗡嗡地叫着。小小鼠太太神情严肃地看着大黄蜂，她希望自己手里能有一个扫把。

“日安，大黄蜂芭比蒂，我很乐意买些蜂蜡，不过你来这下面干什么？你为什么总是要从窗户进屋来，还不停地嗡嗡嗡叫？”小小鼠太太有些生气了。

“嗡嗡嗡！”大黄蜂芭比蒂用恼怒的尖叫声回答道。她顺着通道溜走了，躲进了一间曾用来装橡子的储藏室。

小小鼠太太在圣诞节之前就吃掉了那些橡子，储藏室现在应该是空的。但是里面全是凌乱的干苔藓。小小鼠太太拨扯着苔藓，有三四只蜜蜂探出头来，凶狠地嗡嗡叫了起来。

“我可没有让人寄宿的习惯，这是私闯民宅！”小小鼠太太说，“我要把他们赶出去——”

“嗡嗡嗡！”

“我真想知道谁能帮帮我。”

“嗡嗡嗡！”

“我不会去找杰克逊先生，他从来都不擦脚。”

小小鼠太太决定等吃过饭后再去处理那些蜜蜂。她回到客厅，听到有人在猛烈地咳嗽，坐在那里的正是杰克逊先生！他坐在一把小摇椅里，微笑着转着大拇指玩，脚搭在火炉围栏上。他住在树篱下面的一条排水沟里，那里又脏又潮。

“你好吗，杰克逊先生？天啊，你怎么这么湿呀！”

“谢谢，谢谢，谢谢，小小鼠太太！我坐一会儿把自己晾干。”杰克逊先生说。他坐在那里笑着，水从他外套的燕尾上滴落下来。小小鼠太太拿着一个墩布在他周围转来转去。

他坐了很长一段时间，小小鼠太太不得不问他是不是愿意一起吃些东西。她先给他端上了樱桃核。“谢谢，谢谢，谢谢，小小鼠太太，我没牙，没牙，没牙！”杰克逊先生说。他把嘴张得大大的，其实根本没有必要张那么大，不过，确实，他没有牙。

然后，小小鼠太太给他端来了蓟草花的种子。

“太小了，太碎了，太碎了！噗，噗，噗！”杰克逊先生说，他把蓟草花的种子吹得满屋子都是。

“谢谢，谢谢，谢谢，小小鼠太太，现在，我真的觉得——真的想要——能有一小盘子蜂蜜！”

“恐怕我没有，杰克逊先生！”小小鼠太太说。

“嘎呱呱，小小鼠太太！”杰克逊先生笑着说，“我能闻到蜂蜜的气味，所以我才来拜访的。”

杰克逊先生笨拙地从桌子边站起来，开始查看橱柜里面。小小鼠太太拿着抹布跟在他后面，把他在客厅地板上留下的大大的湿脚印擦掉。杰克逊先生确认橱柜里没有蜂蜜，便顺着过道往前走。

“说实话，说实话，你会被卡住的，杰克逊先生！”

“嘎呱呱，小小鼠太太！”

他先挤进了餐具室。

“嘎呱呱？没有蜂蜜？没有蜂蜜，小小鼠太太？”

有三只小虫子藏在餐具盘里。其中两只逃走了，最小的那只被杰克逊先生抓住了。然后，他又挤进了食品间。蝴蝶小姐正在吃糖块儿，但是她从窗户那儿飞走了。

“嘎呱呱，小小鼠太太，你似乎有很多客人啊！”

“都是不请自来的！”小小鼠太太托玛西娜说。

他们沿着沙子过道继续向前。“嘎呱——”

“嗡嗡嗡！”

他在一个拐角处遇到了大黄蜂芭比蒂，便一口将她吞了下去，但很快就吐了出来。

“我不喜欢大黄蜂，他们浑身都长满了毛。”杰克逊先生说，一边还用衣服袖子擦着自己的嘴巴。

“出去，你这个讨厌的老蛤蟆！”大黄蜂芭比蒂尖叫道。

“我要烦死了！”小小鼠太太喊道。她把自己关进了贮存坚果的地窖里。杰克逊先生把整个蜂窝给捅了，他似乎并不介意被蜜蜂蛰。

等到小小鼠太太壮着胆子出来的时候，所有人都已经走了。但是屋内却凌乱、肮脏得吓人。“我从没有见过这么乱的景象！——蜂蜜的污迹，苔藓，蓟草花——还有大大小小脏兮兮的脚印——弄得我漂亮整洁的房子四处都乱糟糟的。”小小鼠太太说。

她把苔藓和剩下的蜂蜡打扫了。然后她去找了一些小树枝回来，把大门又堵了一部分。

“我要把这门弄小些，让杰克逊先生进不来！”

她从储藏室里面拿出来了肥皂、毛巾和一个硬毛刷。但是她实在太累了，没有力气再干活了。她先是在椅子中睡着了，之后回到床上去睡了。

“我的家还能变得整洁起来吗？”可怜的小小鼠太太说。

第二天，她很早便起了床，开始大扫除，这次大扫除整整进行了两周。她扫啊，擦啊，刷啊，把所有家具都打了一遍蜡，又把她的小锡勺都擦得亮闪闪的。等到一切都变得干净、整洁、漂亮时，她举办了一个派对，邀请了另外五只小老鼠来参加，但没有邀请杰克逊先生。

杰克逊先生闻到了派对的气味，来到土龚边，却没有办法挤进门里。所以，他们从窗户将装满了蜂蜜的橡子壳一杯杯地递给他，他一点儿也没有觉得被冒犯。

杰克逊先生坐在外面，晒着太阳，说：“嘎呱呱！祝你健康，小小鼠太太！”

小脚丫蒂米的故事

从前，有一只肥肥的、生活安逸的灰色小松鼠，名叫小脚丫蒂米。他在一棵高高的树梢上有一个用树叶盖顶的窝。他还有一个妻子名叫古蒂。

小脚丫蒂米坐在外面，享受着微风，他晃动着尾巴，咯咯笑着说：“古蒂呀，坚果都成熟了，咱们必须储备一些，留着冬天和明年春天吃。”

小脚丫古蒂正忙着把苔藓塞进屋顶下面。“我们的小窝好舒服啊，我们肯定能好好睡上一整个冬天。”

“那等我们醒来的时候就会都瘦了的，而春天的时候可没有东西吃。”考虑周全的蒂莫西[1]回答。

当蒂米和古蒂来到坚果灌木丛时，发现已经有其他松鼠在那里了。

蒂米将他的夹克脱下来，挂在一根小树枝上，然后他们便开始安静地干起活来。

每天，他们都要来这里好几趟，采上很多坚果，装在袋子里运走，藏到他们搭窝的那棵树附近的几处空心树桩当中。

那些树洞都被装满之后，他们就把袋子里的坚果倒进一棵树高处的一个洞里，那个洞本来是一只啄木鸟的。坚果都骨碌碌地掉了下去。

“到时候你怎么把它们弄出来呢？这就像个存钱罐。”古蒂说。

“春天之前我就会瘦很多的，亲爱的。”小脚丫蒂米看着那个洞说。

他们收集了很多坚果——因为他们一个都没有丢。

把坚果埋在地里的松鼠都会丢掉大多半坚果，因为他们都记不住埋藏的地点。

森林里最健忘的一只松鼠叫银尾巴。他刚挖坑埋好坚果，转身就会忘记埋在了哪里。等他再挖的时候，找到的并不是属于他的坚果，于是就会发生一场战争。而其他的松鼠也都到处挖坑藏坚果，于是整个森林一片混乱。

不幸的是，在这个时候，一群小鸟正好从这里经过，他们在灌木中飞来飞去，捕食青虫和蜘蛛。那其中有好几种不同的小鸟，他们都唱着不同的歌曲。

领头的小鸟唱：“谁一直在挖我的坚果？谁一直在挖我的坚果？”

另一只小鸟唱：“一点点面包没有奶酪！一点点面包没有奶酪！”

松鼠们全都跟着他们，听他们唱的歌。第一只小鸟飞到一片灌木中，蒂米和古蒂正在那里安静地扎他们的口袋，那只小鸟唱道：“谁一直在挖我的坚果？谁一直在挖我的坚果？”

蒂米没有理会他，而是继续干自己的活。实际上，那只小鸟也没有期待能得到回答。他只是在唱他生来就会的歌而已，那歌并没有任何意义。

但其他松鼠听到这首歌，全都扑向了小脚丫蒂米，对他又抓又打，倒光了他装坚果的口袋。而引起这一切不幸的那只无辜的小鸟被吓得飞走了。

蒂米摔倒在地上，翻来滚去，最后他转身向他窝的方向逃去，一大群松鼠跟在他身后，大叫着：“谁一直在挖走我的坚果？”

他们抓住他，把他拖到了一棵树边，正是那棵上面有个小圆洞的树，他们将他推了进去。那个洞实在很小，以蒂米的身形，是进不去的，但是他们使了很大的力气，愣是将他挤了进去，这个过程中没有弄断蒂米的肋骨，真可以说是个奇迹。“我们把他留在这里，直到他忏悔为止。”松鼠银尾巴说，然后他冲着洞里吼道：“谁一直在挖我的坚果？”

小脚丫蒂米没有回答，他已经顺着树洞跌了下去，落在了一堆坚果上面，这堆坚果有一半是他贡献的。他昏了过去，安静地躺在原地，一动不动。

古蒂收拾了装坚果的口袋回到家。她泡了一杯茶，等着蒂米回来，但是蒂米没有回来，她左等右等，蒂米还是没有回来。

古蒂度过了一个孤单而不快乐的夜晚。第二天早晨，她壮着胆子回到坚果灌木林去找蒂米，但是其他不友好的松鼠把她赶走了。她在整个树林中游荡，呼喊着：

“小脚丫蒂米！小脚丫蒂米！唉，小脚丫蒂米去哪儿了？”

而就在这时，小脚丫蒂米恢复了意识。他发现自己躺在一张小小的苔藓床上，周围非常暗，他觉得浑身酸疼。这里似乎是在地下。蒂米咳嗽了几声，又呻吟了起来，因为他觉得肋骨有些疼。这时传来了一阵快活的声音，那是一只长着条纹的小花栗鼠，他手里举着一盏灯，问蒂米感觉好些了吗。他对小脚丫蒂米非常好，还把自己的睡帽借给他。这个房子里贮备的食物也很充足。

花栗鼠解释说，曾经从树顶上像下雨一样落下过一些坚果。“另外，我还找到了一些被埋起来的。”他听了蒂米的故事，放声大笑。蒂米下不了床，他劝蒂米多吃些。“但是我要是不瘦下来，怎么才能从树洞里出去呢？我妻子会担心的。”“再吃一个坚果，或是两个。我来替你把它们砸开。”花栗鼠说。于是，小脚丫蒂米越来越胖了。

现在，古蒂开始自己收集坚果。她没有再往啄木鸟洞里放过坚果，因为她一直怀疑放进去就再也拿不出来了。她把坚果藏在一棵树的树根下面，坚果全都哗啦啦地滚了下去。有一次，当古蒂倒空一个格外大的装得满满的袋子时，树根下传来了一声清晰的尖叫声。等到下一次，当古蒂再带着一满袋子坚果来的时候，有一只长着条纹的小花栗鼠从树根下匆匆忙忙地爬了出来。

“楼下已经装得满满的了，客厅里也满了，这些坚果还都顺着过道滚动，我丈夫花栗鼠哈奇已经一个人逃走了，他把我丢下了。这些坚果雨到底是怎么回事啊？”

“我郑重请求您的原谅，我不知道有人住在这里。”古蒂说，“不过，哈奇去了哪里？我丈夫小脚丫蒂米也跑了。”

“我知道哈奇在哪里，是一只小鸟告诉我的。”哈奇太太说。她领着古蒂一起去了有啄木鸟洞的那棵树，她们在洞口听了一会儿。

从下面传来了砸坚果的声音，还有一只松鼠浑厚的嗓音和一只花栗鼠尖细的嗓音在一起唱：

我的小老头儿和我吵架了，
我们到底该怎么办才好？
你有能耐你就去办，
快点走开，你这个小老头儿！

“你能从这个小圆洞里挤进去。”古蒂说。

“是的，我能，”花栗鼠说，“不过，我丈夫哈奇会咬我的。”

从下面又传来了砸坚果和啃咬东西的声音，然后是一只松鼠浑厚的嗓音和一只花栗鼠尖细的嗓音一起合唱：

日子一天天荒废过，
日子荒废过，
荒废过日子！

然后古蒂从洞口望进去，冲着下方喊道：“小脚丫蒂米！啊！天！小脚丫蒂米！”蒂米回答道：“是你吗，小脚丫古蒂？哎呀，真的是你！”他爬了上来，把头探出洞口亲吻古蒂，但是他太胖了，身子没有办法出来。

花栗鼠哈奇没有那么胖，但是他不想出来，他就待在下面，咯咯咯地笑。

就这样，一直到两周后，一场大风吹断了大树的上半截，将洞打开了，雨落了进去。然后蒂米便出来了，撑着一把伞回了家。但是花栗鼠哈奇依然在外露宿了一个星期，尽管这令人非常不舒服。

最后，一只大熊穿过树林而来，也许，他也在寻找坚果，到处地嗅来嗅去。

哈奇赶紧匆忙地回了家。哈奇回到家之后，发现自己感冒了，他感觉更不舒服了。

现在，蒂米和古蒂在他们的坚果储藏室门上加了一把小锁头。

但无论何时，只要那只小鸟看到花栗鼠夫妇，他就会唱：“谁一直在挖走我的坚果？谁一直在挖走我的坚果？”但是从来都没有得到过回答。

[1]蒂米的大名。

狐狸托德先生的故事

我曾经写过很多谦谦君子的故事，现在，我要改变一下，来写一个关于两个“讨人嫌”的故事，这两个人是老獾汤米和狐狸托德先生。

没有人会说托德先生好。兔子们都受不了他，他们在半里地外就能闻到他的气息。他喜欢游荡，长着狡猾的小胡子，没人知道他下一刻会出现在哪里。

头一天，他还住在小灌木丛里的一座树枝搭成的小房子里，让老本杰明·邦瑟一家子提心吊胆。隔一天，他就会搬到湖边一棵光秃秃的柳树里，把野鸭和水耗子吓得要命。

冬天和早春的时候，他通常会住在燕麦崖下面、公牛堤顶上岩石间的巢穴里。

他有六处房子，不过他很少待在家中。

在托德先生不在家的时候，那些房子并不总是空着的，因为有些时候老獾汤米会搬进去住。（他从来都没有征得主人同意。）

老獾汤米是个矮胖子，毛发粗硬，走路摇摇摆摆，总是咧着嘴笑，嘴咧得占了整张脸。他的习性也不好。他吃蜂窝、青蛙和虫子，总在晚上借着月光到外面闲逛，从土里挖东西。他的衣服非常脏。他在白天睡觉，还总是穿着靴子爬上床。当然，他睡的床，通常都是托德先生的。

老獾汤米的确偶尔会吃兔子肉馅饼，不过都是偶尔，吃的都是很小的兔子，而且是在其他食物实在紧缺的情况下。他对老邦瑟先生很友好，他们都不喜欢邪恶的水獭和托德先生，所以经常在一起谈论这个恼人的话题。

老邦瑟先生患病多年。他坐在洞穴外面，晒着春日的太阳，身上围着围巾，抽着装了兔子烟草的烟斗。他和他的儿子本杰明以及儿媳妇噗噗住在一起，本杰明和噗噗也有了自己的孩子。那个下午，老邦瑟先生负责看家，因为本杰明和噗噗都出去了。

小兔子宝宝们都不大，刚刚可以睁开他们的蓝眼睛，踢踢腿。他们躺在用兔毛和干草铺成的松软的床上，这床在一个浅浅的洞穴里，和大兔子洞是分开的。说实话，老邦瑟先生把他们都给忘了。

他坐在阳光下，热情地和正要穿过树林的老獾汤米聊着天，汤米带着一个口袋，拿着一个挖土用的小锄头和几个鼹鼠夹子。他伤心地抱怨找不到足够的野鸡蛋，指责托德先生把蛋都偷走了。而水獭们趁他冬眠时吃光了所有的青蛙——“我已经有半个月没有吃过像样的饭了，我现在就靠吃山胡桃度日。我最后得变成素食者，然后吃掉我自己的尾巴。”老獾汤米说。

这算不上笑话，但逗乐了老邦瑟先生，因为老獾汤米又矮又胖，总是笑嘻嘻的。所以老邦瑟先生放声大笑，硬拉着老獾汤米进屋，吃块油饼，再喝点“我儿媳妇噗噗用樱草酿的酒”。老獾汤米便欣然同意，把自己挤进了兔子洞中。

然后，老邦瑟先生又抽了一斗烟，他给了老獾汤米一个卷心菜叶子做的雪茄，这雪茄的劲儿很强，这让老汤米的笑容扯得更大了，他们吐出来的烟弥漫了整个洞穴。老邦瑟先生一边咳嗽一边放声大笑，而老獾汤米则一直吞云吐雾，咧嘴大笑。

老邦瑟先生一边笑一边咳嗽，在卷心菜烟草的烟雾中闭上了眼睛……

而等到噗噗和本杰明回来的时候，老邦瑟先生才醒过来。老獾汤米和所有的小兔子宝宝都不见了！

老邦瑟先生坚持说他没让任何人进过兔子洞。但是屋里那股獾的味道是不容否认的，而且沙地上还有圆圆的重重的脚印。他觉得很丢脸。噗噗紧绷着耳朵，扇了他几巴掌。

本杰明立刻跑去追老獾汤米。要追踪他并没有什么困难，他留下了脚印，是缓缓地沿着穿过树林的蜿蜒小路走的。在这个地方，他拔起了苔藓和酢酱草，在那个地方，又为了采野毒麦而挖了一个特别深的洞，还设了一个鼹鼠夹。一条小溪拦住了路，本杰明轻巧地跳了过去，没有弄湿脚。不过在泥里，可以很清楚地看到老獾沉重的脚印。

这条路通向那片矮灌木丛，那里的大树都已经被砍光了，只有长着叶子的橡树树桩和一大片蓝色风信子——本杰明停了下来，并不是因为花香，而是因为一股特别的气味。

托德先生的小木屋就在前方，难得的一次，托德先生正在家中。不止狐狸的气味——还有那破桶做的烟囱正冒着烟，都可以证明托德先生此刻正在家中！

本杰明直起身子，盯着这一切，他的胡子抽动着。在木屋里，有人失手掉落了一个盘子，说了些什么。本杰明跺了跺脚，就猛冲了过去。他一直跳到树林的另一边才停下来。显然老獾汤米也走了这个方向，在围墙的顶上，又出现了獾的踪迹，在石楠丛上还有拖动口袋的痕迹。

本杰明爬过围墙，进入一片草原。他又发现了一个新设的鼹鼠夹。他依然没跟丢老獾汤米。现在已经快到傍晚了。其他的兔子都从洞中出来，享受傍晚时分的空气。其中一只穿着蓝外套的兔子，正自顾自地忙着寻找蒲公英。“彼得表弟！彼得兔！彼得兔！”本杰明喊道。

穿蓝外套的兔子耳朵竖起，立直了身子，问道：

“怎么了，本杰明表哥？是有猫吗？还是鼬獾约翰？”

“不，不，不！他抢了我的孩子们！——是老獾汤米——都装在一个口袋里——你看到他了吗？”

“老獾汤米？他抢走了几个孩子，本杰明表哥？”

“七个，彼得表弟，这一窝所有的宝宝都被抢走了！他是从这条路走的吗？快告诉我！”

“是的，是的，不到十分钟之前……他说口袋里面是毛毛虫，我还在想如果真是毛毛虫的话，那里面踢蹬得就太厉害了。”

“哪条路？他走了哪条路，彼得表弟？”

“他带着口袋，里面装着活物，我看到他还设了一个鼹鼠夹。让我想想，本杰明表哥，从头到尾告诉我发生了什么。”本杰明就把事情讲了一遍。

“邦瑟姨父这么大年纪了，做事确实不够稳妥。”彼得一边想一边说，“不过现在还有两件事是比较乐观的。一是你的孩子们都活着，因为他们还在不断踢蹬，再有就是老獾汤米已经吃过点心了，他可能会去睡觉，然后留着小兔子们当早餐。”

“他走了哪条路？”

“本杰明表哥，镇定，我很清楚他走了哪条路。因为托德先生在小木屋那边，所以，汤米必定是去了托德先生的另一处房子，那处房子在公牛堤坝的顶上。我会知道这些，是因为他主动问我是否需要给棉花尾巴姐姐带信，他说他要经过棉花尾巴家。”（棉花尾巴嫁给了一只黑兔子，现在住在山上。）

彼得收起自己的蒲公英，陪着这个痛苦焦虑的父亲出发了。他们穿过了好几片田地，开始爬山。老獾汤米的踪迹非常明显。他似乎每隔十几码远就把口袋放下休息一下。

“他肯定累得喘不过气来了，我们离他很近了，从气味上就能判断得出来。真是个脏鬼！”彼得说。

阳光依然和煦温暖，斜斜地照射在山坡的草地上。半路上，他们看到棉花尾巴坐在自家门口，有四五只半大的小兔子在她身边玩耍，其中一只是黑色的，其他的都是棕色的。

棉花尾巴曾看到老獾汤米从远处经过。他们问她她丈夫是否在家，她却答非所问地说她看到老獾汤米休息了两次，并且老獾汤米还点了点头，指着口袋，似乎笑得直不起身子来。

“快点，彼得，老獾会把我的宝宝们煮了的，得再快点！”本杰明说。

他们继续向上爬啊爬啊。“他刚才肯定在家，我看到他的黑耳朵从洞中探了出来。”

“他们住得离公牛堤坝的岩石那儿太近了，没法和邻居吵架。走吧，本杰明表哥。”

当他们靠近公牛堤坝顶上的树林时，便开始蹑手蹑脚地走着。岩石间的树木长得十分茂盛，而就在那里，在那个石崖下面，托德先生在那里安了一个家。那正好在陡峭的堤坝顶上，石头和灌木把那里遮掩了起来。两只兔子小心翼翼地向上爬去，静静地听着，仔细地看着。

那处房子是个笼子、监狱和倒塌的猪圈的结合体。房子有一扇很结实的门，关得很严并且还紧紧地锁着。落日将窗框照得如同红色的火焰一般，但是厨房里的炉子并没有点着火，兔子们从窗户向里望的时候能够看到炉子里面堆着干柴火。

本杰明如释重负地呼了口气。不过厨房桌子上准备的东西让他又是一惊。桌上放着一个空的蓝色柳叶花纹的大馅饼盘子，旁边还摆着一把大号的切肉刀和叉子，另外还有一把斧子。

在桌子的另一边，半折起的桌布上放着一个盘子、一个平底杯、一套刀叉、盐罐和芥末，桌边还有一把椅子——也就是说，这是一个人享用晚餐的准备。

他们没有看见人，也没有看见小兔子们。厨房里面空荡荡的，很安静，时钟嘀嘀嗒嗒地走着。彼得和本杰明把鼻子抵在窗户上，透过暮色向里望着。然后他们绕过岩石，爬到了房子的另一边，那里湿漉漉的，有一股怪味儿，长满了荆棘和石楠。两只兔子吓得直发抖。

“我可怜的小兔子宝宝啊！真是个可怕的地方！我再也见不到他们了！”本杰明叹着气说。

他们爬到了卧室窗户前。这里也像厨房的窗户一样关着，并上了闩。但是有迹象表明这个窗户最近被打开过。蜘蛛网被破坏了，窗台上有刚留下的脏脚印。

屋里面一片漆黑，一开始他们什么都看不见，不过他们听到了一个声音——是低沉而有规律的鼾声。他们的眼睛慢慢适应了黑暗，辨认出有个身影睡在托德先生的床上，正蜷着身子缩在毯子下面。“他穿着靴子就爬到床上去了。”彼得轻声说。本杰明非常紧张，拉着彼得赶快离开了窗台。

老獾汤米的呼噜声依然在继续，从托德先生的床上有规律地传出来。他们完全看不到小兔子们在哪里。

太阳已经下山了，树林中有一只猫头鹰开始叫唤。许多让人不喜欢的东西散落在周围，这些东西本该被埋起来的，比如兔子骨头、颅骨和鸡腿，还有其他吓人的东西。这是一个恐怖的地方，而且非常黑。

他们又回到了房子前面，尝试了各种办法，想要打开厨房窗户的窗闩；想要撬开窗扇上一颗生锈的钉子，但是没有用，特别是现在一点儿光都没有。他们肩并肩坐在窗户外面，低声说着话，静静地听着。

半个小时后，月亮升到了树林上空。清冷明亮的月光照着岩石中的这座房子，照着厨房的窗户。但是，哎呀，还是一只小兔子宝宝都看不到！

月光照射在切肉刀和馅饼盘子上，闪烁着，在肮脏的地板上投射出一道亮光。借着月光，可以看到在厨房壁炉旁边的墙上有一道小铁门——一道老式的、烧柴的砖炉烤箱的门。很快，彼得和本杰明几乎同时注意到，只要他们摇动窗户，对面的那扇小门就也会摇动着回应他们。小兔子们还活着，就被关在烤箱里！

本杰明激动万分，幸好老獾汤米没被吵醒。汤米低沉的呼噜声依然从托德先生的床上传来。不过，这个发现并没有令人多么安心。他们依然打不开窗户，尽管小兔子们还活着，但是根本没有能力自救，他们都还很小，还不会爬呢。

小声商量了一阵儿后，彼得和本杰明决定挖一条地道。他们在堤坝下面一两码的地方开始挖，希望可以从岩石间挖出一条地道，通向屋内。厨房的地板太脏了，看不出来它到底是土的还是石头的。

他们挖啊挖啊，挖了好几个钟头。由于有石头，他们没有办法挖直路，但是在长夜将尽的时候，他们终于挖到了厨房地板下面。本杰明躺在地道里，仰着身子挖着。彼得的爪子已经被磨坏了，他在地道外面，负责把挖出来的沙子运走。他喊道：“天亮了——太阳升起来了！”下面树林中的松鸦开始叽叽喳喳。

本杰明从黑暗的地道中出来，摇晃掉耳朵里的沙子，用爪子抹了抹脸。每过一分钟，阳光都令山顶上暖和一点儿。山谷里是一片白色迷雾的海洋，还能看见被阳光染成金色的树梢。

从迷雾中的田野里又传来了一声松鸦愤怒的叫声——然后是一声狐狸尖锐的号叫！

两只兔子彻底慌了神。他们做了平生最蠢的事情，他们匆匆忙忙地躲进了新挖出来的小地道里，藏到了最里面，那里就在托德先生厨房的地板下方。

托德先生正在向公牛堤坝上爬，他此刻的心情糟透了。最初，他因为打碎了盘子而恼怒。这全是他自己的错，那是一个瓷盘子，是他祖母雌狐威克森·托德留下来的最后一件餐具了。而后，令人讨厌的蚊子弄得他烦上加烦。他又没能成功地在一只母野鸡的窝里抓住她，只在野鸡窝里找到了五颗蛋，其中两个还臭了。托德先生这一整夜过得可真不舒心。

像往常一样，当心情不好的时候，他就决定搬家。一开始，他搬去了秃柳树那里的住处，但是那里太潮湿了，水獭还在附近留下了一条死鱼。托德先生不喜欢任何人留下的东西，除了他自己的。于是他就上山来了，看到老獾留下的不容错认的痕迹，他的心情更差了。除了老獾汤米没有人会把苔藓挖得乱七八糟。

托德先生用他的手杖抽打着地面，真是火冒三丈，他能猜到老獾汤米去了哪里。更令他生气的是，有只松鸦一直跟着他，那只松鸦从一棵树飞到另一棵树，不停地厉声叫着，警告能听到这叫声的所有兔子：有猫或是狐狸正往树林里走。有一次，他从托德先生的头顶一边叫着一边飞过，托德先生向他厉声斥骂，并大声吼叫起来。

托德先生小心翼翼地靠近了他的房子，拿着一把生锈的大钥匙。他嗅来嗅去，胡须不停地抽动。房子上着锁，不过托德先生还是怀疑里面有人。他把生锈的钥匙插入锁孔转动着，藏在地下的两只兔子听得清清楚楚。托德先生轻手轻脚地打开门，走了进去。

自己厨房中的景象令托德先生怒不可遏。厨房里，托德先生的椅子，他的馅饼盘子，他的刀叉，他的芥末和盐罐，还有他本来叠起来放在橱柜里面的桌布——现在全都摆在外面，准备晚餐用（也可能是早餐）——想都不用想，这一切都是讨厌的老獾汤米干的。

很幸运，屋里面有新鲜泥土的味道和肮脏的老獾的味道，盖住了兔子的气息。而吸引托德先生注意力的是一种声音——一串低沉、缓慢而有规律的呼噜声，是从他的床上传来的。

他透过半开着的卧室门的缝隙向里看去，然后他转身匆匆忙忙地跑到了房子外面。他的胡子都翘了起来，脖子上的毛也都竖了起来，真是愤怒到了极点。

接下来的二十分钟里，托德先生不断地悄悄潜进屋内，然后又匆匆地退出来。最后，他终于大胆地向前——直接进了卧室。当他在房子外面时，会气得直刨地。但当他进到屋里后，他又实在不愿意看老獾汤米的那副牙。汤米平躺着，他的嘴张着，咧得大大的，几乎咧到了耳朵了。他很平静、很有规律地打着呼噜，但是他的一只眼睛并没有完全闭紧。

托德先生从卧室进进出出。有两次，他进去的时候带着他的拐杖，还有一次，他拿了煤斗，但是他想了想之后，又拿着出去了。等他放下煤斗再回来的时候，老獾汤米躺得更靠床边了，但是他似乎睡得更香甜了。他是一个懒到不可救药的人，另外，他一点儿都不害怕托德先生，他就是太懒了，躺得太舒服了，不愿意动一下。

托德先生这一次拿着一根晾衣绳回到了卧室。他站在那里打量着老獾汤米，凝神听着他打呼噜的声音，足有一分钟之久。那呼噜声确实非常大，但也似乎很正常。

托德转身背对着床，去开窗户。窗户吱嘎作响，他吓了一跳，赶紧转身看。老獾汤米刚刚睁开一只眼睛，又匆忙地闭上了。呼噜声依然在继续。

托德先生的行为非常古怪，也格外不安。因为床位于卧室的门和窗户之间。他把窗户打开了一点儿，然后把晾衣绳的大部分都放到了外面的窗台上。留在里面的绳子末梢上有一个钩子，被握在他手中。

老獾汤米依然在尽责地打着呼噜。托德先生站着看了他一会儿，然后又离开了屋子。老獾汤米睁开双眼，看着绳子，咧嘴笑了。窗户外面传来一阵响动。老獾汤米又赶紧闭上了眼睛。

托德先生出了前门，绕到了房子后面。路上，他在兔子们挖出来的洞那儿绊了一下。如果他知道是谁躲在洞中的话，肯定会立刻把他们拉出来的。托德先生的脚陷到了地道里，几乎就踩到了彼得和本杰明的头上，但幸运的是，他以为这洞是老獾汤米挖的。他拿起窗台上的那卷绳子，仔细听了一阵儿，然后把绳子绑到了树上。

老獾汤米用一只眼睛透过窗户看着托德先生。他有点儿迷糊了。

托德先生从山泉那里打了满满一大桶水，提着沉重的水桶，他摇摇晃晃地穿过厨房，进入卧室。

老獾汤米依然在很用心地打着呼噜，甚至还发出了哼哼声。

托德先生把水桶放在床边，拿起带着钩子的那端绳子，犹豫了一下，他看了看老獾汤米。那呼噜声就像是要中风了似的，不过他的嘴咧得没有那么大了。

托德先生小心翼翼地爬上了一把放在床头架边上的椅子。他的腿离老獾汤米的牙齿格外近，真的非常危险。他伸长手，把绳子带钩子的那端穿过大床的帐顶，那里本该是挂床帐用的。

由于房子没有人住，托德先生的床帐被叠好收了起来，床单也收了起来。老獾汤米身上只盖着一条毯子。托德先生站在晃晃荡荡的椅子上，仔细地端详着汤米，他睡得太沉了，要是有睡觉比赛的话，他肯定会得第一名。似乎，没有什么事情能把他吵醒，哪怕是在床上方飞荡的绳子。

托德先生安全地从椅子上面下来，又拎着那桶水想要再爬到椅子上去。他打算把水桶挂在钩子上，悬在老獾汤米的头上方，给汤米洗个冷水澡，他从窗外拉动绳子就可以做到。

尽管托德先生心怀恶意，尽管他长着浅棕色的胡须，但是作为一个腿很细的人，要把那么重的东西举到钩子的高度，他的力气真的不够。他几乎没有办法站稳身子。

呼噜声越来越激烈了，老獾汤米的一条腿在毯子下面动了动，不过他依然保持着平静的睡姿。

托德先生拎着桶从椅子上安全地下来了，考虑了一会儿后，他把桶里的水倒到了一个洗脸盆里和一个水罐里，空桶就没有那么重了，他可以拎得动。他把空水桶吊挂在了老獾汤米的头上方。

肯定从来都没有睡得这么沉的人！托德先生在椅子上不停地上上下下，下下上上。由于没有办法一次性把整桶水举高，他就去取了一个牛奶罐来，一点一点地把水往空水桶里面舀。水桶越来越满，像个钟摆一样摇来摇去。有时候，会有水滴溅落下来，不过老獾汤米的鼾声依然很有规律，他一动也未动过——除了一只眼睛。

最后，托德先生的准备工作终于完成了。水桶里面装满了水，绳子在床的上方绷得紧紧的，绳子的另一端穿过窗台，系在外面的树上。

“这会把我的卧室搞得一团糟，不过不这样大清扫一次，我就再也不会在这张床上睡觉了。”

托德先生最后又看了老獾汤米一眼，然后轻手轻脚地离开了卧室。他走到房子外面，关上前门。两只兔子听到他的脚步声就在地道上面响过。他跑到房子后面，想要解开绳子，把满桶的水洒到老獾汤米的身上。

“我要用个惊喜来叫醒他，只是他不会愉快的。”托德先生说。

托德先生刚一走，老獾汤米便赶紧从床上爬起来。他把托德先生的睡衣卷成一团，放在床上，就在水桶的下方，来代替他自己，然后他也离开了房间——嘴咧得大大的，大到了极限。老獾汤米走进厨房，生火烧上水，这个时候，他并没有费心去烹煮那些小兔子。

托德先生到了树边的时候，发现水桶的重量带来的拉力把绳结拽得死死的，已经解不开了。他不得不用牙齿啃绳子，他啃了二十多分钟，最后绳子猛地一抽，溜了出去，差点儿把他的牙齿拉掉，让他狠狠地向后摔了过去。

房子里面传来一声很大的响声，还有水哗啦啦喷溅的声音，还有水桶骨碌碌滚动的声音。不过没有惊叫声。托德先生很疑惑，他静静地坐着，全神贯注地听着，然后他透过窗户向里面望。水从床上滴滴答答地往下流，水桶已经滚到了房间的一个角落。

而就在床的中间，在毯子下面，有一个湿漉漉的被压平了的东西——就在中间，桶掉下来的地方，陷得格外深一些，似乎是把肚子砸穿了。那个东西的头被盖在湿毯子下面，呼噜声已经没有了。除了水从床垫往下滴落的“滴答”“滴答”声以外，没有任何声音。

托德先生看了半个小时，他的眼睛闪闪发光。然后他欢跳雀跃，甚至大胆地敲着窗户，不过床上的那个东西一点儿都没有动。

是的——毫无疑问——结果比他计划的还要好，桶砸到了可怜的老獾汤米，把他给砸死了。

“我要把这个讨厌的老家伙埋在他自己挖的洞里。我要把我的被褥都搬出来，放到太阳下面晒。”托德先生说，“我要洗桌布，并把它铺在草地上、在太阳底下晒白。必须把那毯子挂出来吹吹风，床上肯定需要彻底消毒，然后用长柄炭炉烘干，再用热水瓶加热。我要用到软肥皂，猴子肥皂，还有各式各样的肥皂，还有碱水和硬毛刷，还有杀虫粉，还有碳粉来去味儿。我必须得进行一次彻底消毒。也许我得烧些硫磺粉。”

托德先生匆匆地绕过房子，想去厨房拿一把铲子。“首先，我得把这个洞给弄好了，然后把毯子里的那个人给拖出来……”

他打开了门……

老獾汤米正坐在托德先生的餐桌边，从托德先生的茶壶里往托德先生的杯子中倒茶。他身上非常干爽，而且在咧着嘴笑。他把一杯滚烫的茶泼向了托德先生。

然后托德先生扑向了老獾汤米，老獾汤米在碎瓷片中和托德先生扭打了起来，一场恐怖的大战在厨房爆发。对于躲在地下的两只兔子来说，每一次家具倒下的声音，听起来都像是地板要塌下来一样。他们悄悄地从地道里爬出来，在岩石和灌木丛中徘徊，不安地听着动静。

屋子里面一片喧嚣，十分吓人。在烤箱中的小兔子宝宝们被吵醒了，全都吓得浑身发抖，也许应该庆幸他们还被关在烤箱里面。

厨房里面的一切都被打翻了，只有餐桌还是立着的。除了壁炉台和防火栅栏，所有东西都被打破了。瓶瓶罐罐全都被摔得粉碎。椅子坏了，窗玻璃、钟表都摔碎了，地上还有几缕托德先生的浅棕色胡须。花瓶从壁炉台上滚了下来，罐子从架子上掉了下来，水壶从壶架上翻了下来。老獾汤米一脚踩进了一罐子木莓果酱里。水壶里滚开的水洒到了托德先生的尾巴上。

水壶落下的时候，一直咧着嘴笑的老獾汤米刚好占了上风，他像滚一根圆木一样，把托德先生从门口滚了出去。吼叫和撕咬转战到了门外，他们滚过堤坝，滚下山，在岩石间撞来撞去。老獾汤米和托德先生之间再没有任何情义可言。

河滩边一平静下来，彼得和本杰明就立刻从灌木丛中出来了。

“抓紧时间！跑进去，本杰明表哥！跑进去把小兔子们救出来，我在门口把风！”

但是本杰明被吓坏了。

“哎呀，哎呀，他们很快就会回来的！”

“不，他们不会的。”

“他们会的！”

“真是自己吓唬自己！我觉得他们肯定摔到下面的采石场去了。”

本杰明依然在犹豫，彼得不得不一直用力推着他。

“快点儿，没事儿的。记得出来时把烤箱门关上，本杰明表哥，这样他就不会想起他们了。”

很显然，托德先生的厨房里还有活物。

此时的兔子洞中，气氛却让人不太舒服。

噗噗和老邦瑟先生在晚餐的时候又吵了起来，各自都度过了一个无眠的夜晚，在早饭的时候争吵再度爆发。老邦瑟先生无法再否认他邀请了朋友进过兔子洞，但是他拒绝回应噗噗的质问和责备。那天过得很沉重。

老邦瑟先生闷闷不乐，缩在一个角落里，将一把椅子挡在自己身前。噗噗拿走了他的烟斗，藏起了他的烟草。她进行了一次彻底的大扫除，以缓解自己的情绪。她刚刚把一切做完，躲在椅子后面的老邦瑟先生就不安地猜想她接下来会做些什么。

托德先生的厨房里，现在是一片废墟了，本杰明穿过一片浓重的尘埃，紧张地走向烤箱。他打开烤箱门，手探进去摸索，发现里面有暖暖的扭来扭去的东西。他小心翼翼地提出来，然后去和彼得会合。

“我找到他们了！我们能走了吗？还是我们要先躲起来，彼得表弟？”

彼得支棱起耳朵，远处扭打的声音依然在树林中回响。

五分钟后，两只上气不接下气的兔子从公牛堤坝上飞奔下来，他们俩合力半拖半拉地拽着一个口袋，跌跌撞撞地穿过草地，最后终于安全到了家，冲进了兔子洞中。

当彼得和本杰明带着小兔子们回来时，老邦瑟先生如释重负，噗噗也欣喜若狂。小兔子们被折腾得很厉害，而且也饿了，他们被喂过食物，然后安顿上床睡觉。没多久，他们就康复了。

一个长长的新烟斗和一份新鲜的兔子烟草被送到老邦瑟先生面前，虽然他自尊心很强，还在计较面子，不过还是接受了。

老邦瑟先生得到了原谅，全家人一起吃饭。彼得和本杰明把他们的经历告诉了大家——不过他们停留的时间不够长，没有办法说出老獾汤米和托德先生之间的战斗到底是什么结果。

小猪平平的故事

从前，有一只上了年纪的母猪，叫作蹄子阿姨，她家里有八个孩子，其中有四只小母猪，分别是暴脾气、吸吸、笑笑和点点，另外四只小公猪，分别是亚历山大、平平、下巴颏和秃尾巴。秃尾巴的尾巴曾经发生过一些事故。

这八只小猪的胃口都很好。“哟哟哟，他们吃啊吃，他们真的是吃个不停！”蹄子阿姨骄傲地看着她的孩子们。这时突然传来了一阵恐怖的尖叫声，亚历山大钻进了猪食槽的铁环里，被卡在那里了。蹄子阿姨和我抓着他的后腿才把他拉了出来。

下巴颏总是做丢脸的事情，洗衣日那天，他吃掉了一块肥皂。不一会儿，我们在一篮子干净的衣服中，发现了另一只脏兮兮的小猪。“哟哟哟！这到底是哪个呀？”蹄子阿姨嘟囔道。

整个家里的小猪都是粉色的，或是粉色带黑色斑点的，但这只小猪全身都是黑乎乎的，等把这只小猪放进浴桶里洗过后发现，这是笑笑。

我走进了菜园，发现暴脾气和吸吸把胡萝卜都拔出来了，我打了她们一顿，拎着她们的耳朵把她们揪出了菜园。暴脾气还想咬我。

“蹄子阿姨，蹄子阿姨！你是个值得尊敬的人，可是你的孩子却没有良好的教养。他们每个都调皮捣蛋，只有点点和平平还不错。”

“是啊，是啊。”蹄子阿姨叹了口气，“而且他们喝了好多桶牛奶，我不得不再养一头奶牛才行！乖乖的小点点要留在家做家务，其他的都必须离开。四只小公猪和四只小母猪如果都凑在一起，实在太多了。是啊，是啊，是啊，”蹄子阿姨说，“如果没有他们，食物就会很充足了。”

所以下巴颏和吸吸坐在一辆独轮车里离开了，秃尾巴、笑笑和暴脾气乘着一辆马车走了。

剩下的两只小公猪，平平和亚历山大，要去集市了。我们刷了他们的皮毛，把他们的尾巴绕得更卷翘一些，洗干净他们的小脸，在院子中和他们道别。

蹄子阿姨用一块很大的手帕擦着眼泪，然后她擦了擦小猪平平的鼻涕，又流下了眼泪；接着她又擦了擦亚历山大的鼻涕，眼泪又流下来了。然后她把手帕递给了点点。蹄子阿姨叹了一口气，咕噜着，对小猪们说出了下面的话：

“小猪平平，我的儿子小猪平平，你必须要去集市。牵着你的弟弟亚历山大的手。注意别弄脏你礼拜天的好衣服，记得擦鼻涕——”蹄子阿姨又把手绢递给他们俩，“小心陷阱，小心鸡窝，小心咸肉和鸡蛋，要一直用你的后腿走路。”小猪平平是一只安静的小猪，他神情肃穆地看着自己的母亲，一滴眼泪从他的脸颊上滑落。

蹄子阿姨开始对另一个儿子说话：“我的儿子亚历山大，拉着——”

“喂，喂，喂！”亚历山大咯咯笑了起来。

“拉着你的哥哥平平的手，你必须去集市。注意——”

“喂，喂，喂！”亚历山大又打断了妈妈的话。

“你没好好听我说话！”蹄子阿姨说，“注意看路标和里程碑，不要吃到鲱鱼刺——”

“另外记住，”我强调，“你们只要过了村子的分界线，就回不来了。亚历山大，你没有认真听。这里有两张允许两只猪去往兰开夏集市的许可证。听着，亚历山大。我去警察局弄这些证件可并不容易，我可不想再去一次。”小猪平平严肃地听着，而亚历山大则不可救药地跑着神。

为了保险，我把证件用别针别在了他们的马甲口袋里。蹄子阿姨给每只小猪一个小包袱，八颗薄荷糖，以及写在一卷纸上的行为规范。然后，他们便出发了。

小猪平平和亚历山大快步前进，走了一英里远，至少平平走了一英里。亚历山大有半里路都是不停地从路一边跳到另一边。他手舞足蹈，不停地捏他的哥哥，还唱着歌：

这只小猪去集市，
这只小猪家中留，
这只小猪吃肉肉——

“看看他们给咱们准备了什么饭，平平？”

平平和亚历山大坐在地上，解开了包袱。亚历山大立刻就把自己的饭狼吞虎咽地吃完了。他还吃光了他的薄荷糖。“给我一颗糖吧，求求你了，平平。”

“但我想留着在紧急情况时用。”平平迟疑地说。亚历山大尖声笑了起来，然后他用固定他许可证的别针刺平平，平平挥手打他时，他把别针弄掉了，就想要抢平平的别针，两份证件混在了一起。平平训斥了亚历山大。

不过，不一会儿，他们就和好了，又一起小跑着向前走。他们边走边唱：

汤姆，汤姆，吹笛人的儿子，
他偷了一只猪，然后跑掉了！
但是他会吹的调子只有一首，
《在山的那边遥远的地方》！

“说什么？年轻的先生们？偷了一只猪？你们的许可证呢？”警察说。在一个拐弯的地方他们差一点儿就撞到他身上。平平拿出了自己的证件，亚历山大摸索了一阵后，递出了一个皱巴巴的东西——

“两盎司半糖果，花费三法寻。——这是什么？这可不是许可证。”亚历山大的脸垮了下来，他把许可证给弄丢了。“我有一份许可证的，我真有的，警察先生。”

“看上去你出门的时候他们的确是让你带了。我要经过农场。你可以跟着我走。”

“我也能回去吗？”平平问。

“我觉得你没必要，年轻的先生。你的许可证没问题。”

平平并不愿意独自上路，而且天也开始下雨了。但是和警察争执并不明智，他给了弟弟一颗薄荷糖，目送他走出了自己的视线。

简单介绍下亚历山大的经历——警察大约在下午茶的时候悠闲地走进了我们的房子，后面跟着一只湿漉漉、沮丧的小猪。我把亚历山大处理给了邻居，他安顿下来之后过得很好。

平平垂头丧气地独自前行，他走到十字路口，看到了一个路标——“去集市镇五英里；翻山四英里；去蹄子农场三英里。”

平平很吃惊，今天晚上到达集市镇的希望微乎其微，而明天就是雇佣集市了。一想到亚历山大的玩闹浪费了多少时间，他的心情就更糟了。他惆怅地望了望通往山里的那条路，然后便乖乖地走上了另一条路。他扣紧了外套，以抵御雨水。他从来都不想去，一想到自己独自站在一个拥挤的集市中，被别人审视，推搡，被某个陌生的大个子农夫雇走，他真的非常难过。

“我希望自己能有个小菜园，种些土豆。”平平说。他把凉凉的手插入口袋，摸到了自己的许可证，他把另一只手放入了另一个口袋，摸到了另一张许可证——那是亚历山大的！平平尖叫了起来，然后疯狂地往回跑，希望能追上亚历山大和警察。但是他拐错了一个弯，又拐错了好几个弯，最后彻底迷路了。

天越来越黑，风在低吟，树枝摇曳，吱嘎作响。

平平越来越害怕，哭了起来。“喂，喂，喂，我找不到回家的路了！”经过一个小时的游荡后，他终于离开了森林，月光穿过云层照射了下来，一个从没有见过的村子出现在平平眼前。一条路穿过一片荒原，下面是一条宽阔的山谷，有一条小河在月光下闪烁着波光，而在远处——朦胧的远方——是群山。

他看到一座小木屋，便走了过去，偷偷摸摸地进了屋。“我很担心这里是个鸡窝，不过我还能怎么办呢？”平平说，他浑身湿漉漉的，很冷，而且实在累坏了。

“咸肉和鸡蛋，咸肉和鸡蛋！”一只母鸡在栖息处上叫道。

“陷阱！陷阱！陷阱！咯咯！咯咯！咯咯！”被打扰到的公鸡斥责道。“去集市！去集市！咯咯叽！”他旁边一只正在抱窝的白母鸡叫道。小猪平平被吓坏了，决定天一亮就离开。渐渐地，他和母鸡们都睡着了。

不到一个小时，他们都被吵醒了。鸡窝的主人彼得·汤马斯·派伯森先生提着一盏灯和一个大筐子，准备抓六只鸡，第二天早晨带去集市上卖。他抓住了公鸡旁边的白母鸡，然后他的眼睛落到了缩在角落里的平平身上。他说了一句莫名其妙的话：“哈，这又是一只！”他抓住了平平的脖子，把他丢进了筐子里。然后他又抓住了五只脏兮兮的不停踢蹬乱叫的母鸡，丢到了平平的身上。

筐子里面装了六只鸡和一只小猪，分量可不轻。筐子被带着下山，一路颠簸。尽管快被那些小母鸡抓成碎片了，小猪平平尽量想办法把他的证件和薄荷糖都藏到了衣服里面。

最后，筐子终于被重重地放在了一间厨房的地板上，盖子被掀开来，小猪被抓了出来。他抬头看去，眨着眼睛，看到了一个丑得出奇的老头儿，正咧着大嘴笑。

“反正这只是自己送上门来的。”派伯森先生说着，把小猪的口袋翻了个底朝天。他把筐子推到角落里，扔了一个口袋盖在上面，以便让母鸡们保持安静，然后在炉火上放了一个水壶，接着便解开了他的靴子。

小猪平平拉过一张铜凳子，坐在边缘上，害羞地烤着自己的手。派伯森先生脱下靴子，扔到了厨房另一边的护墙板上。这时传来了一个压抑的声音。“闭嘴！”派伯森先生说。平平烤着手，看着他。

派伯森先生拽下另一只靴子，也像第一只那样扔了出去。又传来一声奇怪的声音。“安静，好不好？”派伯森先生说。平平坐在铜凳的最边缘处。

派伯森先生从一个箱子里拿出了玉米粉，又做了一些粥。平平觉得，就在厨房的另一端，有什么东西正强忍着对这些食物的兴趣，但是他太饿了，没有精力去想那些声音的事儿了。

派伯森先生将三个盘子倒得满满的，他自己一份，平平一份，第三盘——瞪了平平一眼之后——拿走了，还锁了起来。小猪平平战战兢兢地吃光了他的饭。

饭后，派伯森先生查了查日历，摸了摸小猪平平的肋骨，现在这个季节腌咸肉的话已经太晚了，他很舍不得自己的玉米粉。另外，那些母鸡已经看到这只小猪了。他看着自己剩下的熏猪肋肉不多了，然后又迟疑不决地看着小猪。“你可以睡在小地毯上。”彼得·汤马斯·派伯森先生说。

小猪平平睡得很香。早晨，派伯森先生又做了些粥。天气比昨天暖和多了。他看了看箱子里剩下的玉米粉，明显很不满意。“你还会继续走吗？”他问平平。

还没等平平回答，一个邻居在大门口处吹口哨——派伯森先生要带着母鸡搭他的车。派伯森先生匆匆忙忙提起筐子，命令小猪在他走后关上门，不该动的不要动。不然，“我回来就扒了你的皮！”派伯森先生说。

平平突然灵机一动，如果他也请求搭车，也许他也能够及时到达集市。但是他不相信彼得·汤马斯。

慢悠悠地吃过早饭后，小猪平平四处查看了一下小屋。所有东西都被锁起来了。他看到厨房后面的一个桶里面有一些土豆皮。平平吃掉了土豆皮，在桶里洗了盛粥用的盘子。他一边干活一边唱歌：

汤姆用他的笛子吹出了声音，
引来了所有的男孩和女孩，
他们全都跑来听他演奏
《在山的那边遥远的地方》！

突然间，有一个小小的、压抑的声音加入了进来：

在山的那边很远很远的地方，
风会把我的头饰给吹跑！

小猪平平放下正在擦着的盘子，仔细听着。

过了好长一会儿，小猪平平踮着脚尖走过去，站在门口朝厨房的前面偷偷地看，那里什么人都没有。

又过了一会儿，小猪平平走到被锁着的橱柜门那里，嗅了嗅锁孔。这里也格外安静。

又过了一会儿，小猪平平把一块薄荷糖从门下面的缝隙中推了过去。糖很快就消失了。

那天，小猪平平把剩下的六块糖都塞了过去。

等到派伯森先生回来的时候，他看到小猪坐在炉火前，小猪平平刷了灶台，还在炉子上烧了壶水，只是平平拿不到玉米粉，所以做不了饭。

派伯森先生很友善，他拍了拍小猪的后背，做了很多粥，但忘了锁上装玉米粉的箱子。他的确给橱柜的门上了锁，但是却没有把门关严。他早早地就上床睡觉了，告诉小猪平平不管什么原因第二天也不要在十二点之前叫醒他。

小猪平平坐在炉火边，吃着自己的晚餐。就在这时，就在他的胳膊肘边，一个小小的声音说：“我的名字叫小猪薇格，请给我再做点粥吧！”小猪平平跳了起来，环顾四周。

一只非常可爱的黑色伯克夏小猪正笑眯眯地站在他身旁。那小猪有一双闪闪发亮的眯眯眼，双下巴，短短的小翘鼻。她指着小猪平平的盘子，平平急忙把盘子递给了她，然后跑到了装玉米粉的箱子边。“你是怎么来到这里的？”小猪平平问。

“被偷来的。”小猪薇格说，她的嘴里塞满了东西。平平心安理得地从箱子里拿了玉米粉。

“为什么偷你来？”

“为了做咸肉、火腿呗。”小猪薇格肯定地说。

“你为什么不逃跑呢？”被吓到的小猪平平问道。

“吃过饭后我就会跑的。”小猪薇格说。

小猪平平又做了些粥，害羞地看着她。她吃光了第二盘粥，站起身，看着周围，像是准备马上动身。

“你不能在夜里走。”小猪平平说。

小猪薇格似乎有些担心。

“你白天的时候认识路吗？”

“我知道我们能从河对岸的山上看到这座小白房子。你打算去哪里呢，猪先生？”

“去集市——我有两张猪的许可证。我可以带你到桥边，如果你不反对的话。”平平说，他坐在铜凳的边缘上，脑子一团乱。小猪薇格非常感激他，问了他许多问题，都让平平开始不好意思了。他不得不闭上眼睛，假装睡着了。小猪薇格也安静了下来，空气中传来了薄荷糖的气味。

“我以为你已经把糖都吃了。”小猪平平突然醒了过来。

“只啃了点边儿。”小猪薇格说，她就着炉火的光饶有兴趣地研究着糖纸上的话。

“你最好别吃糖，他隔着天花板都能闻到糖的气味。”小猪平平担心地说。

小猪薇格把黏糊糊的糖放回了口袋里。“唱首歌吧。”她要求道。

“抱歉——我牙疼。”小猪平平惊慌地说。

“那我来唱。”小猪薇格回说，“如果我唱‘嘀哩哩嘀’你不会介意吧？有些歌词我已经忘了。”

平平没有反对，他半闭着眼睛坐着，看着她。她把脑袋摇来晃去，打着节拍，用甜美的、小小的咕哝声唱道：

有一只古怪的猪妈妈，
住在一个猪圈里，
她有三只小猪娃，
嘀哩哩嘀哩哩，嗯嗯嗯
小猪们说：呜喂！呜喂！

小猪薇格成功地唱了三四小节，只是每唱一小节，她的头就会更低一些。她闪光的小眼睛慢慢闭上了。

三只小猪长得瘦又弱，
他们瘦得实在太厉害，
因为他们不说嗯嗯嗯！
而且他们不说哼哼哼！
因为他们不说——

小猪薇格的头越来越低，到最后她蜷成了一团，就像一个圆球一样，很快就在壁炉前的地毯上睡着了。

小猪平平踮着脚，给她盖上了一个椅子罩。他害怕自己也睡过去，那天晚上，他一直坐着，听着蟋蟀的叫声和楼上派伯森先生的呼噜声。

第二天一早，天刚蒙蒙亮，小猪平平便扎好了自己的小包袱，叫醒了小猪薇格。她很激动，又有点儿害怕。“但天还黑着呢！我们该怎么找到路呢？”

“公鸡已经叫过了。我们必须在母鸡出来之前出发。不然她们会大喊，叫醒派伯森先生的。”

小猪薇格又坐了下来，哭了起来。

“起来，薇格，等我们习惯了，就看得清路了。来吧！我听见母鸡们咯咯叫了。”

平平一直脾气很好，从来都没有对母鸡说过“嘘”，另外他想起了那个大筐子。他悄悄地打开了房门，走出去后又关好。这里没有菜园，派伯森先生家周围都被家禽刨得乱糟糟的。他和小猪薇格手拉着手，穿过了一片没打理的田地，向大路走去。

在他们穿越荒原时，太阳升了起来，一道阳光从山顶上照射下来。阳光慢慢地滑过斜坡，洒向平静的绿色山谷，在菜园和果园当中有一些白色的小屋。

“那是威斯特莫兰德。”小猪薇格说，她松开了平平的手，跳起了舞，边跳边唱：

汤姆，汤姆，吹笛人的儿子，
偷了一只猪，然后跑掉了！
但是他会吹的调子只有一首，
《在山的那边遥远的地方》！

“快点，小猪薇格，我们必须在村民们起来之前走到那座桥。”

“你为什么想要去集市，小猪平平？”小猪薇格脱口问道。

“我也不想去。我想种土豆。”

“吃块糖吗？”小猪薇格问。平平气呼呼地拒绝了。

“你那可怜的牙又疼了？”小猪薇格问。平平哼哼了起来。

小猪薇格自己吃掉了薄荷糖，然后顺着路的另一边向前走。“小猪薇格！在墙根儿底下走，那儿有个人在犁地。”小猪薇格过来了，他们急匆匆地下山，往村界处走。

突然，平平停了下来，他听到了车轮声。

在他们下方的路上，慢慢地驶来了一辆商人的马车。缰绳轻拍在马背上，车上的杂货商正读着报纸。

“把糖吐出来，小猪薇格，我们可能得跑一段。什么也别说，别担心。看着那座桥！”可怜的平平说道。他几乎快哭了。他开始一瘸一拐地走起来，还挽住了小猪薇格的胳膊。

那个杂货商的注意力本来都在报纸上，如果他的马没有受惊、打响鼻的话，他可能注意不到小猪平平他们，也就那么过去了。他把马车停到一边，放下了马鞭说：“喂！你们要去哪里啊？”小猪平平茫然地望着他。

“你聋了吗？你们是去集市吗？”小猪慢慢地点了点头。

“我本来昨天也想去的。给我看看你们的许可证。”

平平盯着杂货商的马的后蹄，它那里卡了一块石头。

杂货商挥动了一下鞭子。“证件呢？猪的许可证呢？”

小猪平平翻遍了自己全身的口袋，最后拿出证件递给了杂货商。杂货商看了证件，不过似乎依然不满意。“这只猪是个年轻的女士，她的名字叫亚历山大吗？”薇格张了张嘴，又闭了起来。平平像得了哮喘一样疯狂地咳嗽起来。

杂货商用手指划过报纸上的广告栏。“失踪，被窃或是走失，重谢十先令。”他充满怀疑地看着小猪薇格。然后他在车里站了起来，朝着那个犁地的人吹了声口哨。

“你们在这等着，我过去跟他说句话。”杂货商说着，笼起了缰绳。他知道这些猪很狡猾，不过，一只瘸得很厉害的猪可是跑不起来的！

“现在还不能动，小猪薇格，他会回头看的。”杂货商果然回头看了，他看到两只小猪好像树桩一样，一动不动地待在大路中间。然后他检查了一下自己的马的蹄子，那马现在也瘸了。他找到了犁地的人之后，花了些时间才把那石头弄了出去。

“现在，小猪薇格，赶紧跑！”平平说。

从来都没有任何猪像这两只猪一样跑得那么快！他们一路狂奔，尖叫着冲下了长长的白色山坡，跑向那座桥。小胖猪薇格的衬裙都飞起来了，她连跑带跳，蹄子“啪嗒”“啪嗒”地踩在路上。

他们跑啊，跑啊，一直跑下了山，抄了一条在山脚平坦的绿草地上的近路，走到了鹅卵石河床和灯芯草中间。

他们来到了河边，跑到了桥上，手拉着手过了桥——之后，在山的那边遥远的地方，小猪薇格和小猪平平一起跳起了舞。

爱普莉·达普利的童谣

有一只棕色的小老鼠，

名叫爱普莉·达普利，

钻进某家的橱柜里。

橱柜里有很多好东西，

蛋糕，奶酪，果酱和饼干

——全都对老鼠有吸引力！

爱普莉·达普利，

有双锐利的小眼睛。

爱普莉·达普利，

它特别特别爱馅饼。

是谁把棉花尾巴家的门敲起？

嗒嗒嗒，啪啪啪，敲门声似乎熟悉？

探头向外望去，

没有人在那里。

只有一些胡萝卜，

放在门前台阶上。

啊呀呀！我又听到了，

嗒嗒嗒，啪啪啪！

啊哈哈——我敢肯定，

是那只黑色的小兔子！

老刺针，年纪老，

插针包，得不到。

鼻子黑，胡子灰，

路边有棵白蜡树，

树桩里面是华屋。

你认识那个老太太吗？

她住在一只鞋子里面，

她有很多很多个孩子，

多得不知道该怎么办。

如果她住在鞋子做的小房子里，

那这位小老太太肯定是一只老鼠。

迪戈瑞，迪戈瑞·戴尔维特！

一个小小老头儿，穿着黑色天鹅绒。

他挖啊挖，他掘啊掘，

你自己就能看到，

迪戈瑞·戴尔维特挖出了，

多少小土包。

肉汤和土豆，

装在炖锅中，

放到烤箱里，

趁热端上桌。

从前有只小豚鼠，

爱把头发向后梳，

温顺和气又礼貌，

就像带着假发套。

他戴了一个小领结，

就像天空一样蓝。

他的胡子和纽扣，

全都非常非常大。

城里老鼠约翰尼的故事

城里老鼠约翰尼出生在一个橱柜里。蒂米·威利出生在一个菜园里。蒂米·威利是一只乡下的小老鼠，阴差阳错地被装在一个柳条筐中带到了城里。园丁请送货人每个星期往城里送一次菜，菜被他装在一个大柳条筐子里。

园丁把筐子放在菜园门口，送货人经过的时候就会带走。蒂米·威利从柳条间的一个洞钻进了那个装菜的筐中，吃了一些豌豆，然后，蒂米·威利睡着了。他后来是被吓醒的，当时筐子正被搬起装到送货人的马车上。一阵震动后，传来了“嘚嘚”的马蹄声。其他的包裹也都被不断地装到车上，马车走了很久很久——颠——哒——颠——哒，蒂米·威利在杂乱无章的蔬菜中颤抖个不停。

最后，马车停在了一栋房子前，柳条筐被取了下来，送到房子里，放到地上。厨娘给了送货人六便士，后门被“砰”地关上，马车碌碌地走了。但是并没有安静下来，似乎有几百辆马车不断经过的隆隆声，狗的狂吠声，街上的男孩子们吹口哨的声音，厨娘的大笑声，客厅里的女佣顺着楼梯跑上跑下的声音，还有一只金丝雀像蒸汽引擎一样的叫声。

蒂米·威利自出生以来一直住在那个菜园里，面对这一切简直怕得要死。没过多久，厨娘便打开筐子，往外取蔬菜。被吓坏了的蒂米·威利猛地跳出了筐子。

厨娘吓得跳到了椅子上，尖叫着：“有老鼠！有老鼠！快找猫来！给我取个拨火棍来，莎拉！”蒂米·威利没有等着莎拉拿拨火棍来，他沿着踢脚板拼命地跑，直到看见一个小洞，便一头钻了进去。

他向下坠落了半英尺的距离，跌落到一个老鼠的晚宴当中，还打碎了三个玻璃杯。“这到底是谁啊？”城里的老鼠约翰尼问道。但经过最开始的惊慌之后，他立刻恢复了自己的礼仪。他以最好的礼节，将蒂米·威利介绍给了另外九只小老鼠，他们都有着长长的尾巴，戴着白色领结。蒂米·威利自己的尾巴很短，城里的老鼠约翰尼和他的朋友们都注意到了，但是他们的教养都很好，没有做任何评论，他们中只有一只问蒂米·威利是不是曾经被老鼠夹子困住过。

晚宴由八道菜组成，分量并不多，但是非常优雅。桌子上的菜肴，蒂米·威利都没有见过，他有点儿不敢去尝。只是他非常饿，又很希望能展现出社交礼仪。楼上持续不断传来的声音令他非常紧张，他摔了一个盘子。“没关系，盘子不是我们的。”约翰尼说，“那些年轻人为什么没有带着点心回来呢？”

得解释一下，有两只年轻的老鼠，负责伺候其他老鼠，在上菜的间歇，他们在通往厨房的楼梯上和人起了冲突，有好几次，他们都是滚进来的，尖叫着，大笑着，蒂米·威利得知有猫在追他们之后非常惊恐。他立刻就没了胃口，还觉得有些头晕。

“再吃点果冻？”城里的老鼠约翰尼说，“不要了吗？还是你想上床睡觉了？我会给你一个最最舒服的沙发靠枕。”

那个沙发靠枕上面有个洞。城里的老鼠很热诚地介绍说这是最好的床，是专门为客人留着的。但是沙发上散发着猫的气味。蒂米·威利更愿意在火炉围栏下面度过一个不舒服的夜晚。

第二天情况一模一样。一顿非常丰盛的早餐摆了出来——这些老鼠习惯吃咸肉，但蒂米·威利却从小到大都是以植物的根和沙拉为食。城里的老鼠约翰尼和他的朋友们在地板下面喧闹，在夜里的时候大胆地满屋子乱跑。莎拉端着茶盘跌下了楼梯，发出一声巨响。尽管有猫，但还是有不少的面包屑、糖果和果酱可以收集。

蒂米·威利渴望回家，回到阳光照耀的河岸上他那平静的窝里。这里的食物让他不舒服，噪音吵得人睡不着觉。过了几天，他就瘦了很多，城里的老鼠约翰尼也注意到了，于是便问他怎么了。他听了蒂米·威利对他的菜园的描述，还打听了那个菜园的事情。“听起来是个很无聊的地方啊。下雨的时候，你干些什么？”

“下雨的时候，我就坐在我小小的沙土洞穴里，给秋天时存下的玉米和种子剥皮。我会望着外面草地上的画眉鸟和乌鸫，还有我的朋友知更鸟。等到雨过天晴，太阳出来，你真应该去看看我的菜园和那些花儿，玫瑰，石竹，三色紫罗兰，那里一片宁静，只有鸟唱蜂鸣和草地中的羊羔咩咩叫。”

“那只猫又来了！”城里的老鼠约翰尼叫道。他们躲到储煤室后，他继续刚才的谈话：“我承认，我有点儿失望。我们想要好好招待你的，蒂莫西·威廉[1]。”

“噢，是的，是的，你们都特别热心。但是我觉得很不舒服。”蒂米·威利说。

“可能是因为你的牙齿和消化系统不太适应我们的食物。也许你钻进筐子里面回去比较明智。”

“哦？哦！”蒂米·威利叫道。

“哎呀，我们本来可以上个星期就送你回去的。”约翰尼很懊恼地说，“你难道不知道那个大筐子每个星期六都会空着送回去吗？”

就这样，蒂米·威利和他的新朋友作别，他带着一小块蛋糕和一片蔫了的卷心菜叶子躲到了筐子里。经过很多颠簸，他安全回到了自己的菜园里。

有时候，在星期六，蒂米·威利会看着放在大门口的柳条筐，但是他很清楚地知道不能再次进去。也没有人从筐子里面出来，尽管约翰尼曾经半认真地答应过要来拜访。

冬天过去了。当太阳在新的一天再次起来时。蒂米·威利坐在自己的洞穴边晒着自己小身体上的皮毛，嗅着紫罗兰和春草的香气。他几乎已经忘掉他去城里的旅行了。而就在这时，在沙土小路上走来了一个打扮整洁、一丝不苟、背着棕色皮包的人，那是城里的老鼠约翰尼。

蒂米·威利张开双臂欢迎他。“你在全年中最美好的时候来了，我们可以晒着太阳享用些香草布丁。”

“嗯嗯嗯！这里有点儿潮湿啊！”城里的老鼠约翰尼说。他把尾巴夹在胳膊下面，以防沾到泥土。

“那可怕的声音是什么啊？”他大声惊叫道。

“那？”蒂米·威利说，“那是头奶牛而已。我去找她讨点儿牛奶，她们不会伤害人的，除非是碰巧躺到了你的身上。我们那些朋友怎么样了？”

约翰尼的描述很平淡。他解释自己为什么在开春这么早就来拜访，那户人家去了海边过复活节，厨娘要留下做大扫除，只发伙食费，还得到特别指示要把老鼠都清理干净。家里又多了四只小猫，那只大猫把金丝雀给杀死了。

“他们说是我们干的，但是我很清楚到底是怎么回事。”约翰尼说，“那可怕的喧闹声又是怎么回事？”

“不过是割草机的声音。一会儿我去取些割下来的碎草来给你铺床。我肯定你在乡下会更踏实的，约翰尼。”

“嗯嗯嗯——等下个星期二再说吧。他们去了海边，筐子的送货也停了。”

“我肯定你不会再想回城里生活了。”蒂米·威利说。

但约翰尼还是回去了。是随下一次送菜的筐子回去的。他说村子里面太安静了。

一个地方适合一些人居住，另一个地方适合另外一些人居住。至于我自己，我更愿意住在乡下，就像蒂米·威利一样。

[1]蒂莫西·威廉是蒂米·威利的大名。

THE TALE OF BENJAMIN BUNNY

One morning a little rabbit sat on a bank. He pricked his ears and listened to the trit-trot, trit-trot of a pony.

A gig was coming along the road; it was driven by Mr. McGregor, and beside him sat Mrs. McGregor in her best bonnet.

As soon as they had passed, little Benjamin Bunny slid down into the road, and set off—with a hop, skip and a jump—to call upon his relations, who lived in the wood at the back of Mr. McGregor's garden.

That wood was full of rabbit-holes; and in the neatest sandiest hole of all, lived Benjamin's aunt and his cousins—Flopsy, Mopsy, Cotton-tail and Peter.

Old Mrs. Rabbit was a widow; she earned her living by knitting rabbit-wool mittens and muffetees (I once bought a pair at a bazaar). She also sold herbs, and rosemary tea, and rabbit-tobacco (which is what we call lavender).

Little Benjamin did not very much want to see his Aunt. He came round the back of the fir-tree, and nearly tumbled upon the top of his Cousin Peter. Peter was sitting by himself. He looked poorly, and was dressed in a red cotton pocket-handkerchief.

“Peter,”—said little Benjamin, in a whisper—“who has got your clothes?”

Peter replied—“The scarecrow in Mr. McGregor's garden,” and described how he had been chased about the garden, and had dropped his shoes and coat.

Little Benjamin sat down beside his cousin, and assured him that Mr. McGregor had gone out in a gig, and Mrs. McGregor also; and certainly for the day, because she was wearing her best bonnet.

Peter said he hoped that it would rain.

At this point, old Mrs. Rabbit's voice was heard inside the rabbit-hole, calling—“Cotton-tail! Cotton-tail! fetch some more camomile!”

Peter said he thought he might feel better if he went for a walk. They went away hand in hand, and got upon the flat top of the wall at the bottom of the wood. From here they looked down into Mr. McGregor's garden. Peter's coat and shoes were plainly to be seen upon the scarecrow, topped with an old tam-o-shanter of Mr. McGregor's.

Little Benjamin said, “It spoils people's clothes to squeeze under a gate; the proper way to get in, is to climb down a pear tree.”

Peter fell down head first; but it was of no consequence, as the bed below was newly raked and quite soft. It had been sown with lettuces. They left a great many odd little foot-marks all over the bed, especially little Benjamin, who was wearing clogs.

Little Benjamin said that the first thing to be done was to get back Peter's clothes, in order that they might be able to use the pocket-handkerchief. They took them off the scarecrow. There had been rain during the night; there was water in the shoes, and the coat was somewhat shrunk.

Benjamin tried on the tam-o-shanter, but it was too big for him. Then he suggested that they should fill the pocket-handkerchief with onions, as a little present for his Aunt.

Peter did not seem to be enjoying himself; he kept hearing noises. Benjamin, on the contrary, was perfectly at home, and ate a lettuce leaf. He said that he was in the habit of coming to the garden with his father to get lettuces for their Sunday dinner.

(The name of little Benjamin's papa was old Mr. Benjamin Bunny.)

The lettuces certainly were very fine.

Peter did not eat anything; he said he should like to go home. Presently he dropped half the onions. Little Benjamin said that it was not possible to get back up the pear tree, with a load of vegetables. He led the way boldly towards the other end of the garden. They went along a little walk on planks, under a sunny red-brick wall.

The mice sat on their door-steps cracking cherry-stones; they winked at Peter Rabbit and little Benjamin Bunny.

Presently Peter let the pocket-handkerchief go again. They got amongst flower-pots, and frames and tubs; Peter heard noises worse than ever, his eyes were as big as lolly-pops! He was a step or two in front of his cousin, when he suddenly stopped.

This is what those little rabbits saw round that corner!

Little Benjamin took one look, and then, in half a minute less than no time, he hid himself and Peter and the onions underneath a large basket…

The cat got up and stretched herself, and came and sniffed at the basket. Perhaps she liked the smell of onions! Anyway, she sat down upon the top of the basket. She sat there for five hours.

I cannot draw you a picture of Peter and Benjamin underneath the basket, because it was quite dark, and because the smell of onions was fearful; it made Peter Rabbit and little Benjamin cry.

The sun got round behind the wood, and it was quite late in the afternoon; but still the cat sat upon the basket. At length there was a pitter-patter, pitter-patter, and some bits of mortar fell from the wall above. The cat looked up and saw old Mr. Benjamin Bunny prancing along the top of the wall of the upper terrace. He was smoking a pipe of rabbit-tobacco, and had a little switch in his hand. He was looking for his son.

Old Mr. Bunny had no opinion whatever of cats. He took a tremendous jump off the top of the wall on to the top of the cat, and cuffed it off the basket, and kicked it into the garden-house, scratching off a handful of fur. The cat was too much surprised to scratch back.

When old Mr. Bunny had driven the cat into the green-house, he locked the door. Then he came back to the basket and took out his son Benjamin by the ears, and whipped him with the little switch. Then he took out his nephew Peter. Then he took out the handkerchief of onions, and marched out of the garden.

When Mr. McGregor returned about half an hour later, he observed several things which perplexed him. It looked as though some person had been walking all over the garden in a pair of clogs—only the foot-marks were too ridiculously little! Also he could not understand how the cat could have managed to shut herself up inside the green-house, locking the door upon the outside.

When Peter got home, his mother forgave him, because she was so glad to see that he had found his shoes and coat. Cotton-tail and Peter folded up the pocket-handkerchief, and old Mrs. Rabbit strung up the onions and hung them from the kitchen ceiling, with the bunches of herbs and rabbit-tobacco.

THE END

THE TALE OF MRS. TIGGY-WINKLE

Once upon a time there was a little girl called Lucie, who lived at a farm called Little-town. She was a good little girl—only she was always losing her pocket-handkerchiefs!

One day little Lucie came into the farm-yard crying—oh, she did cry so! “I've lost my pocket-handkin! Three handkins and a pinny! Have you seen them, Tabby Kitten?”

The Kitten went on washing her white paws; so Lucie asked a speckled hen—

“Sally Henny-penny, has you found three pocket-handkins?”

But the speckled hen ran into a barn, clucking—

“I go barefoot, barefoot, barefoot!”

And then Lucie asked Cock Robin sitting on a twig. Cock Robin looked sideways at Lucie with his bright black eye, and he flew over a stile and away.

Lucie climbed upon the stile and looked up at the hill behind Little-town—a hill that goes up—up—into the clouds as though it had no top! And a great way up the hillside she thought she saw some white things spread upon the grass.

Lucie scrambled up the hill as fast as her short legs would carry her; she ran along a steep path-way—up and up—until Little-town was right away down below—she could have dropped a pebble down the chimney!

Presently she came to a spring, bubbling out from the hillside. Some one had stood a tin can upon a stone to catch the water—but the water was already running over, for the can was no bigger than an egg-cup! And where the sand upon the path was wet—there were foot-marks of a very small person.

Lucie ran on, and on.

The path ended under a big rock. The grass was short and green, and there were clothes-props cut from bracken stems, with lines of plaited rushes, and a heap of tiny clothes pins—but no pocket-handkerchiefs! But there was something else—a door! straight into the hill; and inside it some one was singing—

“Lily-white and clean, oh!
With little frills between, oh!
Smooth and hot—red rusty spot
Never here be seen, oh!”

Lucie knocked—once—twice, and interrupted the song. A little frightened voice called out “Who's that?”

Lucie opened the door: and what do you think there was inside the hill?—a nice clean kitchen with a flagged floor and wooden beams—just like any other farm kitchen. Only the ceiling was so low that Lucie's head nearly touched it; and the pots and pans were small, and so was everything there.

There was a nice hot singey smell; and at the table, with an iron in her hand, stood a very stout short person staring anxiously at Lucie. Her print gown was tucked up, and she was wearing a large apron over her striped petticoat. Her little black nose went sniffle, sniffle, snuffle, and her eyes went twinkle, twinkle; and underneath her cap—where Lucie had yellow curls—that little person had prickles!

“Who are you?” said Lucie. “Have you seen my pocket-handkins?”

The little person made a bob-curtsey—“Oh, yes, if you please'm; my name is Mrs. Tiggy-winkle; oh, yes if you please'm, I'm an excellent clear-starcher!” And she took something out of a clothes-basket, and spread it on the ironing-blanket.

“What's that thing?” said Lucie—“that's not my pocket-handkin?”

“Oh no, if you please'm; that's a little scarlet waist-coat belonging to Cock Robin!”

And she ironed it and folded it, and put it on one side. Then she took something else off a clothes-horse—

“That isn't my pinny?” said Lucie.

“Oh no, if you please'm; that's a damask table-cloth belonging to Jenny Wren; look how it's stained with currant wine! It's very bad to wash!” said Mrs. Tiggy-winkle.

Mrs. Tiggy-Winkle's nose went sniffle, sniffle, snuffle, and her eyes went twinkle, twinkle; and she fetched another hot iron from the fire.

“There's one of my pocket-handkins!” cried Lucie—“and there's my pinny!”

Mrs. Tiggy-winkle ironed it, and goffered it, and shook out the frills.

“Oh that is lovely!” said Lucie. “And what are those long yellow things with fingers like gloves?”

“Oh, that's a pair of stockings belonging to Sally Henny-penny—look how she's worn the heels out with scratching in the yard! She'll very soon go barefoot!” said Mrs. Tiggy-winkle.

“Why, there's another handkersniff—but it isn't mine; it's red?”

“Oh no, if you please'm; that one belongs to old Mrs. Rabbit; and it did so smell of onions! I've had to wash it separately, I can't get out the smell.”

“There's another one of mine,” said Lucie.

“What are those funny little white things?”

“That's a pair of mittens belonging to Tabby Kitten; I only have to iron them; she washes them herself.”

“There's my last pocket-handkin!” said Lucie.

“And what are you dipping into the basin of starch?”

“They're little dicky shirt-fronts belonging to Tom Tit-mouse—most terrible particular!” said Mrs. Tiggy-winkle. “Now I've finished my ironing; I'm going to air some clothes.”

“What are these dear soft fluffy things?” said Lucie.

“Oh those are woolly coats belonging to the little lambs at Skelghyl.”

“Will their jackets take off?” asked Lucy.

“Oh yes, if you please'm; look at the sheep-mark on the shoulder. And here's one marked for Gatesgarth, and three that come from Little-town. They're always marked at washing!” said Mrs. Tiggy-winkle.

And she hung up all sorts and sizes of clothes—small brown coats of mice; and one velvety black moleskin waist-coat; and a red tail-coat with no tail belonging to Squirrel Nutkin; and a very much shrunk blue jacket belonging to Peter Rabbit; and a petticoat, not marked, that had gone lost in the washing—and at last the basket was empty!

Then Mrs. Tiggy-winkle made tea—a cup for herself and a cup for Lucie. They sat before the fire on a bench and looked sideways at one another. Mrs. Tiggy-winkle's hand, holding the tea-cup, was very very brown, and very very wrinkly with the soap-suds; and all through her gown and her cap, there were hair-pins sticking wrong end out; so that Lucie didn't like to sit too near her.

When they had finished tea, they tied up the clothes in bundles; and Lucie's pocket-handkerchiefs were folded up inside her clean pinny, and fastened with a silver safety-pin.

And then they made up the fire with turf, and came out and locked the door, and hid the key under the door-sill. Then away down the hill trotted Lucie and Mrs. Tiggy-winkle with the bundles of clothes!

All the way down the path little animals came out of the fern to meet them; the very first that they met were Peter Rabbit and Benjamin Bunny! And she gave them their nice clean clothes; and all the little animals and birds were so very much obliged to dear Mrs. Tiggy-winkle. So that at the bottom of the hill when they came to the stile, there was nothing left to carry except Lucie's one little bundle.

Lucie scrambled up the stile with the bundle in her hand; and then she turned to say “Good-night,” and to thank the washer-woman—But what a very odd thing! Mrs. Tiggy-winkle had not waited either for thanks or for the washing bill! She was running running running up the hill—and where was her white frilled cap? and her shawl? and her gown—and her petticoat?

And how small she had grown—and how brown—and covered with prickles!

Why! Mrs. Tiggy-winkle was nothing but a hedgehog.

(Now some people say that little Lucie had been asleep upon the stile—but then how could she have found three clean pocket-handkins and a pinny, pinned with a silver safety-pin?

And besides—I have seen that door into the back of the hill called Cat Bells—and besides I am very well acquainted with dear Mrs. Tiggy-winkle!)

THE END

THE STORY OF A FIERCE BAD RABBIT

This is a fierce bad Rabbit; look at his savage whiskers, and his claws and his turned-up tail.

This is a nice gentle Rabbit. His mother has given him a carrot.

The bad Rabbit would like some carrot. He doesn't say “Please.” He takes it! And he scratches the good Rabbit very badly.

The good Rabbit creeps away, and hides in a hole. It feels sad.

This is a man with a gun. He sees something sitting on a bench. He thinks it is a very funny bird. He comes creeping up behind the trees. And then he shoots—BANG!

This is what happens—But this is all he finds on the bench, when he rushes up with his gun.

The good Rabbit peeps out of its hole. And it sees the bad Rabbit tearing past—without any tail or whiskers!

THE END

THE STORY OF MISS MOPPET

This is a Pussy called Miss Moppet, she thinks she has heard a mouse!

This is the Mouse peeping out behind the cupboard, and making fun of Miss Moppet. He is not afraid of a kitten.

This is Miss Moppet jumping just too late; she misses the Mouse and hits her own head. She thinks it is a very hard cupboard!

The Mouse watches Miss Moppet from the top of the cupboard.

Miss Moppet ties up her head in a duster, and sits before the fire.

The Mouse thinks she is looking very ill. He comes sliding down the bell-pull.

Miss Moppet looks worse and worse. The Mouse comes a little nearer.

Miss Moppet holds her poor head in her paws, and looks at him through a hole in the duster. The Mouse comes very close. And then all of a sudden—Miss Moppet jumps upon the Mouse!

And because the Mouse has teased Miss Moppet—Miss Moppet thinks she will tease the Mouse; which is not at all nice of Miss Moppet. She ties him up in the duster, and tosses it about like a ball. But she forgot about that hole in the duster; and when she untied it—there was no Mouse! He has wriggled out and run away; and he is dancing a jig on the top of the cupboard!

THE END

THE TALE OF TOM KITTEN

Once upon a time there were three little kittens, and their names were—Mittens, Tom Kitten, and Moppet. They had dear little fur coats of their own; and they tumbled about the doorstep and played in the dust.

But one day their mother—Mrs. Tabitha Twitchit—expected friends to tea; so she fetched the kittens indoors, to wash and dress them, before the fine company arrived. First she scrubbed their faces (this one is Moppet). Then she brushed their fur (this one is Mittens). Then she combed their tails and whiskers (this is Tom Kitten). Tom was very naughty, and he scratched.

Mrs. Tabitha dressed Moppet and Mittens in clean pinafores and tuckers; and then she took all sorts of elegant uncomfortable clothes out of a chest of drawers, in order to dress up her son Thomas. Tom Kitten was very fat, and he had grown; several buttons burst off. His mother sewed them on again.

When the three kittens were ready, Mrs. Tabitha unwisely turned them out into the garden, to be out of the way while she made hot buttered toast.

“Now keep your frocks clean, children! You must walk on your hind legs. Keep away from the dirty ash-pit, and from Sally Henny Penny, and from the pig-stye and the Puddle-ducks.”

Moppet and Mittens walked down the garden path unsteadily. Presently they trod upon their pinafores and fell on their noses. When they stood up there were several green smears!

“Let us climb up the rockery, and sit on the garden wall,” said Moppet.

They turned their pinafores back to front, and went up with a skip and a jump; Moppet's white tucker fell down into the road.

Tom Kitten was quite unable to jump when walking upon his hind legs in trousers. He came up the rockery by degrees, breaking the ferns, and shedding buttons right and left. He was all in pieces when he reached the top of the wall. Moppet and Mittens tried to pull him together; his hat fell off, and the rest of his buttons burst.

While they were in difficulties, there was a pit pat paddle pat! and the three Puddle-ducks came along the hard high road, marching one behind the other and doing the goose step—pit pat paddle pat! pit pat waddle pat!

They stopped and stood in a row, and stared up at the kittens. They had very small eyes and looked surprised. Then the two duck-birds, Rebeccah and Jemima Puddle-duck, picked up the hat and tucker and put them on.

Mittens laughed so that she fell off the wall. Moppet and Tom descended after her; the pinafores and all the rest of Tom's clothes came off on the way down.

“Come! Mr. Drake Puddle-duck,” said Moppet—“Come and help us to dress him! Come and button up Tom!”

Mr. Drake Puddle-duck advanced in a slow sideways manner, and picked up the various articles. But he put them on himself! They fitted him even worse than Tom Kitten.

“It's a very fine morning!” said Mr. Drake Puddle-duck. And he and Jemima and Rebeccah Puddle-duck set off up the road, keeping step—pit pat, paddle pat! pit pat, waddle pat!

Then Tabitha Twitchit came down the garden and found her kittens on the wall with no clothes on. She pulled them off the wall, smacked them, and took them back to the house.

“My friends will arrive in a minute, and you are not fit to be seen; I am affronted,” said Mrs. Tabitha Twitchit. She sent them upstairs; and I am sorry to say she told her friends that they were in bed with the measles; which was not true. Quite the contrary; they were not in bed; not in the least.

Somehow there were very extraordinary noises over-head, which disturbed the dignity and repose of the tea-party.

And I think that some day I shall have to make another, larger, book, to tell you more about Tom Kitten!

As for the Puddle-ducks—they went into a pond. The clothes all came off directly, because there were no buttons. And Mr. Drake Puddle-duck, and Jemima and Rebeccah, have been looking for them ever since.

THE END

THE TALE OF THE FLOPSY BUNNIES

It is said that the effect of eating too much lettuce is “soporific.”

I have never felt sleepy after eating lettuces; but then I am not a rabbit. They certainly had a very soporific effect upon the Flopsy Bunnies!

When Benjamin Bunny grew up, he married his Cousin Flopsy. They had a large family, and they were very improvident and cheerful. I do not remember the separate names of their children; they were generally called the “Flopsy Bunnies.”

As there was not always quite enough to eat—Benjamin used to borrow cabbages from Flopsy's brother, Peter Rabbit, who kept a nursery garden. Sometimes Peter Rabbit had no cabbages to spare. When this happened, the Flopsy Bunnies went across the field to a rubbish heap, in the ditch outside Mr. McGregor's garden.

Mr. McGregor's rubbish heap was a mixture. There were jam pots and paper bags, and mountains of chopped grass from the mowing machine (which always tasted oily), and some rotten vegetable marrows and an old boot or two. One day—oh joy!—there were a quantity of overgrown lettuces, which had “shot” into flower.

The Flopsy Bunnies simply stuffed lettuces. By degrees, one after another, they were overcome with slumber, and lay down in the mown grass.

Benjamin was not so much overcome as his children. Before going to sleep he was sufficiently wide awake to put a paper bag over his head to keep off the flies.

The little Flopsy Bunnies slept delightfully in the warm sun. From the lawn beyond the garden came the distant clacketty sound of the mowing machine. The bluebottles buzzed about the wall, and a little old mouse picked over the rubbish among the jam pots (I can tell you her name, she was called Thomasina Tittlemouse, a wood-mouse with a long tail.). She rustled across the paper bag, and awakened Benjamin Bunny. The mouse apologized profusely, and said that she knew Peter Rabbit.

While she and Benjamin were talking, close under the wall, they heard a heavy tread above their heads; and suddenly Mr. McGregor emptied out a sackful of lawn mowings right upon the top of the sleeping Flopsy Bunnies! Benjamin shrank down under his paper bag. The mouse hid in a jam pot. The little rabbits smiled sweetly in their sleep under the shower of grass; they did not awake because the lettuces had been so soporific. They dreamt that their mother Flopsy was tucking them up in a hay bed.

Mr. McGregor looked down after emptying his sack. He saw some funny little brown tips of ears sticking up through the lawn mowings. He stared at them for some time. Presently a fly settled on one of them and it moved.

Mr. McGregor climbed down on to the rubbish heap—

“One, two, three, four! five! six leetle rabbits!” said he as he dropped them into his sack. The Flopsy Bunnies dreamt that their mother was turning them over in bed. They stirred a little in their sleep, but still they did not wake up.

Mr. McGregor tied up the sack and left it on the wall. He went to put away the mowing machine. While he was gone, Mrs. Flopsy Bunny (who had remained at home) came across the field. She looked suspiciously at the sack and wondered where everybody was? Then the mouse came out of her jam pot, and Benjamin took the paper bag off his head, and they told the doleful tale.

Benjamin and Flopsy were in despair, they could not undo the string. But Mrs. Tittlemouse was a resourceful person. She nibbled a hole in the bottom corner of the sack. The little rabbits were pulled out and pinched to wake them. Their parents stuffed the empty sack with three rotten vegetable marrows, an old blacking-brush and two decayed turnips. Then they all hid under a bush and watched for Mr. McGregor.

Mr. McGregor came back and picked up the sack, and carried it off. He carried it hanging down, as if it were rather heavy. The Flopsy Bunnies followed at a safe distance. They watched him go into his house. And then they crept up to the window to listen.

Mr. McGregor threw down the sack on the stone floor in a way that would have been extremely painful to the Flopsy Bunnies, if they had happened to have been inside it. They could hear him drag his chair on the flags, and chuckle—

“One, two, three, four, five, six leetle rabbits!” said Mr. McGregor.

“Eh? What's that? What have they been spoiling now?” enquired Mrs. McGregor.

“One, two, three, four, five, six leetle fat rabbits!” repeated Mr. McGregor, counting on his fingers—“one, two, three—”

“Don't you be silly; what do you mean, you silly old man?”

“In the sack! one, two, three, four, five, six!” replied Mr. McGregor.

(The youngest Flopsy Bunny got upon the window-sill.)

Mrs. McGregor took hold of the sack and felt it. She said she could feel six, but they must be old rabbits, because they were so hard and all different shapes.

“Not fit to eat; but the skins will do fine to line my old cloak.”

“Line your old cloak?” shouted Mr. McGregor—“I shall sell them and buy myself baccy! Rabbit tobacco! I shall skin them and cut off their heads.”

Mrs. McGregor untied the sack and put her hand inside. When she felt the vegetables, she became very very angry. She said that Mr. McGregor had “done it a purpose.” And Mr. McGregor was very angry too. One of the rotten marrows came flying through the kitchen window, and hit the youngest Flopsy Bunny. It was rather hurt. Then Benjamin and Flopsy thought that it was time to go home.

So Mr. McGregor did not get his tobacco, and Mrs. McGregor did not get her rabbit skins.

But next Christmas Thomasina Tittlemouse got a present of enough rabbit-wool to make herself a cloak and a hood, and a handsome muff and a pair of warm mittens.

THE END

THE TALE OF GINGER AND PICKLES

Once upon a time there was a village shop. The name over the window was “Ginger and Pickles.” It was a little small shop just the right size for Dolls—Lucinda and Jane Doll-cook always bought their groceries at Ginger and Pickles. The counter inside was a convenient height for rabbits. Ginger and Pickles sold red spotty pocket-handkerchiefs at a penny three farthings. They also sold sugar, and snuff and goloshes. In fact, although it was such a small shop it sold nearly everything—except a few things that you want in a hurry—like bootlaces, hair-pins and mutton chops.

Ginger and Pickles were the people who kept the shop. Ginger was a yellow tom-cat, and Pickles was a terrier. The rabbits were always a little bit afraid of Pickles. The shop was also patronized by mice—only the mice were rather afraid of Ginger. Ginger usually requested Pickles to serve them, because he said it made his mouth water.

“I cannot bear,” said he, “to see them going out at the door carrying their little parcels.”

“I have the same feeling about rats,” replied Pickles, “but it would never do to eat our customers; they would leave us and go to Tabitha Twitchit's.”

“On the contrary, they would go nowhere,” replied Ginger gloomily.

(Tabitha Twitchit kept the only other shop in the village. She did not give credit.)

Ginger and Pickles gave unlimited credit.

Now the meaning of “credit” is this—when a customer buys a bar of soap, instead of the customer pulling out a purse and paying for it—she says she will pay another time. And Pickles makes a low bow and says, “With pleasure, madam,” and it is written down in a book.

The customers come again and again, and buy quantities, in spite of being afraid of Ginger and Pickles. But there is no money in what is called the “till”.

The customers came in crowds every day and bought quantities, especially the toffee customers. But there was always no money; they never paid for as much as a pennyworth of peppermints. But the sales were enormous, ten times as large as Tabitha Twitchit's.

As there was always no money, Ginger and Pickles were obliged to eat their own goods. Pickles ate biscuits and Ginger ate a dried haddock. They ate them by candle-light after the shop was closed. `When it came to Jan. 1st there was still no money, and Pickles was unable to buy a dog licence.

“It is very unpleasant, I am afraid of the police,” said Pickles.

“It is your own fault for being a terrier; I do not require a licence, and neither does Kep, the Collie dog.”

“It is very uncomfortable, I am afraid I shall be summoned. I have tried in vain to get a licence upon credit at the Post Office,” said Pickles.“The place is full of policemen. I met one as I was coming home. Let us send in the bill again to Samuel Whiskers, Ginger, he owes 22/9 for bacon.”

“I do not believe that he intends to pay at all,” replied Ginger.

“And I feel sure that Anna Maria pockets things—Where are all the cream crackers?”

“You have eaten them yourself,” replied Ginger.

Ginger and Pickles retired into the back parlour. They did accounts. They added up sums and sums, and sums.

“Samuel Whiskers has run up a bill as long as his tail; he has had an ounce and three-quarters of snuff since October. What is seven pounds of butter at 1/3, and a stick of sealing wax and four matches?”

“Send in all the bills again to everybody ‘with compts’” replied Ginger.

After a time they heard a noise in the shop, as if something had been pushed in at the door. They came out of the back parlour. There was an envelope lying on the counter, and a policeman writing in a notebook!

Pickles nearly had a fit, he barked and he barked and made little rushes.

“Bite him, Pickles! bite him!” spluttered Ginger behind a sugar-barrel, “he's only a German doll!”

The policeman went on writing in his notebook; twice he put his pencil in his mouth, and once he dipped it in the treacle.

Pickles barked till he was hoarse. But still the policeman took no notice. He had bead eyes, and his helmet was sewed on with stitches. At length on his last little rush—Pickles found that the shop was empty. The policeman had disappeared. But the envelope remained.

“Do you think that he has gone to fetch a real live policeman? I am afraid it is a summons,” said Pickles.

“No,” replied Ginger, who had opened the envelope, “it is the rates and taxes, £ 3 19 11 3/4.”

“This is the last straw,” said Pickles, “let us close the shop.”

They put up the shutters, and left. But they have not removed from the neighbourhood. In fact some people wish they had gone further.

Ginger is living in the warren. I do not know what occupation he pursues; he looks stout and comfortable.

Pickles is at present a gamekeeper.

The closing of the shop caused great inconvenience. Tabitha Twitchit immediately raised the price of everything a half-penny; and she continued to refuse to give credit.

Of course there are the tradesmen's carts—the butcher, the fishman and Timothy Baker. But a person cannot live on “seed wigs” and sponge-cake and butter-buns—not even when the sponge-cake is as good as Timothy's!

After a time Mr. John Dormouse and his daughter began to sell peppermints and candles. But they did not keep “self-fitting sixes”; and it takes five mice to carry one seven-inch candle. Besides—the candles which they sell behave very strangely in warm weather. And Miss Dormouse refused to take back the ends when they were brought back to her with complaints.

And when Mr. John Dormouse was complained to, he stayed in bed, and would say nothing but “very snug”; which is not the way to carry on a retail business.

So everybody was pleased when Sally Henny Penny sent out a printed poster to say that she was going to re-open the shop—“Henny's Opening Sale! Grand co-operative Jumble! Penny's penny prices! Come buy, come try, come buy!” The poster really was most 'ticing.

There was a rush upon the opening day. The shop was crammed with customers, and there were crowds of mice upon the biscuit canisters. Sally Henny Penny gets rather flustered when she tries to count out change, and she insists on being paid cash; but she is quite harmless. And she has laid in a remarkable assortment of bargains.

There is something to please everybody.

THE END

THE TALE OF MRS. TITTLEMOUSE

Once upon a time there was a wood-mouse, and her name was Mrs. Tittlemouse. She lived in a bank under a hedge. Such a funny house! There were yards and yards of sandy passages, leading to storerooms and nut-cellars and seed-cellars, all amongst the roots of the hedge. There was a kitchen, a parlour, a pantry, and a larder. Also, there was Mrs. Tittlemouse's bedroom, where she slept in a little box bed!

Mrs. Tittlemouse was a most terribly tidy particular little mouse, always sweeping and dusting the soft sandy floors.

Sometimes a beetle lost its way in the passages.

“Shuh! shuh! little dirty feet!” said Mrs. Tittlemouse, clattering her dust-pan.

And one day a little old woman ran up and down in a red spotty cloak.

“Your house is on fire, Mother Ladybird! Fly away home to your children!”

Another day, a big fat spider came in to shelter from the rain.

“Beg pardon, is this not Miss Muffet's?”

“Go away, you bold bad spider! Leaving ends of cobweb all over my nice clean house!”

She bundled the spider out at a window.

He let himself down the hedge with a long thin bit of string.

Mrs. Tittlemouse went on her way to a distant storeroom, to fetch cherry-stones and thistle-down seed for dinner. All along the passage she sniffed, and looked at the floor.

“I smell a smell of honey; is it the cowslips outside, in the hedge?

“I am sure I can see the marks of little dirty feet.”

Suddenly round a corner, she met Babbitty Bumble—“Zizz, Bizz, Bizzz!” said the bumble bee. Mrs. Tittlemouse looked at her severely. She wished that she had a broom.

“Good-day, Babbitty Bumble; I should be glad to buy some beeswax. But what are you doing down here? Why do you always come in at a window, and say Zizz, Bizz, Bizzz?” Mrs. Tittlemouse began to get cross.

“Zizz, Wizz, Wizz!” replied Babbitty Bumble in a peevish squeak. She sidled down a passage, and disappeared into a storeroom which had been used for acorns.

Mrs. Tittlemouse had eaten the acorns before Christmas; the storeroom ought to have been empty. But it was full of untidy dry moss. Mrs. Tittlemouse began to pull out the moss. Three or four other bees put their heads out, and buzzed fiercely.

“I am not in the habit of letting lodgings; this is an intrusion!” said Mrs. Tittlemouse. “I will have them turned out—”

“Buzz! Buzz! Buzzz!”—

“I wonder who would help me?”

“Bizz, Wizz, Wizzz!”—

“I will not have Mr. Jackson; he never wipes his feet.”

Mrs. Tittlemouse decided to leave the bees till after dinner. When she got back to the parlour, she heard some one coughing in a fat voice; and there sat Mr. Jackson himself! He was sitting all over a small rocking-chair, twiddling his thumbs and smiling, with his feet on the fender. He lived in a drain below the hedge, in a very dirty wet ditch.

“How do you do, Mr. Jackson? Deary me, you have got very wet!”

“Thank you, thank you, thank you, Mrs. Tittlemouse! I'll sit awhile and dry myself,” said Mr. Jackson. He sat and smiled, and the water dripped off his coat tails. Mrs. Tittlemouse went round with a mop.

He sat such a while that he had to be asked if he would take some dinner? First she offered him cherry-stones. “Thank you, thank you, Mrs. Tittlemouse! No teeth, no teeth, no teeth!” said Mr. Jackson. He opened his mouth most unnecessarily wide; he certainly had not a tooth in his head.

Then she offered him thistle-down seed—

“Tiddly, widdly, widdly! Pouff, pouff, puff!” said Mr. Jackson. He blew the thistle-down all over the room.

“Thank you, thank you, thank you, Mrs. Tittlemouse! Now what I really—really should like—would be a little dish of honey!”

“I am afraid I have not got any, Mr. Jackson,” said Mrs. Tittlemouse.

“Tiddly, widdly, widdly, Mrs. Tittlemouse!” said the smiling Mr. Jackson. “I can smell it; that is why I came to call.”

Mr. Jackson rose ponderously from the table, and began to look into the cupboards. Mrs. Tittlemouse followed him with a dish-cloth, to wipe his large wet footmarks off the parlour floor. When he had convinced himself that there was no honey in the cupboards, he began to walk down the passage.

“Indeed, indeed, you will stick fast, Mr. Jackson!”

“Tiddly, widdly, widdly, Mrs. Tittlemouse!”

First he squeezed into the pantry.

“Tiddly, widdly, widdly? no honey? no honey, Mrs. Tittlemouse?”

There were three creepy-crawly people hiding in the plate-rack. Two of them got away; but the littlest one he caught. Then he squeezed into the larder. Miss Butterfly was tasting the sugar; but she flew away out of the window.

“Tiddly, widdly, widdly, Mrs. Tittlemouse; you seem to have plenty of visitors!”

“And without any invitation!” said Mrs. Thomasina Tittlemouse.

They went along the sandy passage—“Tiddly widdly—”

“Buzz! Wizz! Wizz!”

He met Babbitty round a corner, and snapped her up, and put her down again.

“I do not like bumble bees. They are all over bristles,” said Mr. Jackson, wiping his mouth with his coat-sleeve.

“Get out, you nasty old toad!” shrieked Babbitty Bumble.

“I shall go distracted!” scolded Mrs. Tittlemouse. She shut herself up in the nut-cellar while Mr. Jackson pulled out the bees-nest. He seemed to have no objection to stings.

When Mrs. Tittlemouse ventured to come out—everybody had gone away. But the untidiness was something dreadful—“Never did I see such a mess—smears of honey; and moss, and thistle-down—and marks of big and little dirty feet—all over my nice clean house!”

She gathered up the moss and the remains of the beeswax. Then she went out and fetched some twigs, to partly close up the front door.

“I will make it too small for Mr. Jackson!”

She fetched soft soap, and flannel, and a new scrubbing brush from the storeroom. But she was too tired to do any more. First she fell asleep in her chair, and then she went to bed.

“Will it ever be tidy again?” said poor Mrs. Tittlemouse.

Next morning she got up very early and began a spring cleaning which lasted a fortnight. She swept, and scrubbed, and dusted; and she rubbed up the furniture with beeswax, and polished her little tin spoons. When it was all beautifully neat and clean, she gave a party to five other little mice, without Mr. Jackson.

He smelt the party and came up the bank, but he could not squeeze in at the door. So they handed him out acorn-cupfuls of honeydew through the window, and he was not at all offended.

He sat outside in the sun, and said—“Tiddly, widdly, widdly! Your very good health, Mrs. Tittlemouse!”

THE END

APPLEY DAPPLY'S NURSERY RHYMES

Appley Dapply,

a little brown mouse,

Goes to the cupboard

in somebody's house.

In somebody's cupboard

there's everything nice,

Cake, cheese, jam, biscuits,

—all charming for mice!

Appley Dapply

has little sharp eyes,

And Appley Dapply

is so fond of pies!

Now who is this knocking

at Cotton-tail's door?

Tap tappit! Tap tappit!

She's heard it before?

And when she peeps out

there is nobody there,

But a present of carrots

put down on the stair.

Hark! I hear it again!

Tap, tap, tappit!

Tap tappit!

Why—I really believe

it's a little black rabbit!

Old Mr. Pricklepin

has never a cushion to stick his pins in,

His nose is black and his beard is gray,

And he lives in an ash stump over the way.

You know the old woman

who lived in a shoe?

And had so many children

she didn't know what to do?

I think if she lived

in a little shoe-house—

That little old woman

was surely a mouse!

Diggory Diggory Delvet!

A little old man in black velvet;

He digs and he delves—

You can see for yourselves.

The mounds dug by Diggory Delvet.

Gravy and potatoes

In a good brown pot—

Put them in the oven,

And serve them very hot!

There once was an amiable guinea-pig,

Who brushed back his hair like a periwig—

He wore a sweet tie,

As blue as the sky—

And his whiskers and buttons

were very big.

THE END

CECILY PARSLEY'S NURSERY RHYMES

CECILY PARSLEY lived in a pen,

And brewed good ale for gentlemen;

Gentlemen came every day,

Till Cecily Parsley ran away.

GOOSEY, GOOSEY, GANDER,

Whither will you wander?

Upstairs and downstairs,

And in my lady's chamber!

THIS pig went to market;

This pig stayed at home;

This pig had a bit of meat;

And this pig had none;

This little pig cried

Wee! wee! wee!

I can't find my way home.

PUSSY-CAT sits by the fire;

How should she be fair?

In walks the little dog,

Says “Pussy! are you there?

“How do you do, Mistress Pussy?

Mistress Pussy, how do you do?”

“I thank you kindly, little dog,

I fare as well as you!”

THREE blind mice, three blind mice,

See how they run!

They all run after the farmer's wife,

And she cut off their tails with a carving knife,

Did ever you see such a thing in your life

As three blind mice!

Bow, wow, wow!

Whose dog art thou?

“I'm little Tom Tinker's dog,

Bow, wow, wow!”

We have a little garden,

A garden of our own,

And every day we water there

The seeds that we have sown.

We love our little garden,

And tend it with such care,

You will not find a faded leaf

Or blighted blossom there.

NINNY NANNY NETTICOAT,

In a white petticoat,

With a red nose—

The longer she stands,

The shorter she grows.

THE END

THE TALE OF LITTLE PIG ROBINSON

Chapter One

When I was a child I used to go to the seaside for the holidays. We stayed in a little town where there was a harbour and fishing boats and fishermen. They sailed away to catch herrings in nets. When the boats came back home again, some had only caught a few herrings. Others had caught so many that they could not all be unloaded on to the quay. Then horses and carts were driven into the shallow water at low tide to meet the heavily laden boats. The fish were shovelled over the side of the boat into the carts, and taken to the railway station, where a special train of fish trucks was waiting.

Great was the excitement when the fishing boats returned with a good catch of herrings. Half the people in the town ran down to the quay, including cats.

There was a white cat called Susan who never missed meeting the boats. She belonged to the wife of an old fisherman named Sam. The wife's name was Betsy. She had rheumatics, and she had no family except Susan and five hens. Betsy sat by the fire; her back ached; she said “Ow! Ow!” whenever she had to put coal on, and stir the pot. Susan sat opposite to Betsy. She felt sorry for Betsy; she wished she knew how to put the coal on and stir the pot. All day long they sat by the fire, while Sam was away fishing. They had a cup of tea and some milk. “Susan,” said Betsy, “I can hardly stand up. Go to the front gate and look out for Master's boat.”

Susan went out and came back. Three or four times she went out into the garden. At last, late in the afternoon, she saw the sails of the fishing fleet, coming in over the sea.

“Go down to the harbour; ask Master for six herrings; I will cook them for supper. Take my basket, Susan.”

Susan took the basket; also she borrowed Betsy's bonnet and little plaid shawl. I saw her hurrying down to the harbour.

Other cats were coming out of the cottages, and running down the steep streets that lead to the sea front. Also ducks. I remember that they were most peculiar ducks with top-knots that looked like tam-o'-shanter caps. Everybody was hurrying to meet the boats—nearly everybody. I only met one person, a dog called Stumpy, who was going the opposite way. He was carrying a paper parcel in his mouth.

Some dogs do not care for fish. Stumpy had been to the butcher's to buy mutton chops for himself and Bob and Percy and Miss Rose. Stumpy was a large, serious, well-behaved brown dog with a short tail. He lived with Bob the retriever and Percy the cat and Miss Rose who kept house. Stumpy had belonged to a very rich old gentleman; and when the old gentleman died he left money to Stumpy—ten shillings a week for the rest of Stumpy's life. So that was why Stumpy and Bob and Percy the cat all lived together in a pretty little house.

Susan with her basket met Stumpy at the corner of Broad Street. Susan made a curtsy. She would have stopped to inquire after Percy, only she was in a hurry to meet the boat. Percy was lame; he had hurt his foot. It had been trapped under the wheel of a milk cart.

Stumpy looked at Susan out of the corner of his eye; he wagged his tail, but he did not stop. He could not bow or say “good afternoon” for fear of dropping the parcel of mutton chops. He turned out of Broad Street into Woodbine Lane, where he lived; he pushed open the front door and disappeared into a house. Presently there was a smell of cooking, and I have no doubt that Stumpy and Bob and Miss Rose enjoyed their mutton chops.

Percy could not be found at dinner-time. He had slipped out of the window, and, like all the other cats in the town, he had gone to meet the fishing boats.

Susan hurried along Broad Street and took the short cut to the harbour, down a steep flight of steps. The ducks had wisely gone another way, round by the sea front. The steps were too steep and slippery for anyone less sure-footed than a cat. Susan went down quickly and easily. There were forty-three steps, rather dark and slimy, between high backs of houses.

A smell of ropes and pitch and a good deal of noise came up from below. At the bottom of the steps was the quay, or landing place, beside the inner harbour.

The tide was out; there was no water; the vessels rested on the dirty mud. Several ships were moored beside the quay; others were anchored inside the breakwater.

Near the steps, coal was being unloaded from two grimy colliers called the “Margery Dawe” of Sunderland, and the “Jenny Jones” of Cardiff. Men ran along planks with wheelbarrowfuls of coal; coal scoops were swung ashore by cranes, and emptied with loud thumping and rattling.

Farther along the quay, another ship called the “Pound of Candles” was taking a mixed cargo on board. Bales, casks, packing-cases, barrels—all manner of goods were being stowed into the hold; sailors and stevedores shouted; chains rattled and clanked. Susan waited for an opportunity to slip past the noisy crowd. She watched a cask of cider that bobbed and swung in the air, on its passage from the quay to the deck of the “Pound of Candles”. A yellow cat who sat in the rigging was also watching the cask.

The rope ran through the pulley; the cask went down bobbitty on to the deck, where a sailor man was waiting for it. Said the sailor down below—

“Look out! Mind your head, young sir! Stand out of the way!”

“Wee, wee, wee!” grunted a small pink pig, scampering round the deck of the “Pound of Candles”.

The yellow cat in the rigging watched the small pink pig. The yellow cat in the rigging looked across at Susan on the quay. The yellow cat winked.

Susan was surprised to see a pig on board a ship. But she was in a hurry. She threaded her way along the quay, amongst coal and cranes, and men wheeling hand-trucks, and noises, and smells. She passed the fish auction, and fish boxes, and fish sorters, and barrels that women were filling with herrings and salt.

Seagulls swooped and screamed. Hundreds of fish boxes and tons of fresh fish were being loaded into the hold of a small steamer. Susan was glad to get away from the crowd, down a much shorter flight of steps on to the shore of the outer harbour. The ducks arrived soon afterwards, waddling and quacking. And old Sam's boat, the “Betsy Timmins”, last of the herring fleet and heavy laden, came in round the breakwater; and drove her blunt nose into the shingle.

Sam was in high spirits; he had had a big catch. He and his mate and two lads commenced to unload their fish into carts, as the tide was too low to float the fishing boat up to the quay. The boat was full of herrings.

But, good luck or bad luck, Sam never failed to throw a handful of herrings to Susan.

“Here's for the two old girls and a hot supper! Catch them, Susan! Honest now! Here's a broken fish for you! Now take the others to Betsy.”

The ducks were dabbling and gobbling; the seagulls were screaming and swooping. Susan climbed the steps with her basket of herrings and went home by back streets.

Old Betsy cooked two herrings for herself and Susan, another two for Sam's supper when he came in. Then she went to bed with a hot bottle wrapped in a flannel petticoat to help her rheumatics.

Sam ate his supper and smoked a pipe by the fire; and then he went to bed. But Susan sat a long time by the fire, considering. She considered many things—fish, and ducks, and Percy with a lame foot, and dogs that eat mutton chops, and the yellow cat on the ship, and the pig. Susan thought it strange to see a pig upon a ship called the “Pound of Candles”. The mice peeped out under the cupboard door. The cinders fell together on the hearth. Susan purred gently in her sleep and dreamed of fish and pigs. She could not understand that pig on board a ship. But I know all about him!

Chapter Two

You remember the song about the Owl and the Pussy Cat and their beautiful pea-green boat? How they took some honey and plenty of money, wrapped up in a five pound note?

They sailed away, for a year and a day,
To the land where the Bong tree grows—
And, there in a wood, a piggy-wig stood,
With a ring at the end of his nose—his nose,
With a ring at the end of his nose.

Now I am going to tell you the story of that pig, and why he went to live in the land of the Bong tree.

When that pig was little he lived in Devonshire, with his aunts, Miss Dorcas and Miss Porcas, at a farm called Piggery Porcombe. Their cosy thatched cottage was in an orchard at the top of a steep red Devonshire lane.

The soil was red, the grass was green; and far away below in the distance they could see red cliffs and a bit of bright blue sea. Ships with white sails sailed over the sea into the harbour of Stymouth.

I have often remarked that the Devonshire farms have very strange names. If you had ever seen Piggery Porcombe you would think that the people who lived there were very queer too! Aunt Dorcas was a stout speckled pig who kept hens. Aunt Porcas was a large smiling black pig who took in washing. We shall not hear very much about them in this story. They led prosperous uneventful lives, and their end was bacon. But their nephew Robinson had the most peculiar adventures that ever happened to a pig.

Little pig Robinson was a charming little fellow; pinky white with small blue eyes, fat cheeks and a double chin, and a turned-up nose, with a real silver ring in it. Robinson could see that ring if he shut one eye and squinted sideways.

He was always contented and happy. All day long he ran about the farm, singing little songs to himself, and grunting “Wee, wee, wee!” His aunts missed those little songs sadly after Robinson had left them.

“Wee? Wee? Wee?” he answered when anybody spoke to him. “Wee? Wee? Wee?” listening with his head on one side and one eye screwed up.

Robinson's old aunts fed him and petted him and kept him on the trot.

“Robinson! Robinson!” called Aunt Dorcas. “Come quick! I hear a hen clucking. Fetch me the egg; don't break it now!”

“Wee, wee, wee!” answered Robinson, like a little Frenchman.

“Robinson! Robinson! I've dropped a clothes peg, come and pick it up for me!” called Aunt Porcas from the drying green (she being almost too fat to stoop down and pick up anything).

“Wee, wee, wee!” answered Robinson.

Both the aunts were very, very stout. And the stiles in the neighbourhood of Stymouth are narrow. The footpath from Piggery Porcombe crosses many fields; a red trodden track between short green grass and daisies. And wherever the footpath crosses over from one field to another field, there is sure to be a stile in the hedge.

“It is not me that is too stout; it is the stiles that are too thin,” said Aunt Dorcas to Aunt Porcas. “Could you manage to squeeze through them if I stayed at home?”

“I could not. Not for two years I could not,” replied Aunt Porcas.“Aggravating, it is aggravating of that carrier man, to go and upset his donkey cart the day before market day. And eggs at two and tuppence a dozen! How far do you call it to walk all the way round by the road instead of crossing the fields?”

“Four miles if it's one,” sighed Aunt Porcas, “and me using my last bit of soap. However will we get our shopping done? The donkey says the cart will take a week to mend.”

“Don't you think you could squeeze through the stiles if you went before dinner?”

“No, I don't, I would stick fast; and so would you,” said Aunt Porcas.

“Don't you think we might venture—” commenced Aunt Dorcas.

“Venture to send Robinson by the footpath to Stymouth?” finished Aunt Porcas.

“Wee, wee, wee!” answered Robinson.

“I scarcely like to send him alone, though he is sensible for his size.”

“Wee, wee, wee!” answered Robinson.

“But there is nothing else to be done,” said Aunt Dorcas.

So Robinson was popped into the wash-tub with the last bit of soap. He was scrubbed and dried and polished as bright as a new pin. Then he was dressed in a little blue cotton frock and knickers, and instructed to go shopping to Stymouth with a big market basket.

In the basket were two dozen eggs, a bunch of daffodils, two spring cauliflowers; also Robinson's dinner of bread-and-jam sandwiches. The eggs and flowers and vegetables he must sell in the market, and bring back various other purchases from shopping.

“Now take care of yourself in Stymouth, Nephew Robinson. Beware of gunpowder, and ships' cooks, and pantechnicons, and sausages, and shoes, and ships, and sealing-wax. Remember the blue bag, the soap, the darning wool—what was the other thing?” said Aunt Dorcas.

“The darning wool, the soap, the blue bag, the yeast—what was the other thing?” said Aunt Porcas.

“Wee, wee, wee!” answered Robinson.

“The blue bag, the soap, the yeast, the darning wool, the cabbage seed—that's five, and there ought to be six. It was two more than four because it was two too many to tie knots in the corners of his hankie, to remember by. Six to buy, it should be—”

“I have it!” said Aunt Porcas. “It was tea—tea, blue bag, soap, darning wool, yeast, cabbage seed. You will buy most of them at Mr. Mumby's. Explain about the carrier, Robinson; tell him we will bring the washing and some more vegetables next week.”

“Wee, wee, wee” answered Robinson, setting off with the big basket.

Aunt Dorcas and Aunt Porcas stood in the porch. They watched him safely out of sight, down the field, and through the first of the many stiles. When they went back to their household tasks they were grunty and snappy with each other, because they were uneasy about Robinson.

“I wish we had not let him go. You and your tiresome blue bag!” said Aunt Dorcas.

“Blue bag, indeed! It was your darning wool and eggs!” grumbled Aunt Porcas. “Bother that carrier man and his donkey cart! Why could not he keep out of the ditch until after market day?”

Chapter Three

The walk to Stymouth was a long one, in spite of going by the fields. But the footpath ran downhill all the way, and Robinson was merry. He sang his little song, for joy of the fine morning, and he chuckled “Wee, wee, wee!” Larks were singing, too, high overhead.

And higher still—high up against blue sky, the great white gulls sailed in wide circles. Their hoarse cries came softened back to earth from a great way up above. Important rooks and lively jackdaws strutted about the meadows amongst the daisies and buttercups. Lambs skipped and baa'ed; the sheep looked round at Robinson.

“Mind yourself in Stymouth, little pig,” said a motherly ewe.

Robinson trotted on until he was out of breath and very hot. He had crossed five big fields, and ever so many stiles; stiles with steps; ladder stiles; stiles of wooden posts; some of them were very awkward with a heavy basket. The farm of Piggery Porcombe was no longer in sight when he looked back. In the distance before him, beyond the farmlands and cliffs—never any nearer—the dark blue sea rose like a wall.

Robinson sat down to rest beside a hedge in a sheltered sunny spot. Yellow pussy willow catkins were in flower above his head; there were primroses in hundreds on the bank, and a warm smell of moss and grass and steaming moist red earth.

“If I eat my dinner now, I will not have to carry it. Wee, wee, wee!” said Robinson.

The walk had made him so hungry; he would have liked to eat an egg as well as the jam sandwiches; but he had been too well brought up. “It would spoil the two dozen,” said Robinson.

He picked a bunch of primroses and tied them up with a bit of darning wool that Aunt Dorcas had given him for a pattern. “I will sell them in the market for my very own self, and buy sweeties with my pennies. How many pennies have I got?” said Robinson, feeling in his pocket. “One from Aunt Dorcas, and one from Aunt Porcas, and one for my primroses for my very own self—oh, wee, wee, wee! There is somebody trotting along the road! I shall be late for market!”

Robinson jumped up and pushed his basket through a very narrow stile, where the footpath crossed into the public road. He saw a man on horseback. Old Mr. Pepperil came up, riding a chestnut horse with white legs. His two tall greyhounds ran before him; they looked through the bars of the gates into every field that they passed. They came bounding up to Robinson, very large and friendly; they licked his face and asked what he had got in that basket. Mr. Pepperil called them.

“Here, Pirate! Here, Postboy! Come here, sir!” He did not wish to be answerable for the eggs.

The road had been recently covered with sharp new flints. Mr. Pepperil walked the chestnut horse on the grass edge, and talked to Robinson. He was a jolly old gentleman, very affable, with a red face and white whiskers. All the green fields and red ploughland between Stymouth and Piggery Porcombe belonged to him.

“Hullo, hullo! And where are you off to, little pig Robinson?”

“Please, Mr. Pepperil, sir, I'm going to market. Wee, wee, wee!” said Robinson.

“What, all by yourself? Where are Miss Dorcas and Miss Porcas? Not ill, I trust?”

Robinson explained about the narrow stiles.

“Dear, dear! Too fat, too fat? So you are going all alone? Why don't your aunts keep a dog to run errands?”

Robinson answered all Mr. Pepperil's questions very sensibly and prettily. He showed much intelligence, and quite a good knowledge of vegetables, for one so young. He trotted along almost under the horse, looking up at its shiny chestnut coat, and the broad white girth, and Mr. Pepperil's gaiters and brown leather boots. Mr. Pepperil was pleased with Robinson; he gave him another penny. At the end of the flints, he gathered up the reins and touched the horse with his heel.

“Well, good day, little pig. Kind regards to the aunts. Mind yourself in Stymouth.” He whistled for his dogs, and trotted away.

Robinson continued to walk along the road. He passed by an orchard where seven thin dirty pigs were grubbing. They had no silver rings in their noses! He crossed Styford bridge without stopping to look over the parapet at the little fishes, swimming head up stream, balanced in the sluggish current; or the white ducks that dabbled amongst floating masses of water-crowsfoot. At Styford Mill he called to leave a message from Aunt Dorcas to the Miller about meal; the Miller's wife gave him an apple.

At the house beyond the mill, there is a big dog that barks; but the big dog Gypsy only smiled and wagged his tail at Robinson. Several carts and gigs overtook him. First, two old farmers who screwed themselves round to stare at Robinson. They had two geese, a sack of potatoes, and some cabbages, sitting on the back seat of their gig. Then an old woman passed in a donkey cart with seven hens, and long pink bundles of rhubarb that had been grown in straw under apple barrels. Then with a rattle and a jingle of cans came Robinson's cousin, little Tom Pigg, driving a strawberry roan pony, in a milk float. He might have offered Robinson a lift, only he happened to be going in the opposite direction; in fact, the strawberry roan pony was running away home.

“This little pig went to market!” shouted little Tom Pigg gaily, as he rattled out of sight in a cloud of dust, leaving Robinson standing in the road.

Robinson walked on along the road, and presently he came to another stile in the opposite hedge, where the footpath followed the fields again. Robinson got his basket through the stile. For the first time he felt some apprehension. In this field there were cows; big sleek Devon cattle, dark red like their native soil. The leader of the herd was a vicious old cow, with brass balls screwed on to the tips of her horns. She stared disagreeably at Robinson. He sidled across the meadow and got out through the farther stile as quickly as he could. Here the new trodden footpath followed round the edge of a crop of young green wheat. Someone let off a gun with a bang that made Robinson jump and cracked one of Aunt Dorcas's eggs in the basket.

A cloud of rooks and jackdaws rose cawing and scolding from the wheat. Other sounds mingled with their cries; noises of the town of Stymouth that began to come in sight through the elm trees that bordered the fields; distant noises from the station; whistling of an engine; the bump of trucks shunting; noise of workshops; the hum of a distant town; the hooter of a steamer entering the harbour. High overhead came the hoarse cry of the gulls, and the squabbling cawing of rooks, old and young, in their rookery up in the elm trees.

Robinson left the fields for the last time and joined a stream of country people on foot and in carts, all going to Stymouth Market.

Chapter Four

Stymouth is a pretty little town, situated at the mouth of the river Pigsty, whose sluggish waters slide gently into a bay sheltered by high red headlands. The town itself seems to be sliding downhill in a basin of hills, all slipping seaward into Stymouth harbour, which is dammed back by quays and the outer breakwater.

The outskirts of the town are untidy, as is frequently the case with seaports. A straggling suburb on the western approach is inhabited principally by goats, and persons who deal in old iron, rags, tarred rope, and fishing nets. There are rope walks, and washing that flaps on waggling lines above banks of stony shingle, littered with seaweed, whelk shells and dead crabs—very different from Aunt Porcas's clothes lines over the clean green grass.

And there are marine stores that sell spy-glasses, and sou'westers, and onions; and there are smells; and curious high sheds, shaped like sentry boxes, where they hang up herring nets to dry; and loud talking inside dirty houses. It seemed a likely place to meet a pantechnicon. Robinson kept in the middle of the road. Somebody in a public-house shouted at him through the window, “Come in, fat pig!” Robinson took to his heels.

The town of Stymouth itself is clean, pleasant, picturesque, and well-behaved (always excepting the harbour); but it is extremely steep downhill. If Robinson had started one of Aunt Dorcas's eggs rolling at the top of High Street, it would have rolled all the way down to the bottom; only it would have got broken certainly against a doorstep, or underfoot. There were crowds in the streets, as it was market day.

Indeed, it was difficult to walk about without being pushed off the pavement; every old woman that Robinson met seemed to have a basket as big as his own. In the roadway were fish barrows, apple barrows, stalls with crockery and hardware, cocks and hens riding in pony carts, donkeys with panniers, and farmers with wagon-loads of hay. Also there was a constant string of coal carts coming up from the docks. To a country-bred pig, the noise was confusing and fearful.

Robinson kept his head very creditably until he got into Fore Street, where a drover's dog was trying to turn three bullocks into a yard, assisted by Stumpy and half the other dogs of the town. Robinson and two other little pigs with baskets of asparagus bolted down an alley and hid in a doorway until the noise of bellowing and barking had passed.

When Robinson took courage to come out again into Fore Street, he decided to follow close behind the tail of a donkey who was carrying panniers piled high with spring broccoli. There was no difficulty in guessing which road led to market. But after all these delays it was not surprising that the church clock struck eleven.

Although it had been open since ten, there were still plenty of customers buying, and wanting to buy, in the market hall. It was a large, airy, light, cheerful, covered-in place, with glass in the roof. It was crowded, but safe and pleasant, compared with the jostling and racket outside in the cobble-paved streets; at all events there was no risk of being run over. There was a loud hum of voices; market folk cried their wares; customers elbowed and pushed round the stalls. Dairy produce, vegetables, fish, and shell fish were displayed upon the flat boards on trestles.

Robinson had found a standing place at one end of a stall where Nanny Nettigoat was selling periwinkles.

“Winkle, winkle! Wink, wink, wink! Maa, maa-a!” bleated Nanny. Winkles were the only thing that she offered for sale, so she felt no jealousy of Robinson's eggs and primroses. She knew nothing about his cauliflowers; he had the sense to keep them in the basket under the table. He stood on an empty box, quite proud and bold behind the trestle table, singing—

“Eggs, new laid! Fresh new-laid eggs! Who'll come and buy my eggs and daffodillies?”

“I will, sure,” said a large brown dog with a stumpy tail, “I'll buy a dozen. My Miss Rose has sent me to market on purpose to buy eggs and butter.”

“I am so sorry, I have no butter, Mr. Stumpy; but I have beautiful cauliflowers,” said Robinson, lifting up the basket, after a cautious glance round at Nanny Nettigoat, who might have tried to nibble them. She was busy measuring periwinkles in a pewter mug for a duck customer in a tam-o'-shanter cap. “They are lovely brown eggs, except one that got cracked; I think that white pussy cat at the opposite stall is selling butter—they are beautiful cauliflowers.”

“I'll buy a cauliflower, lovey, bless his little turned-up nose; did he grow them in his own garden?” said old Betsy, bustling up; her rheumatism was better; she had left Susan to keep house. “No, lovey, I don't want any eggs; I keep hens myself. A cauliflower and a bunch of daffodils for a bow-pot, please,” said Betsy.

“Wee, wee, wee!” replied Robinson.

“Here, Mrs. Perkins, come here! Look at this little pig stuck up at a stall all by himself!”

“Well, I don't know!” exclaimed Mrs. Perkins, pushing through the crowd, followed by two little girls. “Well, I never! Are they quite new laid, sonny? Won't go off pop and spoil my Sunday dress like the eggs Mrs. Wyandotte took first prize with at five flower shows, till they popped and spoiled the judge's black silk dress? Not duck eggs, stained with coffee? That's another trick of flower shows! New laid, guaranteed? Only you say one is cracked? Now I call that real honest; it's no worse for frying. I'll have the dozen eggs and a cauliflower, please. Look, Sarah Polly! Look at his silver nose-ring.”

Sarah Polly and her little girl friend went into fits of giggling, so that Robinson blushed. He was so confused that he did not notice a lady who wanted to buy his last cauliflower, till she touched him. There was nothing else left to sell, but a bunch of primroses. After more giggling and some whispering the two little girls came back, and bought the primroses. They gave him a peppermint, as well as the penny, which Robinson accepted; but without enthusiasm and with a preoccupied manner.

The trouble was that no sooner had he parted with the bunch of primroses than he realised that he had also sold Aunt Dorcas's pattern of darning wool. He wondered if he ought to ask for it back; but Mrs. Perkins and Sarah Polly and her little girl friend had disappeared.

Robinson, having sold everything, came out of the market hall, sucking the peppermint. There were still numbers of people coming in. As Robinson came out upon the steps his basket got caught in the shawl of an elderly sheep, who was pushing her way up. While Robinson was disentangling it, Stumpy came out. He had finished his marketing. His basket was full of heavy purchases. A responsible, trustworthy, obliging dog was Stumpy, glad to do a kindness to anybody.

When Robinson asked him the way to Mr. Mumby's, Stumpy said: “I am going home by Broad Street. Come with me, and I will show you.”

“Wee, wee, wee! Oh, thank you, Stumpy!” said Robinson.

Chapter Five

Old Mr. Mumby was a deaf old man in spectacles, who kept a general store. He sold almost anything you can imagine, except ham—a circumstance much approved by Aunt Dorcas. It was the only general store in Stymouth where you would not find displayed upon the counter a large dish, containing strings of thin, pale-coloured, repulsively uncooked sausages, and rolled bacon hanging from the ceiling.

“What pleasure,” said Aunt Dorcas feelingly—“what possible pleasure can there be in entering a shop where you knock your head against a ham? A ham that may have belonged to a dear second cousin?”

Therefore the aunts bought their sugar and tea, their blue bag, their soap, their frying pans, matches, and mugs from old Mr. Mumby. All these things he sold, and many more besides, and what he did not keep in stock he would obtain to order. But yeast requires to be quite fresh, he did not sell it; he advised Robinson to ask for yeast at a baker's shop. Also he said it was too late in the season to buy cabbage seed; everybody had finished sowing vegetable seeds this year. Worsted for darning he did sell; but Robinson had forgotten the colour.

Robinson bought six sticks of delightfully sticky barley sugar with his pennies, and listened carefully to Mr. Mumby's messages for Aunt Dorcas and Aunt Porcas—how they were to send some cabbages next week when the donkey cart would be mended; and how the kettle was not repaired yet, and there was a new patent box-iron he would like to recommend to Aunt Porcas.

Robinson said “Wee, wee, wee?” and listened, and little dog Tipkins who stood on a stool behind the counter, tying up grocery parcels in blue paper bags—little dog Tipkins whispered to Robinson—“Were there any rats this spring in the barn at Piggery Porcombe? And what would Robinson be doing on Saturday afternoon?”

“Wee, wee, wee!” answered Robinson.

Robinson came out of Mr. Mumby's, heavily laden. The barley sugar was comforting; but he was troubled about the darning wool, the yeast, and the cabbage seed. He was looking about rather anxiously, when again he met old Betsy, who exclaimed:

“Bless the little piggy! Not gone home yet? Now it must not stop in Stymouth till it gets its pocket picked!”

Robinson explained his difficulty about the darning wool. Kind old Betsy was ready with help. “Why, I noticed the wool round the little primrose posy; it was blue-grey colour like the last pair of socks that I knitted for Sam. Come with me to the wool shop—Fleecy Flock's wool shop. I remember the colour; well I do!” said Betsy.

Mrs. Flock was the sheep that had run against Robinson; she had bought herself three turnips and come straight home from market, for fear of missing customers while her shop was locked up.

Such a shop! Such a jumble! Wool all sorts of colours, thick wool, thin wool, fingering wool, and rug wool, bundles and bundles all jumbled up; and she could not put her hoof on anything. She was so confused and slow at finding things that Betsy got impatient.

“No, I don't want wool for slippers; darning wool, Fleecy; darning wool, same colour as I bought for my Sam's socks. Bless me, no, not knitting needles! Darning wool.”

“Baa, baa! Did you say white or black, m'm? Three ply, was it?”

“Oh, dear me, grey darning wool on cards; not heather mixture.”

“I know I have it somewhere,” said Fleecy Flock helplessly, jumbling up the skeins and bundles. “Sim Ram came in this morning with part of the Ewehampton clip; my shop is completely cluttered up—” It took half an hour to find the wool. If Betsy had not been with him, Robinson never would have got it.

“It's that late, I must go home,” said Betsy. “My Sam is on shore today for dinner. If you take my advice you will leave that big heavy basket with the Miss Goldfinches, and hurry with your shopping. It's a long uphill walk home to Piggery Porcombe.”

Robinson, anxious to follow old Betsy's advice, walked towards the Miss Goldfinches'. On the way he came to a baker's, and he remembered the yeast. It was not the right sort of baker's, unfortunately. There was a nice bakery smell, and pastry in the window; but it was an eating house or cook shop.

When he pushed the swing door open, a man in an apron and a square white cap turned round and said, “Hullo! Is this a pork pie walking on its hind legs?”—and four rude men at a dining table burst out laughing.

Robinson left the shop in a hurry. He felt afraid to go into any other baker's shop. He was looking wistfully into another window in Fore Street when Stumpy saw him again. He had taken his own basket home, and come out on another errand. He carried Robinson's basket in his mouth and took him to a very safe baker's, where he was accustomed to buy dog biscuits for himself. There Robinson purchased Aunt Dorcas's yeast at last.

They searched in vain for cabbage seed; they were told that the only likely place was a little store on the quay, kept by a pair of wagtails.

“It is a pity I cannot go with you,” said Stumpy. “My Miss Rose has sprained her ankle; she sent me to fetch twelve postage stamps, and I must take them home to her, before the post goes out. Do not try to carry this heavy basket down and up the steps; leave it with the Miss Goldfinches.”

Robinson was very grateful to Stumpy. The two Miss Goldfinches kept a tea and coffee tavern which was patronized by Aunt Dorcas and the quieter market people. Over the door was a sign board upon which was painted a fat little green bird called “The Contented Siskin”, which was the name of their coffee tavern. They had a stable where the carrier's donkey rested when it came into Stymouth with the washing on Saturdays.

Robinson looked so tired that the elder Miss Goldfinch gave him a cup of tea; but they both told him to drink it up quickly.

“Wee, wee, wee! Yock yock!” said Robinson, scalding his nose.

In spite of their respect for Aunt Dorcas, the Miss Goldfinches disapproved of his solitary shopping; and they said that the basket was far too heavy for him.

“Neither of us could lift it,” said the elder Miss Goldfinch, holding out a tiny claw. “Get your cabbage seed and hurry back. Sim Ram's pony gig is still waiting in our stable. If you come back before he starts I feel sure he will give you a lift; at all events he will make room for your basket under the seat—and he passes Piggery Porcombe. Run away now!”

“Wee, wee, wee!” said Robinson.

“Whatever were they thinking of to let him come alone? He will never get home before dark,” said the elder Miss Goldfinch. “Fly to the stable, Clara; tell Sim Ram's pony not to start without the basket.”

The younger Miss Goldfinch flew across the yard. They were industrious, sprightly little lady birds, who kept lump sugar and thistle seed as well as tea in their tea-caddies. Their tables and china were spotlessly clean.

Chapter Six

Stymouth was full of inns; too full. The farmers usually put up their horses at the “Black Bull” or the “Horse and Farrier”; the smaller market people patronized the “Pig and Whistle”.

There was another inn called the “Crown and Anchor” at the corner of Fore Street. It was much frequented by seamen; several were lounging about the door with their hands in their pockets. One sailor-man in a blue jersey sauntered across the road, staring very hard at Robinson. Said he—“I say, little pig! do you like snuff?”

Now if Robinson had a fault, it was that he could not say “No”; not even to a hedgehog stealing eggs. As a matter of fact, snuff or tobacco made him sick. But instead of saying, “No, thank you, Mr. Man,” and going straight away about his business, he shuffled his feet, half closed one eye, hung his head on one side, and grunted.

The sailor pulled out a horn snuff box and presented a small pinch to Robinson, who wrapped it up in a little bit of paper, intending to give it to Aunt Dorcas. Then, not to be outdone in politeness, he offered the sailor-man some barley sugar.

If Robinson was not fond of snuff, at all events his new acquaintance had no objection to candy. He ate an alarming quantity. Then he pulled Robinson's ear and complimented him, and said he had five chins. He promised to take Robinson to the cabbage seed shop; and, finally, he begged to have the honour of showing him over a ship engaged in the ginger trade, commanded by Captain Barnabas Butcher, and named the “Pound of Candles”.

Robinson did not very much like the name. It reminded him of tallow, of lard, of crackle and trimmings of bacon. But he allowed himself to be led away, smiling shyly, and walking on his toes. If Robinson had only known … that man was a ship's cook!

As they turned down the steep narrow lane, out of High Street, leading to the harbour, old Mr. Mumby at his shop door called out anxiously, “Robinson! Robinson!” But there was too much noise of carts. And a customer coming into the shop at that moment distracted his attention, and he forgot the suspicious behaviour of the sailor. Otherwise, out of regard for the family, he would undoubtedly have ordered his dog, Tipkins, to go and fetch Robinson back. As it was, he was the first person to give useful information to the police, when Robinson had been missed. But it was then too late.

Robinson and his new friend went down the long flight of steps to the harbour basin—very high steps, steep and slippery. The little pig was obliged to jump from step to step until the sailor kindly took hold of him. They walked along the quay hand in hand; their appearance seemed to cause unbounded amusement.

Robinson looked about him with much interest. He had peeped over those steps before when he had come into Stymouth in the donkey cart, but he had never ventured to go down, because the sailors are rather rough, and because they frequently have little snarling terriers on guard about their vessels.

There were ever so many ships in the harbour; the noise and bustle was almost as loud as it had been up above in the market square. A big three-masted ship called the “Goldielocks” was discharging a cargo of oranges; and farther along the quay, a small coasting brig called “Little Bo Peep” of Bristol was loading up with bales of wool belonging to the sheep of Ewehampton and Lambworthy.

Old Sim Ram, with a sheepbell and big curly horns, stood by the gangway keeping count of the bales. Every time the crane swung round and let down another bale of wool into the hold, with a scuffle of rope through the pulley, Simon Ram nodded his old head, and the bell went “tinkle tinkle, tong”, and he gave a gruff bleat.

He was a person who knew Robinson by sight and ought to have warned him. He had often passed Piggery Porcombe when he drove down the lane in his gig. But his blind eye was turned towards the quay; and he had been flustered and confused by an argument with the pursers as to whether thirty-five bales of wool had been hoisted on board already or only thirty-four. So he kept his one useful eye carefully on the wool, and counted it by the notches on his tally stick—another bale—another notch—thirty-five, thirty-six, thirty-seven; he hoped the number would come right at the finish.

His bob-tailed sheepdog, Timothy Gyp, was also acquainted with Robinson, but he was busy superintending a dog fight between an Airedale terrier belonging to the collier “Margery Dawe” and a Spanish dog belonging to the “Goldielocks”. No one took any notice of their growling and snarling, which ended in both rolling over the side of the quay and falling into the water. Robinson kept close to the sailor and held his hand very tight.

The “Pound of Candles” proved to be a good-sized schooner, newly painted and decorated with certain flags, whose significance was not understood by Robinson. She lay near the outer end of the jetty. The tide was running up fast, lapping against the ship's sides and straining the thick hawsers by which she was moored to the quay.

The crew were stowing goods on board and doing things with ropes under the direction of Captain Barnabas Butcher; a lean, brown, nautical person with a rasping voice. He banged things about and grumbled; parts of his remarks were audible on the quay. He was speaking about the tug “Sea-horse”—and about the spring tide, with a north-east wind behind it—and the baker's man and fresh vegetables—“to be shipped at eleven sharp; likewise a joint of…” He stopped short suddenly, and his eye lighted upon the cook and Robinson.

Robinson and the cook went on board across a shaky plank. When Robinson stepped on to the deck, he found himself face to face with a large yellow cat who was blacking boots.

The cat gave a start of surprise and dropped its blacking brush. It then began to wink and make extraordinary faces at Robinson. He had never seen a cat behave in that way before. He inquired whether it was ill. Whereupon the cook threw a boot at it, and it rushed up into the rigging. But Robinson he invited most affably to descend into the cabin, to partake of muffins and crumpets.

I do not know how many muffins Robinson consumed. He went on eating them until he fell asleep; and he went on sleeping until his stool gave a lurch, and he fell off and rolled under the table. One side of the cabin floor swung up to the ceiling; and the other side of the ceiling swung down to the floor. Plates danced about; and there were shoutings and thumpings and rattling of chains and other bad sounds.

Robinson picked himself up, feeling bumped. He scrambled up a sort of a ladder-staircase on to the deck. Then he gave squeal upon squeal of horror! All round the ship there were great big green waves; the houses on the quay were like dolls' houses; and high up inland, above the red cliffs and green fields, he could see the farm of Piggery Porcombe looking no bigger than a postage stamp. A little white patch in the orchard was Aunt Porcas's washing, spread out to bleach upon the grass. Near at hand the black tug “Sea-horse” smoked and plunged and rolled. They were winding in the tow rope which had just been cast loose from the “Pound of Candles”.

Captain Barnabas stood up in the bows of his schooner; he yelled and shouted to the master of the tug. The sailors shouted also, and pulled with a will, and hoisted the sails. The ship heeled over and rushed through the waves, and there was a smell of the sea.

As for Robinson—he tore round and round the deck like one distracted, shrieking very shrill and loud. Once or twice he slipped down; for the deck was extremely sideways; but still he ran and he ran. Gradually his squeals subsided into singing, but still he kept on running, and this is what he sang—

“Poor Pig Robinson Crusoe!
Oh, how in the world could they do so?
They have set him afloat, in a horrible boat,
Oh, poor pig Robinson Crusoe!”

The sailors laughed until they cried; but when Robinson had sung that same verse about fifty times, and upset several sailors by rushing between their legs, they began to get angry. Even the ship's cook was no longer civil to Robinson. On the contrary, he was very rude indeed. He said that if Robinson did not leave off singing through his nose, he would make him into pork chops.

Then Robinson fainted, and fell flat upon the deck of the “Pound of Candles”.

Chapter Seven

It must not be supposed for one moment that Robinson was ill-treated on board ship. Quite the contrary. He was even better fed and more petted on the “Pound of Candles” than he had been at Piggery Porcombe. So, after a few days' fretting for his kind old aunts (especially while he was seasick), Robinson became perfectly contented and happy. He found what is called his “sea legs”; and he scampered about the deck until the time when he became too fat and lazy to scamper.

The cook was never tired of boiling porridge for him. A whole sack full of meal and a sack of potatoes appeared to have been provided especially for his benefit and pleasure. He could eat as much as he pleased. It pleased him to eat a great deal and to lie on the warm boards of the deck. He got lazier and lazier as the ship sailed south into warmer weather. The mate made a pet of him; the crew gave him tit-bits. The cook rubbed his back and scratched his sides—his ribs could not be tickled, because he had laid so much fat on. The only persons who refused to treat him as a joke were the yellow tom-cat and Captain Barnabas Butcher, who was of a sour disposition.

The attitude of the cat was perplexing to Robinson. Obviously it disapproved of the maize meal porridge business, and it spoke mysteriously about the impropriety of greediness, and about the disastrous results of over-indulgence. But it did not explain what those results might be, and as the cat itself cared neither for yellow meal nor 'taties, Robinson thought that its warnings might arise from prejudice. It was not unfriendly. It was mournful and foreboding.

The cat itself was crossed in love. Its morose and gloomy outlook upon life was partly the result of separation from the owl. That sweet hen-bird, a snowy owl of Lapland, had sailed upon a northern whaler, bound for Greenland. Whereas the “Pound of Candles” was heading for the tropic seas.

Therefore the cat neglected its duties, and was upon the worst of terms with the cook. Instead of blacking boots and valeting the Captain, it spent days and nights in the rigging, serenading the moon. Between times it came down on deck, and remonstrated with Robinson.

It never told him plainly why he ought not to eat so much; but it referred frequently to a mysterious date (which Robinson could never remember)—the date of Captain Butcher's birthday, which he celebrated annually by an extra good dinner.

“That's what they are saving up apples for. The onions are done—sprouted with the heat. I heard Captain Barnabas tell the cook that onions were of no consequence as long as there were apples for sauce.”

Robinson paid no attention. In fact, he and the cat were both on the side of the ship, watching a shoal of silvery fishes. The ship was completely becalmed. The cook strolled across the deck to see what the cat was looking at and exclaimed joyfully at sight of fresh fish. Presently half the crew were fishing. They baited their lines with bits of scarlet wool and bits of biscuit; and the boatswain had a successful catch on a line baited with a shiny button.

The worst of button fishing was that so many fish dropped off while being hauled on deck. Consequently Captain Butcher allowed the crew to launch the jolly boat, which was let down from some iron contraption called “the davits” on to the glassy surface of the sea. Five sailors got into the boat; the cat jumped in also. They fished for hours. There was not a breath of wind.

In the absence of the cat, Robinson fell asleep peacefully upon the warm deck. Later he was disturbed by the voices of the mate and the cook, who had not gone fishing. The former was saying—

“I don't fancy loin of pork with sunstroke, Cooky. Stir him up; or else throw a piece of sail cloth over him. I was bred on a farm myself. Pigs should never be let sleep in a hot sun.”

“As why?” inquired the cook.

“Sunstroke,” replied the mate. “Likewise it scorches the skin; makes it peely like; spoils the look of the crackling.”

At this point a rather heavy dirty piece of sail cloth was flung over Robinson, who struggled and kicked with sudden grunts.

“Did he hear you, Matey?” asked the cook in a lower voice.

“Don't know; don't matter; he can't get off the ship,” replied the mate, lighting his pipe. “Might upset his appetite; he's feeding beautiful,” said the cook.

Presently the voice of Captain Barnabas Butcher was heard. He had come up on deck after a siesta below in his cabin.

“Proceed to the crow's nest on the main mast; observe the horizon through a telescope according to latitude and longitude. We ought to be amongst the archipelago by the chart and compass,” said the voice of Captain Butcher.

It reached the ears of Robinson through the sail cloth in muffled tones, but peremptory; although it was not so received by the mate, who occasionally contradicted the Captain when no one else was listening.

“My corns are very painful,” said the mate.

“Send the cat up,” ordered Captain Barnabas briefly.

“The cat is out in the boat fishing.”

“Fetch him in then,” said Captain Barnabas, losing his temper. “He has not blacked my boots for a fortnight.” He went below; that is, down a step-ladder into his cabin, where he proceeded to work out the latitude and longitude again, in search of the archipelago.

“It's to be hoped that he mends his temper before next Thursday, or he won't enjoy roast pork!” said the mate to the cook.

They strolled to the other end of the deck to see what fish had been caught; the boat was coming back.

As the weather was perfectly calm, it was left over night upon the glassy sea, tied below a port-hole (or ship's window) at the stern of the “Pound of Candles”.

The cat was sent up the mast with a telescope; it remained there for some time. When it came down it reported quite untruthfully that there was nothing in sight. No particular watch or look-out was kept that night upon the “Pound of Candles” because the ocean was so calm. The cat was supposed to watch—if anybody did. All the rest of the ship's company played cards.

Not so the cat or Robinson. The cat had noticed a slight movement under the sail cloth. It found Robinson shivering with fright and in floods of tears. He had overheard the conversation about pork.

“I'm sure I have given you enough hints,” said the cat to Robinson.“What do you suppose they were feeding you up for? Now don't start squealing, you little fool! It's as easy as snuff, if you will listen and stop crying. You can row, after a fashion.” (Robinson had been out fishing occasionally and caught several crabs.)

“Well, you have not far to go; I could see the top of the Bong tree on an island N.N.E., when I was up the mast. The straits of the archipelago are too shallow for the “Pound of Candles”, and I'll scuttle all the other boats. Come along, and do what I tell you!” said the cat.

The cat, actuated partly by unselfish friendship, and partly by a grudge against the cook and Captain Barnabas Butcher, assisted Robinson to collect a varied assortment of necessaries. Shoes, sealing-wax, a knife, an armchair, fishing tackle, a straw hat, a saw, fly papers, a potato pot, a telescope, a kettle, a compass, a hammer, a barrel of flour, another of meal, a keg of fresh water, a tumbler, a teapot, nails, a bucket, a screwdriver—

“That reminds me,” said the cat, and what did it do but go round the deck with a gimlet and bore large holes in the three boats that remained on board the “Pound of Candles”.

By this time there began to be ominous sounds below; those of the sailors who had had bad hands were beginning to be tired of carding. So the cat took a hasty farewell of Robinson, pushed him over the ship's side, and he slid down the rope into the boat. The cat unfastened the upper end of the rope and threw it after him. Then it ascended the rigging and pretended to sleep upon its watch.

Robinson stumbled somewhat in taking his seat at the oars. His legs were short for rowing. Captain Barnabas in the cabin suspended his deal, a card in his hand, listening (the cook took the opportunity to look under the card), then he went on slapping down the cards, which drowned the sound of oars upon the placid sea.

After another hand, two sailors left the cabin and went on deck. They noticed something having the appearance of a large black beetle in the distance. One of them said it was an enormous cockroach, swimming with its hind legs. The other said it was a dolphinium. They disputed, rather loudly. Captain Barnabas, who had had a hand with no trumps at all after the cook dealing—Captain Barnabas came on deck and said—

“Bring me my telescope.”

The telescope had disappeared; likewise the shoes, the sealing-wax, the compass, the potato pot, the straw hat, the hammer, the nails, the bucket, the screwdriver, and the armchair.

“Take the jolly boat and see what it is,” ordered Captain Butcher.

“All jolly fine, but suppose it is a dolphinium?” said the mate mutinously.

“Why, bless my life, the jolly boat is gone!” exclaimed a sailor.

“Take another boat, take all the three other boats; it's that pig and that cat!” roared the Captain.

“Nay, sir, the cat's up the rigging asleep.”

“Bother the cat! Get the pig back! The apple sauce will be wasted!” shrieked the cook, dancing about and brandishing a knife and fork.

The davits were swung out, the boats were let down with a swish and a splash, all the sailors tumbled in, and rowed frantically. And most of them were glad to row frantically back to the “Pound of Candles”. For every boat leaked badly, thanks to the cat.

Chapter Eight

Robinson rowed away from the “Pound of Candles”. He tugged steadily at the oars. They were heavy for him. The sun had set, but I understand that in the tropics—I have never been there—there is a phosphorescent light upon the sea. When Robinson lifted his oars, the sparkling water dripped from the blades like diamonds. And presently the moon began to rise above the horizon—rising like half a great silver plate. Robinson rested on his oars and gazed at the ship, motionless in the moonlight, on a sea without a ripple. It was at this moment—he being a quarter of a mile away—that the two sailors came on deck, and thought his boat was a swimming beetle.

Robinson was too far away to see or hear the uproar on board the “Pound of Candles”; but he did presently perceive that three boats were starting in pursuit. Involuntarily he commenced to squeal, and rowed frantically. But before he had time to exhaust himself by racing, the ship's boats turned back. Then Robinson remembered the cat's work with the gimlet, and he knew that the boats were leaking. For the rest of the night he rowed quietly, without haste. He was not inclined to sleep, and the air was pleasantly cool. Next day it was hot, but Robinson slept soundly under the sail cloth, which the cat had been careful to send with him, in case he wished to rig up a tent.

The ship receded from view—you know the sea is not really flat. First he could not see the hull, then he could not see the deck, then only part of the masts, then nothing at all.

Robinson had been steering his course by the ship. Having lost sight of this direction sign, he turned round to consult his compass—when bump, bump, the boat touched a sandbank. Fortunately it did not stick.

Robinson stood up in the boat, working one oar backwards, and gazing around. What should he see but the top of the Bong tree!

Half an hour's rowing brought him to the beach of a large and fertile island. He landed in the most approved manner in a convenient sheltered bay, where a stream of boiling water flowed down the silvery strand. The shore was covered with oysters. Acid drops and sweets grew upon the trees. Yams, which are a sort of sweet potato, abounded ready cooked. The bread-fruit tree grew iced cakes and muffins, ready baked; so no pig need sigh for porridge. Overhead towered the Bong tree.

If you want a more detailed description of the island, you must read “Robinson Crusoe”. The island of the Bong tree was very like Crusoe's, only without its drawbacks. I have never been there myself, so I rely upon the report of the Owl and the Pussy Cat, who visited it eighteen months later, and spent a delightful honeymoon there. They spoke enthusiastically about the climate—only it was a little too warm for the Owl.

Later on Robinson was visited by Stumpy and little dog Tipkins. They found him perfectly contented, and in the best of good health. He was not at all inclined to return to Stymouth. For anything I know he may be living there still upon the island. He grew fatter and fatter and more fatterer; and the ship's cook never found him.

THE END

THE SLY OLD CAT

This is a sly old cat, who gave a tea party to a rat.

This is the rat in his best clothes coming down the area steps.

They had their tea in the kitchen.

“How do you do, Mr. Rat? Will you sit on this chair?” said the cat.

“I will eat my bread and butter first,” said the cat, “and then you shall eat the crumbs that are left, Mr. Rat!”

“This is a very rude way of treating visitors!” said Mr. Rat to himself.

“Now I will pour out my tea,” said the cat, “and you shall lick up the drops that are left in the milk jug, Mr. Rat; and then I will have some dessert!” said the cat.

“I believe she is going to eat me for dessert; I wish I'd never come!” said poor Mr. Rat.

She tipped up the milk jug—that greedy old cat! She didn't want to leave one single drop for the rat.

But the rat jumped on the table and gave the jug a pat, and it slipped down quite tight over the head of the cat! Then the cat banged about the kitchen with its head fast in the jug.

And the rat sat on the table drinking tea out of a mug. Then he put a muffin in a paper bag and went away. And he ate the whole muffin at one sitting; so that is the end of the rat.

And the cat broke the jug against the leg of the kitchen table; so that is the end of the cat.

THE FOX AND THE STORK

“Sir,” said Mr. Tod to King Stork, “will you honour me by taking tea with me?” King Stork bowed. He walked home with Mr. Fox; he took long strides and Mr. Tod trotted.

Mr. Tod is a stingy person. He regretted the invitation as soon as he had given it, when he considered the size of Mr. Stork. So he made a plan. Said he to Mr. Stork—“When I have visitors I use Great Grandmother Vixen's Derby tea set.” He poured the tea into two flat saucers.

King Stork dipped the point of his bill into the saucer, but he could scarcely scoop up a drop. Presently he made a bow and took leave. Mr. Tod lapped up the remaining tea himself.

As he had a conscience which told him he had behaved shabbily—Mr. Tod was surprised to receive an invitation to lunch with King Stork.

The note was brought by a very nervous lapwing.

King Stork's home was upon the top of a high chimney-stack over the roof of a tall old house. As Mr. Tod had no wings for flying up aloft onto roofs—King Stork came down and met him in the courtyard of the house, and led him inside and up a corkscrew staircase. There was a pleasing smell of broth when they reached the attic. The broth was served in two narrow-necked pitchers.

King Stork plunged his long bill into one pitcher and sucked up the broth. Mr. Tod could only lick his lips and sniff. Presently he got up and said, “Good Day!”

King Stork drew his bill out of his empty pitcher. He was a silent old bird. All he said was, “Tit for tat!”

序言

杰克·伦敦（1876—1916）是美国二十世纪现实主义文学的杰出代表。他的创作风格粗犷冷峻，有力地冲击了美国文坛上的浮华文风。其长篇小说《马丁·伊登》等具有深刻社会悲剧意义的现实主义作品，极大地影响了后来的作家们对“美国梦”的描写。他是这一时期美国最富有批判精神的现实主义作家，在美国文学史上素有“美国的高尔基”之称。

杰克·伦敦出生于一个贫苦家庭，自小衣不遮体、食不果腹，小学毕业后便进入社会谋生，当过报童和罐头厂的童工。在贫民窟里，他是个善于打架的“小霸王”，养成了坚毅、勇敢的性格。十七岁时，他上了一艘捕猎船做水手，经过朝鲜、日本，到西伯利亚去捕海豹，途中经受了严寒、风暴、最沉重的苦役的锻炼。他和极为强悍的水手交朋友，听他们讲述形形色色惊心动魄的人生经历。远航归来，他把自己的经历写成了一篇散文《日本港口的台风》，参加了《呼声》杂志的写作竞赛，因为内容独特且有一定深度和表现力，荣获第一名。刚开始写作便取得了这样突出的成绩，显然令他大为振奋，恐怕这也是他自此走上文学创作之路的重要原因之一。

父亲去世后，家里的生活愈加贫苦，为了负担家庭开支，杰克·伦敦四处找活干，尝尽了人间的辛酸。不过，他并没有因此而放弃文学创作，而是一边博览群书，一边笔不停辍地写作。可是，正如他在《马丁·伊登》中所描述的那样，他的稿件全部被出版社和杂志社退了回来。他没有灰心，仍在苦苦奋斗，为自己的创作寻找新的题材。最后，《大陆月刊》刊登了他的短篇小说《为赶路的人干杯》，给了他五美元的稿酬。正是这区区五美元解决了他生活上的燃眉之急，也坚定了他继续写作的信心。1897年3月，他踏上了淘金的路。他和伙伴们在育空河流域历经千辛万苦，差点没了命，却没有找到金子（他们倒是发现了金沙，其实那只是云母）。不过，这段经历却让他收获颇多，大大丰富了他的人生阅历。他把自己的所见所闻做了详细的笔记，那便是他后来发表的阿拉斯加小说的极其珍贵的材料。从育空河回来之后的几年里，他不断读书和写作，每天工作十九个小时。他阅读的范围非常广泛。在经济学方面他读亚当·斯密的《原富》、马尔萨斯的《人口论》、李嘉图的《分配论》、约翰·穆勒的《股份论》；在政治学方面他读亚里士多德的著作，读吉本的《罗马帝国衰亡史》，探索中世纪政治和教会的斗争；他读宗教改革的先驱马丁·路德和加尔文的作品，探索宗教对政治的影响；为了了解现代政治的起源，他阅读霍布斯、洛克和休谟的著作；在文学方面，他读英、法、俄、德各国名家的文学作品，还读各国的文学理论，寻求思想的解放。他最崇拜的作家是英国的斯蒂文森和吉卜林（英国第一个获得诺贝尔文学奖的作家）。他有着边读书边做笔记的习惯，不断摘取各个作者的名言，将其写在小纸条上，贴在房间里的各个地方，作为激励自己写作的动力。

1900年，杰克·伦敦的第一本小说集《狼子》出版，这立即为他赢得了巨大的声誉和优厚的收入。他原本可以在成功与安定的环境里继续从事写作，可是他是个不安分的人，血管里燃烧着火焰，总是渴望着沸腾的生活。1902年，为了拓宽视野，为了寻找更新的素材，他买了几套破旧的衣服、一双破鞋和一顶肮脏的便帽，以流落英伦的美国水手的身份住进了伦敦的贫民窟。在那里，他见到了大英帝国最繁华的城市伦敦的另一面——极为可怕的一面。疾病、失望和死亡是那儿居民生活里的家常便饭。那儿污水横流、垃圾遍地，不啻人间地狱。他发现了一个可怕的现实：英国的农村年复一年地把大量壮健的劳动力输入这里，而这些个体到第三代时就已经灭绝。他曾说过：“随时都有四五十万人在叫作伦敦的这个社会陷阱里悲惨地死亡。”他在伦敦东区的贫民窟住了三个月，在那儿读了几百本关于它的小册子、书籍和政府报告，访问了无数男男女女，拍了许多照片；他排过领救济面包的长队，住过济贫院，睡过街道和公园，看到了人们如何在肮脏不堪的生活环境里挣扎和死亡。回到美国后，他出版了《深渊里的人们》一书。这本书带给他的经济收入并不高，却让他在美国的社会主义者之间声名鹊起。在当时的美国，虽然倡导“言论自由”，然而主流社会却对“社会主义思想”持排斥态度。杰克·伦敦并不理会来自四面八方的批评，而是坚持自己的观点，公开表明自己拥护社会主义的态度。他到加州大学做讲演时，大力称赞社会主义，并用人类社会残酷的现实佐证自己的政治见解，结果遭到一些人的谩骂，幸好得到了主张言论自由的校长的保护。他还到商人俱乐部宣传社会主义革命，并把1905年俄国革命中曾杀死过几个沙皇官员的革命者称作自己的兄弟，随即引起轩然大波。第二天他就遭到各报的围攻，报纸上出现了愤怒的社论，说“杰克·伦敦把俄国杀人犯称作兄弟”。

杰克·伦敦一生著述颇丰，共创作了十九部长篇小说、一百五十多篇短篇小说以及大量文学报告集，还写了三个剧本以及相当多的随笔和论文。他的作品中最著名的有《马丁·伊登》《野性的呼唤》《白牙》等，还有本书所包含的《热爱生命》《生火》《墨西哥人》《一块牛排》《黄金谷》《为赶路的人干杯》以及《北方的奥德赛》。

《热爱生命》描述的是一个淘金者的故事。主人公独行于茫茫旷野上，他的同伴离他而去，使他陷于绝境之中。饥饿时时在考验着他的意志，威胁着他的生命。周围只可以看得到贫瘠的荒原，看不到可以果腹的东西，只能靠少之又少的难以下咽的浆果维系生命。后来，就连浆果也找不到了。就在生命即将消逝的时候，他遇到了一只生病的狼。他发现这只病狼跟在他的身后，舔着他的血迹尾随着他。就这样，两个濒临死亡的生灵拖着垂死的身躯，都想把对方作为自己的食物。为了活着回去，为了战胜这只令他作呕的病狼，他拖着虚弱到极点的身子，拼尽最后的一丝力气，将病狼咬死，喝了一些含有大量病菌的狼血，最终活了下来。这篇小说阐明了一个道理：只要有坚定的信念，一个人就可以战胜困难。生命是伟大的，而生命是靠信念支撑的！

《生火》这篇短篇小说，首先对极地环境进行了生动的描述。那儿是一片冰天雪地，气温极低，人和动物极难生存，每时每刻都跟死神相伴。主人公带着一只狗在冰原上艰难跋涉，呼出的热气立刻被冻成冰霜，然后飘落在地。可想而知，那该是多么寒冷！环境越是严酷，人和狗的生存愿望便越是强烈。他们最渴望的是生一堆火，能够暖一暖马上就要冻僵的手脚和身子，然而终难如愿。主人公企图将狗杀死，把自己那眼看就要冻坏的双手放在余温未散的狗的尸体里暖一暖。可是，狗看出了他的小算盘，急忙躲开。主人公经过顽强挣扎，最后还是冻死在了路上。这个故事本身就是典型的自然主义风格——自然环境是无情的，它不会因为人的需要而改变本质。小说通过细腻的描写展示了生命与死亡的大较量。人类固然有着强大的决心，大自然却是残酷的。相比之下，人是那般渺小！

《墨西哥人》以墨西哥革命为背景，讲述了一个名叫菲力普·利维拉的不满十八岁的墨西哥青年积极投身革命的故事。他不堪独裁政权的迫害，只身逃往美国洛杉矶，找到了流亡国外的墨西哥革命党人，以坚忍不拔的毅力，为祖国的革命事业做出了重大贡献。他在革命的紧要关头，为了给革命事业筹集资金，沉着、勇敢、机智地击败了美国一流拳击手。杰克·伦敦通过这篇小说表达了他对墨西哥人民反抗独裁政权的革命斗争的支持和同情，同时也对美国资产阶级社会的种族歧视表示了厌恶和谴责。

在杰克·伦敦的作品中，我们时常能感受到英雄主义情结。他塑造的各种各样的主人公，有的与严寒、饥饿、死亡殊死搏斗，有的与邪恶势力进行不屈不挠的斗争——无论什么样的主人公，胸腔里都跳动着一颗强大的“杰克·伦敦式的心脏”。从这本书的每一篇故事里，你都可以感受到这一点！

方华文

作于苏州大学

2016年8月16日

为赶路的人干杯

“你把它掺进去呀！”

“你听我说，基德，这味道太烈了些吧？威士忌加酒精就已经够呛了，要是再加上白兰地、胡椒汁和……”

“叫你掺你就掺。到底是谁在调制这鸡尾酒呢？”马拉摩特·基德透过一团团的水蒸气满脸慈祥地笑了笑，“孩子，你要是跟我一样在这儿待久了，天天吃野兔和鲑鱼腩度日，你就会明白一年一度的圣诞节是多么珍贵了。而过圣诞节没有喝到鸡尾酒，便等于是已经把洞挖到了岩床上，却连一条富矿脉也没有找到。”

“你说得很在理。”大吉姆·贝尔登很赞成基德的话。他的矿场在梅兹梅，这次是特地赶来过圣诞的。谁都知道，在过去的两个月里，他完全靠吃鹿肉过日子。“那次咱们在塔纳纳河畔自制烈酒喝，当时的情景你还没忘吧？”

“我想是不会忘的。伙计们，用糖和酸面团竟酿出了那样棒的烧酒，大家喝醉后大吵大闹着，那场景让人看了真痛快。当时，你还没有出生呢。”马拉摩特·基德说着，把头转向了年轻的采矿专家斯坦利·普林斯，此人来这儿刚满两年，“那个时候，这一带没有白种女人。梅森想娶露丝，而露丝的父亲是塔纳纳族的酋长，他反对他们的婚事，部落里其余的人也一个样。死脑筋吧？嘿，我用了我最后一磅糖，那是我一生中酿得最好的酒了。你真该看看那场追击，一路沿河岸而下，直至水陆联运点。”

“那个印第安女人后来怎么样啦？”高个子的法裔加拿大人路易斯·萨沃伊听得来了兴趣，开口问道。去年冬天在四十英里矿区时，他听说过这个胆大妄为的事件。

马拉摩特·基德天生就是一个擅长讲故事的人，于是便讲起了这个北方的洛钦瓦尔(1)的动人故事。一桩桩发生在北方的带着荒蛮气息的事件刺激着他的心房，勾起他对南方朦朦胧胧的思念，使他想到了那儿阳光普照的牧草地——那儿的生活总是给人以希望，而不只是一片与寒冷和死亡奋力抗争的荒芜。

“我们踏上育空河时，第一次融冰刚结束。”基德在故事的结尾处讲道，“部落里的追兵只比我们晚到了一刻钟，可正是这一刻钟使我们得以脱险。因为第二次融冰冲开了上游淤塞的冰块，把他们拦在了对岸。待到他们最终追到努克鲁克托的时候，全矿区的人都已经聚集在那里等着他们了。至于婚礼的情况，你还是问这位鲁博神父吧，当时是他主持的。”

这位耶稣会的神父听了，将烟斗从嘴边拿开，只是郑重一笑，以表达内心的喜悦，而新教徒和天主教徒则兴奋得鼓起了掌。

“太棒了！”路易斯·萨沃伊深受故事的浪漫情调感染，不由得高声叫了起来，“这个印第安小女子！我勇敢的梅森！太棒了！”

接着，当第一批盛满鸡尾酒的锡杯分配完毕后，“激情的贝特尔斯”匆匆站起身，亮开嗓子唱起了他最爱的祝酒歌：

有一个亨利·华德·比契尔，
还有主日学校的教员们，
他们喝着檫木根酿的酒呀，推杯把盏；
但你照样深信不疑，
要是给这种酒一个恰当的名称，
禁果佳酿就是它的美名。
啊，禁果佳酿就是它的美名！

酒乡的人一起高唱起来——

啊，禁果佳酿就是它的美名！
但你照样深信不疑，
要是给这种酒一个恰当的名称，
禁果佳酿就是它的美名！

马拉摩特·基德调制的那种令人振奋的混合酒起作用了。宿营地的人和过路的投宿客几杯酒下肚，顿时觉得浑身暖烘烘的，筋骨也舒展开了。大家围着餐桌，又是说笑，又是唱歌，又是讲述过去的冒险经历。他们来自五湖四海，互相敬着酒。英国人普林斯提议为“山姆大叔，新世界的早熟婴儿”(2)干杯；美国人贝特尔斯的祝酒词则是“为女王干杯，愿上帝保佑她”；萨沃伊和德国商人迈耶斯碰杯，为“阿尔萨斯-洛林”(3)干杯。

接着，马拉摩特·基德站起身，举杯在手，向防油纸糊的窗户望了一眼（窗上结的冰霜足足有三英寸厚），然后说道：“祝今夜赶路的人身强体健；愿他带有足够的干粮；愿拉雪橇的狗能坚持到底；愿他的火柴不湿，能点得亮篝火。”

啪！啪！就在这时，大家听见几声熟悉而悦耳的狗鞭响，爱斯基摩狗呜呜地号叫着，一辆雪橇嘎吱一声停在了木屋外。于是，大家止住了谈笑，等待着客人进屋来。

“是个老手，先顾狗，再顾他自己。”当他们听见了狗的撕咬声、像狼一样的嗥吠和痛苦的狺狺狂吠时，马拉摩特·基德悄声对普林斯说。他们耳朵灵敏，一听就知道来客正一边打退他们的狗，一边喂他自己的狗。

最后，大伙儿期盼已久的敲门声终于响起了，声音响亮、有力。来客走进门，被屋里的灯光照花了眼，便在门口停顿了片刻，屋里的人借此机会将他仔细打量了一番。但见他气宇轩昂，生得英俊潇洒，穿一身羊毛极地服和皮衣，个头有六英尺二三英寸高，肩膀宽度适中，厚胸脯，一张不留胡须的脸冻得通红，长长的眉毛和睫毛上都结满了白色冰碴子，狼皮大帽子的护耳同护颈都松松地敞开来，俨然就是一位从茫茫的夜幕里走出来的冰雪世界里的国王。他的短大衣外面系着一条子弹带，皮带上吊着两支大大的柯尔特(4)自动手枪和一把猎刀，手里拿着一根必不可少的狗鞭，还背着一支口径最大、式样最新的无烟步枪。随即，他走上前来，步子稳健、灵活，但仍看得出他已疲惫不堪。

屋里陷入了一阵尴尬的沉默，但他热诚地招呼了一声，“伙计们，你们好！”这一声很快缓解了气氛。紧接着，马拉摩特·基德跟他握了手。二人虽然从来没有见过面，可是久闻彼此大名，一见面就相互认了出来。做主人的二话不说，先给他介绍了在座的各位，又将一缸子酒塞到他手里，这才容他解释来意。

“有三个男人赶着八只狗拉的一辆篮子雪橇曾从此处路过。他们过去有多久了？”他问道。

“都过去两天了。你在追赶他们吗？”

“对，那是我的雪橇和狗。那几个坏家伙竟敢在我的眼皮底下把雪橇偷走。我追他们，已经缩短了两天的路程，再赶一程就追上了。”

“他们恐怕会动粗吧？”为了不使谈话中断，贝尔登开口问道，因为这时候，马拉摩特·基德已经把咖啡放在炉子上，正忙着煎腌猪肉和鹿肉呢。

这个陌生人意味深长地拍了拍他的左轮手枪。

“你什么时候离开道森(5)的？”

“十二点。”

“昨天夜里十二点？”贝尔登想当然地问。

“今天中午十二点。”

周围顿时响起一阵惊呼。这很棒了。此时刚到午夜，想不到他在十二个小时内竟然在冰雪覆盖的河道上跑了七十五英里的路，这可不是开玩笑的。

不过，大家很快就把话题转移了，有人回忆起了童年时候的事情。趁着那位年轻的陌生来客吃着这顿粗粝的饭食时，马拉摩特·基德仔细观察了一下他的面相，立刻断定这是一张正直、诚实、坦率的脸，他很是喜欢。此人年龄虽然不大，脸上却已有一道道辛勤劳作和历经艰险所留下的皱纹。虽然他言语之间不乏亲切感，休息时态度也显得很温和，但他那双蓝眼睛定会在一旦付诸行动，特别是遇到危险的时候，闪射出刚毅的光芒。那有力的下颚和方正的下巴显露出了他顽强、坚忍不拔、百折不挠的性格。不过，尽管他勇猛得像头雄狮，却带有一丝女性的温柔气质，这说明他有一颗多愁善感的心。

“我和我老婆就是这么结婚的。”贝尔登讲述完他那段激动人心的求偶过程，最后说道，“回到她家，她说道，‘爸爸，我们回来了。’‘老天会惩罚你的。’她父亲骂了她一句，然后转过身对我说，‘吉姆，把你那身漂亮衣服脱下来，快给我犁地去，吃饭前争取把那四十英亩地耕出来。’吩咐完我，他又对她说，‘还有你，萨尔，你给他们做饭去。’随后，他哼了声鼻子，吻了她一下。当时，就别提我有多高兴了。他见我仍没有下地去，就吼了起来，‘快去呀，吉姆！’我就连忙跑到谷仓里去啦。”

“你回美国，是有孩子在这儿等着你？”陌生客问道。

“没有。萨尔在有孩子之前就死了。也正是因为如此，我才来的。”说到这里，贝尔登神情恍惚地给烟斗点火，其实烟斗本来就没有熄灭。随后，他又高兴地问道：“你呢，陌生人，成家了吗？”

陌生客没吱声，默默地打开了怀表盖，将怀表从用作表链的皮带上摘下，递了过来。贝尔登挑亮那盏昏暗的油灯，细细看了看表匣里面，啧啧赞叹了几声，然后把怀表递给了路易斯·萨沃伊。后者看了，连呼了几声“我的天”，随即便转给了普林斯。只见普林斯双手发抖，眼睛里平添出几分温柔的神色。就这样，怀表在一双双粗硬的大手间传看着——里面镶着一张女人的照片，是这些男人酷爱的那种小鸟依人的女人，怀中还抱着一个婴儿。没有看到这“奇观”的人们顿起好奇之心，而看过的则沉默了下来，沉湎于对往事的回忆之中。这些汉子不怕面对饥饿的煎熬、疾病的折磨，也不怕暴死在荒野上和洪水里，可是这个陌生女子同孩子的照片却触动了他们的柔情，把他们变成了软弱的女人和孩子。

“还没见过小家伙呢——听她说是个男孩，已经两岁了。”陌生客收回他的宝贝怀表时说。他又恋恋不舍地多看了几眼那照片，才啪的一声合上了表盖，转过了脸去，然而却难掩眼中克制已久、夺眶而出的泪水。

马拉摩特·基德把他带到一张床前，要他睡下。

“四点整叫醒我。别误了我。”他说完这话，没一会儿，就疲倦地睡了过去，鼾声阵阵。

“天哪！真是条好汉，”普林斯说道，“赶狗跑了七十五英里，再睡三个小时，又上路。他是谁，基德？”

“他叫杰克·韦斯顿戴尔，来这儿混已有三年了，除了像牛马一样干活的名声之外，什么也没有捞到，运气要多坏有多坏。我以前并不了解他，后来是听希特卡·查理讲了他的事情。”

“真是不容易啊，把可爱的娇妻抛在家中，一个人在这个荒凉之地苦熬岁月，这鬼地方一年抵外面两年。”

“他的毛病在于太顽固，犟得像头牛。他两次下赌场，赢了不少钱，后来又都叫他输了个精光。”

这时，贝特尔斯一阵高歌打断了他们的谈话，照片所产生的效应也随之消失了。在觥筹交错的狂欢之中，大家很快就将常年吃猪狗食、干牛马活的艰难处境抛之脑后。唯独基德一人看起来心神不定，一次次焦虑地看表。后来，他戴上手套和海狸皮帽子跑到屋外，进了贮藏室，在那儿窸窸窣窣地忙碌起来。

他实在等不下去了，没有按指定的时间叫醒那位陌生客，而是提前了一刻钟。那个年轻的大个子浑身僵硬，给他使劲揉搓一通后才站立起来。他吃力地蹒跚着走出木屋，发现他的狗已套上了雪橇，一切都已准备妥当，只等他启程上路了。大家祝他好运，愿他尽快追上歹徒。鲁博神父匆匆为他祝福后，便急忙回到了木屋里，众人紧随其后。这也难怪，在零下七十四度的严寒中待久了，裸露在外的耳朵和手会被冻坏的。

马拉摩特·基德送他上了大路，诚挚地握住他的手，叮嘱了他几句。

“你在雪橇上会找到一百磅鲑鱼子，”基德说，“路上当狗粮，顶得上一百五十磅鱼。你也许指望在佩利能买到狗粮，其实是买不到的。”陌生客颇觉意外，眼睛里闪过一道光，但没有吱声。“在到五指河的路上，你连一口狗食和人粮也搞不到。中间有两百英里的路呢，非常难走。千万要当心三十英里河上没有结冰的地方，一定得抄近路，走巴尔杰湖上那条捷径。”

“这事你是怎么知道的？消息总不能比我来得还快吧？”

“我什么也不知道，而且，我也不想知道。不过，你追寻的那群狗根本不是你的，而是去年春天希特卡·查理卖给他们的。然而，希特卡·查理提到过你，说你是个正派人，他的话我相信。我观察了你的面相，我喜欢你的这张脸。我看得出——算了，该死的，你还是快点赶路吧，到海的那边去，回到你老婆身边吧。这里有……”说到此处，基德一把摘下手套，将钱袋掏了出来。

“不，我用不着。”陌生客颤抖着紧握住基德的手，滚滚的泪珠在他脸上结成了冰。

“路上别心疼狗，累倒一条就解下来，买新的替换上，每一磅也就值十美元嘛。在五指河、小鲑鱼河以及胡塔林卡都可以买得到的。小心别把脚弄湿，免得冻坏。”基德临分手时谆谆叮嘱，“行驶速度保持在一小时二十五英里以上。如果低于这个数，你就生一堆火，换换袜子，休息一下。”

陌生客走了可能还不到一刻钟，便传来了雪橇铃铛的叮当声——又有客人来了。门开了，一个西北地区的骑警走了进来，后面跟着两个驭狗的混血儿。这一行人跟韦斯顿戴尔一样，也是全副武装，也是满脸倦容。两个混血儿是惯于行路者，虽疲倦却不以为然。那位年轻的骑警则累得像是浑身散了架。是他那个种族坚忍不拔的精神一路支撑着他，只要他不倒下就不会停止前进的步伐。

“韦斯顿戴尔走了多久了？”他问道，“他在这儿歇过脚，是不是？”这一番问话简直是多余的，根据路上的雪橇印迹便可一目了然。

马拉摩特·基德给贝尔登丢了个眼色，后者会意，便搪塞地回答：“走了好一会儿啦。”

“听着，伙计，要说实话！”警察告诫道。

“你们好像是要抓他哟。他在道森犯什么事了？”

“他抢了哈利·麦克法兰四万美元，然后去太平洋港湾公司的商店换成了一张在西雅图支付的支票。要是我们不追上他，谁去阻止他兑换呢？他到底是何时离开这里的？”

马拉摩特·基德已向每个人都使过了眼色，所以大家都装得跟没事人一样，年轻的警察对上的是一张张面无表情的脸。

他大步走到普林斯面前，将问题抛给了普林斯。普林斯呆呆地望着这位同胞那张坦率、诚恳的脸，有点痛心，但回答时仍闪烁其词、支支吾吾的。

这时候，警察一眼瞧见了鲁博神父（他不能撒谎）。神父回答说：“他和他的狗在这儿休息了四个小时，是一刻钟之前离开的。”

“都走了一刻钟了，而且攒足了劲！上帝呀！”可怜的警察又累又失望，几近昏倒，踉跄着朝后退了几步，嘴里唠唠叨叨地说自己从道森赶过来，一口气跑了十个小时，拉雪橇的狗都累趴下了。

马拉摩特·基德递给他一缸子鸡尾酒叫他提提神。他一饮而尽，然后转身向门口走去，命令那两个驭狗人跟他一起上路。但屋里暖意融融，加上对于休息的渴盼太过强烈，于是二人费力地抗议着。基德是熟悉法语方言的，他不安地仔细听着。

驭狗人说狗已经累垮了，跑不了一英里地就得射杀西瓦施和巴贝特，其他狗也强不了多少，最好让人和狗都休息休息。

“能借我五条狗吗？”他转向马拉摩特·基德问道。

基德摇了一下头。

“我可以用康士坦丁上尉的名义给你开一张五千美元的支票——这是我的授权书——我得到了授权，可以酌情开支票的。”

基德再次无声地拒绝了。

“那我就要以女王的名义征用了。”

基德不相信他敢动真格的，便只是笑了笑，朝自己那装满长枪短枪的武器架瞅了一眼。那个英国人明白自己寡不敌众、无力回天，就扭转身，向门口走去。而两个驭狗人仍反对立刻动身。他气得冲到他们跟前，骂他们是娘儿们，是杂种。那个年纪比较大的混血儿站起来的时候，一张黝黑的脸被气得通红，咬牙切齿地回敬了几句狠话，抱怨他非得让领队的狗累断腿，最后葬身于雪原才肯罢休。

年轻的警察——聚集起全身的力气——迈着坚定的步子向门口走去，尽管他已疲惫不堪，却强装出精神抖擞的样子。人人都了解实际情况，不由对他那种不认输的韧劲肃然起敬。话虽如此，他却难掩从脸上掠过的一阵痛苦的表情。那些狗身上结满了冰霜，蜷缩着卧在雪里，它们已经无法站立了。驭狗人憋了一肚子气，残酷无情地用鞭子狠狠抽打它们，打得那些可怜的狗儿呜呜呜地哀号。后来，他们割断套索，把领队的狗巴贝特拖了出来，其他的狗才拉动雪橇，启程上路了。

“流氓、无赖、骗子！”“他妈的！真不是个东西！”“这个强盗！”“印第安人都不如！”屋里的人对那个陌生客骂不绝口，一个个义愤填膺——一是因为他们觉得自己受到了欺骗，二是由于他们认为北方的行为准则遭到了破坏（根据这一准则，诚实是至高无上的，最应该受到珍视）。“明明知道那小子行迹诡异，却还要帮他。”众人抱怨着，一齐将谴责的目光投向了马拉摩特·基德。正在屋角处照料巴贝特的基德见状便从那儿站了起来，把最后一点酒给大家斟上，要请大家饮完这最后一巡酒。

“今天晚上真冷呀，伙计们——冷到骨头缝里了。”他开始为自己辩解，但这一开场白显得牛头不对马嘴，“大家都是在风雪路上跋涉过的，其中滋味谁都清楚。一个人落难的时候，最怕的就是墙倒众人推。这件事，诸位只知其一不知其二。江湖上的人同吃一锅饭，睡觉时合盖一条毯子，这里边恐怕数杰克做得最好了。去年秋天，他把积攒下的四万美元交给乔·卡斯特尔，让卡斯特尔到加拿大边境跟前的自治领地购买采矿权。他原本是可以成为百万富翁的，可他却留在了圈城照料自己的一个患坏血病的朋友。你们猜猜卡斯特尔做了些什么！他跑到麦克法兰的赌场里，把赌注加到最大限额，一下子把钱全输光了。第二天有人发现他死在了雪地里。可怜的杰克本来打算今年冬天回家看望老婆和没见过面的孩子。要知道，他没有多拿，只拿走了卡斯特尔输掉的——那四万美元。事已至此，你们说说该怎么办呢？”

基德扫视了一眼围成一圈的“道德法官们”，见大家紧绷着的脸趋于缓和，便高举起酒杯说：“祝今夜赶路的人身强体健；愿他带有足够的干粮；愿拉雪橇的狗能坚持到底；愿他的火柴不湿，能点得亮篝火。愿上帝保佑他一路顺利，祝他好运气，愿他……”

“愿那个骑警迷路！”贝特尔斯举起空酒杯，跟大伙儿碰杯，嘴里大声叫道。

————————————————————

(1) 这里是指代英国作家司各特的长诗《玛密恩》中的男主角。其中有一首诗叫《洛钦瓦尔》，描写了洛钦瓦尔因为爱慕美丽的艾伦，就在她结婚的那天将她抢走了。这里隐指梅森。

(2) 喻指美国。

(3) 阿尔萨斯-洛林（Alsace-Lorraine）：法国东部地区，普法战争后法国于1871年割让给德国。1919年第一次世界大战后，这块土地归还法国。第二次世界大战期间，被德国占领，后又归还法国。

(4) 美国著名枪械公司。

(5) 加拿大西北部城市。

北方的奥德赛(1)

1

雪橇行走在路上，挽具咯吱作响，领头狗身上的铃铛发出叮当叮当的声音，这一切汇成了一首永恒的悲歌。然而，无论人还是狗，全都精疲力竭，默然无声。车道上满是新雪，使行路变得缓慢。他们远道而来，雪橇上满载猎杀的麋鹿，一只只冻得跟石头一样硬；雪橇陷在松软的雪地上，就是不肯前行，简直跟人一样倔强。天色渐晚，但今夜他们不准备半路宿营。白雪从静谧的空中落下——那不是雪花，而是晶莹剔透、小巧玲珑的水晶粒。天气很暖和——差不多也就是零下十度吧——大家并不把这种天气放在眼里。迈耶斯和贝特尔斯将帽子上的护耳翻上去，露出耳朵，马拉摩特·基德甚至摘下了手套。

狗儿早在下午就已疲惫不堪，此刻它们却又开始展现出新的活力。它们之中比较精明的狗已经开始躁动不安了——似乎难耐挽绳的束缚，渴望快速奔跑，却又犹豫不决，支棱起耳朵，呼哧呼哧用鼻子嗅探着。后来，它们迁怒于自己比较拖沓的伙伴们，动不动就咬伙伴们的后腿，催促它们加快步子。受到责备的狗像是得了传染病，接着又把这种病传染给其他的狗。最后，走在顶前边的那辆雪橇的领队狗发出一声兴奋的长吠，在雪地里俯下身子向前猛冲，将领圈拉得紧紧的，其余的狗也就紧跟着向前冲。只见雪橇皮带收紧、挽绳绷直，一辆辆像离弦的箭似的向前冲去。赶雪橇的人紧紧抓住辕杆，加速前进，免得被后边的雪橇撞倒。一天的疲倦霎时烟消云散，驭手们放开嗓门一声喊，给狗儿们加油，狗儿也发出快乐的汪汪声作为回应。人和狗一起发力，在越来越浓的暮色里奔走如飞。

“加油！加油！”驭手们你一声我一声地叫喊着，只见雪橇队突然离开大道，翘起一边的滑板，犹如一只只乘风破浪的帆船。

雪橇队向前冲了有一百码，在一扇羊皮纸糊的窗户跟前骤然停了下来，窗户内的灯光让木屋的情况显而易见——熊熊燃烧的育空(2)炉子和热气腾腾的茶壶。这座木屋来了不速之客。六十几条爱斯基摩狗气势汹汹地狂吠不已，这些毛茸茸的家伙一边叫一边张牙舞爪地朝第一辆雪橇的狗儿们扑了过来。屋门被猛地推开，一个穿着红色西北警察制服的人走了出来，踩着没膝深的雪走进发狂的爱斯基摩狗群里，用狗鞭的鞭柄抽打它们，态度冷静、公正，让它们一个个安静了下来。随后，他跟驭手们一一握手——马拉摩特·基德就是以这种形式被一个陌生人迎进了他自己的木屋。

按说，出来迎接的应该是斯坦利·普林斯——如前所言，普林斯留在木屋里负责照看火炉和烹茶。岂不知，此刻普林斯正在屋里忙着招待客人呢。总共有十来个客人，说不清身份，反正都是为女王效力的，有执法的，也有投递邮件的。他们血统各异，但相同的生活将他们铸造成了同一类型的人——身材瘦而结实，成块的肌肉线条分明；一张张脸被晒成了紫铜色；心灵纯净，目光清朗、坦荡。这些人驾着雪橇为女王而奔忙，令女王的敌人胆战心惊；他们吃的都是粗茶淡饭，心里却充满了欢乐。他们见过世面，创造过辉煌的业绩，成就过一段段传奇，然而他们自己却浑然不知。

他们显得悠闲自在，就像在自己家中一样。他们当中有两个人四肢伸展地躺在马拉摩特·基德的床上，嘴里哼唱着法国情歌——当初他们的法国先祖来到西北地区，和印第安女子成双配对时唱的就是这种歌。贝特尔斯的床铺也遭到了同样的侵占——但见三四个身强力壮的邮差身上捂着毯子，一边搓着脚丫子，一边在听一个人讲故事。讲述者曾经在沃尔斯利将军(3)的舰队里服过役，随沃尔斯利进攻过喀土穆(4)。等到他说累了，一个牛仔就讲起了当年自己跟随野牛比尔(5)游历欧洲各国首都的经历，说他们经常出入于宫廷，见到了许多王侯和贵妇人。木屋的一个角落里有两个混血儿，他们曾是战友，一道参加过一次最终失败了的战役。此时，他们修补着挽具，回忆着逝去的岁月，回忆着西北地区风起云涌的起义以及路易斯·里尔(6)称王的经历。

这些客人粗话不断，相互插科打诨，彼此开玩笑。他们用轻松的语气谈论自己在风雪路上以及大江大河上遭遇的艰险，就好像在说着家长里短——他们回忆这些往事，只是因为其中包含着滑稽或好玩的片段。这些无冕英雄见证了历史创造的过程，但在他们的眼里，那些伟大、传奇的事件只不过是日常生活里的平凡琐事，普林斯听他们讲述，不由心迷神往。他把自己珍贵的烟草毫不在乎地分给他们；为了报答他的热情招待，生了锈的回忆的锁链松开了，遗忘已久的奥德赛式的故事也复活了。

当谈话终止，客人们最后一次加满烟斗，解开捆得紧紧的毛皮铺盖卷准备睡觉时，普林斯掉过头来找老朋友基德，向他了解更多有关这些客人的情况。

“哦，那个牛仔的情况你已经知道了，”马拉摩特·基德一面回答，一面动手解开他的鹿皮鞋的带子，“和他一块儿躺在床上的那个伙计有点英国血统，这不难看得出。至于其他人，全都是森林里的好汉，血缘关系复杂得只有老天才知道。靠近门口睡的那两个，却是地地道道的‘法种’，或称‘森林小子’(7)；那个围着绒线围巾的小伙子——你只要看看他的眉眼和下巴——一定是哪个苏格兰男人到过他妈妈那烟雾腾腾的帐篷后才有的他；那个把斗篷枕在头下的帅气小伙子有一半法国血统——他刚才说的话你也听到了，他不喜欢那两个睡在他旁边的印第安人。要知道，当初这些‘法种’在里尔的领导下起义的时候，纯种的印第安人并没有响应，自那以后，他们之间的感情就大不如以前了。”

“我说，炉子旁边那个阴沉着脸的伙计是什么情况？他肯定不会说英语，一晚上连口都没有开过。”

“错了。他的英语很棒。他听别人讲话，你注意到他的眼神了没有？我注意到了，他显然跟其他人并非乡亲同胞，那些人一说家乡话你就可以看得出他听不懂了。我也搞不清他究竟是什么情况，现在咱们就弄他个水落石出吧。”

“请你给炉子里添几根柴！”马拉摩特·基德提高嗓门，眼睛盯着那个不明身份的人喊了一声。

那人照着做了。

“他显然受过训练，习惯于遵守命令。”普林斯小声嘀咕道。

马拉摩特·基德点了点头，脱下袜子，然后小心地从躺下来休息的人们中间穿过，走到炉子跟前，把他的湿袜子和另外二十多双同样的袜子挂在了一起。

“你估计什么时候能赶到道森？”他搭讪着问。

那人先看了他几眼，然后才回答道：“他们说还有七十五英里。是这样吧？我估计还要两天。”

可以听出他的口音带有一丁点儿地方腔，但说话脱口而出，没有为斟词酌句打绊。

“以前来过这一带吗？”

“没来过。”

“去过西北地区吗？”

“去过。”

“是那里出生的？”

“不是。”

“哦，那你究竟是哪里人？你跟他们不是同一类人。”马拉摩特·基德说着，用手泛泛指了指那些驭狗人，连睡在普林斯床铺上的那两个警察也包括了进去，“你到底是何方神圣？你这样的脸我是见过的，只是记不清在什么地方了。”

“我知道你。”那人答非所问地说，一下子就把马拉摩特·基德的问题岔开了。

“在哪儿？你见过我？”

“不是你，是你的牧师朋友。那是很久以前的事了，在帕斯蒂里克。他曾问过我，问我认不认识你，马拉摩特·基德。他给了我一点干粮。我在那地方没有久留。你听他提起过我吗？”

“噢，想起来了！你就是那个用海獭皮换狗的人？”

那个人点点头，磕了磕烟斗，把里面的灰磕出来，然后把皮毛毯子在身上裹紧，表示谈话到此结束。马拉摩特·基德将那盏昏暗的油灯吹灭，钻到毯子下和普林斯躺在了一起。

“怎么样？他是干什么的？”

“还不清楚——他把我的问题岔开了，真是守口如瓶啊。他这种人会叫你顿起好奇之心。对于他，我是有所耳闻的。八年前他去海边，那里的人不了解他的身份，觉得他是个神秘人物。他在寒冬腊月打北方来，千里迢迢，沿着白令海峡南下，风风火火的，好像有鬼在追他似的。他到底来自何处，无人知晓，只知道他来自很远的地方。他抵达戈洛文湾时已经累坏了，从瑞典传教士那儿搞到一点食物，问了问南下的路便又走了。这些都是我们事后听说的。后来，他横渡诺顿湾，离开了海岸线。当时雪骤风急，天公不作美，可他坚持到底，一路前行。他未能在圣迈克尔斯上岸，于是最后到了帕斯蒂里克。要是换上别人，早就去见阎王爷了。那一路，他失去了一切，只剩下两条狗，自己也差一点饿死。

“鲁博神父见他急着赶路，就给了他一点干粮，可是说什么也不愿把狗给他，因为等我一到，神父自己也要出行呢。那位尤利西斯(8)先生心里非常清楚，没有狗他是无法上路的。于是，他盘桓数日，四处想办法。他的雪橇上有一捆硝得很好的海獭皮——要知道，海獭皮的价值等同于黄金。当时，帕斯蒂里克有个俄国商人，简直就是个老年夏洛克(9)，他正好有几条狗预备宰杀。结果，他们没用多长时间就把这笔生意谈妥了。当那位神秘人物再次登程南下时，有了一队奔跑如飞的狗，而那位夏洛克先生得到了一批海獭皮。海獭皮我可是亲眼看了，真是上等货色。据估算，每条狗至少让那位夏洛克先生赚了五百块。这倒不是说那位神秘人物不懂得海獭的价值——他好歹也是个懂行的印第安人，虽说话不多，却也听得出他是跟白人打过交道的。

“海上的冰融化以后，努尼瓦克岛(10)有人过来说他曾到岛上找过干粮，后来就不见了踪影。此后八年他如同石沉大海，音讯全无，现在却突然出现在这里。他是从哪里冒出来的呢？来此处干什么？有什么目的？他是个印第安人，神出鬼没的，而且受过训练，这在印第安人中是很少见的。普林斯，这又是北方的一个谜团，等着你去破解呢。”

“多谢器重。不过我手头的事情太多，恐怕忙不过来。”普林斯回答说。

没等他把话说完，马拉摩特·基德已经鼾声如雷了。而这位年轻的采矿工程师则心潮起伏，睁大眼睛望着那茫茫的夜色，在等待着激荡的思绪平复下来。后来，他总算睡着了，可是大脑仍很活跃，梦见自己游荡于一片不知名的白雪皑皑的荒原上，和雪橇狗一起跋涉在永无尽头的道路上，沿途目睹人们如何在活着时备受苦难，又如何勇敢地走向死亡。

第二天一早，离天亮还有几个小时，几个驭狗人便和警察动身往道森去了。尽管如此，当局只关心女王陛下的利益，他们掌控着她之下的那些小人物的命运，途中也没让邮差们好好休息。一个星期后，他们赶到了斯图尔特河，雪橇上满载着送往盐湖的邮件。拉雪橇的狗换了班，邮差却仍是原班人马。

他们原指望能休息几天，放松放松。此外，克朗代克是北方地区新建起来的城市，大家都渴望领略一下这座黄金城的风采——此处的金砂似泉水一般源源不断，歌舞笙箫彻夜不息。然而，他们却只能烤一烤湿袜子，在暮色里用烟斗抽几口烟，跟上一趟来时一样情绪低落。有一两个胆大的动起了逃跑的念头，盘算着翻越人迹罕至的落基山到东边去，再经过麦肯齐山谷前往齐普砚地区，那儿是他们的常来常往之地。另外有两三个人也在打着自己的小算盘，决定合同期满后回家去，也走同一条路线；他们对这趟充满艰辛的返乡之旅满怀期待，激动得就像城里人期待着到林间度假一样。

那个曾拿海獭皮换狗的人显得心神不定，对周围人的谈话一点不感兴趣。后来，他把马拉摩特·基德拉到一边，叽叽咕咕小声说了一会儿话。普林斯瞅着他们，心里充满了好奇，见他们戴上帽子和手套出了门，就更觉得他俩的行踪神秘兮兮的了。俩人回来后，马拉摩特·基德将一杆金秤放在桌上，称出六十盎司的碎金放进那个神秘人物的口袋里。驭狗人的头头随即也加入了他们的密谈，几个人进行了一场交易。第二天，雪橇队朝着大河的上游进发，而那个曾拿海獭皮换狗的人却带上几磅重的干粮，独自返回道森去了。

事后，当普林斯问起，马拉摩特·基德回答说：“真是叫人摸不着头脑，但那个可怜的家伙出于某种原因，想摆脱现在的工作——至少对他而言那原因极为重要，只是他死活不愿挑明。要知道，干这一行犹如服兵役，随便不得。他签了两年的合同，重获自由的唯一途径就是出钱赎身。他不能逃跑，不然他就不能再留在这儿了，可他偏偏又十分渴望留在这个地区。据他说，他一到道森就打定主意扎根于此了，只可惜他囊中羞涩，又举目无亲，我是唯一一个他还说过几句话的人。他和副总督交涉过，说好只要从我这儿借到钱便可以赎身。他说年内便能将钱还清，还说如果我愿意，可以为我指出一条发财之路。他说他自己虽然并没有亲眼见过，却知道那是一条铺满了黄金的道路。

“实不相瞒，他把我拉到外边时都快要哭了，跪倒在雪地里苦苦哀求我，直到我把他硬拉了起来。他像个疯子一样，唠唠叨叨说个没完。他对天发誓，说他为了实现这一目标已奋斗多年，如希望落空，定会令他生不如死。我问他是什么目标，他却不肯说，只说生怕当局会叫他去另一条道上运送邮件，两年内回不了道森，那时他的目标就实现不了了。我这一辈子从没见过有谁竟如此伤心，便答应借钱给他，并又一次将他从雪地里拽了起来。我跟他说，让他把这笔钱当作我的一份股金。你猜他同意了吗？不！他发誓要把他赚得的财富全部给我，让我享受连做梦也想不到的富有。反正，他的好话说了一大篓子。一个人为了筹得做事的本钱，会绞尽脑汁、不择手段，可是一旦成功，叫他分一半红利给投资人通常也是很难的。这是经验之谈，普林斯，你可要记好了。他要是留在本地区不走，咱们会听到他的下文的。”

“他要是一拍屁股走了呢？”

“那就是我的好心没有得到好报，那六十盎司的金子全当打水漂了。”

严寒袭来，随之而至的还有漫漫的长夜，太阳在南方雪野的地平线那儿又玩起了亘古不变的躲猫猫游戏。马拉摩特·基德的那笔款子仍没有下落。后来，在一月初的一个阴冷的上午，几辆满载货物的狗拉雪橇停在了他那位于斯图尔特河下游的木屋门前。雪橇上坐着那个用海獭皮换狗的人，同来的还有一个身材高大的人（上帝恐怕也记不清自己怎么会造出了一个这样的人来）。一旦说起运气、胆量和一铲就铲出价值五百美元的金砂的趣闻，人们总会提到阿克塞尔·冈德森的大名；在营火边，每当大家议论起勇气、力量和天不怕地不怕的精神，也必定会讲到他的事迹。一旦谈兴低落，只要一提跟他同甘共苦的那个女人，人们的谈话就一定会变得又热烈起来。

显然，上帝在创造阿克塞尔·冈德森时，运用了远古时期的手法，将其塑造成了洪荒时代的那一类人。他身材魁伟，足足有七英尺高，衣着华贵，俨然一副黄金国国王的派头。他的胸脯、脖子和手脚都跟巨人一样。连骨头带肉有三百磅重，脚上的雪鞋比别人的要长出一码多。他方鼻阔嘴，有着一双无所畏惧的淡蓝色眼睛，一看面相就知道是个天不怕地不怕的主儿。他的头发结着冰霜，黄黄的，像熟透了的玉米须扫过黝黑的脸膛，犹如阳光穿过了黑夜，一直披到他的熊皮袄上。只见他一马当先，身后领着一队雪橇狗，沿着狭窄的小道虎虎生风地走了过来，身上隐约有一股海上霸王的劲儿。他用狗鞭的鞭柄猛敲马拉摩特·基德的房门，简直就像是个北欧海盗南下抢劫，正恶狠狠地把城堡的大门擂得山响。

普林斯挽起袖子，露出他细皮嫩肉的胳膊，一边揉面团一边不住地斜瞟着来客——这三位客人一起光临，此情此景一生一遇。对于那个神秘人物（马拉摩特·基德戏称之为尤利西斯），他仍然兴趣不减，但更叫他感兴趣的则是阿克塞尔·冈德森和他的妻子。赶了一天的路，女人已倦容满面。自从她的丈夫找到了富矿脉，发了大财，她就变得娇气了，过惯了养尊处优的日子，也就容易感到累了。她依偎在丈夫宽阔的胸脯上，就像一朵娇弱的鲜花靠在墙上，一边懒洋洋地回应着马拉摩特·基德善意的玩笑，一边时不时地用她那深深的黑眼睛扫一眼普林斯，惹得普林斯热血沸腾。普林斯毕竟是个男人，身体健康，已经一连好几个月都没见上个女人。这个女人虽说比他大，又是个印第安种，但她不同于他所见过的那些印第安婆娘，她是个见多识广的女性——根据她的谈吐看得出，她不仅去过丈夫的国家，还去过许多其他国家。白种女人懂得的事情，她几乎全懂，此外还懂得许多白种女人不懂的事情。用晒干的鱼她就能做出一顿饭，在雪地里也能搭一张床，然而她喜欢拿男人们开涮，故意津津乐道地说出许多盛宴上的菜名，挑动听者肚子里的馋虫——那些菜名是旧时的回忆，他们几乎已经淡忘。对于鹿、熊和小蓝狐的生活习性，她了如指掌，也非常熟悉北方海洋里野生两栖动物的情况。无论是森林狩猎还是江河行船，她样样精通；无论是人的足迹还是鸟兽的爪印，她都一看便知。普林斯还注意到她在看他们的营地规则时眼里露出了赞赏的目光。这套规则是“激情的贝特尔斯”在情绪激动之时拟定出来的，言简意赅、诙谐幽默，每次有女士前来，他都会把它翻过去，免得叫她们看了尴尬。谁料到这个土著女子竟然……唉，说什么也晚了。

阿克塞尔·冈德森的贤内助就是这么一个人。她的名字与传说和她的丈夫一起，在整个北方广为流传。进餐时，马拉摩特·基德仗着自己是多年的老朋友，老是取笑她，普林斯一改初见时的腼腆，也跟着插科打诨。她虽以一敌二，但不甘示弱，丈夫不善言辞，无法加入智斗，只能为她喝彩助阵。阿克塞尔·冈德森颇为妻子感到自豪，从他的每一个眼神、每一个动作都可以看得出妻子在他的生活中占有重要的位置。那个用海獭皮换狗的人只顾不声不响地吃饭，在这场热闹的交锋中竟然被大家忘记了。没等其他人吃完，他就早早退了席，到外边去照料雪橇狗了。没过多大一会儿，他的伙伴们戴上帽子，穿上毛皮大衣，也跟了过去。

多日没有下雪，育空大道的路面被冻得硬邦邦的，雪橇行走在上面毫不费力，犹如滑行在冰面上。尤利西斯驾着第一辆雪橇领头，普林斯和阿克塞尔·冈德森的妻子驾第二辆紧随其后，马拉摩特·基德则和这位黄发巨人驾第三辆押后阵。

“虽然这只是一种‘预感’，基德，”他说道，“但我觉得还是靠谱的。那地方他从来都没有去过，可是他说得有鼻子有眼，而且还让我看了地图——那地图多年前我在库特尼地区早已有所耳闻。我倒是很想叫你一块入伙，可是他是个怪人，把话说得很死：如果有任何别的人插手此事，那他会就此作罢。不过等我回来，我会让你第一个尝到甜头的。我将把我旁边的那个矿分给你，而且把城建基金的股份分一半给你。”

“别说啦！别说啦！”他见对方想说客气话，便提高了嗓门说道，“这事由我做主。再说，事成之前，我有问题还要和你商量呢。假如一切顺利，那儿就成了第二个克里普尔克里克(11)了。听清楚了吗，伙计？第二个克里普尔克里克！要知道，那可是石英矿，而非砂矿。如果干得顺手，那儿就成了摇钱树，赚个几百万不在话下。那地方我以前就听人说过，所以你应该也不会陌生。到时候，咱们叫一座城市拔地而起，那儿有成千上万的工人、优良的水道、轮船、繁忙的运输生意，有小火轮往上游一趟趟运货，也许咱们还要修铁路，建锯木厂和发电站，还要有自己的银行、贸易公司，成立辛迪加(12)……想想吧！此事必须保密，等我回来再说！”

几辆雪橇停了下来，前面的路要穿过斯图尔特河的河口。眼前是一片茫茫无际的冰雪世界，一直向神秘的东方延伸。他们把捆在雪橇上的雪鞋解了下来。阿克塞尔·冈德森跟大家握了握手，然后走到了前边去。他那巨大的蹼足似的雪鞋踩进柔软如羽毛般的雪里，陷下去足有半码多深，把雪压得实实的，好让雪橇狗行走。他的妻子跟在最后一辆雪橇后面，脚上穿着沉重的雪鞋，却显得轻巧，一看便知是长年锻炼出来的。朋友间几声愉快的告别打破了雪野的沉寂；雪橇狗汪汪地叫着。那个曾用海獭皮换狗的人，正挥鞭教训一只倔强的狗。

一个小时之后，他们出发上路了，雪橇犹如黑色的铅笔，在巨大的白纸上画出一条长长的直线。

2

几个星期之后的某天晚上，马拉摩特·基德和普林斯见一本旧杂志上有棋谱，便把那一页撕下来埋头研究起来。基德才从他的博南扎矿山回来，打算好好休息一下，为之后的长长的猎鹿季做好准备。普林斯不是在江河上行船就是奔走于雪野之上，忙碌了几乎一个冬天，也想躲在木屋里享受一个星期的清福。

“看这黑棋子，跳马将军。不行，这是一步败棋。瞧，下一步……”

“为什么要让卒子进两步呢？应该叫卒子过界河，把象吃掉……”

“且慢！这样一来，防线就会有一个缺口了……”

“别担心，不会有缺口的。放心好啦！你会明白这是一步高棋。”

这盘棋真是妙趣横生。外边有人敲门，等到敲门声第二次响起时，马拉摩特·基德才说了声“请进”。房门猛地被推开了，有一个“东西”摇摇晃晃地走了进来。普林斯迎面一看，不由得跳了起来，眼里显露出惊恐的神情，马拉摩特·基德见了，急转过身去看个究竟。这一看不当紧，虽说他是见过不少恐怖场面的，却也被吓得不轻。那“东西”不管这一套，踉踉跄跄向他们逼近。普林斯慢慢向后退去，一直退到了挂着他那把史密斯-威森(13)手枪的地方。

“天呀！这是什么东西？”他悄声问马拉摩特·基德。

“不清楚。看样子像是又冻又饿。”基德一边回着话，一边悄悄地朝着对面的那个方向摸去。“小心点！这家伙也许是个疯子。”他走过去关好门，回来时警告道。

那“东西”向桌子跟前走去，油灯的亮光照在它的眼睛上。它显然很高兴，发出一阵怪异的咯咯声，表达着内心的喜悦。普林斯和基德发现那“东西”竟然是个人。只见那人朝后一晃身子，把手插在皮裤上，唱起了水手的起锚歌，就像这时有人正升起船帆，转动绞盘，耳边涛声阵阵：

美国船，顺流而下，
能干的小伙子呀！拉呀拉！
你想知道船长是谁吗？
能干的小伙子呀！拉呀拉！
他就是江奈生·琼斯，来自于南卡罗来纳
能干的小伙子呀！拉呀拉！
……

他唱了半截便戛然而止，像狼一样嗥叫一声，摇摇晃晃朝食品架子那儿走过去，未等他们反应过来，就已经把牙齿咬进了一块生腌肉里。马拉摩特·基德想夺下那块肉，于是二人进行了一场激烈的争斗。后来，陌生人的疯劲倏然消失了，真是来得快，去得也快。他有气无力地交出了那块生腌肉。基德和普林斯把他架到一张凳子上——他坐在那里，半个身子趴在桌子上。一小杯威士忌落肚，他有了些精神。马拉摩特·基德把糖罐拿来，由着他用勺子舀着吃。待他的胃里有了点东西，普林斯哆嗦着手，端给他一杯淡牛肉茶。

那家伙的眼睛里闪射出一种阴沉、疯狂的光，一明一暗的，每喝一口茶就会随之一闪。他的脸瘦得皮包骨头，脸颊深陷，简直没有了人形。无尽的霜冻给他的脸留下了刀刻一般的痕印，旧伤未好又添新疤。又干又硬的皮肤透着血黑色，几条深深的锯齿形裂痕中露出红的血肉。他的毛皮衣又脏又破，一边的毛已经烧焦，有几处烧出了缺口——显然是他曾挨着火睡觉才导致了这样的后果。

马拉摩特·基德望着他那被太阳晒黑了的毛皮衣服，用手指了指他衣服上被用刀子割成一条条的地方（这是饥饿留下的可怕标志(14)），一字一顿、清清楚楚地问道：“你是何人？”

那人充耳不闻，并未搭理。

“你是从哪儿来的？”

“美国佬的船，顺流而下。”他声音颤抖地唱了一句，算是答复。

“毫无疑问，这个叫花子一定是从河的上游过来的。”基德对普林斯说道，同时扳着来客的身子把他晃了晃，想让他回答得明白些。

谁知这一晃，那人竟尖叫起来，用手捂住腰，显然那里很痛。接着，他慢慢站了起来，身子半倚在桌上。

“她嘲笑我……是这样的……她的眼睛里充满了仇恨……她硬是不肯来……”

他说着说着便没有了声，身子向后倒去，马拉摩特·基德一把抓住他的手腕，大着嗓门问道：“你在说什么人？谁硬是不肯来？”

“我说的是她——乌恩卡。她嘲笑我，打我，情况就是这样。后来……”

“后来怎么啦？”

“后来……”

“后来到底怎么啦？”

“后来他就一动不动躺在雪地里，躺了很长时间，现在还躺在那儿。”

马拉摩特·基德和普林斯面面相觑，简直听不明白。

“到底是谁躺在雪地里呀？”

“是她——乌恩卡。她看着我，眼睛里充满了仇恨。后来……”

“说呀，说呀！”

“后来她拿起刀子刺来……一下，两下……可是她已经虚弱得没有了力气。路上我走得非常慢。那儿遍地黄金，简直多极了。”

“乌恩卡现在在何处？”马拉摩特·基德总算听出了些名堂，猜想那个女子可能就躺在一英里以外的某个地方。他狠劲摇晃来客，一遍又一遍地问：“乌恩卡现在在何处？乌恩卡是谁？”

“她在……在……在雪地里。”

“往下说！”基德狠狠地握紧对方的手腕说。

“我……我原本……原本也想躺在雪地里。可是，我有一笔债……有一笔债要还。我有一笔债……有一笔债要还。我必须……”来客语无伦次，断断续续说到这里，把手伸进旅行袋里，摸出一个鹿皮口袋，“这里是五……五磅金子……是还给……还给马拉摩……马拉摩特·基德的债款。”话刚说完，他就一头栽倒在桌子上，马拉摩特·基德再怎么扶也扶不起来了。

“他是尤利西斯，”马拉摩特·基德把那袋金子扔到桌子上，平静地说，“看来，阿克塞尔·冈德森和那个女人凶多吉少。来，咱们把他抬到床上，给他盖上毯子暖暖。他是印第安人，缓一缓就没事了，那时再让他把来龙去脉讲清楚。”

他们把他身上的衣服割下来，发现他胸口的右侧有两处没有愈合的刀伤，伤口已经结痂了。

3

“我将照我自己的方式讲述这一切，但你们会明白的。我将从头说起，先说说我和那个女人，然后再说那个男人吧。”

这个曾用海獭皮换狗的人向火炉靠近了一点，就像是一个被剥夺了烤火权利的人一样，生怕普罗米修斯(15)的这份礼物会随时消失。马拉摩特·基德挑亮油灯，把它挪了个位置，让灯光可以照在讲述人的脸上。普林斯也把身体从床边挪过来，凑近倾听。

“我叫纳斯，是个酋长，父亲也是酋长。我是在日落以后，日出之前，在黑沉沉的大海上，在我父亲的皮舟上出生的。那天夜里，男人奋力划桨，女人们则把冲进舟里的海水舀出去，大家拼全力和暴风雨搏斗。海水溅在我母亲的胸口上结成了冰，待风浪退去，她的呼吸也随之停止了。而我……在大风大浪里啼哭不止，然而却活了下来。

“我们的居住地是阿卡坦……”

“那是个什么地方？”马拉摩特·基德问道。

“阿卡坦属于阿留申群岛。那个地方比契格尼克岛、卡尔达拉克岛以及乌尼马克岛都要远。我们居住的那个地方处于茫茫的大海之中，简直就是世界的边缘。我们在海上捕鱼，捉海豹和海獭。我们的住房建在森林与沙滩之间的一座条状石山上，一家一家挨在一起，黄黄的沙滩上停放着我们的皮舟。我们的人数不多，活动的范围极其狭小。我们东面有几座陌生的岛——都跟阿卡坦一样。因此，我们就以为全世界到处都是岛屿，并对此不以为意。

“我跟族里的人有所不同。有一天，一条船被冲上了沙滩，只剩了几根弯曲的船骨和几块被海浪冲翘了的船板——我族里的人从来也没造过这样的船；山顶上有一棵松树，那棵树直直的，挺拔、高大，从那儿的三个方向都可以瞭望大海，我记得这棵树也是岛上从前没有的。据说，有两个陌生人在那里转悠来转悠去，从白天到黑夜，许多天徘徊不去。这两人乘船而来，他们的船被浪打翻，残骸被冲到了沙滩上。他们跟你们一样是白人，当时身体虚弱，就像空手而归的海豹猎手家饿扁了肚子的小孩。这些事情我是听一些老头老太太们讲的，而他们也是从父辈那儿听来的。起初，那两个白人不习惯我们的生活方式，但他们吃了我们的鱼和鱼油后，身体变得强壮了起来，而且十分凶猛。他们各自盖了房，挑漂亮的女人为妻，并生了孩子，其中一个孩子就是我的曾祖父。

“我刚才说过，我跟族里的人有所不同，因为我身上流淌着那个乘船而来的强壮而奇异的白种人的血液。据说那两个白人来之前，我们族里有自己的规矩，可他们性情暴烈，喜欢寻衅滋事，老是跟族里的人打架，最后谁也不敢招惹他们了。于是，他们就自封为酋长，取消了我们的老规矩，并且给我们定下了新规矩，将我们以前以母亲为家主的规矩改成了以父亲为家主。他们还规定：头生的儿子有权继承父亲的一切，他的弟弟和姐妹都得自谋生计。除此之外，还有一些别的规矩也是他们定的。他们教给我们捕鱼和猎熊的新方法（那时森林里熊满为患）；他们还教我们多多储备食物，以防荒年的到来。这些都是好事。

“可是，当他们当上酋长，再也没有人敢惹怒他们后，这两个怪异的白人彼此打了起来。其中的一个，也就是我身上流着他的血的那个人，把刺海豹的鱼叉扎进了另一个白人的身体，扎进去有一胳膊那么深。双方的子女继承了这场仇杀，深仇大恨子孙相传，两家之间常常制造流血事件，甚至到了我这一代仍旧怨恨难释，以致两家各自都只剩下了一根独苗传宗接代。我们家族只剩了我一个人，对方家族只剩下了一个独生女，那就是乌恩卡。她和她的母亲在一起生活。一天夜里，她的父亲和我的父亲出海捕鱼，再也没有回来。后来，他们的尸体被大潮冲上了沙滩，二人至死还紧紧扭打在一起。

“人们见我们两家宿怨太深，都嗟叹不已。老人们直摇头，说乌恩卡的子孙后代和我的子嗣还将继续仇杀。我小的时候听他们这么说，后来竟笃信不疑，将乌恩卡视为仇敌，深信她的孩子会和我的子女进行厮杀。此事我天天都在想，百思不得其解，长大后询问为何会出现这种情况，老人们的回答是：‘我们也不清楚，反正你们的父辈就是这个样。’我不明白为什么前人已逝，后人还要继承旧怨，觉得这样做没有道理。但既然老人们这么说，我一个年轻人也无可奈何。

“他们说我得赶快结婚生子，这样我的孩子就会比乌恩卡的子女先长大，先养成气力。结婚并非难事，因为我是酋长。我的父辈功绩卓著并且为族里的人定下了规矩，所以我是受到敬重的。再说，我有很多财富，无论哪个女孩都愿意嫁给我，只是没有一个合我的意。老人们和一些女孩的母亲都催我赶快结婚，因为那时已有好几个猎手对乌恩卡的母亲许下了很高的彩礼，向乌恩卡求婚呢。万一乌恩卡的孩子先长大，我的孩子肯定会死于非命。

“就这样，我一直没有找到合意的女孩，直到某天的黄昏时分，我捕鱼归来，太阳西沉，夕阳满目，微风习习，几只皮舟疾驰在白浪之间。突然，乌恩卡的皮舟从我身旁掠过。她看了我一眼。但见她乌云一般的黑发随风飘扬，湿漉漉的脸蛋沾着水珠子。我刚才说过，我当时只看到一片落日的余晖，再加上自己又是个血气方刚的青年，难免会看花眼。但不管怎么说吧，我当时觉得这是命中注定的缘分。她催舟向前，划了几桨之后又回头看了看——只有乌恩卡那样的女子才会有如此迷人的回眸。我又一次感觉到这就是缘分。我俩你追我赶，从那些慢悠悠的大皮船旁边飞驰而过，人们纷纷为我们喝彩。后来，我们把那些船远远甩在了后边。她飞快地划着皮舟，虽然我的心像一片满帆，却没能追上她。风力加大，白浪翻涌，我们的船像海豹一样在波涛上飞驰，沿着夕阳铺就的金色航道一直向前。”

讲述到此处，纳斯弯下腰，屁股半离开凳子，摆出划桨的姿势，仿佛又回到了当年赛皮舟的那一刻，透过炉火，他仿佛又看见那飞驰的皮舟和乌恩卡那随风飘扬的黑发。呼呼的海风犹在耳畔，鼻孔里腥咸的海水味弥漫开来。

“可她一到岸就跑上沙滩，咯咯笑着，回了她母亲的房屋。那天晚上，我产生了一个惊人的想法，一个无愧于阿卡坦酋长之位的想法。于是，月亮升起时，我去了她母亲的房屋，见门外堆放着雅什·努什的彩礼。雅什·努什是个身强力壮的猎手，一心想跟乌恩卡结婚生子。曾经也有别的小伙子把自己的彩礼搬来堆放在那儿，后来都知趣地撤走了。那些小伙子拿来的彩礼一个比一个多，后者必定超过前者。

“当时我冲着满天的星月大笑几声，然后回到我自己储存财产的屋子里搬东西，一连搬了许多趟，直至我的彩礼比雅什·努什的那堆高出一扎(16)才住手。我的彩礼包括：晒干后烟熏过的鱼；四十张海豹皮和二十张兽皮，而且每张皮都扎了口，里面装满了鱼油；另外还有十张熊皮，那是春天它们出来觅食时我在森林里猎到的。我的彩礼中还有珠子项链、毯子和红布，是我跟东方客用东西交换来的，而那些东方客则是和更东边的人做贸易换来的。我看了看雅什·努什的那堆彩礼，不由得大笑起来。我身为阿卡坦的酋长，财富比部落里任何一个年轻人都要雄厚。再说，我的父辈曾经立下了丰功伟绩，并为部落制定规矩，其大名被族人口口相传。

“就这样，第二天早晨我到海滩上，用眼角的余光偷偷向乌恩卡母亲的房屋那儿瞥了一眼，发现我的彩礼原封未动放在那儿。女人们面带微笑地窃窃私语着。我感到纳闷，觉得自己的彩礼应该是多得史无前例的呀。当天夜里，我又加了一些进去，还在彩礼堆的旁边放了一条从未下过海的、用硝得非常好的毛皮制作的皮舟。然而，那些东西次日仍堆放在那里，成了人们的笑料。乌恩卡的母亲是个狡诈的女人，而在族人面前丢人现眼，备受侮辱，最终使我恼羞成怒。夜里，我又拿了一些东西过去，使那堆彩礼变成了小山。这还不算，我还把我的大皮船也拖了去，那只船论价值抵得上二十条皮舟。次日清晨，那堆彩礼不见了踪影。

“接下来，我就开始准备结婚了。为了宴会上的美食和发放的礼品，连住在东边的居民也来了。乌恩卡比我大四个太阳（按我们的算法，一个‘太阳’就是一年）。比较起来，我只是个小弟弟。但我是酋长，又是酋长的儿子，所以年龄不成问题。

“但就在这时，一艘双桅帆船在海面上露出帆来——随着一阵阵风刮来，那船帆越来越近、越来越大。船上忙作一团，人们在用抽水机把船舱里的水朝外抽，但见一股股清水从排水口流出来。船头站着一个身材魁梧的男人，一边查看着水深，一边发号施令，声若滚雷。他的眼睛呈淡蓝色，似深深的海水，头发像海狮的鬃毛，颜色黄似南方人收割的稻草，又似水手用来编绳子的马尼拉黄麻。

“那几年倒是常见有轮船从远方来，但靠到阿卡坦岸边的却是第一艘。婚宴一时中断，妇女和孩子们躲进了家中，我们这些男人张弓搭箭，拿起长矛准备迎战。不过，等到船头触到了沙滩，那些陌生人却只顾忙着他们自己的事，并不理会我们。待海潮一退，他们就将轮船放倒，着手修补船底的一个大窟窿。女人们又悄悄回到宴席上，宴会继续进行。

“涨潮的时候，那些海上浪人把船拖到了深水区，然后来见我们。他们拿着礼物，显得很友好。我请他们入席，就像对待所有来宾一样诚心欢迎他们，赠给他们礼物，因为这毕竟是我结婚的日子，而我又是阿卡坦的酋长。那个头发像海狮鬃毛的男人也在那些人中间，他人高马大、力大无穷，走起路来似乎连地面都发颤。他眼睛望着乌恩卡，死死盯住她不放，两条胳膊抱在胸前，久久不肯离去，一直待到太阳落山、星星出来，才回到了他的船上去。他走后，我牵起乌恩卡的手，把她领到我家里。大伙儿在那里载歌载舞，一片欢声笑语，女人们对我们说着那些遇到这种场合必说的意味深长的话，不过我们却没有往心里去。最后，大家尽欢而散，纷纷告别，只剩下了我们俩。

“欢庆的余音尚未散尽，那个海上浪人的头目走进了我的家门。他带来了几个黑瓶子，于是我们喝着瓶子中的液体，寻欢作乐。要知道，当时我只是个年轻人，又生活在一个与世隔绝的地方。于是，我浑身的血像火一样燃烧起来，一颗心轻飘飘的，宛若海浪的泡沫，轻得能飞到悬崖上去。乌恩卡一声不响地坐在角落里的一堆兽皮上，眼睛睁得大大的，好像有点害怕。那个头发像海狮鬃毛的男子直愣愣地看着她，看了很长时间。后来，他手下的人送来了一捆一捆的东西，堆在我面前。那些东西阿卡坦的人见都没有见过，其中有长短枪支、火药、子弹、亮晃晃的斧头、钢刀和灵巧的工具，还有一些我闻所未闻的稀奇古怪的玩意儿。他做了个手势，表示那些东西都是我的了。我觉得他如此慷慨，真是个了不起的人。可谁知他又做了个手势，表示要把乌恩卡领走，带到他的船上去。你们听明白了吗？他要把乌恩卡领走，带到他的船上去。祖辈的那腔英雄热血顿时涌遍了我的全身，我操起长矛，准备把他戳个透心凉。可是，酒瓶里的那些东西偷走了我的力气，他揪住我的脖领，把我的头往墙上猛撞。我只觉得自己软绵绵的，像个刚出生的婴儿，两腿撑不住身子。乌恩卡被拖向门口时，尖声大叫，用手乱抓房里的东西，结果弄得那些东西散落了一地。后来，那个头目伸出粗壮的胳膊将她抱起，她就用手扯他的黄头发，惹得他哈哈大笑，那笑声就像是一只巨大的雄海豹发情时的叫声。

“我爬上滩头，呼喊族人出来营救，可是他们吓得不敢出来。只有雅什·努什是个男子汉，挺身而出，却被那些人用船桨打在头上，打得他趴在沙滩上，动也动不了了。后来，那些家伙唱着得胜歌升起船帆，乘风而去。

“人们说这样也好，因为从今往后再也没有族人之间的流血仇杀了。而我一句话也没说，耐心等到月圆之时，在皮舟上装了一些干鱼和鱼油当干粮，只身去了东方。途中，我见到了很多岛屿和很多人。一直偏居一隅的我此时才发现世界竟是那么大。我比手势和人们交谈，但他们说没见过那艘船以及那个头发像海狮鬃毛的人。他们让我再朝东找找看。那一路，我夜宿古怪的地方，吃稀奇的食物，接触陌生的面孔。很多人都笑我，觉得我脑子不正常。有时遇见一些老年人，他们就叫我面朝阳光，衷心为我祝福；年轻女子听我讲述那艘怪异的船和那些海上浪人带走了乌恩卡时，眼圈都会湿润起来。

“就这样，我穿越波涛汹涌的大海，挺过了狂风暴雨，抵达了乌纳拉斯卡。那儿倒是有两艘双桅帆船，不过都不是我要找的那艘。于是，我就继续往东走，越发觉得世界广阔。我到了乌纳莫克岛、科迪亚克岛以及阿托格纳克岛，但在那些地方也都没有打听到那艘船的下落。一天，我到了一个到处是岩石的地方，看见一些人在山上挖大洞。岸边停放着一艘双桅帆船，但不是我要找的那艘。那些人正把挖出来的石头装上船。我觉得他们荒唐可笑，因为世界上到处都有石头，没必要来这儿挖。他们给我食物吃，叫我为他们干活。等到船吃水深了，船长给了我些工钱打发我走。我问他要到哪儿去，他用手指了指南面。我做了个手势示意想跟他走，起初他只是付之一笑，后来觉得船上缺人，也就让我上船当了帮手。在船上，我学着说他们的话，帮他们拉锚索，突遇狂风时则帮着收帆，还和他们一道轮班掌舵。不过这也不足为奇，因为我的祖先和这些航海人本来就属于同一血统。

“我当时心想，要找那个头发像海狮鬃毛的人并不难，只要跟他的白人族群打成一片就不难发现他的下落。一天，我们望到了陆地，便驾船穿过海峡，到了一个港口。我原以为那儿停泊的船也只不过有我的手指头那么多，谁知码头上的船竟连绵数英里，密密麻麻如鱼群般排列在一起。我上船打听那个头发像海狮鬃毛的人，人们都只是打个哈哈，回答时操着各方语言。我发现他们来自四面八方、天涯海角。

“后来我走进了那座城市，逢人便看他们的脸。可是那里的人太多了，多得就像岸边密密匝匝的鳕鱼，数也数不清。城市的喧嚣声吵得我简直受不了，眼前的车水马龙看得我头晕眼花。我继续前行，走啊走，穿过歌声荡漾、阳光和煦的大地，走过庄稼丰饶的平原，步入一座座大城市，发现城里到处是过着女人那种生活的男人，到处是满口假话，因贪图黄金而发黑的心肠。而在阿卡坦，我的族人还在狩猎和捕鱼，他们并不知道世界之大，过得心满意足。

“始终让我忘不了的是乌恩卡捕鱼归来时看我的那种目光。我坚信，到了某个时候我一定会找到她。在家乡，当她在朦胧的暮色里行走在寂静的小径上，当她引得我追逐她，穿过沾满晨露的田野时，她的眼神是那样迷人——只有乌恩卡才会有那样的眼神。

“我一路流浪，经过了上千个城市。有的人心肠好，给我东西吃，有的则取笑我，还有的出口骂我。但我都咬紧牙关默默坚持着，去了许多奇怪的地方，见了许多奇怪的景象。有时候，我，一个酋长，又是酋长之子，还要放下身段为人打工糊口——那些雇主说话粗声粗气，一个个铁石心肠，只知道敛财聚富，全不顾别人的劳苦和忧伤。至于要找的那个人，我却一点消息也没有打听到。后来，我又回到了海边，就像海豹回到了自己的栖息地。那是一个港口，位于北方的一个国家。在那里，我总算打听到了那个黄发海上浪人的一星半点的消息，方才知道他原来是个海豹猎手，知道他正在海上寻找猎物。

“于是，我就跟几个懒惰的西瓦希人(17)一起乘上一只猎海豹的船，朝着北方漫无目的地寻找。当时，正值猎海豹的旺季。我们累死累活，找了好几个月，见了许多船只，听了许多有关他胡作非为的传闻，但始终未在海上看到他的影踪。我们一路向北，甚至到了普里比洛夫群岛(18)，在那儿的沙滩上猎杀了成群的海豹，然后把它们仍温热的尸体搬上船，海豹身体流出的血和油从排水口直朝外淌，弄得甲板上都无法站人了。一艘速度很慢的蒸汽船追了过来，用大炮向我们开火。而我们扯起满帆破浪而去，隐身于茫茫大雾中。海浪冲上甲板，把甲板上的血污冲洗了个干净。

“如我所说，就在我们被吓得魂飞魄散、狼狈逃窜之时，那个黄头发的海上浪人登上了普里比洛夫群岛。他到了那儿的加工厂，叫他的几个喽啰扣住厂里的工人，并命令其余的人从仓库里搬出一万张生皮装上他的船。这虽然只是传闻，但我相信是真的。我沿岸航行，虽没有遇见过他，但北边的海上却广有他的传闻，说他无法无天、胆大妄为，那儿有三个国家都派船在搜捕他。我还听到了一些关于乌恩卡的传闻，船老大们说起她都赞不绝口。她一直跟着那家伙，据说已经习惯了他的生活方式，日子过得很快活。但我却不以为然，深知她一定惦念着自己的同胞，向往着阿卡坦那黄色的沙滩。

“后来，我掉头返回，经过很长时间的航行，又回到了海峡旁的那个港口。到了那里，我听说他已经横渡大洋，前往温暖的东部，到俄罗斯海域以南去捕猎海豹了。此时，我已经成了一个真正的水手，跟他那一族的人同船航行，沿着他的踪迹前去捕猎海豹。在那片新的水域，船只很少，而我们整整一个春天都跟在海豹群后边紧追不舍，将它们赶向北方。途中，母海豹纷纷怀孕，拖着笨重的身子游入了俄罗斯海域，船员们怨声载道，心生畏惧。那一片浓雾重重，每天去捕杀海豹的船只上都有人员失踪。船员们拒绝再出去作业，船长只好命令原路返回。而我心里有数，知道那个黄发海上浪人绝不会知难而退，一定会紧追海豹群，哪怕一直追到少有人敢涉足的俄罗斯群岛。于是，趁着夜里天黑，当瞭望哨在船头甲板上打盹的时候，我偷走一条小船，独自一人朝着那个温暖而狭长的海岸划去。我一直向南划，在江户湾(19)遇到了一些水手，他们狂放不羁、无所畏惧。吉原(20)的姑娘小巧玲珑、肤如凝脂，个个都很漂亮。可是我不能停留，因为我知道乌恩卡正漂泊于北方海豹栖息地那波涛汹涌的海上。

“在江户湾遇到的那些人来自世界各地，不信鬼神，以四海为家，船上挂着日本国的旗帜。我随着他们一起去富饶的铜岛海岸捕杀海豹，盐舱里的海豹皮堆得像小山一样。那片水域静悄悄的，临离开时也没见着一个人影。后来，有一天，一阵狂风吹散了大雾，一艘双桅帆船急急地向我们驶来，它后面有一艘烟囱里冒着浓烟的俄国战舰紧追不舍。我们借助风势飞速逃离，双桅帆船跟在我们屁股后面，离我们越来越近——我们每前进两英尺，它就能追过来三英尺。双桅帆船的船尾站着一个人，正是那个头发像海狮鬃毛的家伙。他手扶操纵杆，操纵着风帆，哈哈哈地放声大笑。乌恩卡在他的身旁——我一眼就认出了她。俄国战舰的炮弹掠过海面飞来时，那家伙把乌恩卡送进了船舱。正如我刚才所言，他们的船速比我们的快，随着海水的起伏，我们看见了双桅帆船那绿颜色的舵。我背对俄国人的炮火，冲向舵盘驾船疾行，心里咒骂着那个头发像海狮鬃毛的家伙。我们都清楚他在打什么鬼主意——他想把我们甩到后面，让我们成为挡箭牌，而他则可以逃之夭夭。我们的桅杆被炮弹击中，使得我们的船像受伤的海鸥一样在风中挣扎；他却带着乌恩卡溜之大吉，消失在了海天交接之处。

“我们有什么办法呢？新剥下的海豹皮本身就很能说明问题了。于是，我们被押送到一个俄国港口，后来又到了一个荒凉的地方，被逼着在矿山挖盐。有些人累死了，有的活了下来。”

纳斯说着，一把掀开肩膀上的毯子，露出疙疙瘩瘩的肉，那分明是鞭子抽打后留下的一道道伤痕。普林斯连忙替他盖好，因为那样子实在惨不忍睹。

“我们在那儿熬了很久，有时也有人逃向南方，但每一次都会被抓回来。因此，等到我们这些从江户湾来的人一天夜里暴动，夺下警卫队的枪逃跑时，我们就向北逃去。北方的土地非常辽阔，有潮湿的平原，还有茫茫的大森林。正值寒冷的季节，地上雪积得很厚，我们没有一个人认得路。在无边无际的森林里，我们一连跋涉了几个月，累得要死。当时是怎么熬过来的，我都记不清了，只记得那时没有东西吃，常常躺着等死。最后，我们总算走到了海边，那儿是一片冰天雪地。此时，我们一行只剩下了三个人，其中一个就是江户来的船长。这位船长熟悉那片辽阔土地的情况，知道何处海面上结冰，可以从冰上走到对岸。于是他就领着我们向那儿走，不知走了有多久，反正路途非常遥远，远到最后只剩下我们俩了。到了那个地方，我们遇到了五个陌生人，他们是当地的土著人，身边有许多雪橇狗，雪橇上还有很多兽皮。但我们却穷得一无所有，于是就想打劫他们。在雪地里经过一场混战，那几个陌生人和船长都死了，狗和兽皮都归了我。接下来，我就踏上了布满裂缝的冰面，站在一块浮冰上漂游，后来从西边起了一阵狂风，才把我刮到了岸边。上岸之后，我去了戈洛文湾和帕斯蒂里克，后来遇到了那个神父。再接下来，我一路向南走，回到了我最初去过的那片阳光普照的温暖地带。

“不过，那儿的海产并不丰富，出海捕猎海豹利润小，风险大。捕猎的船队散了摊，我向船长和船员们打听乌恩卡他们的下落，却无人知晓。于是，我离开奔涌不息的大海去了内陆，所到之处，见到的全是静止不动的树木、房屋和大山。我走了很远的路，学到了很多的东西，甚至学会了读书写字。我觉得这是必需的，因为我心想乌恩卡一定也掌握了这些本事，一旦我们重逢……一旦我们重逢……

“我就是这样流浪四方，犹如一只没有舵盘的帆船，随着风向漂泊。不过，我始终在睁大眼睛看，竖起耳朵听，遇到游历广的人便打听，因为我知道，他们要是见过我找的那两个人，一定会记得的。后来，我碰到一个刚从山里出来的人，他有几块矿石，那里面嵌着许多跟豆子一样大的金粒。此人不仅仅听说过他们，还见过他们，并且很了解他们。他说那俩人发了财，就住在他们挖掘金子的那个地方。

“那地方很荒凉，非常遥远。我找到他们的大本营时，发现那儿隐于大山深处，工人在洞里挖金子日夜不息，终年不见阳光。不过我去得不凑巧，听人说他们不在本地，而是去了英国。据说，他们去招商引资，准备成立公司。我去看了看他们住的房子，觉得他们的房子就像人们在远古国度所会见到的那种宫殿。夜里，我从一扇窗户偷偷爬了进去，想瞧瞧他让乌恩卡过的是什么样的日子。我挨个房间查看，觉得他们的生活十分优越，不次于王公贵族。工人们说他对待乌恩卡就像对待王后一样。许多人都感到奇怪，不知她究竟属于哪个民族，因为她带着外来的血统，跟阿卡坦的女人不一样。至于她的身世，无人知晓。话又说回来，就算她贵如王后，我可是酋长呢，还是酋长之子，我送给她的兽皮、皮船和珍珠可是价值连城呢。

“不过，话也不多说了。我毕竟是个水手，精通海上航行那一套，于是我便跟踪到了英国，后来又跟到了别的几个国家。有时，我从人们的口中了解到他们的下落，有时则从报上看到他们的消息，却一次也没有见过他们的面。他们有的是钱，路上走得快，而我一贫如洗，当然追不上。后来，他们遇到麻烦，财富荡然一空，就像一缕轻烟随风飘走了。当时，报纸连篇累牍报道此事。事情过后，却再无人提起。我心里清楚：他们一定又回去干老行当，又去采矿挖金了。

“他们成了穷光蛋，从世人的眼里消失了。我寻找他们，从一个营地寻到另一个营地，甚至一直向北到了库特尼地区。在那个地区，我获得了一条已经过时的线索。他们来过，但已经走了，有人说走的是这个方向，有的说是那个，还有人说他们去了育空河一带。我这里找找，那里找找，辗转各地，最后弄得我都厌倦了，觉得这个世界简直太大了。一次，我和一个西北的土著人走在库特尼地区，路途艰难遥远。他饿得走不动了，觉得还不如死了好。他曾经去过育空地区，翻山越岭，走的是一条没人走过的小路。此时，他知道自己死期已至，便把身上的一张地图给了我，并告诉了我一个秘密的地方，对天发誓那儿有许多黄金。

“当时，寻金的人潮滚滚涌向北方。我身无分文，只好受雇于人，为别人驭狗。其余的情况你都知道了。在道森，我遇见了他们俩。乌恩卡没有认出我，因为她走时我还只是个年轻人，后来她的生活又是那么丰富多彩，已无暇忆及这个曾为她付了高昂彩礼的人。

“记得吗？你出钱帮我摆脱了那趟苦役的束缚。我掉头回去准备以我的方式解决过去的一切——这一时刻我等待已久，如今找到了他们，万不可因操之过急而误事。正如我刚才所言，一定要以我的方式解决问题。回想起自己的这一段人生经历，回想起途中目睹的灾难和亲身经受的折磨，回想起在俄国海边那茫茫无际的森林里受冻挨饿的情景，我气愤难平。后来的情况你也知道——我领着他和乌恩卡去东方寻宝，那儿去的人多，回来的却少。我领着他们去了一个地方，那儿满是累累白骨和人们的诅咒，还有那谁也无法带得走的黄金。

“那一趟，道路漫长，雪深难行。我们的狗很多，它们吃得也多，而我们的雪橇不可能将开春之前所需的东西都带上——我们必须在河流化冻之前赶回来。于是我们把干粮贮藏在沿途的各个地方，一是为了减轻雪橇的负担，二是为了让我们返回时不至于饿肚子。到了麦克奎森，那儿的营地里有三个人，我们就在营地跟前挖了个粮窖，到梅奥后又挖了一个——梅奥有一个狩猎人营地，住着十来个佩利人(21)，他们是从南边越过边界来打猎的。之后，我们一路向东，再也看不见人迹了，能看见的只有沉睡的河流、静寂的森林和无声无息的北国雪野。我刚才说过，那一趟道路漫长、雪深难行。有时候，苦苦走一天也走不了八英里或十英里的路，夜里累得倒头便睡，像死猪一样。他们做梦也没有想到我是纳斯——阿卡坦的酋长，一个一心要报仇雪恨的人。

“这时候，我们挖的贮藏干粮的粮窖比以前的要小。夜里，我沿着走过的路悄悄回去把干粮换个地方贮藏，看上去会让人以为干粮被狼獾偷吃了。此事干得神不知鬼不觉。有些地方十分危险，不小心就会掉入河中，那儿水流湍急，河面上结着浮冰，底下却暗流涌动。就是在这样一个地方，我赶的雪橇和狗一起栽了下去。他和乌恩卡自认倒霉，但什么也没说。栽下去的那辆雪橇上装着很多干粮，拉雪橇的狗也是最强壮的。可他只是满不在乎地哈哈一笑，因为他是一个不畏艰险的强者。干粮少了，他就给狗喂得很少，后来索性把狗一条条解下套，宰杀后再喂给它们的同伴吃。他说回家时这样反倒好，落个一身轻，沿途从粮窖取干粮吃，用不着狗和雪橇了。当时要说用不着狗和雪橇倒是真的，因为我们的干粮已少得可怜。待我们走到了那个满是累累白骨和诅咒的黄金地时，当天夜里最后一条狗也死在了挽具里。

“那张地图标的位置很正确，我们到达了那个地方，那儿地处群山的中心，必须在一座冰封的分水岭峭壁上凿出阶梯攀上山巅。站在山顶四下望去，但见皑皑白雪填平了所有的沟壑，平展得就像一派丰收景象的辽阔的平原。周围群山巍峨，冰雪覆盖的山头直插云天，与星辰做伴。在那一片古怪的雪原当中，有一处地方按说是座山谷，却见那儿白雪皑皑，覆着雪的地面猛地向下沉去，像是要沉到地球的心脏部位。我们要是没有做过水手的话，看到这种光景，一定会头晕目眩的。当时，我们站在令人发晕的峭壁边缘，想找一条下去的路。脚下的峭壁有一面（也只有这一面）是倾斜的，倾斜得就跟飓风袭来时的甲板一样。不知道那是怎么形成的，但情况的确如此。只听他说：‘这是地狱之门。走吧，咱们下去吧。’于是，我们就走下去了。

“在斜坡底部有一座小木屋，为前人所建，用的是从崖顶抛下来的木头，年代已非常久远。不同时期都有人丧命于此，成了孤魂野鬼。屋里有一些桦树皮，上面刻着他们的遗言以及诅咒。我们看后得知：一个死于坏血病；一个是由于合伙人偷走了他仅有的一点干粮和弹药悄悄溜走，导致他最后被饿死了；一个是因为遭到一只脸上有白斑的灰熊攻击，伤重而亡；一个是因为没有打到猎物，活活饿死的……还有一些其他情况，反正都是因为贪恋黄金，最后死在了黄金的旁边，只不过各有各的死法罢了。他们辛苦得来的黄金成了无用之物，黄澄澄散落一地，令人觉得如在梦中。

“不过，我远途领来的这家伙却不糊涂，大脑很清楚。只听他说：‘咱们干粮已尽，现在要做的只是看一眼这黄金，弄清它是从哪儿得来的，究竟有多少，然后赶快离开，免得让黄金迷住心窍，乱了咱们的方寸。咱们以后还会回来的，那时多带点干粮，再将黄金全部据为咱们的财产。’接下来，我们查看了黄金矿的矿脉，发现它跟人的脉络一样直透崖壁。我们进行了测量，然后从上到下画出轮廓，打下几根木桩，又在树上刻了字，标示明白此处是我们的财产。那时，我们肚子里空空如也，饿得双腿发抖，肚子也很难受，心也扑通扑通地快要跳出来了。最后，我们爬上那道高耸的崖壁，踏上了归途。

“在最后的一段路上，我们俩一左一右架着乌恩卡走，一不小心就栽跟头，最终总算挣扎到了那个粮窖，可是那儿空空如也。我转移干粮的那件事干得很巧妙，他觉得是狼獾偷走的，于是便破口大骂狼獾，还骂上帝不保佑他。乌恩卡却表现得很勇敢，只是笑了笑，把自己的手放进了他的大手里。我急忙将脸转开，努力克制住情绪。‘咱们不妨生堆火休息休息，明天早晨再说。可以把鹿皮鞋当干粮吃，积攒些气力。’乌恩卡这样说道。说干就干，我们把鹿皮鞋的统子切成一条一条的，煮了半夜，煮软了才能嚼碎下咽。第二天早晨，我们商量了一下我们的处境。走到下一个粮窖得走五天的路，那是我们力所不及的，当务之急是打点猎物果腹。

“‘走，咱们打猎去。’他说。

“‘好的，’我说，‘咱们打猎去。’

“他吩咐乌恩卡留在火堆旁保存体力，而我们俩出发打猎去了。趁着他去寻找鹿迹的当儿，我摸到了我偷换的那个贮藏干粮的地方。我只吃了一点干粮，免得叫他们见我长了气力而看出破绽。晚上在回营地的路上，他饿得老摔跟头。我也装出十分衰弱的样子，踉踉跄跄的，常被雪鞋绊倒，每走一步仿佛都要栽倒，再也爬不起来似的。后来我们把鹿皮鞋吃了，添了点力气。

“他真是个了不起的人，有一股精神始终支撑着他，至死不渝，除非为了乌恩卡，否则有泪决不轻弹。第二天，我跟着他去打猎，为的是看看他最后的结局。他走几步就要躺倒休息一下，到了晚上已气息奄奄。然而次日早晨他有气无力地骂了声娘，又咬紧牙继续前行了。他走路东倒西歪像个醉汉，有好几次我都以为他要完蛋了，可他是一个极为坚强的人，有着打不垮的铁人精神，硬是硬撑着挺过了整整一天。他打到了两只松鸡，却舍不得吃。按说，松鸡不必用火烤，是可以生吃的，吃了就能活命，可他心里只想着乌恩卡，只顾挣扎着向宿营地赶。后来，他实在走不动了，只能手脚并用地在雪地上爬。我走到他跟前，从他的眼里看出他的生命即将结束。即便到了这个时候也不算太晚，只要吃了松鸡就可以挽救他的性命。可他不肯吃，而是丢掉猎枪，像狗一样用嘴叼着松鸡爬行。我走在他身旁，腰杆挺得直直的。他停下来休息时会不解地看我一眼，不明白我怎么会这样结实。此时，我看得出他已说不出话来了，只见他嘴唇张合，却听不到声音从嘴里出来。说实在的，他真是一个了不起的人，我的心都有些软了。然而，我想到了自己在俄国海边那茫茫无际的森林里受冻挨饿的情景，想起了乌恩卡本是我的妻子，我为她付出了兽皮、皮船和珍珠这般高昂的彩礼。

“我们就这样穿过了白雪皑皑的森林，犹如湿漉漉的海雾般的寂静沉甸甸地压在我们身上。过去的生活犹如幻影悬浮在眼前，在周围晃动。我仿佛看见了阿卡坦那黄色的海滩，看见了捕鱼归来的飞驰的皮舟，看见了坐落于森林边的一栋栋房屋，还仿佛看见了那两个自封为酋长的人——一个是我的祖先，另一个是我妻子乌恩卡的祖先，正是他们给族人立下了种种规矩。此外，我仿佛还看到了雅什·努什走在我的身旁，头发里粘着湿湿的沙粒，他被打倒时折断了的长矛仍握在手中。我知道，那个时刻来临了，我看见了乌恩卡期许的眼神。

“正如我所言，我们就那样穿过了茫茫林海，直至嗅到了宿营地的烟火味。我弯下腰，将松鸡从他的嘴里夺了下来。他侧身躺着喘气，眼睛里涌出诧异的神色，慢慢伸手去摸索挂在身上的腰刀。我拿走了他的刀，冲着他的脸大笑。即便这个时候，他仍一副大惑不解的样子。于是，我摆出拿黑瓶子喝酒的架势，做了个手势，就好像雪地上堆了好多货物似的，把我新婚之夜出现的情景表演了一番。我一句话也没说，但他明白了。不过他并不害怕。只见他嘴角露出一丝冷笑，一副怒不可遏的样子，并因此而产生了一股新的力量。宿营地就在不远处，但雪深难行，他爬得像蜗牛一样慢。一次，他躺着久久动不了身。我把他翻过来，死死盯住他的眼睛。他的眼里忽而有了活力，忽而死气沉沉。我松手放开他时，他又艰难地向前爬行。就这样，我们来到了篝火旁。乌恩卡见了，立刻冲到了他身旁。他嘴唇动了动，却没有说出话来，后来就用手指着我，想让乌恩卡明白是我在捣鬼。随后，他就静静地躺在雪地里，一动也不动，躺了很久很久。直到现在，他仍旧躺在那儿。

“我一直没有吭声，只是在那儿烤着松鸡。松鸡烤好之后，我才说了话，用的是她许多年都没有听到过的家乡的语言。她直起了腰，惊讶得瞪大了眼睛，问我是什么人，这种话是从何处学来的。

“‘我是纳斯。’我说道。

“‘什么？真的吗？’她凑过来要看个仔细。

“‘是真的，’我回答说，‘我是纳斯，阿卡坦的酋长，是我们家族的最后一个传人，而你是你们家族的最后一个传人。’

“她听了哈哈大笑起来。我宁愿再目睹许多灾难，再经历许多艰险，也不愿听到那样的笑声，它让我心里发寒。就这样，我坐在皑皑白雪里，周围寂静无声，孤零零地陪伴着一个死人和一个疯笑的女子。

“‘来吧！’我觉得她神经有些错乱，于是便劝道，‘你吃点东西，咱们离开这里。回阿卡坦的路远着呢。’

“她没理会我，而是把脸埋在他的黄头发里，大笑不止，直笑得天都好像快要塌下来似的。我原以为她认出我后会喜出望外，会立刻想起过去的岁月，谁知却是这般情景，让我感到很是奇怪。

“‘来吧！’我用力抓住她的手大声说道，‘路远难行，还是早点动身的好！’

“‘到哪儿去？’她止住了怪笑，坐起来问我。

“‘回阿卡坦呀。’我回答道。我想着回家乡会叫她的脸色转晴，谁知她跟他一样，嘴角露出一丝冷笑，一副怒不可遏的样子。

“‘好呀，’她说道，‘那咱俩就手拉着手回阿卡坦去，一起住进土坯房，一起吃鱼肉和鱼油度日，再生个孩子，视其为掌上明珠。咱们忘掉一切烦忧，快快活活、幸幸福福。好呀，简直好极啦。走吧，赶快走吧，咱们一起回家乡，回阿卡坦去！’

“她边说边用手指梳着他的黄头发，一边还阴阳怪气地笑着，眼神里却万念俱灰。

“我默默无语地坐着，真不明白这个女人为何如此古怪。记得那天夜里他把她从我身边拖走时，她又是尖声叫喊又是扯他的头发。而现在，她却在抚弄他的头发，不愿离开。回想起自己付出的代价和多年来的苦苦等待，我一把拽住她要将她拖走，一如他多年前那般。而她也跟那天夜里一样死活不肯走，拼命地挣扎，就像母鸡不愿离开小鸡。我拽着她，把她从火堆和那个黄发男人身边拖开，然后松了手。她坐在那里听我说话。我袒露心扉，倒出了心里的苦水，讲了我漂泊异国他乡的苦难经历，讲了我多年的旅途奔波和忍饥挨饿的生活，讲了自始至终伴随着我的希望。我把一切都和盘托出，甚至还讲了我和黄发男人之间白天发生的事情，以及我小时候的生活经历。我说着说着，见她的眼里出现了柔情，那柔情好像黎明时的一片阳光。在那里，我看到了怜悯，看到了一个女人的温柔和爱情，看到了乌恩卡的芳心和灵魂。我觉得自己又成了那个年轻人，而乌恩卡的眼里又露出了当年她跑上沙滩，咯咯笑着奔向母亲房屋时出现过的眼神。那种冷酷、令人不安的感觉倏然消失，我忘掉了饥饿和疲倦，觉得团聚的时刻就在眼前。我感到她的胸脯在召唤我，召唤我把脸埋在上面，将一切都忘掉。她向我张开了双臂，我扑进了她怀里。突然，她眼里升腾起仇恨的怒火，伸手拔出我腰间的刀，连刺我两刀。

“‘你是条狗！猪猡！’她冷笑一声，把我推倒在雪地上。随即，她狂笑一阵，笑声击碎了周围的沉寂。最后，她又回到了死去的黄发男人身旁。

“如我所说，她刺了我两刀，但由于饥饿乏力，刺得不狠，我命不该绝。不过，当时我决定留下来，和他们长眠在一起——我跟这两人的生活密不可分，为了他们我千里迢迢来到了此处。可是，有一笔债压在我的身上，使得我不能就此安息。

“返回的路很漫长，途中寒风刺骨，没有吃的东西可以果腹。那几个佩利人没有猎到麋鹿，把我贮藏的干粮吃光了。麦克奎森的那三个白人也是如此，偷吃了我们的干粮，待我找回来时，见他们饿得只剩下了骨头架，死在了木屋里。离开那儿之后，我饿得什么都记不得了。来到了这里，我才见到了食物和火——啊，多么暖和的火呀！”

他讲述完之后，把身子凑到炉子跟前烤火，甚至显得有些羡慕我们的生活。在油灯的投射下，他悲惨的身影久久地映在墙上。

“乌恩卡后来怎么样了呢？”普林斯对于刚才听到的故事仍然难以忘怀，不由高声问道。

“乌恩卡吗？她不肯吃松鸡，只是搂着他的脖子躺在那儿，把脸深深地埋在他的黄发里。我把火挪得近一点，让她不至于受冻，而她却躲到了一边。我跟过去，又在那儿生了一堆火。可这样做一点也不顶用，因为她一口东西也不肯吃。直到现在，他们还依偎着躺在雪地里呢。”

“你有什么打算吗？”马拉摩特·基德问道。

“不知道。阿卡坦是个弹丸之地，反正我是不愿再回去了，不愿再生活在那个世界的角落里了。不过，说来说去，活着对我而言也没有太大的意义了。我倒想去找康士坦丁警官，让他给我戴上手铐，末了上绞架完事。那样，我就可以安眠了。唉，说不清呀，真不知以后该怎样才好。”

“基德，你听我说，”普林斯在一旁插话说，“这可是谋杀呀！”

“胡说！”马拉摩特·基德喝止了他，“有些事情是超出咱们的智慧和衡量标准的。孰是孰非难以说得清，咱们可不能妄加评判。”

纳斯朝着炉子又贴近了一些。屋子里静悄悄的，掉根针在地上都能够听得见。每个人的眼前都仿佛出现了无数幻象，一幕幕场景忽隐忽现。

————————————————————

(1) 《奥德赛》是古希腊史诗，此处喻指充满艰辛、危险的行程。

(2) 育空位于加拿大西北边陲，约十分之一位于北极圈内，气候严寒。

(3) 沃尔斯利（1833—1913），维多利亚时代的英军总司令。

(4) 喀土穆处于两条尼罗河的交汇处，是苏丹的首都。

(5) 野牛比尔（1846—1917），威廉·弗雷德里克·科迪的绰号，美国西部拓荒时代的传奇人物，传说曾在17个月中捕杀野牛4280头，将牛肉供应给修筑太平洋大铁路的工人。

(6) 路易斯·里尔（1844—1885），加拿大历史上的一位著名政治家，曾领导过两次反抗加拿大政府的运动，致力于保护西北地区梅蒂人的权利与文化。今日他被许多加拿大人视为民族英雄。

(7) 第一批加拿大法裔移民，在森林里靠狩猎为生。

(8) 古希腊史诗《奥德赛》里的主人公，此处喻指文中的“神秘人物”。

(9) 夏洛克是莎士比亚作品中的一个人物，是个放高利贷的守财奴。这句话的意思就是讽刺俄国商人是个吝啬鬼。

(10) 白令海的第二大岛。

(11) 美国著名矿区，位于科罗拉多州。

(12) 具有垄断性的大企业。

(13) 手枪制造商。史密斯-威森公司自1852年创始至今一直是手枪界的领头羊。

(14) 显然，来客曾因饥饿过度将毛皮衣割成条吃下果腹。

(15) 普罗米修斯是希腊神话中的一个人物，他从太阳神阿波罗那里盗走火种送给人类，给人类带来了光明。

(16) 长度单位，即一手掌那么长，大约在15厘米至20厘米之间。

(17) 北美太平洋沿岸的印第安人。

(18) 白令海中的群岛，属美国阿拉斯加州。

(19) 现称东京湾，位于日本关东地区。

(20) 日本第一花柳街，是江户时代公开允许的妓院集中地。

(21) 佩利是加拿大的一个地区。

热爱生命

胜算不会太多——
生活是一场赌博：
既然已经下注，
输光老本也要搏一搏。

他们两个一瘸一拐，步履艰难地走下河岸。有一次前边的那个还在乱石间被绊了一下，差点摔倒。二人疲惫不堪，浑身发软，从脸上的表情看来他们经历了漫长的艰辛跋涉。他们的肩上负着沉甸甸的用毛毯包起来的行李卷，用额上的一条皮带勒着，如此有助于减轻肩上的负荷重量。他们各拿着一支步枪，弓着腰走路，肩膀前倾，头始终朝前看，眼睛盯着地面。

“我真希望我们身上能有几发子弹，可惜它们全都躺在地窖里。”走在后面的男人说。

他说话的声音单调、死板，不带有任何感情成分在里边。走在前面的同伴未作理会，只顾深一脚浅一脚地前行，涉入乳白色的河水里(1)，那河水在岩石间流淌，泛着泡沫。

后面的那个紧跟着他。他们下水前连鞋袜都没有脱，尽管河水冰冷刺骨——冷得他们脚腕生疼、腿脚麻木。有些地方河水没膝，冲得他们站都站不稳。

跟在后面的那个踩在一块光滑的石头上，差点滑倒，幸亏他猛地一用劲才稳住了脚，同时疼得尖叫了一声。他感到头晕目眩，一边摇晃着身子，一边将空着的那只手伸出去，像是要在空气中寻找支撑物。站稳后，他举步前行，但身子又一摇晃，差点摔倒。他只好站着不动，把目光投向了前边那个自始至终都未曾回头的人。

他纹丝不动，站了足足一分钟，犹豫了一会儿，最后才高声叫道：

“喂，比尔，我的脚腕扭伤啦。”

比尔踉跄着脚步，在乳白色的河水里走着，依然没有回头。这个男人望着他的背影，虽然脸上依旧没有表情，眼睛里却流露出受伤小鹿般无助的神情。

另一个男人一瘸一拐地登上对面的河岸，头也不回地径直向前行进。河里的人眼睁睁地瞧着，嘴唇有点发抖，嘴边乱蓬蓬的棕色胡子也很明显地跟着抖动，他不由自主地伸出舌头来将嘴唇舔了舔。

“比尔！”他大声叫喊着。

这是一个坚强的男人身处困境时发出的求救声，可是比尔还是没有回头。他目送着比尔离去，看着他怪模怪样地摇晃着身子，跌跌撞撞、步履蹒跚地爬上河对岸的缓坡，向着低矮山丘上那朦胧的天际线走去。他望着比尔的背影，直至比尔翻过山头，彻底消失。然后，他收回了目光，缓慢地环顾了一下四周，比尔走了，现在只剩下他孤零零一个人了。

太阳快接近地平线了，像一团快要熄灭的火球，隐没在无形无体的浓雾和水汽中，显得朦朦胧胧，让人觉得宛若一种轮廓模糊、虚无缥缈的物体。他掏出怀表看了看，单腿立着休息了一会儿。现在是四点钟。在这个七月末或八月初的时节——近一两个星期来，他都辨不清具体日子——他知道太阳落山处大约是在西北方。他望望南面，知道在那些荒凉的小山后面就是大熊湖；他还知道在那个方向，北极圈的禁区界线穿过加拿大的无人区。他所站的地方是科珀曼河的一条支流，而科珀曼河的干流则向北流去，汇入加冕湾和北冰洋。他从没有到过那个地方，有一次却在哈德逊湾公司的图表上见到过。

他又环顾一周，扫视了一眼周围的环境，目光所及之处并不叫人感到乐观。只见四面都是茫茫无际的地平线，一座座山丘又低又矮，没有树木、灌木丛和青草——什么都没有，只有辽阔、可怕的荒野。顿时，他眼中露出了恐惧的神色。

“比尔！”他不由低声地喊了一两声，“比尔！”

站在乳白色的河水里，他心里感到害怕，觉得周围的旷野在以一种排山倒海的力量向他压来，残忍地要将他压扁，得意扬扬地露出一副狰狞的面容。他吓得浑身发抖，像染了疟疾打摆子一样，抖得连手里的枪都掉进了水里，发出扑通一声响。这声响动才算把他惊醒了。他战胜恐惧，重新振作起精神，在水里摸了摸，把枪找了回来。接着，他将行李卷的重量向左肩移了移，如此可以减轻一部分受伤脚腕的负荷。之后，他慢慢地、小心谨慎地朝着岸边走去，每走一步，脸上的肌肉都疼得要抽搐一下。

他没敢止步，而是不顾疼痛，带着一股孤注一掷的拼劲，发了疯似的冲上河岸，登上山丘（他的同伴就是翻越了这座山丘，消失了踪影），样子古怪、可笑，跟那位一瘸一拐向前冲的同伴相比更是有过之而无不及。可是到了山头，只看见一条死气沉沉、寸草不生的浅谷。恐惧感油然而生，他又一次战胜了恐惧感，把行李卷的重量又向左肩移了移，然后蹒跚地走下山坡。

谷底积满了水，厚厚的苔藓像海绵一样，紧贴在水面上。他每走一步，就积水四溅，每次抬脚，那湿漉漉的苔藓都力图吸住他，发出吧唧吧唧的声音，像是舍不得让他的脚离开似的。他挑着好路走，从一块沼地走到另一块沼地，一路循着比尔的足迹，穿过一座座岩石堆——那些岩石堆矗立在海洋一般的苔藓地里，犹如一个个小岛。

他虽然孤零零的一个人，却没有迷路。他知道，再往前去，就会走到一个小湖跟前，湖边有许多枯死的赤松和冷杉，细瘦、干瘪。当地人把那儿叫作提钦尼奇利，意即“小棍子之地”。有一条小溪汇入湖中——跟刚才涉过的河水不同，溪水不是乳白色的；他清楚地记得小溪的岸边净是灯芯草，连一棵树也没有。他将沿着这条小溪一直走到水源地，走到一道分水岭跟前。然后，他将翻过分水岭，找到另一条小溪的源头，顺着溪水向西走，走到狄斯河（小溪汇入此河）。在狄斯河畔，他将会找到一个地窖，地窖上堆了许多石头，上面放着一个翻过来的独木舟。地窖里有他那支空枪所需要的子弹，还有钓钩、钓线和一张小渔网——打猎和钓鱼用的工具那儿一应俱全。同时，他还会找到面粉（量并不多），此外还有一块腌猪肉和一些豆子。

比尔会在那里等着他的。他们将划着独木舟顺着狄斯河向南顺流而下，直达大熊湖。到了大熊湖，他们将继续向南划，一路向南，到达麦肯齐河，再顺着河流头也不回地向南划，让寒冷的冬天想撵也撵不上他们。就让河水冻成冰块吧，就让天也寒地也冻吧，反正他们会一路向南抵达温暖的哈德逊湾公司的站点，那儿树木高大、茂密，那儿的食物多得吃也吃不完。

他艰难地向前走着，心里翻江倒海想个不停。他不仅拼尽全力跋涉着，脑子也在拼尽全力地思索着，心里认定比尔没有抛弃他，而是在地窖那儿等着他。他必须这样想，否则就没必要拼着性命朝前走了，还不如躺下来死掉好了。太阳像个朦朦胧胧的球，慢慢地向西北方下沉，而他朝着南方一点一点挪着步子（有时一步仅仅是一英寸）——这是他和比尔逃亡的路线，二人想在严冬到来之前逃到南方去。他反复地想着地窖里的食物和哈德逊湾公司那个站点的美餐，想了一遍又一遍。他已经两天没进食了；至于说吃不上自己爱吃的东西，那就更是不止两天了。他多次弯下腰，摘几颗灰白色的沼地浆果，把它们放到口里，嚼一嚼，然后咽下肚。这种沼地浆果其实只是一小粒种子，外面包着一汪水，送进嘴里就化，种子嚼起来又辣又苦。他知道这种浆果并没有养分，但是他仍然抱着希望，耐心地咀嚼着，哪还管什么营养不营养以及味道如何。

九点钟的时候，他被一块岩石的边绊了一下，由于极度疲倦和虚弱，晃了几晃便栽倒了。他侧着身子在地上躺了一会儿，纹丝不动。后来，他从行李卷的背带里挣出身子，笨拙地坐起来。天还没有黑，暮色朦胧，他在乱石中间摸索着干枯的苔藓，然后将干苔藓聚成堆生火，生了一堆不死不活、直冒黑烟的火，再在火上架了一个白铁罐子煮水。

他打开行李卷，做的第一件事就是清点包在里面的火柴。火柴总共有六十七根。不放心，他连着数了三遍，然后将它们分成几份，分别用油纸包起来，一份放在他的空烟草袋里，一份放在破帽子的帽圈里，最后的一份贴胸放在衬衫里。一切安顿完之后，他心里突然感到一阵莫名的恐慌，于是又将火柴从各处取出重新清点——不多不少，还是六十七根。

接下来，他把湿鞋湿袜放在火边烘烤。鹿皮鞋湿透了，都快成了破布；毡袜多处已磨穿，两只脚皮开肉绽，淌血不止。一只脚的脚腕胀得血管直跳，他检查了一下，发现它已经肿得和膝盖一样粗了。行李卷里总共有两条毯子，他拿起其中的一条，从上面撕下一个长条，紧紧缠在脚腕上，然后又撕下几条裹在脚上，以代替鹿皮鞋和袜子。料理停当，他把白铁罐子里滚烫的热水喝了，上好表的发条，钻进两条毯子中间倒头便睡。

这一觉他睡得跟死人一样。半夜时分，黑暗降临，但很快又消失了。太阳从东北方升了起来——最起码来说，那个方向出现了曙光，因为即便有太阳，也被灰色的云团遮得严严实实。

早晨六点钟，他睡醒了，仰面朝天地躺在那儿，呆呆地望着灰蒙蒙的天空，觉得饥肠辘辘。他翻过身侧躺着，胳膊肘压在身下，忽然听见一阵呼哧呼哧的很大的鼻息声，不由吓了一大跳，发现一只公鹿正用警惕、好奇的目光盯着他瞧。那公鹿离他不过五十英尺光景，他脑子里立刻出现了鹿肉排在火上烤得嗞嗞作响、香味扑鼻的情景。他下意识地抓起那支空枪，瞄准，扣动了扳机。公鹿打了个响鼻跑开了，鹿蹄在岩脊上飞奔，发出嗒嗒嗒的声响。

他骂了声娘，把手中的空枪扔到了一旁，然后哼哼唧唧地硬撑着要站起身子。这个过程极其缓慢、极其艰难。他体内的关节像生了锈的铰链，在骨槽里咯吱咯吱地转动着，阻力很大，一屈一伸必须靠着顽强的意志才能做得到。最后，他总算站了起来，但又花了一分钟左右的工夫才直起腰，让他能够像正常人一样站得笔直。

他奋力爬上一个小山包，放眼望去，见不到树木，见不到灌木丛，什么都看不到，只能看得到一望无际的灰色苔藓，零零星星有一些岩石、小湖和小溪点缀其中，但也全都是灰蒙蒙的。天空也是灰色的，那儿没有太阳，连太阳的影子也看不见。他分不清哪个方向才是北方，也不记得昨晚是从哪个方向来到此处的。不过，他没有迷路，对此他深有把握。要不了多久他就能走到“小棍子之地”的。他心里觉得那地方就在左边的某处，路不远，可能再翻过一座小山头就到了。

他又回到睡觉的地方，把东西收拾一下打包成行李卷。至于那三小包火柴，他虽然没有特意清点，但还是检查了一下，以确保它们被放在了行李卷里。对于那个鼓鼓囊囊的鹿皮金袋，他踌躇再三，舍不得丢弃。袋子不大，两只手能攥得过来。金袋重十五磅，差不多跟整个行李卷一样重。丢下还是拿走，这一时叫他犯了愁。最后，他忍痛将金袋扔到一边，继续打包行李。可是，他中途又停下手，看了看那个鹿皮金袋，急忙把它捡了起来，气哼哼地扫了一眼四周，仿佛那片荒原要和他抢夺金袋似的。接下来，他把金袋放入行李卷，站起身，一步一摇晃地开始了一天的行程。

他向左侧走去，一路走走停停，摘一些沼地浆果充饥。扭伤的脚腕变得僵直，比以前瘸得更厉害了。但脚腕之痛跟胃痛比起来就是小巫见大巫了。由于饥饿，胃痛得钻心。一阵又一阵，饥饿像是在用它的牙齿啃着他的胃，使得一心一意朝着“小棍子之地”赶路的他老是分心。沼地浆果并不能减轻这种剧痛，浆果刺激性的味道反而使他的舌头和上颚也跟着痛了起来。

他来到一条山谷跟前，惊起一群石松鸡，它们拍打着翅膀，咯咯咯地叫着，从岩石间和沼地上腾空而起。他用石块去砸，却一只也没有击中。他把行李卷放在地上，像猫捉麻雀一样向落下来的鸟偷偷摸过去。锋利的岩石划破了裤腿，他的膝盖被划伤，流下的鲜血滴了一路。但胃痛盖住了伤口的疼痛。他猫着腰在潮湿的苔藓地上一步一步向前移动着，全然不顾身上的衣服已经湿透、寒冷难耐，对食物的渴望强烈到使他忘掉了一切。石松鸡总是在他快到跟前时腾空而起，盘旋不去，咯咯咯地叫着，像是在嘲笑他。他气得直骂娘，冲着它们大吼大叫。

他继续向前寻找，曾经摸到了一只大概是睡着了的石松鸡跟前。他没有看见那只鸡，直至它从岩缝间的巢里飞起，差点扑到他脸上，这才一惊。他和那只鸡一样慌乱，伸出手胡乱抓了一把，只抓了三根尾羽到手。眼睁睁看着松鸡飞走，他心里恨恨不已，就好像那只松鸡做了什么对不起他的事似的。无奈，他回到原地，背起了行李卷。

时间在一分一秒地慢慢逝去，他走过一片片生态更为活跃的山谷与沼地。一群驯鹿走了过去，大约有二十多只，都在猎枪的射程以内，撩得他心里发痒。他一阵发狂，真想追过去，坚信自己一定能把猎物追到手。这时，一只黑狐狸朝他走了过来，嘴里叼着一只松鸡。他大叫一声，声音大得怕人，吓得狐狸没命地逃窜，但是仍然没有丢掉松鸡。

傍晚时分，他沿着一条小溪朝前走，小溪流过长得稀稀拉拉的灯芯草草丛，溪水因为含有石灰而变成了乳白色。他用手抓紧灯芯草靠近根部的地方，揪下一些草芽——那些草芽像葱苗，只有瓦钉那么大，嫩嫩的，嚼起来很爽脆，味道似乎很不错。谁知那玩意儿的纤维却不容易咬断。它由一丝丝充满水分的纤维组成，跟沼地浆果一样，完全没有养分。他顾不了许多，甩掉行李卷，爬进灯芯草草丛，牛吃草那般大嚼大咽起来。

他非常疲倦，总希望能歇一会儿，躺下来睡个觉缓缓劲。然而，有一种力量在催促他向前——与其说是因为他渴望早一点抵达“小棍子之地”，倒不如说是饥饿在迫使他往前走。他在小水坑里找青蛙，又用指甲挖土找蚯蚓，尽管他也知道，在这遥远的北方是既没有青蛙也没有蚯蚓的。

遇到小水坑他就乱摸一通，次次都无功而返。最后，当暮色笼罩四野，他在一个水坑里总算发现了一条孤零零的小鱼，跟鲦鱼那么大。他把胳膊伸下水去抓，水一直没到肩头，而那条鱼一出溜就逃掉了。他两手并用去捉，把坑底的乳白色泥浆搅了起来。由于激动，他不慎掉进了水里，半个身子都浸湿了。水被搅浑，看不清鱼在哪儿，他只好等泥浆沉淀下去再说。

他又开始下劲捉鱼，水又一次被搅浑了。他一时焦急，便解下身上的白铁罐子，把坑里的水往外舀。起初，他发狂一样地舀，把水溅了一身，同时，泼出去的水因为距离水坑太近，又流了回来。后来，虽然他的心依旧扑通乱跳，手发抖，但谨慎了一些，尽量让自己冷静了下来。奋斗了半个小时后，坑里的氷已几乎被舀干，只剩下了一丁点儿。可是，鱼却不见了。他这才发现石头堆里面有一条暗缝，那条鱼已从暗缝钻到了旁边一个相连的大水坑，那大水坑里的水就是舀一天一夜也舀不干。要是早知道，就应该先用石头将暗缝堵死，鱼也就抓到手了。

他追悔莫及，四肢无力地瘫倒在潮湿的地上。起初他只是低声地啜泣，后来，他冲着那把他团团围住的无情的荒原号啕大哭了起来。大哭之后，又是一阵抽噎，他抽噎了许久许久。

他生起一堆火，喝了几夸脱(2)热水暖身子，然后按昨晚的那种方式在一块岩架上扎营。临睡前，他最后检查了一下火柴是否还是干燥的，并且上好表的发条。毯子潮湿、发黏。脚腕一跳一跳地疼。然而，他已经不在乎这些了，他所在乎的只是饥饿。睡觉睡不安宁，他老是梦见各种各样的酒席、宴会，梦见丰盛可口的饭菜。

醒来时，他浑身发冷，感到很不舒服。天上没有太阳。原本就灰蒙蒙的大地和天空，此时越显得昏天黑地。寒风刺骨，初雪落下，染白了山巅。他生了火，煮了些开水，周围的空气也越来越浓，最后成了白茫茫的一片。从天上掉下来的是半雨半雪，雪花是大片大片的，湿而软。起初，雪花一落地就化，后来雪越下越大，盖满了地面，扑灭了篝火，弄湿了他收集来当柴烧的干苔藓。

他见情况不妙，急忙背上行李卷往前走，一路跌跌撞撞，不知要去向何处。此刻，他想到的不是“小棍子之地”，不是比尔，也不是狄斯河边那条翻过来的独木舟下掩盖的地窖。他心里只有一个字，那就是“吃”。他简直饿疯了，根本不管自己走的路对不对，反正只要能走出眼前的水洼地就行。他在湿漉漉的雪地里摸索着前行，一路寻找着沼地浆果，遇见灯芯草便连根拔起。但这种东西索然无味，又不顶饥。后来，他发现了一种带酸味的野草，就找了来吃下肚子。可惜能找到的并不多，因为这种野草贴着地面生长，很容易被几英寸厚的雪埋住。

这天夜里，他生不成火，也没喝上热水，钻进毯子下蒙眬睡去，中间屡屡饿醒。雪变成了冰冷的雨水。雨滴落在他仰着的脸上，多次把他淋醒。第二天，天空一片铅色，仍没有太阳。雨已经停了。刀绞一样的饥饿感也消失了。他已经丧失了想吃食物的感觉，只觉得胃里隐隐作痛，但这对他的影响并不大。他的脑子比较清晰了，又能够专心致志思考到“小棍子之地”和狄斯河边那个地窖的事宜了。

他拿起那条残缺不全的毯子，把它撕成一条一条的，缠在血淋淋的脚上，又用几条当绷带裹在扭伤的脚腕上，为这一天的旅程做好准备。打包行李卷时，他看着那个鼓囊囊的鹿皮金袋思考良久，最后还是带着它上了路。

一场雨过后，雪已经融化了，只剩下山头还留着雪帽。太阳出来了，他总算能够定出罗盘的方位了，这时他方知自己迷了路。也许，在前两天的跋涉中，他往左边走，左得过了头。现在，为了校正方向，以便走上正道，他朝着右边走去。

饿得胃痛的感觉虽然不再那么强烈，他却觉得全身软弱无力，寻找沼地浆果和灯芯草时也不得不走两步便停下来歇口气。他的舌头发干、发胀，好像上面长满了细细的绒毛，嘴里有一种苦苦的味道。他的心脏给他添了不少麻烦。每走几分钟，他的心脏就会扑通扑通地猛跳一阵，然后像越来越急促的鼓点一样窜动着，让他痛苦不堪，使得他头晕目眩，喘不过气来。

中午时分，他在一个大水坑里发现了两条鲦鱼。要想把水舀干去捉鱼，那是不可能的。不过，他现在大脑很清晰，最后用白铁罐子把它们捞了起来。它们也不过只有他的小拇指那么大，好在他现在并不觉得特别饿。胃里的隐痛已经越来越弱，越来越麻木了。他的胃好像睡着了似的。他把鱼生吃下去，费劲地咀嚼着——进食已经成了一种纯理性的行为。他没有吃的欲望，却知道要活下去就必须吃。

到了傍晚，他又捉到了三条鲦鱼，当时就吃掉了两条，留下一条第二天作为早餐。此时，太阳已经晒干了剩下不多的几块苔藓，总算可以烧点热水喝下去暖身子了。在这一天里，他走了不到十英里的路；次日，由于心脏受不了，他走走停停，只走了不到五英里。不过，他的胃却没有一点不舒服的感觉，就像是进入了梦乡。他来到了一个陌生的地区，鹿越来越多，狼也多起来了。在荒芜的原野上不时会传来狼的号叫声，有一次他还瞧见三只狼从他前面的路上偷偷溜过。

又过了一夜。到了早晨，他变得比较理智了，于是就解开系着那鼓囊囊的鹿皮金袋的皮绳，敞开袋口倒出一股黄澄澄的粗金沙和金块，将这些金子大致分成了两堆，一堆包在一块毯子里，藏在一块显眼的岩石下，另一堆则放回了金袋。同时，他从剩下的那条毯子上又撕下几条布，用来裹脚。对于猎枪，他仍然舍不得丢掉，因为狄斯河边的地窖里藏有子弹。

这是一个大雾天。这一天，饥饿感又卷土重来了。他感到虚弱极了，饿得头昏眼花，有时候什么都看不见。打绊和摔跟头对于他已不是稀罕事。一次，他脚下一绊，一个跟头摔到了石松鸡的巢穴里，那里面有四只刚孵出的雏鸟，恐怕刚孵出一天吧——几只活蹦乱跳的小生命一口就能吃进肚。他把它们活生生塞到嘴里，像嚼蛋壳似的咀嚼着，狼吞虎咽地将它们全吃了。松鸡母亲咯咯咯地大叫着，扑闪着翅膀攻击他。他把枪当棍子狠劲打去，被它躲开了。他又用石块砸，其中有一块石头砸伤了它的翅膀。松鸡振翅一飞，扇着受伤的翅膀慌乱地逃跑了，而他在后边紧追不舍。

那几只雏鸡吊起了他的胃口。他拖着受伤的脚腕，一瘸一拐，跌跌撞撞地往前追，又是用石块砸，又是大声吆喝，有时则不声不响，摔倒了就咬咬牙爬起来，继续耐着性子追去；当满眼昏花，快看不见的时候，他用手揉揉眼睛，仍紧追不舍。

追逐中，他穿过了谷底的沼地，发现湿漉漉的苔藓上有一些脚印。那不是他自己的脚印——这他看得出来。一定是比尔的。不过，他不能停下，因为松鸡仍在逃窜。他必须先把它抓住，然后再拐回来查看脚印。

母松鸡被追得精疲力竭，他自己也累瘫了。它歪着身子倒在地上喘个不停，他也斜躺着呼哧呼哧喘粗气，中间仅仅隔着十来英尺的距离，然而他却没有力气爬过去。等他缓过劲时，它也歇了过来。当他急不可耐地伸手去抓时，它就扑棱扑棱翅膀逃到了他够不着的地方。这场追赶就这样一直持续着。直到夜晚，它终于逃掉了。他浑身软得像面条，脚下一绊，栽了个跟头，脸都磕破了，行李卷重重压在背上。他一动不动趴了许久，后来翻过身侧躺着，给表上了发条，在那儿一直躺到次日早晨。

这一天又是个大雾天。最后剩下的那条毯子有一半都被他当成了裹脚布。此时，他已经找不到比尔的脚印了。他已顾不上这许多了。饥饿已将他逼到了山穷水尽的地步。不过，他心里还是会掠过一丝思绪，觉得比尔可能也迷了路。到了中午时分，行李卷压得他有点不堪重负。他取出金袋，把金子又一分为二，将其中的一半胡乱扔在了地上。下午，他把剩下来的那一点也扔掉了。现在，他只有半条毯子、一个白铁罐子和那支猎枪了。

他脑子里开始出现了幻觉，总觉得还剩下一颗子弹在猎枪的枪膛里，只是他疏忽了，没想起来而已。可是另一方面，他也明明白白知道枪膛是空的。但这种幻觉挥之不去。他与之斗争，斗争了好几个小时。最后，他拉开了枪栓，面对的是一个事实——枪膛里空空如也。失望给他带来的是痛苦，仿佛他原先真的指望能看到那颗子弹似的。

他迈着沉重的步伐继续朝前走，走了半个小时，那种幻觉又出现了。他又与之斗争，可它却久久不肯离去，直到为了摆脱它，他又打开了枪膛，使自己不再幻想。有时候，他胡思乱想得越发离谱，脚下艰难跋涉，机械地挪动着步子，心里生出的各种稀奇古怪的想法和念头却像蛀虫一样啃噬着他的脑髓。不过，这类脱离现实的遐思每一次都只是昙花一现，撕心裂肺的饥饿感总会叫他重新回到现实中来。有一次，他从这种遐想中猛醒，被眼前的情景惊得差点没昏过去。他晃了几晃，就像个醉汉一样，努力不让自己摔倒。他觉得前边站着一匹马。天呀，那儿有一匹马！他简直不能相信自己的眼睛。就在这时，他感到眼前一黑，金星乱冒。他狠狠揉了揉眼睛，好让自己看清楚一些。这一下不当紧，他看到的不是马，而是一头大棕熊！那家伙一副好斗的样子，正好奇地盯着他瞧。

他举枪上肩，但中途意识到枪是空的，于是就又把枪放下，从腰间那镶着珍珠的刀鞘里拔出了猎刀。前面就是肉，吃了就能活命呀！他用大拇指试试刀刃，觉得刀刃很锋利，刀尖也很锋利。眼看他就要扑上去把熊杀死了。可是他的心脏却扑通扑通乱跳起来，向上一蹿一蹿地顶着心口——这一通乱跳像是给他的头勒上了紧箍咒，勒得他的大脑感到天旋地转。

这时，他的心里突然涌起一股强烈的恐惧感，驱散了那种发狠拼命的勇气。他弱得手无缚鸡之力，万一那头猛兽冲过来攻击他该如何是好？他只好手握猎刀，死死盯住那只熊，摆出一副极其吓人的姿势。那只熊笨手笨脚地跨近两步，直立起来，试探性地咆哮一声。此时，这个人要是跑，熊肯定会追，可是他没有跑。恐惧激发了他的勇气，使得他热血沸腾。他也咆哮一声，声音凶狠，充满了野性，宣泄出了在生死攸关的时刻那种紧紧抱住生命之根不肯撒手的恐惧。

熊见这个神秘的生物站得笔直，全无惧色，自己倒是有了几分怯意，于是向一旁退了几步，威胁性地吼了几声。可是他纹丝不动，似一尊雕像一样站在那儿，直到危险过去，才猛然哆嗦了一阵，瘫倒在湿漉漉的苔藓地上。

他重新振作起来，继续前进，心里又添了一种新的恐惧——他倒不害怕因为吃不到东西而被活活饿死，而是害怕不等饥饿耗尽他的最后一点求生力，自己就已经被活活吃掉了。此处狼多，狼嗥之声在荒原上四处飘荡，在空中织出了一张瘆人的大网，吓得他不由举起双手，要用力支撑住这顶被大风吹得歪斜的帐篷的篷布。

不时有狼从他面前三三两两地跑过。不过，那些狼都躲着他，一是因为它们的数量不多，二是由于它们要捕食的是驯鹿。驯鹿不会反抗，谁知道这个直立走路的奇怪生物会不会对它们又抓又咬呢。

傍晚时分，他碰见了一堆饿狼啃剩下的动物骨头。这堆七零八落的骨头在一个小时之前还是一只尖叫着逃窜的活蹦乱跳的小鹿！他打量着这些骨头，发现它们已经被啃得精光发亮，只剩下血髓在骨头表面泛着粉红色。在天黑之前，他说不定也会落得这种下场！生命就要这样结束了吗？它可真是一种虚无缥缈、转瞬即逝的东西！活着才会感到痛苦，死了就没有感觉了，就像睡着了一样。死亡意味着结束，意味着休息。可是，让他死，他为什么又于心不甘呢？

不过，对于这些大道理他没有思考过多，而是蹲在苔藓地上，拿起一根骨头放在嘴里，吮吸着那残余在骨头上微微泛红的血髓。他的嘴里泛起一股甜甜的肉味，那味道丝丝缕缕、隐隐约约，像思绪一般。这一吮叫他发了狂，只见他咬紧骨头，使劲地啃，有时咬碎了一点骨头，有时却硌碎了自己的牙。后来，他用石块砸那骨头，把它捣成酱吞到肚里。匆忙之中，他砸到了自己的指头上；使他感到惊奇的是，在石块砸在手指上的瞬间，他却未感到十分疼痛。

接下来的几天雨雪交加，天气十分糟糕。他都没有何时宿营、何时上路的概念了，而是日夜兼程地走。摔倒了，他就躺在那儿休息休息；一旦即将熄灭的生命火花闪烁起来，微微燃烧，他就又艰难地向前跋涉。作为一个人，他已经不再挣扎，而他体内的生命却不愿死去，逼着他朝前走。他不再感到痛苦，他的大脑神经已变得迟钝、麻木，脑海里充斥着怪异的幻象和美妙的梦境。

一路上，他把砸碎了的鹿骨取出来吮吸和咀嚼——这些残屑是他收集起来带着路上吃的。他不再翻山越岭，而是机械性地沿着一条流过一片宽阔浅谷的河流前行。无论是河水还是浅谷他一概视而不见，眼里只看得到种种幻象。灵魂和肉体虽然在同行，肩并肩地跋涉，然而它们又是分离的，联系它们的纽带极薄极弱。

一天，他一觉醒来，神智清楚地仰卧在一块突出的岩石上。阳光明媚、和煦。远处传来小鹿鸣叫的声音。他模模糊糊记得下过雨、刮过风、落过雪，可是他顶着风吹雨打究竟度过了两天还是两个星期，他就说不清了。

他一动不动地躺了一会儿。和煦的阳光洒在身上，让他那饱经苦难的躯体有了丝丝暖意。他心想这是一个晴好的日子。也许，他可以想办法确定自己的方位。他忍着痛苦一使劲，侧过身子来，发现脚下有一条水面开阔、缓缓流淌的大河。这一景象很是陌生，叫他感到惊奇。他顺着河水流淌的方向慢慢望去，只见那宽宽的水面蜿蜒穿行于光秃秃的、荒凉的山丘之间——那山丘比他以前所见过的任何山丘都更荒凉、更光秃、更低矮。随后，他慢慢地、从容地、心平气和地，或者说是漫不经心地又顺着这条陌生的河流流淌的方向望了一眼，把目光投向水天交接之处，看到它汇入了一片闪闪发光的明亮的大海。他仍然一副十分镇定的样子。他觉得眼前的情景极为反常，可能是幻象或海市蜃楼——多半是幻象，是他混乱的大脑臆想出来的。接着，他看见那明亮的大海上停泊着一艘轮船，于是就更加确信这是幻象了。他把眼睛闭了一会儿，然后又睁开。奇怪，幻象竟然还在那里！说奇怪，其实也没什么奇怪的。他知道荒原中央绝不会有什么大海或轮船，正像他知道自己的空枪里没有子弹一样。

这时，他听到背后有一种呼哧呼哧的声音——一种喘不过气或者咳嗽的声音。他翻转过身子来，由于虚弱和僵硬，动作非常缓慢。近旁什么也看不到。但是他耐心地等着。那呼哧呼哧的声音和咳嗽声又一次响起。在离他不到二十英尺远的两块锯齿状的岩石之间，他隐约看到了一只灰狼的脑袋。这只狼的尖耳朵并不像别的狼那样支棱着，它双眼浑浊无光、布满血丝，脑袋有气无力地耷拉着，一副惨相。在阳光下，这头野兽不时地眨巴着眼睛，像是生病了。就在他张望之际，那只狼又发出了呼哧呼哧的呼吸和咳嗽声。

至少这副情景是真的，他想，于是他又翻了个身，将身子转向另一侧，想看看刚才被幻象遮住的现实世界。可是，远处仍可见那片闪闪发光的大海，那艘轮船也依旧历历在目。难道这就是现实世界？他闭着眼睛，想了好一会儿，终于想清楚了。原来，他一直在朝着北偏东方向走，早已离开狄斯分水岭，走到了科珀曼山谷。这条水面开阔、缓缓流淌的大河就是科珀曼河。那片闪闪发光的大海是北冰洋。那艘轮船是捕鲸船，本应该驶往麦肯齐河口的，却偏东了，向东边偏得太远了，目前停泊在加冕湾里。他记起了很久以前看到过的那张哈德逊湾公司的图表，觉得一切都清楚了，一切都是合情合理的。

他坐起来，把注意力放在了眼前的事上。裹在脚上的毯子已经磨穿，一双脚血肉模糊，没有一处好肉；最后的一条毯子被撕成条，用光了；猎枪和猎刀都不见了；帽子不知在什么地方丢了，帽圈里那包火柴也一块儿丢了，但贴胸放在烟草袋里的那几根用油纸包着的火柴还在，而且是干的。他检查了一下怀表，看到它仍在走，时针指着十一点。显然，他一直没有忘记给表上发条。

他冷静下来、精力集中，虽然身体极度虚弱，却感觉不到痛苦。他已经不再感到饥饿了，即便想到食物，也不觉得愉悦。现在，他无论做什么，都是凭着理性。他齐膝撕下了两截裤腿，把它们裹在脚上。那只白铁罐子他总算还保留了下来。他将烧些开水喝，然后向轮船那儿进发——他预料到那将是一段极其艰难的旅途。

他的一举一动都很缓慢，浑身哆嗦，就像中风了一样。当他准备去收集一些干苔藓生火时，却怎么也站不起来了。他尝试了几次，最后只好手脚并用地爬行了。有一次他爬到了那只病狼附近。那头野兽一面很不情愿地拖着身子躲开他，一面用它那好像连弯一下的力气都没有的舌头舔着自己的上下颚。他注意到病狼的舌头不是通常那种健康的红色，而是一种暗黄色，好像蒙着一层粗糙的、半干的黏液。

后来，他喝了一品脱的热水，总算可以站起来了，甚至还能走路了，但就像濒临死亡的人那样，身子一摇一晃的，走几步就得停下来歇一歇。他的步子软弱无力，很不稳，而跟在他身后的病狼也同样脚步不稳，踉踉跄跄的。夜里，闪闪发光的大海笼罩在黑暗之中，他知道自己和大海之间的距离恐怕只缩短了不足四英里。

这一整夜，他老听到那只病狼在咳嗽，还会不时听到小鹿呦呦的叫声。他周围全是生命，不过那是强壮的生命，非常活跃而健康的生命，同时他也知道，那只病狼之所以要紧跟着他这个病人，是希望他先死。次日早晨，他一睁眼就看到那头野兽正用一种居心不良、饥肠辘辘的目光瞅着他。它夹着尾巴卧在那儿，像一条穷途末路的丧家犬，在清晨的寒风中瑟瑟发抖。他鼓起劲，对它呵斥一声，声音又低又哑，而那家伙只是有气无力地朝他龇了龇牙。

太阳升起，光芒万丈。他跋涉了一个上午，跌跌绊绊地朝着闪闪发光的大海上的那艘轮船走去。天气好极了。此时正值高纬度地区的小阳春，非常短暂，可能只有一个星期，也许明后天就会结束。

下午，他发现了一些痕印，那是另外一个人留下的——并非走路留下的足印，而是爬行留下的印迹。他觉得那可能是比尔留下的，不过他对此麻木不仁、漠不关心，已经一点兴趣都没有了。事实上，他内心的热忱和感情已荡然无存。他也不再感到痛苦。他的胃和神经都处于睡眠状态。但是，他体内的生命还在，正是这种生命在催促他向前。他已疲倦到了极点，但生命不愿意消亡。由于生命拒绝死去，他才仍然要吃沼地浆果和鲦鱼，要喝热水，要一直提防着那只病狼。

他跟着比尔爬行留下的印迹朝前走，很快就走到了头——只见湿漉漉的苔藓地上乱扔着几根刚啃光不久的骨头，骨头上还留有许多狼的爪印。他发现了一个鼓囊囊的鹿皮金袋，跟他自己的那个一模一样，已经被狼的利齿咬破了。按说他手脚无力，是提不起金袋的，但他一用劲还是将其拎了起来。比尔至死都没有把金子扔掉。哈！哈！比尔可真是太可笑了。他将活下去，带着比尔的金子到闪闪发光的大海里的那艘轮船上去。他的笑声沙哑、恐怖，跟乌鸦的怪叫一样，而那只病狼也随着他发出嗷呜嗷呜的惨叫。蓦然，他收住了笑声。如果此处真是比尔死去的地方，如果这些发红发白、被啃得精光的骨头真是比尔的遗骨，他怎么能加以嘲笑呢？

他转身走开了。不错，比尔抛弃了他，但他绝不能因此就拿走比尔的金子，也绝不能吮吸比尔的骨头以求自己活命。话又说回来，要是换上比尔，比尔恐怕会这么做的。他一边沉思着，一边踉踉跄跄地向前挪着步子。

他走到了一个水坑跟前，弯下腰在水里找鱼，却突然像被蜜蜂蜇了一下，把头缩了回去。原来，他在水里看见了自己的倒影，发现他的那张脸变得十分吓人。这一印象久久不散，让他感到震惊。水坑里有三条鲦鱼，可是坑太大，水是舀不干的；他用白铁罐子去捉，试了几次都功亏一篑，最后只好放弃。他生怕自己会由于极度虚弱，跌进水坑里淹死。也正是因为这一层原因，尽管沙洲上有许多原木，他也不敢骑上一根顺着河流漂向大海。

这一天，他把自己和那条船之间的距离缩短了三英里；次日缩短了两英里——因为这天他是爬行的，跟比尔生前一样。到了第五天晚上，他发现那条船距离他仍有七英里，而他一天连一英里也爬不了了。小阳春的天气仍在持续，他继续朝前爬，中途屡次昏过去又醒过来，那只病狼始终跟在他后面，又是咳嗽又是呼哧呼哧地喘气。他的膝盖已经和他的脚一样鲜血淋漓，尽管他撕下了身上的衬衫来垫膝盖，仍然在身后的苔藓和岩石上留下了一路血迹。他曾回头看了看，发现那只狼正在饥不择食地舔他洒在路上的血。从中，他清楚地看到了或许将会出现的结局……除非……除非他先把狼干掉。眼前正上演着一场无比悲惨的求生悲剧——有病的人挣扎着向前爬行，有病的狼一摇一晃跟在后边，两个生物拖着垂死之躯走在荒原上，进行着你死我活的斗争。

要是一只健康的狼把他吃掉，倒也罢了，可是一想到自己要喂这么一只令人作呕、只剩下一口气的狼，他就心生厌恶。对此他还是比较挑剔的。他又开始神游他方了，脑子里出现的种种幻象搅得他像是吃了迷魂药一般，清醒的时候少，糊涂的时候多。

一次昏厥后，他被贴着耳朵根响起的呼哧呼哧的喘息声惊醒了。那只病狼见他醒来，不由瘸着腿朝后一跳，虚弱得立足不稳，摔倒在了地上。那情景可笑极了，可是他一点也不觉得有趣，甚至也不感到后怕。到了这种地步，他的恐惧感早已飞到了九霄云外。不过，这会儿他的脑子倒是挺清醒的。于是他躺在那儿，思考了起来。那艘轮船离他还有不到四英里远，他只要揉一揉浑浊的眼睛，就能清楚地看见。他还看得见有一只小船鼓起白帆，劈波斩浪地航行在闪闪发光的大海上。可是，这四英里的路他爬是爬不到的。对此他是很清楚的，即便如此，他也并不感到惊惶。他知道，自己恐怕连半英里也爬不动了。然而，他渴望活下去。吃了那么多的苦，老天爷不会允许他此时死掉。命运对他实在太苛刻了。尽管奄奄一息，他还是不愿就这样去见阎王爷。也许，这只不过是他表现出的一股疯劲，但即便落入了死神的魔爪，他也要挣扎一番，拒绝走上黄泉路。

他闭上眼睛，提高了警惕，让自己平静下来。疲倦感像潮水一般涌遍全身各处，而他坚强地振作起精神，免得被这潮水所淹没。要命的疲倦感似汹涌的大海，翻起一个个浪头，一点一点地在淹没他的意识。有时候，他几乎完全被吞没，只是双手胡乱划动，在那茫茫的潮水上浮沉；后来，他的魂魄又奇特地回转了来，求生的意识随之浮现，变得比之前还要强烈。

他一动不动地仰面躺着，耳朵听得见病狼呼哧呼哧的喘息声，一呼一吸的，离他越来越近了。病狼在步步逼近，而他始终躺着未动。不知过了多长时间之后，它已经到了他耳边，又干瘪又粗糙的舌头就像砂纸一样磨着他的脸颊。他的两只手伸了出去——或者，他至少是凭着意志逼着那双手伸了出去。他的指头弯得像鹰爪一样，可是却抓了个空。敏捷和准确是需要力气的，而他没有这份力气。

病狼的耐心可真是惊人，他的耐心也同样惊人。这一天，一半时间他都躺着不动，苦苦挣扎着不让自己失去意识，等着那只想吃掉他的狼，而他也渴望吃掉对方。有时候，疲倦感像海水涌来将他淹没，使他深陷梦境；然而，无论是梦还是醒，他自始至终都在等待着那呼哧呼哧的喘息声响起，等待着粗糙的狼舌来舔他。

他一直没有听到那喘息声。后来，当他慢慢从一场梦里醒来时，感觉到那条舌头在舔他的手。他静静地等着。狼牙轻轻地咬在了他的手上，越咬越紧——病狼拼尽最后一丝力气要将牙齿咬进自己等待已久的食物里。这一刻他也等了许久，只见他用那只被咬破了的手一把抓住了狼颚。病狼无力地挣扎着，他的手也同样无力地抓住不放，另一只手则慢慢摸过来，双手将狼箍住。五分钟后，他把全身的重量都压在了狼的身上。他手上的力量虽然还不足以把狼掐死，可是他的脸已经紧紧地压住了狼的咽喉，咬得嘴里满是狼毛。咬了有半个小时的时间，他感到一小股温热的液体慢慢流进了他的喉咙。这东西并不好喝，就像硬灌到他胃里的铅液，而且完全是凭着他自己的意志硬灌下去的。后来，他翻过身，仰面朝天地睡着了。

“贝德福德号”捕鲸船上有几个科学考察队的队员，他们从甲板上望见岸上有个奇怪的目标物，它正沿着沙滩朝着海水移动。他们看不清那是什么，但由于是科考人员，需要探个究竟，于是就上了一条在旁边作业的小船向岸边驶去。他们发现它是有生命的，不过很难把它称作人。它什么也看不见，没有了任何意识，就像只大爬虫一样在地上蠕动着。它付出的努力十有八九都会落空，但它锲而不舍，扭动着身体吃力地向前爬着，一小时大概也爬不了二十英尺。

三个星期后的一天，这个人躺在“贝德福德号”捕鲸船的小床上，消瘦的脸上热泪纵横，说出了他的身份以及他所经历的磨难。他用含混不清的声音、断断续续的语句谈及他的母亲，谈及阳光灿烂的南加利福尼亚，以及橘林和花丛中的家园。

没过几天，他就跟那些科考队队员以及船员坐在同一张桌子旁边吃饭了。望着丰盛的食物，他目光贪婪，看着食物进入别人的口中，总有些不情愿。别人每每咽下一口饭菜，他的眼里都会显露出深深的惋惜。他的神智非常清醒，可是每逢吃饭的时候，他都会怨恨同桌进餐的人。一种恐惧感老是萦绕在他的心间——他怕船上的食物吃不了多长时间。不知有多少次，他询问厨子、船舱服务生和船长，问船上贮存的食物够不够吃，那些人每次都叫他放宽心。可是，他不相信他们的话，依旧会疑神疑鬼地溜到贮藏室那儿亲自窥探。

大家留意到他在发福，像发面团一样每天胖一点。科考队队员见了直摇头，给他讲了科学道理，限制他的食量，可是他的腰围仍在增加，衣服下的身体仍在膨胀。

水手们都咧着嘴笑——他们是知道内情的。科考队队员观察后也知道了其中的缘故。他们发现他吃过早饭后就四处转悠，遇见哪个水手就截住人家，像个乞丐一样伸手要吃的。水手会笑笑，递给他一块硬面包。他贪婪地把面包抓在手里看着它，就像守财奴看黄金那样，然后将其塞进怀里。其他水手遇见这种情况，也会笑一笑向他赠送面包。

科考队队员不动声色，什么也没说，而是暗中检查了他的床铺，发现那儿满都是硬面包，连褥子下也塞满了，每个角落都被硬面包塞得严严实实。他的脑子很正常，这样做只是以备不时之需，以防再次饿肚子——仅此而已。科考队队员说他以后会恢复正常的。果真，未等“贝德福德号”捕鲸船在旧金山湾里抛锚，他就已经恢复了正常。

————————————————————

(1) 因石灰含量过高，河水呈乳白色。

(2) 容量单位。一夸脱等于0.946升。

生火

破晓时分，天气寒冷，四周灰蒙蒙一片，简直是刺骨般的寒冷，昏天黑地的。他离开育空大道，爬上了高高的泥土河岸，这儿有一条少有人走的凄凉的小径向东通往又粗又壮的云杉树林。河岸的坡度很陡，他爬到顶时停下来喘气。他看了看表，也算给自己找了个歇气的理由。此时是九点钟，虽然天空没有一片云彩，却也没有太阳，亦没有出太阳的迹象。虽然是晴天，却似乎有一种无形的、朦胧的东西覆盖在一景一物之上，一种难以名状的阴森气氛使得天色越发昏暗，这全都是因为没有太阳所致。有没有太阳他并不在意，反正他已经习以为常了。他已多日不见阳光，而且他知道还得再过几天，那个叫人心情愉悦的火球才会从正南方向的地平线上探出头来，然后又会很快消失。

他回头看了一眼自己走过的路。育空河宽达一英里，深藏于三英尺厚的冰层下，冰上覆盖着数英尺厚的雪，望上去一片洁白，在流冰拥塞处微微起伏。极目远眺，南方和北方都是一望无际的白色，唯有一条深色的细线弯弯曲曲地绕过云杉覆盖的小岛向南伸去，再弯弯曲曲地一路向北，最后隐没于另一个云杉覆盖的小岛的后面。那条深色的细线是一条小径，它向南五百英里通向迪耶(1)附近的奇尔库特山隘，通向海边，向北七十英里则通往道森，再向北一千英里通往努拉托，最后到达一千五百英里外靠近白令海的圣迈克尔。

不过，那条神秘、绵长如细线一般的道路，那不见太阳的天空，那刺骨的寒冷，那离奇古怪的景色，所有的这一切并没有对他产生任何影响。这倒不是因为他对此久已习惯。其实，他初来乍到，是一个“新人”，这是他来此处的第一个冬天。问题在于他缺乏想象力。他对于周遭的事物反应灵敏而机警，但仅仅局限于对事物本身的了解，对其中所包含的深意却不甚了了。零下五十度意味着冰点下八十多度(2)。他只觉得天气很冷，让他很不舒服，仅此而已。他没有推想到自己作为恒温动物的脆弱，没有推想到人体一般来说是很娇气的，只能生活在一定的冷热范围之内，也没有继而推想到关于永恒以及人类在宇宙中的位置的问题。零下五十度会形成霜冻，给人体造成伤害，必须戴手套、护耳帽，穿鹿皮鞋和厚袜子加以保护。而对他来说，零下五十度就是零下五十度，至于其他的方面，他并没有多想。

他把目光收回来继续往前走，边想心事，边随口吐了一口唾沫。只听噼啪一声响，像是什么东西炸裂了一样，吓了他一大跳。他又吐了一口，又是一声响，那口唾液未等落地，在空中就冻成冰炸裂了。他知道，零下五十度时唾液在雪地上会冻成冰炸裂开，可是在空中炸裂开就叫人费解了。毫无疑问，实际气温要低于零下五十度，至于低多少他就不得而知了。不过，气温低不低无关紧要。此行，他要到亨德森河的左岔口去干他的老行当，伙计们已候在那儿了。那些人来自印第安河流域，是翻越分水岭过来的，而他则绕道而去，想看看是否有可能在春季把原木从育空河一带的小岛上运出去。他将在六点钟到达营地，那时天黑不久，晚是晚了些，但那儿有朋友们迎候，有篝火和晚餐。至于午餐么，他用手按了按外套下的那个鼓囊囊的包裹。一些面包被用手帕包住，紧紧贴着皮肤放在衬衣下面——只有这样，面包才不至于冻硬。一想到把这些面包切成片，在咸肉油里浸一浸，再夹上一大片煎咸肉吃下去，他就美滋滋地笑了。

他钻入高大的云杉林里。林间的道路轮廓模糊，前边倒是有雪橇经过，但后来又落了一英尺厚的雪。他庆幸自己没有乘雪橇，而是轻装行进。事实上他什么也没带，只有那份用手帕包了的午餐在身上。不过，天气如此寒冷，却叫他始料未及。他感到浑身冷极了，不由得用戴着手套的手揉了揉冻麻了的鼻头和脸颊。他留着串脸胡，那胡子可以遮住脸，却遮不住髙高的颧骨，也遮不住高耸在寒风中的大鼻子。

他屁股后边跟着一只大狗，一只土生土长的爱斯基摩狗，一只地道的狼狗，灰色的皮毛，与其野狼兄弟在外表和性情上没什么区别。极度的严寒天气叫它情绪低落。它很清楚，这种天气根本不适合出门旅行。它的本能比人的判断力要灵验。实际上，此时的气温之低不仅仅是零下五十度，恐怕已超过零下六十度，乃至超过零下七十度了。此时的气温是零下七十五度。鉴于融冰点为零上三十二度，这就意味着此时为冰点以下一百零七度。对于温度计那一套，狗一无所知。也许，它对于极度严寒的天气并不具备人的那种清醒的认识，但它的本能却很管用。它感到一种模糊而不祥的忧虑，而这种忧虑在搅扰、压抑着它，使得它紧随主人身后，用质疑的目光望着主人反常的一举一动，似乎在盼望着主人赶快到营地去，或者找个地方避寒，生一堆火取暖。它知道篝火的好处，它渴望有一堆火，要不然就在雪下面挖个洞钻进去，躲开这刺骨的寒风。

它呼出的气即刻凝固成极细的霜粉，落到皮毛上，尤其是它的面颊、口鼻和睫毛上，已经被这种结晶的气体染白了。主人那红色的胡子也结上了霜，而且结得更加紧实，他每呼出一口热气，霜和冰就会增加一分。在这种情况下，他还要嚼烟叶，冰块牢牢地附着在唇边，使得他在吐出汁液后无法把下巴擦干净。结果，他的胡子成了水晶状，具有了琥珀的颜色和硬度，在下巴上变得越来越长。假如他此刻跌倒，胡子一定会像玻璃一样摔成无数碎片。但是，他对此并不在意，当地咀嚼烟草的人无不受到如此惩罚，再说他以前外出时也曾两次遇到寒潮。只不过那两次都不如这次冷，据六十英里站的酒精温度计显示，那两次的气温分别是零下五十度和零下五十五度。

他穿过平川上连绵数英里的树林一路向前，横跨一片布满系船柱的平展、宽阔的沙滩，走下一处河岸，来到了一条结了冰的小河边。这就是亨德森河。他知道他离岔口还有十英里的路。看看表，十点正。按每小时走四英里计算，他估计可在十二点半到达岔口。他决定在那儿吃午饭以示庆贺。

他摇摇晃晃地沿着河床前行，狗沮丧地耷拉着尾巴，一路紧跟着他。雪橇留下的旧痕清晰可见，但自从最后一辆雪橇驶过，车道上又落了十多英寸厚的雪。河岸边寂静一片，此处已有一个月没有见行人出现过了。他脚不停步，继续向前走去。他平时就不喜欢思考问题，此时更是如此——他一门心思要赶到岔口吃午饭，然后于六点钟抵达营地与伙计们会合，其他的事情一概不考虑。他没人说话，即便有也不可能说话，因为他的嘴上挂满了冰碴子。于是他就一个劲地嚼烟叶，使得他那琥珀色的胡须由于结冰变得越来越长。

每隔一会儿，他就会想到天气真冷，想到自己从来没有遇到过这么冷的天气。他一边走，一边用戴着手套的手背揉脸颊和鼻头，双手机械性地交替揉着。尽管如此，只要他的手一停下，脸颊照样会发麻，紧接着鼻头也会发麻。他觉得他的脸颊一定会冻坏的。他知道一定会的，心里不由后悔至极，后悔没有给帽子上安装巴德的那种防寒用的鼻带。那种鼻带遮在脸上，可以起到保护脸颊的作用。不过，有没有鼻带关系也不大。脸颊即便被冻上了，那又怎么样？只不过疼一疼罢了，不会很严重的。

他虽大脑空空，却眼观六路，注意着河道的变化，细心观察着那些弯道和树丛，每走一步都留意着脚下。一次，他绕过一个弯道时，倏然一惊，像受惊的马一样猛地倒退几步，绕开了自己一直走着的那条路。他知道这条河已经冻透——在北极的冬天，没有一条河是可以流淌的。但他也知道，有些泉水会从山坡上流下来，在白雪的覆盖下流淌在冰冻的河面上。他知道这些泉水天气再冷也不会被冻住，并深知它们的危险。它们简直是一个个陷阱——一汪汪的水在雪下面形成小水洼，大约有三英寸深，有的地方甚至深达三英尺。有时，水洼上会结半英寸厚的薄冰，而冰面上覆盖着白雪。有的水洼是一层水夹一层薄冰，人不小心踩上去，就会将一层层的冰踏碎，深陷其中，有时水深及腰。

正是因为有这种现象，他才惊得连连后退。他感到两脚在下沉，听见雪下面的薄冰发出咔嚓咔嚓的破裂声。这样冷的天气把脚弄湿，会给他带来麻烦和危险，至少会耽误他的行程。那时，他就不得不停下来生堆火，一边烤鞋袜，一边烤脚取暖。他站在那里仔细观察着河床及河岸，断定水是从右边流过来的。他思考片刻，揉了揉鼻头和脸颊，然后绕到左侧，谨小慎微地摸索着前行，每走一步都要试探着先踩一下路面。走出危险地段之后，他又嚼了几口烟叶，接着便大步流星，按照原来的那种每小时四英里的速度继续赶路了。

在随后两个小时里他又遇到了几个类似的“陷阱”。通常是覆盖在水洼上面的雪有明显的凹陷，一看就知道有危险。不过，有一次他差点掉进水中。还有一次，他怀疑有危险，便逼着狗走到前面去。狗不愿意，直朝后缩，而他推着它朝前走。无奈，狗飞快地从看似牢固的雪地上跑过，突然踏破了冰层，掉了下去。它挣扎着到达水洼边，爬上了一处结实些的地方。它的前爪和腿被水浸湿，上面的水几乎瞬间就结了冰。它急忙把腿上的冰舔掉，然后卧在雪地上开始用牙齿咬掉爪趾间的冰碴。这是一种本能的反应。如果让冰碴留在那儿，它的爪子会被冻伤。它并不了解其中的道理，只不过是受到内心深处一种神秘力量的驱动而那样做的。而那个人却是知道这个道理的，并据此做出了判断——只见他摘掉右手的手套，帮着它清理冰碴。手套摘掉没超过一分钟，他就惊讶地发觉手指很快就被冻麻了。天气真是太冷了！慌得他急忙将手套又戴上，并把手狠劲捶在胸口上以消除麻木感。

此时是十二点钟，天空一天里最明亮的时候。不过，冬天的太阳还在遥远的南方，尚未冒出地平线。在地平线与亨德森河之间，他行走的这片区域丘陵起伏，天气晴朗，但却看不到自己的影子。十二点半整，他到达了河湾的岔口。他很满意自己行走的速度，心想照此速度一定能在下午六点跟伙计们会合。他解开外套和衬衣的纽扣，取出午餐。这一举动所用的时间没超过十五秒，但就在这短暂的一瞬间，他露出的手指就被冻麻了。他没急着戴手套，双手往大腿上狠狠拍打了十多下，然后坐在一根白雪覆盖的原木上准备吃东西。这一通拍打之后，手指感到一阵剧痛，但剧痛很快又消失了，这叫他觉得意外。他简直连咬一口面包的机会都没有。他又将手指在大腿上拍打了几下，然后戴上手套，同时把另一只手露出来吃东西用。他想下嘴去咬面包，可是胡子上的冰让他咬不成。怪都怪他忘了要生火先把冰融化掉。他扑哧笑出了声，笑自己傻里傻气的。而就在他笑的时候，他注意到自己裸露的手指又开始悄然发麻了。他还注意到，他坐下时脚趾刚刚感到的刺痛，现在已经消失。真不知那是因为脚趾暖和了过来还是被冻麻了。他让脚趾在鹿皮鞋里动了动，断定它们是被冻麻了。

他慌不迭又将手套戴上，站起了身，心里觉得有点害怕。他在地上不停地跺脚，直至又产生了那种刺痛感。他心想，这鬼天气实在太冷了。硫黄湾(3)来的那个人曾说过这个地区有时候冷如冰窖，看来此言不虚。他当时还嘲笑人家呢！这说明：一个人万不能自以为是。那人说寒冷，这可是千真万确的事实。他来回踱步，又是跺脚又是抡胳膊，最后总算有了几分暖意。接下来，他取出火柴，准备生火。在身边的矮树丛里，有许多以前河面水位还高时留下的干树枝，他取来做柴火，小心点着，火势由小变大，很快就熊熊燃烧起来。他把脸上的冰烤化，在火的保护下吃了些面包。一时间，寒冷被火战胜了。狗烤着火，一副心满意足的样子。它尽量靠近火堆，同时又注意着不让火烧焦自己的皮毛。

他吃完午餐，填满了烟管，舒舒服服地抽了一会儿，然后戴上手套，让帽子的护耳紧紧罩住耳朵，沿着河道向左岔口走去。狗很失望，渴望回到篝火旁。这个人简直就不知道什么叫作寒冷。也许他祖祖辈辈就没有尝过寒冷是什么滋味，不知道什么是真正的寒冷，不知道冰点以下一百零七度的寒冷是怎么个情况。但这条狗却是知道的，它祖祖辈辈对此都一清二楚——这是一种世代相传的知识。它知道：在这种天寒地冻的时候出行有害无益；寒潮到来时，应该挖个雪洞躲进去，直至空中寒云散开才出来(4)。不过，这条狗和这个人之间的关系并不是十分亲密。它只不过是他的奴隶罢了，它所受到的唯一的关爱就是鞭打，要不然就是听到主人威吓它，发出啪啪的抽鞭子的声音。所以，它无心也无意把内心的担忧传达给主人。它渴望回到篝火旁，并非为主人的安危着想，而是为了它自身考虑。可是，主人吹了声口哨，啪啪啪地模仿了几声抽鞭子的声音，吓得它只好乖乖跟在他的后边，又踏上了行程。

他嚼了一些烟叶，胡子又变成了琥珀色，呼出的湿气很快化为白色粉末，落到胡须、眉毛和睫毛上。亨德森河左边支流上的暗泉似乎并不多见，他走了半小时也没有察觉到任何踪迹。接着，祸从天降。他来到一处，并没有看见泉水，只看得见平展、柔软的白雪，好像下面是坚实的冰，却一脚踩进了水里。水不深，他急忙跳到了坚实的冰面上，然而膝部以下还是被水浸湿了。

他怒不可遏，大骂自己倒了血霉。他原指望六点钟赶到营地跟朋友们会合，这下可得耽误一个小时了，因为他必须生火烤干鞋袜。气温如此之低，生火很有必要，他非常清楚这一点，于是转身要去岸上，只能爬过去。岸上的灌木丛里有一些和之前一样的干柴，缠结在几棵小云杉树的树干上——主要是细枝细条，但也有大一些的枝条和去年的细干草。他把几根粗大一些的树枝丢到雪地上，垫在下面，以免最初的小火被融化的雪水浸灭。随后，他从衣袋里取出一小块桦树皮，擦了火柴把它点燃。桦树皮甚至比纸燃烧得还快。他把它放在柴堆上，再添上一把把干草和极为细小的干枝。

他深知自己身处险境，生火时十分当心，动作缓慢。火势渐渐加大，他添加的树枝也越来越粗。他蹲在雪地上，把绞缠在灌木丛中的树枝一根根抽出来，直接添进火里。他知道自己只能成功不能失败。当气温在零下七十五度时，要生火，是容不得失败的（这是指在鞋袜被水浸湿的情况下）。如果鞋袜是干的，即使火没生着，他还可以跑上半英里，让血液流动起来就是了。可在零下七十五度时，对于又湿又冻的脚，血液是不可能恢复循环的。无论他跑得多快，湿脚也只会被冻得更厉害。

对这些情况，他是非常清楚的。硫黄湾的那个老江湖去年秋天曾给他分享过经验，此刻他对那一番指点心存感激。他的脚已完全失去了知觉。为了生火他不得不取下手套，结果手指很快便冻麻了。他以每小时四英里的速度赶路时，心脏将血液输送到体表以及身体的各个部位。但一停下来，血液的输送就放缓了。太空的寒潮袭击着毫无保护的地球的顶端(5)，而他身处这一区域，正承受着那寒潮的强大的冲击。他体内的血液在寒潮面前畏首畏尾，虽然像那只狗一样仍具有生命力，但也像狗一样唯恐避而不及，恨不得找个地缝钻进去，以躲过这可怕的寒冷。只要他以每小时四英里的速度走起来，血液便可以输送到体表，而现在，血液却像潮水一般，慢慢退去了，退到了身体的某个幽深之处。最先有失血感觉的是他的四肢。虽然还没有完全冻僵，但他湿脚的冻伤在加剧，裸露出的手指也越冻越麻。他的鼻子和脸颊都快冻成了冰块，皮肤因失血而变得冰冷。

不过，他尚无丧命之忧。脚趾、鼻子和脸颊只不过稍微挨冻而已，篝火已经越烧越旺了。他把手指般粗细的树枝添进火里，不一会儿就可以添入手腕粗细的树枝了。那时他便可脱去鞋袜，一边把它们烤干，一边把光着的脚烤暖和——当然，烤脚之前，先要用雪把它们擦一遍。火算是生着了，他算是安全了。想起硫黄湾那个老江湖的话，他不由微微一笑。那老兄曾语气郑重地说，气温到了零下五十度，谁也别指望能独身一人穿过克朗代克河(6)流域。他这不是来了吗？路上遇到过危险，他单枪匹马地克服，最终活了下来。他不以为然地觉得，那些老江湖中有的人未免有些娘儿们气了。一个人只要下定决心，就能够成功。只要你是个英雄汉，独身走路算什么！不过，让他感到意外的是，他的脸颊和鼻子冻僵的速度竟如此之快。他也没想到自己的手指会在这么短的时间失去知觉。由于手指没有了活力，他几乎无法用它们抓取树枝——那些手指就好像脱离了他的躯体，脱离了他本人。他摸到树枝时，不得不先看看是不是用手抓住了——那树枝其实就在他的指间。

这一切都算不了什么。反正火已经生着了，在毕毕剥剥地燃烧，每一个跳动的火苗都给人以生的希望。他开始解鞋带。鹿皮鞋上结了一层冰，齐膝长的厚厚的德国袜子冻得简直成了铁板一块，而鞋带则像淬过火，成了麻花状的铁条纠缠在一起。他摸索着用麻木的手指解鞋带，后来意识到这是无用的愚蠢之举，便从刀鞘里将刀抽了出来。

可是，他还没来得及用刀割断鞋带，祸事就发生了。怪只怪他自己处理不当，或者说他犯了一个错误。他本来就不该在云杉树下生火，他应该把火生在空地上。当初只图方便——在云杉树下，可以从树丛中抽出细枝，直接投入火里。岂不知就在这棵云杉树上，积雪压弯了树枝。几个星期没刮过风，每一个枝杈上都堆着厚厚的雪。每次他抽取枝条，云杉树就会微微一颤——那种颤动极其轻微，他难以察觉，但是足以导致灾难的发生。在这棵树的高处，一根树杈上的积雪掉了下来，砸在了下边的树杈上，结果引起连锁反应，面积越来越广，最终导致整棵树上的积雪纷纷掉落，像雪崩一样，猛地砸向他的后背，盖在了篝火上，一下子就把火压灭了！刚才还是一堆熊熊燃烧的火，这当儿只剩杂乱的白雪铺地，一片狼藉。

他慌了神，就好像刚刚听到了死刑判决书，呆呆地坐在那里，痴痴望着刚才还篝火熊熊的地方。后来，他稳定住了情绪。看来，硫黄湾的那个老江湖所言不差。哪怕路上有一个人跟他结伴而行，他也不至于陷入这样的险境。遇见这种情况，同伴可以为他把火生着。这下子他得靠自己再次生火了，而这一次是容不得失手的。即便把火生着了，他也有很大的可能会冻坏几根脚趾。此刻，他的脚大概已严重冻伤，而把火再次生着还需要一些时间。

他心里转着这些念头，不过他并不是耽于思考、坐以待毙，而是一边想一边行动着。他又为篝火铺了一个基架——这次是在空地上，不用担心树上掉雪砸灭火苗。然后，他从泉水冲来的杂物中找到一些干草和细枝。在这一过程，他手指动弹不得，只能用两个手掌去抽取。这样，他搞到了许多腐枝和绿苔，并非理想的燃料，但也只能凑合着用了。他有条不紊地准备着，还弄来一抱粗一些的树枝，准备等火旺之后添入。这段时间，狗始终卧在那里观望，眼里充满了渴望——它指望着他提供篝火，可是那火却迟迟生不着。

一切准备妥当后，他把手伸进衣袋，打算再取出一块桦树皮来。他知道桦树皮就在那儿，虽然手指没有了感觉，但摸索时可以听见桦树皮在窸窣作响。他使出了吃奶的力气，却无法用手抓牢它。此时，他一直意识清楚，知道自己脚上的冻伤每时每刻都在加重。这一意识让他深陷恐惧之中，但他与之搏斗，竭力保持镇静。他用牙齿叼起手套戴在手上，然后前后甩胳膊，双手用力拍打身子两边。活动时，他时而坐下，时而站起。狗自始至终卧在雪地上观看，狼一般的尾巴卷起来盖在前爪上取暖，支棱着野狼似的尖耳朵。主人又是拍打手，又是甩胳膊，见狗天然一身皮毛，暖和、安然地卧在那儿，突然感到一阵强烈的忌妒。

过了一会儿，他那麻木的手指开始隐隐约约有了一丝感觉，先是感到微微有点疼痛，继而疼痛感加剧，最后成了针扎一般的剧痛。而他却高兴得喊出了声。他摘下右手的手套掏出桦树皮，而露出的手指又很快被冻麻了。接下来，他掏出了一束硫黄火柴。但是，严寒此时已将他所有的手指都冻僵了。他竭力想把其中的一根火柴和其他的火柴分开，却把整整一束火柴掉在了雪地上。他试图捡起来，结果没有成功——冻僵的手指无法伸屈，也无法抓住物体。他的一举一动都谨小慎微，早已顾不上冰冷的脚、鼻头和脸颊，全部注意力均放在了火柴上。捡火柴时，他靠的是视觉而非触觉；当看见手指伸到了那束火柴的两边时，他便把它们合拢——其实，那仅是他的一种意愿，因为火柴虽近在眼前，手指却不听使唤。他又将手套戴回到了右手上，在膝盖上猛地拍打一番。接下来，他用两只戴着手套的手把那束火柴捧起，连带着许多雪，放在了膝头上。可是，情况并未有所改善。

费了九牛二虎之力，他总算用两只手掌的掌根再次捧起那束火柴，将其送至嘴边。接着，他一用劲张开嘴，只听见脸上结的冰咔嚓咔嚓地断裂开来。然后，他下颚内收，翘起上嘴唇，用上齿碰了一下那束火柴，想从中分离出一根来。结果，他大功告成，一根火柴落在了他的膝头。但事情却没有因此出现转机——他无法将这根火柴捡起来。这时他灵机一动，就用牙齿叼起火柴，在腿上划了划，划了有二十次才算划着了。随即，他用牙叼着燃烧的火柴去点那块桦树皮。可是燃烧的硫黄气钻入鼻孔和肺里，刺激得他一阵阵咳嗽。火柴则落到雪地上熄灭了。

一阵绝望的情绪袭来，他努力控制着这种情绪，心想那位硫黄湾的老江湖所说的话果然句句真实，零下五十度时出行，的确需要有个旅伴。他又用劲拍打手，而这次却没能产生任何感觉。突然，他不管三七二十一，用牙齿扯下手套，露出两手，将那束火柴夹在两个掌根之间——由于胳膊上的肌肉尚未冻伤，手掌根还能用得上劲。随后，他把那束火柴在大腿上划了一下。剌啦一声，火柴点燃了。七十根硫黄火柴全都点燃了！四处无风，不用担心火柴会被风吹灭。他把头偏向一边，避开令人窒息的硫黄味，用燃烧的火柴去点桦树皮。这时，他感到手上有烧灼的疼痛感。他手上的肉在燃烧，鼻子可以闻得到，内心深处也能感受得到。疼痛感在加剧，变成了撕心裂肺的痛。他咬牙忍受，笨拙地把燃烧的火柴凑近桦树皮，可是由于他的手也在燃烧，老碍事，把大部分火焰都吸掉了。桦树皮并没有轻易就点着。

最后，他疼得实在无法忍受，便猛地将两个掌根分开了。那束熊熊燃烧的火柴刺啦一声掉进了雪里，幸好桦树皮已被点着。他开始把干草和细枝添到火里。他不能用手去捡拾，只能用两个掌根夹取。枝条上沾着小块的腐木和绿苔，他就用牙齿尽量剔除掉。他小心翼翼地保护着火苗，动作很是笨拙。火意味着生命，万不能叫它熄灭。由于血液供不到体表，冷得他开始发抖，行动愈加困难。一大块绿苔掉下来，不偏不倚正好压在了小火堆上。他急忙用手指去捅，想把绿苔捅开，却因为浑身发抖，捅得过了头，捅乱了小火堆，结果使那些燃烧的干草和细枝散落一地。他试图再次把它们聚拢，并付出了巨大努力，然而由于全身抖得厉害，燃烧的枝条散而难聚。一根根枝条冒了一阵黑烟，末了全都熄灭了。这个生火的人彻底失败了。他漠然地看看周围，不经意把目光落在了狗的身上——那只狗卧在熄灭了的火堆的另一侧雪地上，不安地弓起身子，时而微微抬起一只前爪，然后又抬起另一只，身子来回蠕动，露出渴望和急切的神情。

一看见狗，他心里顿时起了一个疯狂的念头。他想起了一个传说，说的是一个人路遇暴风雪，于是杀死一头公牛，自己钻进牛的尸体里侥幸活了下来。他要把狗杀死，要将双手伸进狗那暖和的体内，直到麻木感消失，然后他就能再生一堆火了。主意拿定，他开始对狗说话，唤它到跟前来。可是，他的声音有点古怪，使狗觉得害怕，因为它以前从未听过主人以这种腔调说过话。这种情况有些蹊跷。它多疑的天性令它感到了危险，虽然并不知是什么危险，但它的内心却对主人生起了一种莫名的恐惧。听见主人的声音，它耳朵耷拉了下来，愈加焦虑不安地蠕动着身子，两只前爪一上一下倒换得更加厉害了，就是不肯到主人跟前去。他跪下身子，向狗爬去。这异常的姿势再次使狗起了疑心，它谨慎地躲开了。

他坐直身子，在雪地上坐了一会儿，努力想恢复平静。随后，他靠牙齿的帮助戴上手套，站了起来。他先朝脚下瞧瞧，看看自己是不是真的站了起来——他的双脚失去了知觉，似乎与地面两不相干。他的这种直立的姿势逐渐驱散了狗内心的疑虑。接着，他用专横的语气命令狗，啪啪啪地发出了狗鞭抽打的声音，唤醒了狗素有的忠诚，于是它走了过来。当它走到伸手可及的地方时，主人按捺不住，猛地伸开双臂扑了过去。这时他大吃一惊，发现自己的双手已无法抓住狗，手指不能弯曲也没有感觉。他一时竟忘了他的手已冻伤，而且伤情越来越严重。说时迟那时快，未等狗逃开，他将它死死锁在自己的怀里，搂住它不放，一屁股坐在了雪地上，而狗在一个劲地嗥叫、哀鸣和挣扎。

不过，他也只能将狗锁在怀里坐在雪地上，别无良策。他意识到自己是杀不死狗的，对此他只能干瞪眼空着急。他的两只手毫无用处，既不能拔出刀来将狗刺死，也无法掐死它。最后只好放它走了。狗儿噌的发疯似的跑了，夹着尾巴，嘴里尖声号叫着。它跑了有四十英尺远，停下来好奇地打量着他，两只耳朵直竖起来。而他低头望着自己的双手，想看看它们在什么地方，发现它们吊在胳膊的末端。他觉得这种现象真是奇怪——一个人竟然必须用眼睛观察，才知道自己的手在何处。他前后使劲甩胳膊，在身子的两侧狠狠拍打戴着手套的手。这套动作很剧烈，他做了有五分钟的样子，心脏总算把足够的血液输送到了体表，使他不再打哆嗦了。可是双手仍无知觉。他有一种模糊的感觉，觉得两只手就像重物一样悬挂在手臂末端，但当他试图驱散这种感觉时，他却无法再感知到了。

一种对死亡的畏惧感缓慢地朝他袭来。这种畏惧感很快变得非常强烈。他意识到这不仅仅是冻坏手指脚趾或失去手脚的问题了，而是生死攸关的问题，而他胜算不大。这叫他惊恐万分，于是他转身跑上河床，沿着那条古老、印迹模糊的小径飞奔。狗也跑了起来，寸步不离地跟着他。他茫无目的地瞎跑，一生中从来都没有如此害怕过。他深一脚浅一脚在雪地里狼狈前行，慢慢恢复了理智，看到了河岸、旧木堆、光秃的白杨和天空。奔跑使他感觉好了些，身上不再打哆嗦了。这么跑下去，或许他的脚也会解冻。假如能往远处跑，就能抵达营地跟伙计们会合。他无疑会失掉部分手指、脚趾，脸也会冻坏，但伙计们会照料他，把剩余的手指和脚趾保住。与此同时，他心里也产生了一种不祥的想法，认为根本别指望能到达营地跟伙计们会合了——路程太远，他又被冻伤了，伤情太严重，他很快就会被冻成冰棍，一命呜呼的。他把这种不祥的想法置之脑后，不去想它。有时它自己涌上前来，非要引起他的注意，而他又把它推回去，竭力去想别的事情。

让他感到奇怪的是，他的双脚已经完全冻麻，甚至连接触地面和承受身体的重量也察觉不到了，可就是这样一双脚竟然还能跑。他觉得自己好像在贴着地面飞行，好像并没有与地面接触。他曾在某个地方见过一幅带翅膀的墨丘利(7)的画，心想墨丘利贴着地面飞行时，大概就和他现在的感觉一样。

他一口气跑到营地跟伙计们会合的计划是有漏洞的，那就是他缺乏耐力。他跌跌绊绊、踉踉跄跄，最后，一个趔趄瘫倒在了地上。他竭力想爬起来，却失败了。他决定先坐着休息休息。等再次站起来时，他将缓步走，持续不断地朝前走。正当他坐着缓气时，突然感到暖洋洋的，十分舒服。他不再发抖了，甚至觉得有一股暖流涌到了胸口，涌遍了全身。然而，他触了触鼻子和脸颊，那儿一点感觉也没有。奔跑是不能让那儿解冻的，也不能让手脚解冻。这时，他想到自己身体被冻伤的部位会越来越多。他极力把这想法压下去，把它忘掉，极力去想别的事情。他觉得这种想法会造成恐慌，而他最怕的就是恐慌。可是，这想法老是冒出来，坚决不肯离去，最后导致他脑子里出现了一种幻觉，仿佛看见自己全身冻成了一个冰块。这叫他简直无法忍受，于是他又在小径上狂奔起来。他一度放慢脚步，可是一想到身体冻伤的部分在扩大，就又向前奔跑。

这段时间，狗一直寸步不离地跟着他。他第二次倒地时，它就在他前面卧下，卷起尾巴盖在前爪上，样子好奇、热切又关心。见它一副暖和安然的神情，他气得不得了，开口就骂，骂得它顺从地耷拉下了耳朵。此时，他浑身发抖，这次抖得更厉害了。他正在输掉这场跟严寒展开的斗争。严寒从四面八方袭来，钻进他的体内。他怕得再一次挣扎着前行，但没跑到一百英尺，就摇摇晃晃一头栽倒在地上。这是他最后一次产生恐慌感了。待喘过气，恢复平静后，他坐起来，心里出现了一个念头，想要不失尊严地迎接死亡。不过，这一念头并没有使他觉得有什么尊严，他倒觉得自己在冒傻气，就像一只头被剁掉还四处瞎跑的鸡——他心里想到的就是这种比喻。去他妈的，反正都是个死，还不如死得体面一些。他内心又获得了平静，随之而至的是一种昏昏欲睡的感觉。在睡梦中死去，这倒是一种很好的死法。这感觉就像是被麻醉了一般。看来，被冻死并不像人们想的那么糟。比这更糟的死法多着呢。

他想象着伙计们第二天发现他的尸体时的情景。突然，他胡思乱想起来，觉得自己跟那些人在一起顺着小径寻来，要找到他自己的尸体。他夹在那些人中间，拐了个弯，发现他自己躺在雪地上。他的灵魂已脱离躯体，仿佛变成了另外一个人，正和伙计们一起望着躺在雪地里的自己。他心想这鬼天气真是太冷了，回美国后，可以给人们讲一讲什么叫作真正的严寒。他神游他方，仿佛看到了硫黄湾的那个老江湖，而且看得清清楚楚，看见老江湖在暖暖和和、舒舒服服地抽烟袋。

“你说得很对，老人家，你说得很对。”他喃喃地对着硫黄湾的那个老江湖说。

他昏昏然睡着了，觉得这恐怕是他平生最舒服、最甜蜜的一觉了。狗卧在他面前，等着他睡醒。白昼很快过去，随即是漫长的黄昏。狗看不到有任何要生火的迹象。它从未见过一个人会一直坐在雪地里，连火也不生。暮色悄然降临，它渴望烤火，有些急不可耐，前爪一上一下动个不停，嘴里呜呜地轻声哀鸣，后来可能觉得会挨骂，耳朵耷拉了下来。可是，主人一声未吭。它提高了哀鸣声，最后爬到了主人跟前，嗅到了死亡的气息。顿时，它全身的毛竖起来，连连后退。它待了一会儿，冲着天空汪汪乱叫——此时的天上群星闪耀，一颗颗星星在发光、跳动。末了，它朝着自己所熟悉的营地的方向跑去，那儿会有别的主人为它提供食物和火。

————————————————————

(1) 阿拉斯加州一小镇。

(2) 此处用的是华氏度。根据华氏度，在标准大气压下，冰的熔点为32度，水的沸点为212度。

(3) 印第安河流域的三角洲。

(4) 北极地区冬季的严寒，造成含微粒云团在空中悬浮久久不散。

(5) 此处指北极。

(6) 育空河的支流。

(7) 罗马神话中诸神的信使。

黄金谷

此处是峡谷的绿色心脏，布局呆板的崖壁一到此处便豁然开朗，一改粗犷的格调，构成了一个封闭的小天地，每个角落都荡漾着甜蜜、丰实及柔情的气息。这儿的万物都在休养生息。连狭窄、汹涌的山涧也如被缰绳收住的野马，水流变得绵长起来，最后形成了一潭静静的清水。一只红色的公鹿低垂着它那多角的头，半闭着眼睛，站在齐膝深的水里打盹。

在水潭的一侧，也就是入水口的那个地方，有一小片草地，那凉爽、生命力旺盛的绿丛一直延伸到险峻的崖壁脚下。离水潭远一些的地方有一个土坡，坡度平缓，与对面的崖壁相连。坡上青草悠悠，花木繁茂，到处姹紫嫣红，一簇簇橘红色、绛紫色，还有金黄色的花。坡下的峡谷是个封闭的世界，外边是看不到的。两边的峭壁突然向一处靠拢，峡谷的尽头乱石嶙峋，青苔铺地，隐没于一片绿茵茵的藤葛、爬山虎和杂树之中。峡谷两旁层峦叠嶂，远处大山的山麓松林遍布。再往远处，清真寺尖塔般的山峰常年积雪，白皑皑的，宛若天边的白云，亮晃晃地反射着太阳的光辉。

峡谷里没有灰尘。树叶和花瓣洁净无瑕。青草似刚织成的天鹅绒一般。水潭边有三棵白杨树，在这静谧的空气中，树上的杨絮飘落，就像白白的绒毛。土坡上，带有酒香的石兰灌木的花朵使空气里充满春天的气息，而那经验丰富的叶片却开始垂直卷起，准备迎接即将来到的夏季干旱。在土坡空旷的地带，在石兰灌木未蔓延到的地方，百合花迎风摆动，就像许多暂作休息的彩蛾，颤抖着，时刻准备再次振翅高飞。斑斓闪烁的浆果鹃遍布四处，眼见它们的枝干就要由豆绿变成茜红，一大串一大串的花朵似蜡制的铃铛，散发着馥郁的芬芳。这种花呈乳白色，形似幽谷百合，芳香四溢，散发着春天的气息。

一丝风也没有，空气浓香醉人。如果空气凝重、潮湿，这种芳香可能会叫人觉得甜得发腻。不过，这儿的空气清爽、轻盈，犹如星光融入大气，浸透了阳光的温暖和花的芬芳。

偶尔会有一只蝴蝶飞来，穿梭于斑驳的光影之间。四周回响着山蜂那低沉的、令人昏昏欲睡的嗡嗡声——这些采花吮蜜的饕餮之徒，你推我搡地争先觅食，倒是一团和气，根本无暇诉诸武力。小溪涓涓流淌，蜿蜒穿过峡谷，静悄悄的，只偶尔发出轻微的汩汩声。这种水声很像一个人昏昏欲睡时的低语，困劲一上来就停了，困劲一过去就又提高了音量。

在这个峡谷的中心，一切都在轻盈地飘荡着。阳光和蝴蝶在树丛中飘进飘出。蜜蜂的嗡嗡声和小溪的低语也在飘动。飘来荡去的声音和色彩交织在一起，织出了一张细密、无形的网，而这就是主宰此处一切的精神。那是一种追求平静的精神，静而不死，蕴含着平稳搏动的生命，安静却不沉寂，活泼却不突兀。它并不激烈，没有争斗及艰辛，而是一份安恬，充满了勃勃生机。这儿的精神是和平生活的精神，沉湎于安逸，满足于眼前的繁荣，对于远方传来的战争谣言无动于衷。

那只多角的红色公鹿受到这种精神的支配，站在树荫遮蔽的没膝深的水里打盹。那儿甚至连只打搅它的苍蝇都没有。它显得懒洋洋的。有时，小溪一觉睡醒，发出几声低语，它会抖动抖动耳朵，但仍然懒洋洋的，因为它知道小溪可能是怀疑它睡着了，发发牢骚而已。

突然，这只公鹿竖起了耳朵，紧张起来，好像听到了什么声音，急切地要弄清那是什么声音。它转过头，面朝峡谷，翕动着灵敏的鼻子嗅着空气。它的目光无法穿透小溪贯穿其中的那道绿色屏障，但它的耳朵却听到了人的声音——那是一阵歌声，声音坚实、单调。接着，它又听到了金属碰击岩石发出的刺耳的声音。听见这声音，它突然一惊，打了个响鼻，纵身一跳，从水中跳到了草地上，站在天鹅绒一般的小草上，竖起耳朵，又嗅了嗅空气。接着，它静悄悄地走过这一小片草地，中途停了停，又侧耳听了听，随即便从峡谷里消失了，像个幽灵一样，脚步轻盈，一点声音都没有。

钉着铁掌的鞋跟碰击岩石发出的刺耳的声音又响了起来。那个人的声音变得越来越大。那是一首颂歌，由于渐渐接近，声音愈加清晰，连歌词也能听得清了：

回过头来，转过你的脸，
看一看那美轮美奂的小山，
（罪恶，罪恶，叫人轻看！）
瞧瞧周围，把周围看一看，
快将罪恶的包袱抛到一边。
（说不定今晨就会遇见上帝！）

伴随歌声传来的是踢踏踢踏爬山的声音。随着红色公鹿的悄然消失，峡谷里宁静的气氛也荡然无存了。那道绿色的屏障突然被破开，一个人探出头来，瞧了瞧这儿的草地、水潭和斜坡。他属于那种从容不迫的人。只见他打量一眼四周的环境，然后细细察看一草一木，看看和自己最初的印象是否相符。到了最后——也就是把一切都看清楚之后，他才开了口，用生动的语言由衷赞叹道：

“好一个洞天福地，真是人间仙境！看看这山山水水、花花草草，真是美不胜收！这简直是淘金者的乐园！卡尤塞人(1)的天堂！眼睛累了，这凉爽的绿色可以缓解疲劳！这儿用不上那种包治百病的粉红色药丸(2)，完全是一片秘密的绿洲，专为淘金者而设，让他们疲倦的双脚得到休息。真他妈的棒！”

他沙色皮肤，一脸和气和幽默——这两点是他脸上最明显的特征。这张脸表情丰富，随着心情和思绪迅速发生改变。因而，他在想什么便一目了然。由于心潮起伏，他脸上也潮水涌动，犹如一阵阵风掠过湖面。他的头发稀稀拉拉，乱蓬蓬的，发色跟肤色相仿，都淡得说不准是什么颜色。只有他的眼睛蓝得惊人，仿佛他身上所有的颜色都注入了这双眼睛。这双眼睛笑吟吟的，充满了快乐，颇有几分孩童的天真和好奇在里面，而同时，这双眼睛里还隐约透露出一种靠人生阅历磨炼出来的沉着自信和刚强坚毅。

从藤葛和爬山虎构成的那道绿色屏障后边，他先将一把矿工用的锄头、一把铲子和一个淘金盘扔了出来，然后自己也跟着爬出，来到了这片空地上。他下身穿着一条褪色的工装裤，上身套着一件黑布衬衫，脚上蹬着一双钉着平头钉的皮靴，头戴一顶不成样子的脏帽子，一看就知道它历经风吹雨打、日晒烟熏。他直直地站在那里，睁大眼睛看着这片与世隔绝的天地，鼻翼愉悦地翕动着，尽情呼吸着峡谷乐园里馨香的空气。他的眼睛笑得眯成了一条蓝色的缝，脸上乐开了花，咧着嘴在笑。只听他大声喊道：

“看这随风摇曳的蒲公英和快乐的蜀葵，真是芳香扑鼻！说什么玫瑰香油和科隆香水，和这里的花香一比，可就太逊色了！”

他有个自言自语的习惯。尽管他面部表情变化很快，能够反映出内里的心情和思绪，但他的舌头还是不甘落后，总是要把他的心情和思绪再复述一遍，就像博斯威尔(3)再世。

他趴在水潭的入水口处开始痛饮，一口接一口，饮了很长时间。“味道真好！”他喃喃赞叹道，一边抬起头，目光掠过水面望着山坡，一边用手背抹了抹嘴。谁知山坡引起了他的注意。他仍趴在那儿，仔细地研究了很久山的结构。他那经验丰富的眼睛将目光从山坡移向岩块剥落的崖壁，再转回来，移到水潭边。随后，他爬起身，把山坡又观察了一遍。

“这地方看起来不错。”他末了说了一句，随手拎起了他的锄头、铲子和淘金盘。

他走到水潭的下边，踩着一块块石头轻巧地跨过小溪，然后在靠近水边的山坡上挖了一铲土放到淘金盘里。随即，他蹲下身子，双手捧着盘子，将盘子的一半浸入溪水中，接下来就灵巧地来回转动它，让水流进泥沙，再流出去。比较大、比较轻的砂土粒浮到了上面来，他熟练地将盘子一歪，就把这些砂土粒漂出去了。有时，为了加快速度，他就把盘子放稳，用手拣出大石子和碎石。

盘子里的东西减少得很快，后来只剩下了细泥和极小的砂粒。到了这一步，他就淘得非常细腻和精心了。这是细淘。他越淘越细致，用眼睛仔细观察，用手细之又细、一丝不苟地挑拣。末了，盘子里似乎只剩下了水，别无其他。不过，他敏捷地把盘子转了半圈，让盘子里的水从浅浅的边沿流入小溪里，然后就发现盘底有一层黑砂。这是薄薄的一层黑砂，薄得像黑颜料留下的一丝痕迹。他凑近细心一看，发现里面含有一粒小小的金砂。他把盘子的边向下一压，让一点溪水流进来，又猛地一晃，使水冲刷盘底，把那些黑砂粒冲来冲去的。总算没有白费力气，他又发现了一粒小小的金砂。

此时的淘砂精益求精，其精细程度已完全超过了寻常的淘砂程序。他一点一点地把黑砂漂到盘子的浅边外面。每漂一次，他都要把黑砂一粒粒逐个检查一遍，然后才让其漂出去。他睁圆双眼，让这些黑砂一点一点地滑出去。突然，盘子边上出现了一粒只有针尖大的金砂。他让水倒流，那粒金砂也回到了盘底。以这样的方式，他又发现了一粒，接着又是一粒。他谨小慎微地看顾着这些金砂，宛若牧羊人放牧羊群，不让任何一粒流失。最后，一盘子的泥土都让水冲走了，只剩下了几粒金砂。他数了数，然后一扬手，竟然把盘子里他辛苦了半天淘出的金砂连同最后的一点水全泼掉了。

不过，他站起身时，一双蓝眼睛却熠熠闪光，里面充满了欲望。“七粒。”他出声咕哝道，念叨了一遍他千辛万苦淘出来，却又随手丢掉的金砂粒的数目。“七粒。”他又念叨了一遍，语气凝重，仿佛要将这个数目留在记忆里。

他静静地在那儿站了很久，观望着那片山坡，目光好奇、热烈。他异常兴奋，就像是一只猎犬敏锐地嗅到了猎物的气味。

他沿着小溪向下游走了几步，又铲了一盘泥土。

又是一番细淘，他谨小慎微地收集着淘出来的金砂，数过之后又全都泼进了溪水里。

“五粒。”他咕哝道，随后又重复了一遍。

他不由得又观察了几眼小山，沿着小溪向下游再走几步，又铲了一盘土。就这样，他不断淘着金砂，金砂的数量在持续减少。“四粒，三粒，两粒，两粒，一粒。”——他向下游走着，脑子里列出了一张金砂数目表。后来，一盘土只淘得出一粒金砂了，这时他便停下来，用干树枝生起一堆火。接着，他把淘金盘放进火里烧，直至将其烧成蓝黑色。之后，他拿起盘子，很挑剔地检查了一遍，才满意地点了点头。这种底色的盘子，里面哪怕有再小的黄点也逃不过他的眼睛。

他继续向小溪的下游走了几步，又淘了一盘，结果仅淘到一粒金砂。第三盘竟一无所获。他没有因此而止步，每隔一英尺，便挖上几铲土，又连着淘了三盘。结果盘盘皆空。这没有叫他气馁，反而让他感到高兴。他越是淘不着，就越喜悦盈怀，最后只见他站起身来，喜不自胜地大叫一声：

“要是在这里挖不到金子，就让上帝用酸苹果砸掉我的脑袋好啦！”

他回到出发点，向着小溪的上游开始一盘盘地淘。最初，金砂的数量在增加，增加得很快。“十四粒，十八粒，二十一粒，二十六粒。”——他在脑子里又列出了一张金砂数目表。在水潭的上边，他的收获达到了鼎盛，一盘淘出了二十五粒金砂。

“这么多，丢掉真可惜。”他一边让水把金砂冲走，一边惋惜地说。

太阳已经升到了天空的最高处，他仍在苦干不休。他逆流而上，一盘一盘地淘着，淘出的金砂数量在持续减少。

“太棒啦，越来越少了！”当一盘土只淘出一粒金砂时，他兴高采烈地叫道。后来，一连几盘，颗粒无收，他便直起腰，满怀信心地向山坡上望了一眼。

“哈哈！黄金先生！”他大声叫喊道，就好像在对藏在山坡上的什么人讲话似的，“哈哈！黄金先生！我来啦！我来啦！我一定会抓住你的！你听见了没有，黄金先生？我一定会抓住你的，就像老鹰抓小鸡一样！”

他转身来，抬头望了一眼那万里无云的蓝天上高悬着的太阳，然后顺着刚才淘金时挖出来的那些土坑信步走去。走到水潭的下边，他跨过小溪，钻到那道绿色屏障后面不见了。此时，若想恢复这个地方原来的那种宁静、安闲的气氛已经不太可能——他大着嗓门在唱拉格泰姆风格的曲子，仍然让歌声主宰着整个峡谷。

过了一会儿，他又回来了，铁钉鞋踏在石头上咯噔咯噔响，声音比上一次还要大。那道绿色屏障激烈地晃动起来，哗啦哗啦地来回摇摆着。丁零哐啷，一阵金属的摩擦碰撞。他的声音传来，调门更高了，换上了一种严厉呵斥的口气。似有一个庞然大物冲过来，呼哧呼哧喘着粗气。只听一阵噼里啪啦的树枝断裂声，但见树叶纷纷落地，随即有一匹马从绿色屏障后冲了出来。它驮着一个行李包，包袱上挂着一条条被扯断的藤蔓和爬山虎。这只动物见自己置身于如此一番景色之中，不由得惊讶万分，四处张望，之后便垂下头来，心满意足地吃起了草。接着，又有一匹马跌跌撞撞地冲了过来，踩在布满青苔的石头上蹄下一打滑，后来落到松软的草地上才稳住了身体。它背上有一副高鞍头的墨西哥式马鞍，由于用久了，已经褪色，破破烂烂的，马背上没有人。

他跟在最后边，立稳脚跟，卸下行李和马鞍，看好了露宿的地方，随即解开缰绳，放两匹马去吃草。接着，他解开粮袋，拿出一个平底锅和一个咖啡壶，拾来一抱干柴，用几块石头垒了一个生火的地方。

“哎哟哟！”他叫了一声，“我肚子饿极啦，简直能吞下一头牛。给我两个人的饭，我也照样吃得下去。”

他直起腰，将手伸进工装裤的口袋里取火柴，同时目光越过水潭投向那个山坡。他已经抓到了火柴盒，可是指头一松，把空手抽了出来。他明显有些犹豫不决，瞧瞧准备好了的烹调食物，再瞧瞧那个山坡。

“看来我得杀个回马枪，再去瞧瞧。”他末了说道，迈出步子准备跨过小溪。

“这么做没有什么道理，”他辩解似的咕哝道，“但也不过就是晚一个小时吃饭，饿不死的。”

在距离第一次铲土淘金起点处几英尺的地方，他又开辟了第二条淘金路线。日落西山，投下的影子变长了，而他仍在不停地干着。后来，他又开辟了第三条路线，继续淘着。这样，顺着山坡而上，他横向辟出了一条又一条的淘金路线，每条线的中点淘出的金砂最多，而两端却一无所获。越是往上走，这些线就越短。淘金线在不断缩短，形成了一种规律——以此看来，当线短得不能再短时，到头来便会聚成一个点。这种排列构成一个倒写的“V”字。这个“V”字向里收缩的两边，就是金砂分布的边界。

显而易见，他的目的是找到这个“V”字的顶点。他时不时会瞄一眼“V”字的两条斜边，再望望坡上，竭力想确定那个顶点的方位——那儿就是金砂的尽头。在那里，居住着“黄金先生”（他总是这样亲热地称呼坡上那个想象中的掘金点）。他大声吆喝着：

“快出来吧，黄金先生！还是识相点，乖乖给我出来吧！”

“那好吧，”他补充了一句，语气显得很坚定，接着就信誓旦旦地威胁道，“咱就骑驴看唱本，走着瞧。我早晚都会找到你，把你这个缩头乌龟揪出来。不把你揪出来，就不是英雄好汉！”

每铲一盘土，他都要端到小溪边淘洗。越往坡顶走，盘子里淘出来的金砂就越多。后来，他舍不得扔了，便将金砂收集起来，装在他原来随随便便塞在裤子后袋里的一个装发酵粉的空铁罐里。他只顾埋头苦干，没注意到夜幕已在慢慢降临。直到怎么也辨别不出盘底的金砂了，他才意识到时间已过去了很久。他猛地直起腰来，脸上显出一副诧异和惊讶的表情，带着拖腔说：

“真是活见鬼，我把午饭都忘记吃了！”

他深一脚浅一脚地摸黑跨过小溪，将耽搁已久的火生着。这顿晚饭吃的是薄煎饼、咸肉和热过的熟豆子。饭后，他守着半明半暗的木炭抽了一袋烟，听着夜间的窸窣声，望了一会儿峡谷里如水般的月光。之后，他打开铺盖卷，脱下笨重的皮鞋，把毯子拉到了下巴底下。月光下，他的脸惨白惨白的，宛如死尸一般。不过，这是一具魂魄未散的死尸——他突然用胳臂肘撑起身子，望了望对面的山坡。

“晚安，黄金先生，”他睡意蒙眬地说道，“晚安。”

次日，灰蒙蒙的晨曦垂降，太阳升起，阳光直射到他的眼皮上。他这才突然惊醒过来，瞧瞧四周，记起了自己为何身处此地，把眼前的现实与昨天发生的事情联系在了一起。

至于起床穿衣，其实他只需要系好鞋带就行。他望一眼火堆，再望一眼山坡，有点举棋不定，最后他终于战胜了诱惑，将火生着。

“悠着点，悠着点，比尔，别着急，”他告诫着自己，“瞎着急有什么用？除了累一身臭汗，什么用也不顶。黄金先生在等着你呢。在你吃完早饭之前，他不会跑掉的。当务之急，比尔，是先吃点新鲜的东西，然后再去找他算账也不迟。”

他到水潭边砍了短短一截树枝，从口袋里掏出一段钓丝和一个用旧的高档湿毛钩(4)。

“一大早，鱼儿可能容易上钩。”他甩出第一竿，把鱼钩甩进水潭里，嘴中喃喃自语道。过了一小会儿，只听他大叫一声：“看看，我说得不错吧？我说得不错吧？”

他没有卷线的轮盘，也不愿在这上面浪费时间，而是单凭自身的力气，麻利地从水里拉出了一条银光闪闪、长达十英寸的鳟鱼。接下来，他又很快地一连钓起了三条，充作早餐。然后，他走到踏脚石跟前，准备穿过小溪到山坡上去。就在这时，他突然想起了什么，于是停下了脚步。

“最好先到小溪下游走一趟，”他说，“说不定有谁藏在附近窥探呢。”

不过，他还是踩着石头跨过了小溪。接着，他说了一句“我真该去走一趟呀”，随即便将一切都抛到脑后，开始干起了活。

夜色降临时，他挺起了身子。由于老弓着背干活，他觉得后腰都累僵了，于是伸手去按摩后腰上酸痛的肌肉，嘴里说道：

“现在你想想，这到底是怎么啦？瞧我又把午饭忘了个干干净净！要是再不注意，我准会变成一个一天只吃两顿饭的怪人的。”

当天夜里，他钻进毯子里睡觉时，自言自语地说：“黄金真是迷魂药，叫人心神不定的。”不过，入睡前，他还是没忘记冲着山坡喊一声：“晚安，黄金先生！晚安！”

日出时，他便起床匆匆吃了些早点，早早地就开始干起了活。有一种狂热好像正在他体内滋生，淘到的金砂越来越多，他的狂热越高涨不退。他的脸上红通通的，不同于被太阳晒出的那种红。他不知道疲倦，忘记了时间的流逝。每当装满一盘土，他就跑到山下去淘洗，然后又气喘吁吁，一摇一晃地跑上山去，重新把淘金盘装满。

现在，他淘到了离水边一百码的地方。那个倒写的“V”字正在按照一定的比例缩小，可淘金的地面宽度在一点点变窄。他在心里估摸了一下这个“V”字的两条边在山坡上的交汇点。“V”字的交汇点正是他要找的目标，为了确定它的位置，他不知淘了多少盘土和金砂。

“交汇点应该就在那丛石兰灌木上方大概两码左右，向右偏一码的地方。”他最终得出了结论说。

接着，他经不住诱惑，说了句“这是明摆着的，简直跟和尚头上的虱子一样”，便放下手中的活，不再辛苦地按路线淘金了，索性直接爬到了自己估计出来的交汇点。他在那儿铲了一盘土，端到山下淘洗，没有发现金砂的踪影。他深挖浅挖，又淘了十几盘，连一粒最微小的金砂也没有找到。他气极了，怪自己不该那般经不住诱惑，狠狠地责备了一番自己的不虔诚和自以为是。随后，他走下山坡，又开始按路线挖土淘洗。

“心急吃不了热豆腐，比尔，悠着点，”他轻声告诫着自己，“干这一行，急于求成是不行的。你也该明白了。放聪明些，比尔，放聪明些。慢慢地一步一步来，只有这样才能奏效。坚持干下去，水到渠自成。”

横线在缩短，“V”字的两边越来越靠拢了，可是深度也在增加。矿脉钻到山体里去了。现在只有深挖三十英寸，才能淘到金砂。有时无论是挖二十五英寸，还是挖三十五英寸，他都淘不到金砂。在“V”字的底部，靠近水潭的地方，他在草根附近发现了一些金砂。越往坡上走，金砂就埋得越深。后来，为了能淘一盘含金砂的土，就得挖一个三英尺深的坑，这可不是闹着玩的。而在他和那个顶点之间，还需要挖无数个这样的坑。“鬼知道还要挖多深。”他停下来喘气时，发出了这么一声叹息，用手揉了揉酸痛的后背。

欲望在燃烧，他不顾后背酸痛和肌肉僵硬，挥动着锄头和铲子不停地挖那松软的褐色泥土，沿着山坡向上掘进。他面前是一片平展的草坡，草坡上繁花似锦，芳香扑鼻，而他身后却是一片狼藉。山坡原本平滑的皮肤，现在坑坑洼洼，像是起了红斑狼疮。他的进度很慢，就像是一条蛞蝓爬过后留下的一路令人恶心的脏污，破坏了美丽的环境。

坑越挖越深，工作量越来越大，但淘到的金子也越来越多，这对他是一种安慰。他估算着每盘金砂的价值——二十美分，三十美分，五十美分，乃至六十美分……夜幕降临时，他一铲子下去，挖出来的土竟然淘出了价值一美元的金砂。

“怕就怕遇见倒霉的事，有哪个居心叵测的家伙闯到我的这片乐土来捣乱。”夜里睡觉时，他把毯子拉到下巴跟前，睡眼蒙眬地咕哝了一句。

突然，他一个鲤鱼打挺坐起身，厉声警告自己：“比尔！你给我听好啦，比尔！竖起耳朵听着！明天一早，你一定要到周围走走，看看有什么情况。明白吗？明天早晨你可别忘了！”

他打了个呵欠，望着对面的山坡，高喊了一声：“晚安，黄金先生！”

次日晨，他比太阳起得还早。当第一缕阳光照到他身上时，他已吃完了早餐，正沿着峡谷的崖壁攀爬（由于坍塌，崖壁上有了踏脚的地方）。到了崖顶，放眼望去，他发现周围渺无人迹，只看得到一重重的山，连绵起伏。他向东望去，目光越过群山峻岭，远隔许多英里可以看见一排远山，山巅白雪皑皑——那是主峰，西部世界高可触天的脊梁。向北面和南面眺望，则可以比较清楚地看到那些纵横交错的山脉融入到了这条峰峦似海的主要山脉里。西面的山头一个接着一个渐变矮小，逐一变成平缓的山丘，最终形成在他视野之外的平坦谷地。

在如此辽阔的区域内，他没有看到一个人影，也没看到人类留下的痕迹——除了他脚下千疮百孔的山坡。他久久眺望，细心观察。他曾以为自己看到了脚下的这条峡谷里飘出的一缕淡淡的青烟。他又看了看，最后断定那是山间的紫色烟岚，崖壁环绕，便因此显现出更暗淡的颜色。

“嘿，听着，黄金先生！”他冲着脚下的峡谷喊道，“快给我老老实实滚出来！我来啦，黄金先生！我来啦！”

他脚上穿的皮鞋很沉，使他走起路显得有些笨拙，可是他从那高得叫人头发晕的崖顶下来的时候却轻快、灵巧得像只山羊。崖壁边上有一块石头在他脚下松动，不过他一点也没有惊慌。他好像很清楚落石要经过多长时间才会导致灾难。在这千钧一发之际，他利用落石暂时垫脚，以图借助它抵达安全之地。即使有的地方坡度太陡，无法立足，他不会有丝毫的犹豫。哪怕有一丁点可以落脚的地方，哪怕只能站一秒钟，他也会用脚点一下，然后借势向前跳去。而且，有时就连站一站的地方也没有，他便用手抓住崖壁上的一块突出的岩石，一条山缝，或者一丛根基不牢的灌木，纵身荡过去。最后，他猛力一跳，大吼一声，跳离了崖壁，随着几吨重的泥土和碎石一起落到了地面。

这天早晨，他淘第一盘就淘出了价值两美元多的粗金——这盘土取自“V”字的中心。由此向两面淘过去，含金量迅速下滑。此时，他所掘的横线已经变得非常短了。这个倒写的“V”字的两条边，中间相隔只有几码远了，它们的交点已近在咫尺。可是，需要越挖越深才有金砂。中午刚过，他挖掘时发现必须挖到五英尺深才能挖到它们。

据此看来，金矿已不再是虚无的迹象，而是实实在在的现实了。这是一个名副其实的金矿。他决定先去找到矿穴，然后再回来这儿继续挖。不过，淘出来的金砂数量越来越多，这叫他颇感困惑。傍晚时分，他每一盘能淘到价值三至四美元的金砂。他困窘地挠挠头，望望坡上几英尺远的石兰灌木丛（他估计那儿是“V”字的顶点）。只见他点点头，像宣布神谕一样说道：“二者必居其一，比尔，二者必居其一。要么，黄金如天女散花，被撒在这山坡上，要么就是金子多得不得了，叫你搬都搬不完。搬不走，那岂不可惜，你说是不是？”想到这叫人高兴的困境，他哑然失笑。

夜幕降临时，他仍在小溪边淘金，眼睛在越来越浓的黑暗中费力地看着淘金盘，为了能淘出价值五美元的金砂奋斗着。

“真希望有一盏电灯，让我继续干下去。”他说。

这天夜里，他辗转反侧，多次努力稳定情绪，闭上眼睛，希望能够睡着，可是强烈的欲望令他热血沸腾，使他一再睁开眼睛，带着倦意喃喃自语：“要是太阳出来就好了。”

最后，他终于睡着了，但星光刚刚暗淡下来，他就又把眼睛睁开了。天刚亮，他就已经吃完早饭，爬上山坡，向黄金先生的隐身之处走去了。

他开辟的第一条横线，只够挖三个坑。此时，含金砂的矿脉已经变得很窄了，他找了四天的金矿点几乎近在跟在。

“沉住气，比尔，悠着点。”他不断对自己说着，同时动手在“V”字两边的交汇点挖着最后的一个坑。

“我已经牢牢抓住了你，黄金先生，想跑是跑不掉的。”坑越挖越深，他不知把这话说了有多少遍。

四英尺，五英尺，六英尺，他不停地向地底下挖着。挖掘的难度在不断增加。哐当一声，他的锄头触着了断岩。他停下来观察了一下。

“是蚀烂了的石英！”他末了做出结论说。他用铲子清理掉坑底的松土，然后用锄头敲打松脆的石英，每敲一下，这块正在崩裂的石头上就有一些碎块掉下来。他把铲子插到松散的碎石里。突然，眼前金光一闪。他扔开手中的铲子，蹲下身子，用双手捧起一块快要解体的石英，抹掉上面的土，就像一个庄稼人刚挖出土豆后拭去上面的泥土一样。

“沙达纳帕里斯(5)也没有这么好的运气！”他大喊道，“是金块啊！是金块啊！”

他手里捧着的，一半是石头，另一半完全是纯金。他把它放在淘金盘里，又拿起一块检查了一下。起初，一点黄颜色也看不到，但他用有力的指头把松脆的石英剥掉之后，发现两只手里全是亮闪闪的黄金。他一块一块地擦掉它们面上的泥土，然后把它们扔到淘金盘里。这儿简直就是一个宝库。石英多已蚀烂，所剩无几，还没有金子多。他时不时会找到一块纯金——真正的纯金，上面一点杂质都没有。有一块含金石，他用锄头从正中敲开，里面金光闪闪，就像是一把璀璨的金黄色的珠宝。他歪着脑袋瞧着它，慢慢地旋转它，欣赏着它那夺目的光彩。

“还说你们挖的金子多，吹你们的牛吧！”他轻蔑地哼了哼鼻子说，“要跟这儿比，你们那一点连狗屁都算不上。这儿遍地是黄金。我要给这条峡谷起个名字，叫它‘黄金谷’！”

说话间，他仍蹲着身子逐个检查那些碎块，然后把它们一一扔到淘金盘里。蓦地，一种危险的预感袭上心来，使他觉得好像有一道影子扑了过来。可是他看看周围，并没有什么影子。他的心像是跳到了嗓子眼，堵得他透不过气来。他觉得周身的血慢慢变冷了，衬衫也已被冷汗湿透，紧紧贴在了肉上。

他既没有跳起来，也没有东张西望。他纹丝不动，仔细分析着这到底是什么样的预感。他觉得有一种神秘的力量对他敲响了警钟，于是竭力想弄清那力量来自于何方；他感到有一种看不见的东西在威胁着他，千方百计想分辨清那究竟是何物。

有时候，一个人会感觉到一种敌对的气息，只是那种感觉朦朦胧胧，看不见也摸不着。此时，他感觉到了这种气息，却说不清自己是怎么感觉到的。他只知道这种感觉就像乌云遮住了太阳，觉得有样阴森森的东西在威胁着他的生命，令他窒息，仿佛有一片阴影罩住了他，在吞噬他，要剥夺他的性命。

他身上的每一个细胞都在命令他跳起来去对付那看不见的危险，不过，他的理智控制住了他的恐慌。他蹲着没动，手里捧着一块金子。他不敢回头看，但他知道有什么就在他的身后，就在土坑的外边。他假装对手里的金子兴致盎然，用鉴别的目光左看右看，反过来倒过去，将上面的泥土全都擦掉。在这段时间里，他知道，有个人正在他的肩膀后面，将目光投射向这块金子。

他假装欣赏着手里的金子，耳朵却注意倾听着，听见身后有呼吸声。他的目光在眼前的地面搜索，想找件武器，然而只看到了挖出来的金子，而那东西在这危急时刻是派不上用场的。锄头也在跟前，只是目前的状况也是用不上的。他意识到了自己身处的困境——他在一个七英尺深的坑里，地方狭窄，看不到地面，犹如在陷阱里一般。

他依旧蹲着不动，内心却一丝不乱，异常冷静。他权衡了一切因素，可想来想去，仍无良策。他把石英碎块逐一捡起，挨个擦去上面的泥土，将露出来的金子扔到盘子里。他实在想不出办法来。但他很清楚，自己早晚都必须站起来，面对身后的危险。就这样，几分钟过去了。每一分钟他都在想着事情已迫在眉睫——他必须站起来，要么……想到这里，被冷汗湿透的衬衫在身上贴得更紧了……要么他将守着他的宝贝迎接死亡。

他仍然蹲着，一面擦掉金块上的泥土，一面权衡利弊，考虑着该怎样站起来才好——要么一跃而起，三下两下爬到坑外，在那儿的平地上跟那个威胁着他的家伙较量较量；要么就慢慢地、随意地站起来，装出一副不经意看见身后那家伙的样子。他的本能和全身每一个渴望战斗的细胞都赞成孤注一掷，冲出去拼个你死我活。然而他的理智和心计却赞成用缓兵之计，去谨慎地面对那个威胁着他的人。就在举棋不定的时候，他听见了啪的一声巨响，同时感到后背的左侧受到重重一击，那一击似一团火刺透了他的身体。他纵身一跳，但没跳多高便跌落在了地上。他身体蜷缩着，犹如树叶遇火缩成了一团，胸口压在淘金盘上，脸埋在泥土和碎石里，两条腿在狭窄的坑底扭在一起，一阵阵地抽搐着。接着，他全身抖如筛糠，似疟疾症发作一般。之后，一声长长的叹息之后，他慢慢吸了口气，慢慢地，他缓缓将这口气吐出，身体渐渐瘫软，最后一动也不动了。

坑外那家伙手里拿着左轮手枪，站在坑沿朝下张望着，把坑底的这个趴着不动的躯体打量了许久。过了一会儿，那个不速之客在坑沿坐下，这样便于观察坑内的情况，然后把手枪放在膝盖上，伸手进衣袋，掏出一小片棕褐色的纸，放一些烟丝在上边，用手一卷，再将两头一塞，做成了一支棕褐色的又短又粗的卷烟。他的眼睛始终盯着坑底的那个人，一刻也没离开过。他点着烟，徐徐抽了一口，把烟吸进肺里，慢腾腾地吞云吐雾。抽着抽着烟灭了，他又重新点着。他一边抽烟，一边观察着脚下的那个人。

最后，他把烟蒂扔掉，站了起来。他移步靠近坑沿，两脚踏在土坑壁上，双手撑在两侧（右手仍握着枪），身体一点一点往下移。脚离坑底有一码远的时候，他一松手，跳了下去。

他的脚刚一沾地，坑底的那个淘金人便闪电般地出手，抓住他的两条腿将他掀翻在地。刚才向下跳的时候，他那只握枪的手举过头顶，而就在自己的腿被抓住的那一瞬间，他立马把枪口转向了坑底。身体还在半空中，双脚尚未落地时，他扣动了扳机。在这狭小的空间，枪声震耳欲聋。坑里硝烟弥漫，弄得他什么也看不见。他仰面摔倒在地，那个淘金人猛虎般扑在了他身上。尽管被淘金人压着，这位不速之客仍将右胳膊一弯，准备再开一枪。淘金人飞快地用胳膊肘撞了一下他的手腕，枪口被撞得向上一翘，子弹射进了坑壁的泥土里。

紧接着，不速之客感到淘金人牢牢地抓住了他的手腕。二人激烈搏斗，开始夺枪，都想将枪口指向对方。此时，坑里的硝烟在渐渐消散。不速之客仰面躺在地上，可以模糊地看见一点东西了。可是，他的对手突然故意对准他的眼睛撒了一把土，他又什么也看不见了。他猛然一惊，不由松开了抓枪的手。随即，他感到脑子里突然一片漆黑，紧接着，就连那片漆黑也消失了。

淘金人朝着他开了一枪又一枪，直到将子弹打空。随后，他把枪扔掉，气喘吁吁地一屁股坐在了死人的腿上。

他抽泣了几声，几乎有点透不过气来了。“狗日的，鼠辈！”他喘着粗气骂道，“竟然偷偷跟着我，等我找到了金子，就在我背后开冷枪！”

他又气又累，说话都带着哭腔。他低头看了看死者的脸，见他脸上撒满泥土和碎石，难以看得清五官。

“从未见过这家伙，”他在仔细瞧过之后说，“只不过是个小贼！死去吧！竟然在我背后开冷枪！竟然在我背后开冷枪！”

他解开自己的衬衫，摸摸左面的胸部和背部。

“子弹打穿了，但不碍事！”他高兴地高声说，“我敢打赌，他瞄得倒是挺准的，可就在他转过枪口，扣动扳机之际——啪，让他射偏了！结果，我把他给收拾了！哼，叫他栽在了我手里！”

他用手指摸了摸身上的弹孔，脸上划过一丝遗憾的神情。“这伤口要疼起来了，”他说道，“我得赶快包扎好伤口，赶紧离开这儿。”

他爬出土坑，到了山坡下的宿营地。半小时之后，他又回来了，把驮行李的马也牵了来。他的衬衣敞着，露出了包扎伤口的绷带。他的左手动作缓慢、笨拙，但这并不妨碍他使用左边的胳臂。

他将行李绳捆在死者的腋下，将尸体拖出了土坑，然后开始挖金子。他挖啊挖，一连挖了几个小时，肩膀酸了就休息休息，休息时会骂上一句：“狗日的不是个东西，竟然在我背后开冷枪！竟然在我背后开冷枪！”

他将坑里的金子悉数挖出，用毯子裹起来，打成了几个包，然后估计了一下价值。

“要没有四百磅，那我就是个霍屯督人(6)，”他末了说道，“就算里面含两百磅的石英和泥土，纯金也有两百磅。比尔！醒醒吧！两百磅金子呀！四万美元呢！全都属于你，全是你一个人的！”

他喜上眉梢，高兴得直挠头，手指无意中摸到了一个以前没发现的头上的槽沟，有几英寸长，是另一颗子弹犁出的，贴着头皮擦过。

他怒不可遏，大步向死者走去。

“你还冲我下毒手！”他咆哮道，“想跟我较量，是不是？哼，我倒把你给收拾了。不仅如此，我还要给你一个体面的葬礼呢。也算对得起你了。”

他把尸体拖到坑沿，将其推了下去。尸体嗵的一声砸在了坑底，侧着身子，面部扭过来朝着亮光。淘金人居高临下望着死者。

“谁叫你在别人的背后放冷枪！”他斥责道。

他挥动锄头和铲子，用土把坑填平，然后把金子放到马背上。金子太重，让这匹驮行李的马有点吃不消。一到宿营地，他把一部分金子转移到了他的坐骑背上。即便如此，他还得被迫丢掉一部分装备——锄头、铲子、淘金盘、多余的粮食和炊具，另还有其他一些七零八碎的东西。

太阳已经升到了头顶，他赶着马儿走向那道由藤蔓和爬山虎构成的屏障。在攀登巨大的岩石时，马儿几乎直立了起来，不顾一切地闯进了盘根错节的树丛里。那匹带鞍子的坐骑一度重重摔倒在地，他便拿开金子包囊，帮它站起来。待马儿重新上路后，他把头伸出树丛，最后看了一眼那面山坡。

“别了，卑鄙的小人！”他说完就不见了。

接着就是窸窸窣窣、咔嚓咔嚓一阵拉扯藤葛和折断树枝的声音。马儿穿过树丛，使得小树前后乱摇。钉着铁掌的马蹄踏在石头上发出嗒嗒嗒的声音，时不时还响起他高嗓门的呵斥声。后来，他大声唱起了歌：

回过头来，转过你的脸，
看一看那美轮美奂的小山，
（罪恶，罪恶，叫人轻看！）
瞧瞧周围，把周围看一看，
快将罪恶的包袱抛到一边。
（说不定今晨就会遇见上帝！）

歌声越来越小，最后归于沉寂，峡谷又恢复了原来的宁静。小溪又开始打盹和低声细语；山蜂那令人昏昏欲睡的嗡嗡声又响了起来；白杨树的花絮如白白的绒毛在香气四溢的空气里飘荡；蝴蝶在树丛里翻飞；明媚的阳光洒在一草一木之上。只有从草地上的马蹄印和那面被挖得坑坑洼洼的山坡能看出：这儿宁静曾经一度被扰攘喧嚣的过客所打破，而现在他们已经离去。

————————————————————

(1) 北美印第安部落集团萨哈普廷人中的一个种族。

(2) 这种药丸于19世纪末由威廉医生发明，据说能治很多病。此处喻指欺骗。

(3) 博斯威尔（1740—1795），英国传记作家。

(4) 飞蝇钓中一种利用皮、毛与线模拟沉水性昆虫而制成的毛钩。

(5) 淘金者。

(6) 居住在西南非洲的土著人。此处喻指眼拙。

一块牛排

汤姆·金用最后一口面包擦干净了盘子里最后一滴加了面粉的肉汤，然后将面包送进嘴里，满腹心事地慢慢嚼着。当他从桌边站起来时，仍然觉得饥肠辘辘，肚子饿得难受。可是，只有他一个人是吃过东西的。隔壁房间里，两个孩子早早就被打发上床睡觉了，为的是叫他们忘记自己还没有吃晚饭。他的妻子粒米未进，默默坐在那儿，担心地瞧着他。她是个工人阶级主妇，瘦削、憔悴，但风韵犹存，看得出她年轻时很漂亮。煮汤用的面粉是她跟走廊对面的邻居借来的，面包则是用家里唯一的两便士买的。

他坐在窗旁一把摇摇晃晃的椅子上，椅子被压得咯吱作响，而后他习惯性地把烟斗塞到嘴里，手伸进上衣口袋取烟丝。口袋里没有烟丝，他这才从遐思中清醒过来，皱皱眉头，怪自己如此健忘，然后把烟斗放到了一边。他动作很缓慢，几乎可以说是有点笨拙，就好像由于身上肌肉太多，不堪重负似的。他是个身体结实、看起来呆头呆脑的人，相貌也不算十分讨人喜欢。他身着破旧的粗布衣衫，邋里邋遢的，脚上的鞋很久以前曾换过鞋底，鞋帮已经旧了，烂得都快提不起那沉重的鞋底了。他的棉布衬衣是两个先令的廉价货，领口已经磨破，上面留有一些无法去除的油漆斑点。

不过，汤姆·金的脸让人一看就知道他是干什么的。那是一张典型的职业拳击手的脸，一张在拳击场上滚打了许多年的人才有的脸，具有一个斗士应该具有的所有特征，而且那些特征非常明显。显而易见，这是一张不苟言笑的脸，其性格一目了然。这张脸刮得光光的，两片嘴唇破了相，合在一起，显得十分严酷——那嘴看上去就像是脸上的一道疤。他的下巴显得咄咄逼人，厚实而粗野。他紧锁的浓眉之下，一双目光呆滞、毫无表情的眼睛深陷在厚重的眼皮之下。他看上去简直就像一只凶猛的野兽，尤其是他那双疲倦的狮子般的眼睛，一双好斗的野兽之眼。他的额头并不宽，发际线靠前，头发剪得很短，脑袋上每一个狰狞的肿块都暴露无遗。他的鼻子断过两次，因挨了无数次击打而变得奇形怪状。他的耳朵老是肿着，比原来大一倍，看似花椰菜，以此装点他的脸。他脸上的胡子虽然才刮过，却又长出一片青黑的胡楂。

总之，要是有人在黑胡同里或者哪个偏僻的地方看见这张脸，定会心生畏惧。不过，汤姆·金既不是罪犯，也没有干过作奸犯科的事。除了职业要求在拳击场上跟人打斗之外，他没有伤害过任何人。谁也没见他和别人吵过嘴。他是以拳击为职业的人，好斗的野蛮行为只留在拳击场上表现出来。一出拳击场，他就判若两人，变得行动迟缓、性情随和。年轻时他花钱如流水，慷慨大方，仗义疏财。他对人很少计较，从不树敌。对他来说，拳击只不过是一种职业。在拳击场上，他把人打伤、打残，甚至打死，心里却并无恶意。这纯粹是一桩生意。观众花钱到场子里来，就是为了看拳击手竞技，看谁把谁打翻在地。获胜方可以赢得大笔大笔的钱。他还记得二十年前跟乌鲁木鲁·高杰过招时的情景。他知道高杰的下巴在纽卡斯尔市的比赛中被打断，刚刚治好才四个月，于是就对准那个地方发动猛攻，在第九个回合里把高杰的下巴又打断了。这倒不是说他对髙杰有仇，而是因为打倒髙杰便可以赢得那一大笔钱。高杰也没有因此对他怀恨在心。比赛就是比赛，二人都清楚，彼此只是在场上一赌输赢。

汤姆·金向来话不多，此时他正默默地坐在窗前，一声不吭，满脸愁容地盯着自己的手。只见他的手背上青筋暴起，一根根血管粗大、肿胀；他的指关节曾经被击碎，已经变了形，一看就知道他出拳时的状况是何等惨烈。他从没听谁说过一个人的生与死取决于他动脉的好坏，但他很清楚这些粗大肿胀的血管意味着什么。他的心脏曾以过大的压力通过这些血管输送了太多的血液。而今，这些血管已经不管用了，由于过度拉伸而弹性尽失，由于血管肿胀，他的耐力也大不如以前。现在，他动辄便感到疲倦。他再也不能电闪雷鸣般地跟对手鏖战二十个回合了。过去，在拳击场上，双方竭尽全力拼搏，你一拳我一拳地打啊打，锣声响了一遍又一遍，进攻一次比一次猛烈，他被打得靠到绳子上，又把对手打得靠到绳子上，最后在第二十个回合里，搏斗到达白热化阶段，出拳快如闪电，全场观众站起来齐声喝彩，他冲锋、击打、躲闪，拳头雨点般落在对手身上，自己的身上也没少挨拳头。而他的心脏一直都在忠实地给各条血管输送汹涌的血液。那些血管虽然一时膨胀，但总会缩回原状。不过，每次比赛之后，虽然最初微不可察，但血管的确都会变得比前次粗一丁点儿。此刻他盯着手上的血管和被打碎了的指关节，仿佛看到了在他一拳打在本尼·琼斯（人称威尔士恶煞神）的脑袋上，第一次将一个指关节打碎之前，这双手年轻美丽的模样。

这时，饥饿感又一次朝他袭来。

“唉，难道我连一块牛排也吃不上吗！”他大声地嘟哝道，攥紧他那巨大的拳头，将胸中压抑着的怨气吐了出来。

“伯克家的店和索里家的店我都去过了。”他的妻子略带歉意地说。

“他们都不愿意吗？”他问道。

“少半分钱也不行。伯克说……”妻子欲言又止，把后半句话咽了回去。

“说呀！他说什么？”

“他说他认为今天晚上桑德尔会打败你，还说你欠他的账已经够多了。”

汤姆·金哼了一声，没有说什么，心里却浮想联翩，想到年轻时养的那只斗牛犬，他不知给它喂了多少牛排。那时，他就是要赊一千块牛排，伯克也会欣然同意的。可是，岁月催人老呀。汤姆·金老了。在二流俱乐部里混饭吃的老年拳击手还想从商贩那儿赊账，有点太异想天开了。

今天早晨一起床，他就渴望有块牛排吃，此时这种欲望仍未消散。对于今晚的这场拳击赛，他事先并没有好好训练过。今年澳大利亚大旱，生活艰难，连临时的工作都不容易找到。他训练时没有人陪练，伙食也不算好，常常吃了上顿没下顿。即便能找到工作，也是干些粗活，出卖几天的苦力。为了保持腿力，他常常在清晨围绕道曼公园(1)一圈一圈地跑。可是，这样的训练谈何容易——没有陪练员，又要挣钱养活妻子和两个孩子。自从他得到跟桑德尔比赛的机会之后，商贩们在赊账方面才对他稍微放宽了一点。欢乐俱乐部的秘书给他预支了三英镑（这是输掉比赛的人所能得到的钱数），死活不愿再多预支一点。他时不时能从老友那儿借几个先令应急。老友说很想多借给他一些，但遇到这大旱年，他们自己也举步维艰。说来说去，事实不容隐瞒——他训练得很不够，难以叫人满意。他本应吃好一点的伙食，保持轻松的心态。再说，他已是四十岁的人了，不如二十岁的时候容易进入状态。

“现在几点啦，莉兹？”他问道。

他的妻子到走廊对面问了一下，回来说：

“八点差一刻。”

“再过几分钟，他们就要开始第一场比赛了，”他说道，“只是预热赛。接下来是狄勒·威尔斯和格里德利的四回合比赛，然后是斯达莱特和一个海员拳击手的十回合比赛。一个小时之后才该我上场。”

随后，他沉默了下来，又过了十分钟才站了起来。

“老实说，莉兹，我训练得很不够。”

他伸手拿起帽子，向门口走去，没有去吻妻子——每次出门比赛前他都会吻她。不过，今天晚上，妻子主动吻了他，伸开双臂搂住他，让他俯下身子。他身材魁梧，像一座铁塔，而她娇小玲珑。

“祝你好运，汤姆，”她说，“你一定要打败他。”

“是啊，我一定要打败他，”他嘴里念叨着，“只能胜，不能输。我一定要打败他。”

妻子小鸟依人般偎傍在他怀里，而他哈哈一笑，装出很开心的样子。他的目光掠过妻子的肩头，扫视了一眼空空如也的房屋。这是他在这个世界上拥有的一切：欠租的房子，他的妻子和孩子。现在，他要离开这一切，融入夜色里，去为妻儿觅食。这样的觅食，可不是像现代工人那样用机器挣钱，而是用古老、原始、惨烈、野兽一样的方式，靠搏斗挣钱。

“我一定要打败他。”他又念叨了一遍，这次，声音里透露出了几分孤注一掷的语气，“打赢了，就能拿到三十英镑——除了还账，还能剩下很多钱。如果输了，就一分钱也拿不到，连坐电车回家的钱也不会给我。输家的那一份钱，秘书已经提前支给了我。再见，老伴，如果打赢了，我立刻就回家来。”

“我等着你回来！”妻子在走廊里冲着离去的他喊道。

从家到欢乐俱乐部足足有两英里的路。他边走边回忆自己事业的鼎盛期——他曾经是新南威尔士的重量级冠军，常常坐着马车去拳击场；押大注的赌家会抢着为他付车费，抢着跟他同行。那些人中有汤米·彭斯，还有那个美国黑人杰克·约翰逊——那些人可都是有私家汽车的高贵主儿。现在可好，他得靠两条腿走着去了！谁都知道，大赛之前辛辛苦苦走两英里的路可不是件好事。他老了，如今的世界对上了年纪的人来说真是寸步难行。除了找点粗活干，他别的什么也干不了。即便如此，他的断鼻梁、肿耳朵还都对他很不利。他真后悔当初没有学一样手艺。从长远来看，有样手艺会好一些。可惜没人为他指点迷津。不过，他心里清楚：即便有人指点，他也不会听的。想当年，日子过得真是轻松——财源滚滚……赛场上场面激烈、辉煌……比赛完，中间还有一段休养和放松的时间……逢迎巴结的大有人在，拍肩表示亲热的、握手寒暄的比比皆是，花花公子们争着请他喝酒，只为了能跟他说上一会儿话……他荣誉加身，全场的观众为他欢呼，他秋风扫落叶般将对手击倒，裁判宣布“金获胜！”，次日他的名字就会出现在报纸的体育专栏里。

那是何等风光的日子呀！可是现在细细想起来，当年被他打倒的都是些上了年纪的拳击手。那时，他年轻，正处于上升期，对手年纪大，处于没落期。怪不得他赢得那么轻松——原来那些老拳击手伤痕累累，血管肿胀，指关节被击碎，由于常年鏖战于拳击场，老骨头已累散了架。当年在鲁斯卡特湾比赛，他对自己在第十八个回合击败斯托希尔·比尔老头时的情景仍记忆犹新，记得老比尔赛后在更衣室里哇哇地哭，哭得像个小孩子一样。也许，老比尔当年也欠了房租，家里也有妻儿要养活。也许，比赛的那一天，比尔也渴望能吃上一块牛排。比尔披挂上阵，结果惨遭失败。而今，他自己在经历了相同的磨难之后总算明白了过来：在二十年前的那天晚上，在年轻的汤姆·金只是为了名和利而战时，斯托希尔·比尔是下了更大的赌注才上台比赛的，怪不得斯托希尔·比尔赛后会在更衣室里哭得那么伤心。

好吧，一个拳击手一生能打多少场比赛是注定的。这已经成了行内的铁律。有的人能打一百场艰苦卓绝的比赛，而有的则打二十场便草草收场。每个人的素质和体力都不一样，打的场数也不一样，一旦气数尽了，他的生涯也就完结了。按说，他打的场数比大多数同行都多，一场场艰苦卓绝的战斗，数量之多早已远远超过了自己的定数——这种比赛使心和肺运行到仿佛要炸开的程度，使动脉失去了弹性，使年轻时的那种平滑、柔韧的肌肉变得僵硬；由于持久的劳累过度，精神和身体都受到了巨大的损耗。是啊，在拳击手里他算得上是佼佼者。他这一辈的拳击手均已退出历史舞台，只剩下了他一个仍在坚持。他亲眼看着那些人纷纷谢幕，其中一些人的退出跟他不无关系。

拳击赛举办方常常安排他对阵那些老头，容他将老家伙们打得落花流水，每逢他们像老将斯托希尔·比尔一样躲在更衣室里痛哭失声时，他却笑了起来。而今，他自己老了，他们又安排年轻的选手来对付他。那个小屁孩桑德尔就是其中之一！他是从新西兰来的，在那儿战绩辉煌，但在澳大利亚却无人知道他的深浅，所以他们让他来对战老将汤姆·金。如果桑德尔旗开得胜，就安排他对垒更强的选手，赚更多的钱。因而，今晚这一仗桑德尔一定会拼死一搏。这一仗取胜，他便什么都有了——金钱、荣誉和前途；头发斑白的汤姆·金则是一只拦路虎，阻碍他走向金钱和荣誉。而汤姆·金取胜，什么也得不到，只能拿到三十英镑，用以偿还房租和买东西赊的账。他心潮起伏，迟钝的大脑中出现了年轻人的形象：正值韶华，所向披靡，肌肉柔韧，皮肤光滑，永不衰竭的心肺，对于“力量是有限的”论调总会付之一笑。是呀，年轻人简直就是涅墨西斯(2)。他们毁掉了拳击场上的老将，压根没想过同时也在摧毁他们自己。他们的动脉因此而肿胀，指关节因此而破碎。最后，他们又被后起之秀所毁掉。因为青春转瞬即逝，而岁月渐老。

走到卡斯尔雷街，他向左转，穿过三个街区，来到了欢乐俱乐部。一群聚集在俱乐部门外的街头小混混恭敬地给他让开了一条路，他听见其中一个对他的同伴说：“就是他！他就是汤姆·金！”

进门后，他在去更衣室的路上遇见了俱乐部的秘书——一个目光犀利、面目机灵的年轻人。他跟他握了握手。

“你感觉怎么样，汤姆？”他问道。

“感觉非常好。”他回答说。他情知自己是在睁着眼说瞎话。如果他有一英镑，他会立刻去买块可口的牛排来填肚子。

出了更衣室之后，他带着助手，穿过甬道走向大厅中央用绳子圈起来的拳击场。早已等在那里的观众爆发出一片欢呼声。他分别向左右的观众致意，尽管观众席里的面孔他几乎全不认识。大多数观众都是年轻人，当他在拳击场上赢得他最初的荣耀时，还没有出娘胎呢。他轻快地跳到台上，低头从绳子下面钻到他的那个角落，在一个折叠凳子上坐下。裁判杰克·鲍尔走过来，跟他握了握手。鲍尔是个没落的拳击手，已经有十多年没有作为主角登台过了。金很高兴由他当裁判。他们俩都是老一辈拳击手。即便他有犯规的动作，对桑德尔稍微过分一点，他知道鲍尔一定会放他一马的。

年轻气盛、雄心勃勃的重量级拳击选手接二连三地跳到台上，由裁判介绍给观众。介绍的同时，裁判还宣布了他们各自提出的挑战。

“年轻的普隆托，”鲍尔宣布道，“来自北悉尼，他愿意追加五十英镑，向获胜者挑战。”

观众席上爆发出一阵欢呼声；当桑德尔钻过绳子跳到台上，在他的那个角落坐下时，观众席再次爆发出一阵欢呼声。汤姆·金好奇地瞧着对面的桑德尔——再过几分钟，他们俩就会扭打在一起，展开无情的搏斗，二人都会使出全身的力气，恨不得一拳将对方打昏过去。他看不出桑德尔有什么特殊之处——对方跟他一样，也在拳击衣外面套着长裤子和绒线衫。桑德尔长得英俊潇洒，一头蓬松的金色卷发，从他粗壮、肌肉发达的脖子可以看出他身体很是健壮。

年轻的普隆托分别走到两个角落里，跟两位主角握了手，然后就跳下了台子。挑战在继续进行。不断有年轻人钻过绳子跳上台（都是些无名小辈，但胃口都很大），一个个当众宣布要靠自己的力量和技巧跟获胜者一决雌雄。要是在几年之前，正值自己所向无敌的黄金时代，汤姆·金看到这样的场面，一定会觉得又好笑，又无聊。而现在，他着了迷似的坐在那里，无法摆脱浮现在眼前的年轻人的幻象——这些年轻选手如雨后春笋在拳击界涌现，跳上台来，咋咋呼呼地挑战，一代代老将们在他们的面前倒下。他们踩着老将们的肩膀走向成功。这些年轻人如潮水般涌来，人数越来越多，汹涌澎湃，势不可挡，把老一辈人冲到一旁，而他们自己也在变老，也逐渐在走下坡路，身后又会有年轻人不断拥来，犹如长江后浪推前浪。新生代翅膀长硬，就将老一代踩在脚下，而后边则又会出现另一个新生代，永无止境。年轻人必然有他们的意志，这种意志永远不会消亡。

金向记者席瞟了一眼，冲《运动员报》的摩根和《裁判报》的科比特点了点头。随后，他伸出手，由桑德尔的一个助手严格地检查绕在他指节上的细绷带，并且在这个人的严密监视之下，由他自己的助手锡德·沙利文和查理·贝茨给他套上拳套，并把它们扎紧。同时，在桑德尔那个角落，也有金的一个助手在履行同样的职责。桑德尔的长裤被拽了下来，当他站起身时，他的套头绒线衫也被脱了下来。汤姆·金望过去，看到的是年轻的化身：厚厚的胸脯，强壮的筋肉，一身肌肉就像活物一样在缎子似的白皮肤之下滑动，浑身上下充满了勃勃生机。汤姆·金知道，这样的生命还没有在长期搏击中，从疼痛的毛孔里散尽其朝气，年轻人经历了这样的搏击后，就要付出代价，当他从这里走出去的时候，就不会像进来时那么年轻了。

两个人走向前，准备交手。当的一声锣响，助手们噼里啪啦收起折叠凳，爬出场外。二人握过手后，立刻摆出了迎战的姿势。转眼间，桑德尔进进退退，一个左勾拳打在金的眼上，又一个右勾拳落在了他的肋骨上，忽而灵巧地跳开躲闪，忽而咄咄逼人地冲过来进攻，就像一个由钢铁零件和弹簧组成的机械装置，受到一种微力扳机的操纵。他动作敏捷、灵巧，一招一式令人眼花缭乱，引得全场的观众大声喝彩。但是汤姆没有眼花。他打过的比赛不胜枚举，遇到过的年轻选手多之又多。他深知花拳绣腿不顶用——过于敏捷和过于灵巧的招式不具备危险性。显而易见，桑德尔来势汹汹，想速战速决。这是意料之中的。年轻人都是这样——一开始就猛打猛冲，恨不得一下子就能凭借自己的虎力和冲劲如泰山压顶般压倒对方，岂不知这样会消耗自己的精力和锐气。

桑德尔进退有方，四面出击，忽而此处，忽而彼处，脚步轻盈，心情急切，快如一阵疾风，只看得见他雪白而结实的肌肉晃来晃去，一次次发动令人眼花缭乱的进攻，躲闪、腾跳，如飞梭般飞来飞去，巡回往返千次有余，目标只有一个，那就是摧毁汤姆·金，因为汤姆·金是他走向成功的绊脚石。汤姆·金则耐心地忍受着。他心里有数，虽然自己不再年轻，但他了解年轻人。他心想：必须按兵不动，等到对方消耗掉一些体力再说。当桑德尔一个重拳打来时，他暗中一笑，故意将脑袋一偏，让那一拳落在了自己的头顶。这一招实在恶毒，但根据拳击规则又是很正当的。拳击场上，选手理应当心自己的指关节，如果他非得用指关节击打对手的头顶，那就是自讨苦吃了。金本来可以把头一低，让那一拳落空，谁都伤不着，可他想起早年跟威尔士恶煞神对决，自己一拳打在对方的头顶上，将指关节击碎的经历，才用了这样的计谋。比赛就是比赛，容不得心软。这一招叫桑德尔失去了一个指关节。眼下，桑德尔不会放在心上，而会打下去，全然不管那个指关节，势头不减地将比赛进行到底。不过，以后等到时间长了，打的场数多了，麻烦就来了，那时他会为失去这个指关节而痛惜，回想起他是一拳打在汤姆·金的头上才将指关节击碎的。

第一局完全是桑德尔的天下，他那快如旋风的猛攻赢得了全场的喝彩。他出拳有排山倒海之势，将金压倒，而金只是在防卫。金从不主动出拳，只是一个劲地遮挡、躲闪，或者用身子扭抱对方以免遭到痛击。他偶尔进行一次佯攻，对方重拳落下时，却摇摇头躲开，步伐坚实，从不跳跃弹起，不随便浪费一丝一毫的气力。这个谨慎的老拳击手，必须等到桑德尔将年轻的锐气发泄完，才敢进行反击。金动作缓慢，却有条不紊，慢悠悠转动着罩着厚眼皮的眼睛珠子，看上去似睡非睡，又像是有些头昏眼花。岂不知这是一双能观六路的眼睛，在拳击场上历练了二十多年，任什么都逃不过它们的注意。即便一拳打到了跟前，这双眼睛也不会眨动一下，而是冷静地观察，测算着那一拳和他之间的距离。

第一局结束后有一分钟的休息时间，他瘫坐在他的那个角落里，两腿伸开，胳膊搭在两旁的绳子上，胸脯和腹部剧烈地一起一伏，大口吸进助手们用毛巾扇过来的空气。他闭上眼睛，听着场子里鼎沸的人声。“你为什么不还手，汤姆？”许多人在喊，“你不会害怕他吧，对不对？”

“肌肉发硬了，”他听见一个坐在前排的人这样议论，“他的动作快不了啦。我赌桑德尔赢，赌金加倍，用英镑计算。”

锣声一响，两人都离开各自的角落，走上前去。桑德尔求战心切，两人之间的距离有四分之三是由他大步流星跨过的，而金情愿少走几步。这完全符合他那节省体力的策略。大赛前，他训练得不充分，又没有足够的食物填肚子，所以每走一步都得算计好。再说，来比赛场之前，他已经走了两英里的路了。这一局跟上一局情况雷同，桑德尔的进攻仍如暴风骤雨。观众对金感到气愤，大声责问他为何不还手。金只是装出进攻的样子，虚晃几拳，拳拳落空，除此之外，他只是一个劲招架、退缩，或者扭抱对方。桑德尔渴望速战速决，可是金有自己的算盘，拒绝按他的路子打。他咧嘴一笑，那张在拳击场上被打得伤痕累累的脸上露出一种忧愁和悲情，战术上仍我行我素，保存着自身的力量，表现出上年纪的人才有的谨慎态度。而血气方刚的桑德尔表现出的则是青春的豪放和纵情，任意挥霍着自己的精力。金不愧为拳击场上的将才，其运筹帷幄的智慧源自于常年艰苦卓绝的搏斗。他目光冷静、头脑清晰，行动方寸不乱，耐心等待着桑德尔把锐气消耗殆尽。大多数观众都觉得他大势已去，已无指望逆转，于是便吆喝着要将押在桑德尔身上的赌注再加一倍。但也有几个另有看法的观众，他们了解金过去的行事风格，认为将赌注压在他身上容易赢钱。

第三局开始的时候，仍是桑德尔在唱独角戏，由他一个人发起进攻，出拳猛揍对方。半分钟过后，桑德尔由于过分自信，露出了一个破绽。金眼疾手快，刹那间，一个右勾拳打了过去。这是他货真价实的第一拳——一个勾拳，胳膊弯成拱形，使拳头坚实有力，半扭转身子，将全身的重量都压在了拳头上。这就像一头似乎沉睡着的狮子，突然闪电似的伸出一只爪子来。下颚侧面被击中的桑德尔，像一头公牛般轰然倒下。观众惊呆了，敬畏得发出一片低低的喝彩声。他们发现这个老拳击手的肌肉并没有变得僵硬，一拳下去，如铁锤重击。

桑德尔魂飞魄散，翻过身想站起来，可他的助手们大声叫他别动，等着裁判数数。他单膝跪着，准备站起来的样子，等待着来到他身旁的裁判在他耳朵边大声数数。裁判数到九的时候，他站起来摆出了准备搏斗的姿势。看着他，汤姆·金不由扼腕叹息，觉得刚才那一拳要是离对方的下巴尖再近一英寸就好了。那样，他就能把桑德尔打昏，揣上三十英镑的奖金回家去见自己的妻儿了。

这一局已接近尾声，快要到规定的三分钟了，此时桑德尔对自己的敌手方才肃然起敬，敬重起动作缓慢、睡眼惺忪的金。金眼见这局比赛即将结束，看到助手们蹲在场外，时刻准备着钻过绳子跳进场内，于是便将搏斗的中心点向自己的角落那儿引。锣声一响，他立刻就坐到了他的凳子上休息，而桑德尔则需要走完斜穿赛场的对角线才能回到他自己的角落里。这虽然是件小事，但若干小事汇集在一起便不是小事了。桑德尔多走几步路，就多消耗几分体力，同时会减少一些宝贵的休息时间。每一局开始，金离开他的角落时总是磨磨蹭蹭的，这样便迫使对方前来迎战时多走一些路。每一局结束时，他则将搏斗引向他的那个角落，锣声一响他就可以立刻坐下来休息。

接下来又是两局的拼杀，金精打细算地节省着力气，而桑德尔仍在肆意挥霍。后者进攻势头猛烈，只求速决，让金感到很不舒服，因为对方雨点般的拳头有相当大一部分打中了他。观众席中，急性子的年轻人大声催促他迎战，拼死一搏，而他依旧不紧不慢，坚持自己的打法。后来在第六局，桑德尔又大意了一次，汤姆·金那可怕的右勾拳又闪电般打中了他的下巴，于是桑德尔又等到裁判数到九才起来。

打到第七局的时候，桑德尔的优势已不再，他开始稳扎稳打——他意识到这将是他入行以来最艰难的一场比赛。汤姆·金固然是老家伙，却比他以前遇到过的任何老家伙都厉害——这个老家伙从不丧失理智，在防御方面技高一筹，不出拳则已，一出拳便如铁锤砸来，无论是左勾拳还是右勾拳，一拳就能把人打翻在地。不过，话又说回来，汤姆·金是不敢频频出拳的。他一直没敢忘记自己的指关节已经被击碎，情知要想坚持打完这场比赛，每一拳都必须击中要害。当他坐在自己的角落里，望着对面的敌手时，心里突然产生了一个想法，如果把自己的智慧与桑德尔的活力结合在一起，就可以造就一名世界重量级拳击赛的冠军。不过，这也是问题所在。桑德尔绝不会当上世界冠军，因为他缺乏智慧，而获得智慧又得付出青春才行，等到他有了智慧，青春也就成了东逝之水。

凡是对自己有利的方法，金无所不用。只要一有机会，他就扭住对手，往往还会趁机用肩膀硬撞对方的肋骨。按照拳击的理论，用肩膀撞击和用拳头攻击同样有效，会造成相同的伤害，而且就节省体力来说，前一种方法远胜后一种。一扭住对方，金就将全身的重量压上去，死活不愿松开，非逼得裁判过来干涉，把他们俩掰开，尚未学会趁此休息的桑德尔每次还会协助裁判一把。每当金冲过来进行贴身战，用肩膀抵住他的肋骨，把头靠在他的左臂上时，他总是忍不住地挥舞起双臂，扭动着肌肉，几乎总是把右拳从自己背后挥过去，打那个突出的脸。这一手打得很巧妙，观众非常钦佩，然而却并不会造成较大的伤害，因而也只能算是白费气力。可是桑德尔不知疲倦，也不知节制，金见状总是咧嘴一笑，顽强地忍受着。

桑德尔后来形成了一种套路，老是用右拳猛击金的身体，看上去就好像金遭到了重击似的。老观众却不以为然，他们倒是欣赏金的打法——金每次都会在对方的拳头落下之前，左拳巧妙地打向对方的二头肌。诚然，桑德尔拳拳击中了金，但由于自己的二头肌次次都被击中，力量便被弱化了许多。在第九局里，金在一分钟内一连三次挥动右臂，用右勾拳击打在桑德尔的下巴上，桑德尔三次倒地，如一堵墙一样重重倒在垫子上。每一次，桑德尔都会休息够规定的九秒钟，然后站起来，虽然摇摇晃晃，却仍然强壮有力。这时，他进攻的速度大大放慢，浪费的力量也随之减少。这是一场恶斗，而他仍在持续消耗自己的主要本钱——青春，汤姆·金的本钱则是经验。如今，金的体力衰退，精力大不如前，然而他却有了计谋，有了在长期拳击赛中积累起的智慧，懂得怎样谨慎地运用自己的力量。他不仅懂得绝不能有一个多余的动作，还懂得怎样引诱对方消耗体力。他一次又一次运动手脚和躯体，假装要进攻，引得桑德尔后跳、躲闪或反击，他自己以逸待劳，却叫桑德尔以劳待逸。这是一个拳坛老将的战略部署。

第十局一开局，汤姆·金就开始用左勾拳直击对方的脸，阻止了对方猛烈的攻势。这时的桑德尔已学乖，立刻收回左臂，低头一闪，把右拳一勾，从侧面向他的脑袋砸去。这一拳打得太高，收效并不十分大，但金挨了这一拳，眼前一黑，又出现了过去的那种大脑短暂丧失意识的症状。刹那间，或者说在极短极短的一瞬间，他完全顿了下来。在这一瞬间，对手的身影从他的视野中消失了，由白白的一片观众的面孔组成的背景也消失了。这一瞬间过去之后，他又看到了对手以及由观众面孔组成的背景。他好像睡了一会儿，方才睁开眼睛一样。不过，他丧失意识的时间极短，还没等他倒下去，便一闪过去了。观众只看到他摇晃了一下，膝盖一弯，紧接着就见他恢复了过来，用左肩紧紧地护住下巴。

桑德尔又用同样的套路打了几拳，打得金头晕目眩，但他抵挡住了，继而转守为攻。他假装要使用左勾拳，后退半步，然而却用尽全身的力气挥动右拳直击对方的上首，时间计算得分秒不差，趁着桑德尔低头躲闪之际，直直地、重重地打到了他的脸上，打得他两脚腾空，缩成一团向后一歪，脑袋和肩膀同时砸在了垫子上面。金连着发动了两次这样的进攻，然后放开手痛揍对手，一拳又一拳，将对手打得靠在了绳子上。他不让桑德尔有喘息或还手之机，接连出拳，使得全场观众站起来欢呼，喝彩声此起彼伏、不绝于耳。可是，桑德尔的气力和耐力均不同凡响，他仍站立不倒，看起来非被打昏不可。台子旁边有位警官害怕这可怕的一幕发生，急忙起身要阻止他们再打下去。就在这时，锣声响了，宣告这一局结束。桑德尔摇摇晃晃回到他的角落里，对警官说他一点事也没有，仍然充满了力量。为了证明这一点，他向后连跳了两下，警官一看只好作罢。

汤姆·金瘫在自己的角落里，气喘如牛，心里大失所望。假如比赛在刚才中止了，裁判就会宣布他为赢家，奖金就会归他。跟桑德尔不一样，他参加比赛不是为了荣誉或者前程，而是为了那三十英镑的奖金。现在可好，经过这一分钟的休息，桑德尔便会恢复过来的。

后生可畏——这句话猛然跳进了他的脑海里。记得头一次听到这话，是在他将斯托希尔·比尔打得落花流水的那天晚上。那天晚上打完比赛，一个富佬请他喝酒，拍拍他的肩膀，对他说了这句话。后生的确可畏！那个富佬所言不虚。在很早以前的那天晚上，他曾是个后生。今日的后生却坐在对面的角落里。至于他自己，则是一个已经苦战了半个小时的老人。如果按桑德尔那样打法，他恐怕连一刻钟也撑不下来。问题的关键在于：他的体力无法恢复。他血管肿胀、心脏疲惫，这使他在中间休息的时间里无法重新积聚起力量。一开始，他的力量就不够充沛，两腿发沉，现在腿肚子都有点抽筋了。比赛前，他就不该走那两英里的路。还有，他早上一起来就渴望吃块牛排，却没能吃得上。想起这来他就恨得牙根痒痒，恨肉店的老板不肯赊账给他。让一个老人空着肚子上台比赛，谈何容易！区区一块牛排，最多不过值几个便士，然而对现在的他来说却意味着三十英镑。

随着一声锣响，第十一局开始了。桑德尔几个箭步冲了过来，显示出一种他实际并不具有的锐气。金情知那只不过是虚张声势，自打有了拳击赛就有了这种把戏。他扭抱住对方，躲避锋芒，然后分身，容桑德尔摆开阵势——这是他渴望看到的。他先是佯装用左勾拳，使对方低头一闪，同时举拳招架，然后他便退半步，用右勾拳以泰山压顶之势砸在对方的脸上，打得桑德尔摔倒在了垫子上。这之后，他发动凌厉攻势，不让对方有片刻喘息机会，虽然自己也挨上几拳，但他击中对方的次数要多得多，打得桑德尔靠在了绳子上。他左一拳右一拳，用各种拳路击打对方，挣脱对方的扭抱，或者用重拳打得对方甚至来不及扭抱住他。每逢桑德尔快要倒下去的时候，他就举起一只手撑住他，另一只手立刻挥拳砸过去，打得他靠在绳子上，倒也无法倒了。

这时候，全场都疯狂了，成了汤姆·金的天下，几乎每一个人都在为他助威。“加油，汤姆！”“打垮他！打垮他！”“胜利属于你，汤姆！胜利属于你，汤姆！”比赛就要在旋风式的攻击之下结束了，而观众花钱来这儿，要看的就是这种场面。

半小时以来，汤姆·金一直在保存实力，力图此刻毕其功于一役，把所有的力量都用了出来。对他而言，成败在此一举。他的气力消耗得很快，他只希望在最后一点气力用完之前，能够打得对方爬不起来。因此，他一面继续猛攻，一面冷静地估计着他拳头的分量以及它们造成的损伤。他意识到桑德尔是一个很难被打垮的人。桑德尔的体力和耐力简直强到极点——那是年轻人未经损伤的体力和耐力。桑德尔势必能成为拳坛新星。他具有成功的素质。只有这样坚韧的体质，方能造就叱咤风云的拳击手。

桑德尔站不稳了，踉踉跄跄的，但汤姆自己的腿也在抽筋，指关节也疼了起来。他咬紧牙关继续猛烈攻击，可每一拳打出去，他的手都疼得钻心。现在，他虽然一拳也没有挨到，力量却在锐减，固然拳拳击中要害，分量却大不如先前了。他每打一拳都要付出艰苦的努力，两腿似灌了铅一般重，移动时显然有些费劲。桑德尔的支持者看见了他的这种征兆为之振奋，开始为桑德尔大声加油。

金受到刺激，振作起精神来，连着打了两拳——一个左勾拳瞄得稍微高了些，打在了对方的胸口上，一个右勾拳打在了对方的下巴上。这两拳打得并不重，可是桑德尔已经无力支撑，开始眼冒金星，便一头栽倒，躺在那儿打起了哆嗦。裁判走过来，冲着他的耳朵开始数那决定命运的秒数。如果在数到十秒之前他还没有起来，他就输了。观众们都站在那儿等候，全场鸦雀无声。金两腿发抖，勉强坚持着。他感到天旋地转，觉得观众的脸好像一片大海，在眼前波翻浪涌，裁判数数的声音似从遥远的地方传到他耳朵里来。不过，他意志笃定，认为自己稳操胜券，觉得桑德尔挨了那样一顿重拳，是不可能再站起来的。

只有血气方刚的年轻选手才能站起来——桑德尔站起来了。裁判数到四秒的时候，他翻了个身，面孔朝下，瞎摸着去抓绳子。数到七的时候，他挣扎着单膝跪起，似醉汉一般脑袋晃来晃去的。当裁判高声数道“九！”，他已站得笔直，摆出了标准的防御姿势，用左臂护住脸，右臂护住腹部。他护住要害部位之后，便脚步蹒跚地向金靠过去，希望能扭住他，以争取时间。

桑德尔站起来的瞬间，金就冲了过去，不料打出去的两拳都被对方的胳膊挡住了。一转眼，桑德尔便贴了过来，拼命地抱紧他，裁判介入将两人分开。金也急于摆脱纠缠。他知道年轻人恢复得快，认为只要不让桑德尔恢复元气，对方就会成为他的手下败将。只要狠狠的一拳就可以解决问题。桑德尔败局已定，而他必胜无疑。他在战略和战术上都已占了上风。桑德尔趔趔趄趄，立足不稳，身处一个节骨眼上，成败在此一举。只要结结实实给他一拳，就能够将他放翻，让他再也爬不起来。这时，汤姆·金突然感到一阵悲哀，想起了自己在家里渴望吃到的那块牛排，觉得有那块牛排为这必要的一拳垫底就好了。他拼尽全力打了一拳，但这一拳不够重，也不够快。桑德尔摇摆了一下，没有摔倒，踉踉跄跄地走到绳子跟前，靠在了绳子上。金摇摇晃晃地跟了过去，忍住钻心的疼痛又打了一拳。可是他的身体已经不听指挥了。他只剩下一种战斗的意志了，而由于疲劳过度，这种战斗的意志也变得薄弱和模糊了。这一拳原本是瞄准对方下巴的，却落在了对方的肩膀上。他有意打高些，谁知疲倦的肌肉不听指挥。这一拳的反推力很强，使得他连连后退，差点摔倒。接着，他又打了一拳，这一拳完全落了个空。身体极度虚弱的他倒在了桑德尔的身上，紧紧扭抱住对方的身体，以免自己摔倒在地。

金靠在那儿，不愿再分开。他力气已尽，到了穷途末路。后生可畏——即便在两人靠在一起的时候，他也感觉得到桑德尔的力量在一点点增强。等到裁判把他们分开，他看到的是一个恢复了元气的朝气蓬勃的青年。桑德尔每时每刻都在变得越来越强壮。他头几拳软绵绵的，不起什么作用，后来拳头变得又准又狠。汤姆·金眼睛昏花，他看见那只戴手套的拳头朝自己的下颚砸过来，想伸胳膊将其挡住。他看到了危险，想采取措施应对，可是胳膊像是灌满了铅一样，重得抬不起来，怎么举也举不起。他试图用意志力将它举起来，而就在这时，那只戴手套的拳头击中了他。他砰地挨了重重一拳，像被闪电击中了一样，顿时眼前一黑昏了过去。

再睁开眼时，他已经坐在了他的那个角落里，只听见观众喊声震天，犹如邦迪海滩(3)的海浪在咆哮。他的后脑勺下垫着一块湿海绵，锡特·沙利文正在向他脸上和胸口上喷冷水，让他清醒过来。他的手套已经被取下。桑德尔正弯下腰跟他握手。他一点也不恨这个打昏他的人，于是便真诚地紧紧握了握对方的手，握得他那碎了的指关节都发痛了。之后，桑德尔走到台子中央，观众停止了山呼海啸般的欢呼声，接着便听见他宣布自己接受年轻的普隆托的挑战，而且提出要加注，把赌注增加到一百英镑。金在一旁漠然地观望着，他的助手则忙着为他擦去冒着热气的汗水，揩干他的脸，准备送他离场。他觉得很饿。不是那种一点点折磨人的寻常的饥饿感，而是一种令人虚脱的饥饿感，先是心口一紧，继而疼痛传遍全身。回想起刚才的恶战，他打得桑德尔摇摇欲坠，站都站不稳，几近失败。唉，怨都怨自己没能吃上那块牛排！正是缺了那块牛排，那关键的一拳才丧失了威力，导致了他的失败。失败的根源完全是那块牛排！

他的助手们搀扶着他，想帮助他钻过绳子。他挣脱他们的手，自个儿低头钻了过去，重重地跳到了台下。助手们走在前边，为他在人头攒动的中央通道上辟出一条路，他则跟在后面。在更衣室换好衣服后，他向大街上走去，在大厅入口处有一个年轻人跟上来同他说话。

“刚才你已经控制住了他，为什么不把他放翻呢？”那个年轻人问。

“你懂个什么，见鬼去吧！”汤姆·金说完，下了台阶，走到了人行道上。

街角那家酒馆的门开得大大的，只见里面灯火辉煌，女服务员笑容满面，他听见许多顾客都在谈论这场比赛，还听见吧台那儿传来叮当叮当响的硬币声。有人喊他进去喝一杯。他明显犹豫了一下，随后便谢绝了，继续走他的路。

他口袋里连一个铜板也没有，回家的两英里路好像特别长。他的确老了。走过道曼公园的时候，他突然在一条凳子上坐了下来，他想到了正在家里眼巴巴等着他，盼望着知道这场比赛结果的妻子。这事实比任何致命的拳头都沉重，简直叫他无法去面对。

他感到虚弱不堪、浑身酸痛，碎了的指关节疼痛难忍，似乎在警告他：即便能找份粗活干，也要等一个星期后才可以握得住锄头或者铲子。心口饿得发慌，那种感觉让他直想呕吐。他心里感到一阵悲凉，眼中涌出了少有的泪水。他双手捂脸，洒下了英雄泪，不禁想起了年老的斯托希尔·比尔，想起了很久以前的那个晚上自己是怎样对待他老人家的。可怜的斯托希尔·比尔老前辈呀！现在他总算明白了当年比尔为什么在更衣室里放声痛哭了。

————————————————————

(1) 位于澳大利亚悉尼市。

(2) 古希腊神话中的复仇女神。

(3) 位于悉尼。

墨西哥人

1

没有人对他知根知底——最不了解他的恐怕要数革命委员会里的人。在他们的眼里，他是个“神秘人物”，是个“大爱国者”。他以自己的方式行事，和他们一样，也是在为即将来到的墨西哥革命埋头苦干。一开始，委员会里没人喜欢他，过了很久他们才发现他是同路人。他头一次出现在他们那拥挤、忙乱的活动场所时，大家都怀疑他是个奸细，是迪亚斯(1)的秘密警察收买来的爪牙。委员会里已有很多同志被关进美国各地的普通监狱和军事监狱，还有一些同志甚至披枷带锁被押出了边境，面朝土坯墙排成队，在那儿遭到处决。

第一眼看到这个男孩子，大家对他的印象就不好。称他为男孩子，是因为他未满十八岁，而且照他的年龄来看，他的个头也不算高。他说他叫菲力普·利维拉，说他的志向是为革命效力。他就说了这么两句话——一句废话也没有，也不做进一步的解释，然后就站在那儿等待着，脸上没有笑容，眼神缺乏善意。连身材高大、脾气暴烈的保利诺·维拉也感到心里一哆嗦，觉得他是个阴险、可怕、令人捉摸不透的人物，黑黑的眼睛里有一种阴冷似毒蛇的神情。那双眼睛像冷冷的火焰在熊熊燃烧，似乎凝聚着深仇大恨。他的目光扫过那些革命者的脸，落到了矮小的赛斯比太太正在忙着敲字的打字机上。在他们目光交汇的那一刹那——她那时碰巧抬起了头——她也感觉到他身上有一种难以名状的东西，以至不由停下了手。而后为了继续敲那封她正在写的信，她不得不往回读了读打过的内容。

保利诺·维拉询问似的看了看阿莱兰诺和拉莫斯，后两者也询问似的看了看他，然后又互相对视了一眼。他们的目光中出现了迟疑不决的神色。这个身材瘦削的小伙子来历不明，让人感到不安。他们是正直的普通革命者，对迪亚斯及其暴政恨之入骨，但这种仇恨是充满朴素爱国主义情怀的仇恨，而这位小伙子则像一个不可理解的谜团，叫他们吃不透。他有些与众不同，然而究竟有哪些不同，他们也说不出个所以然。维拉历来冲动，遇事不假思索，这时率先打破了僵局。

“很好，”他冷冷地说，“你说你愿意为革命效力。那就请你脱下外套，把外套挂到那边去。容我交代一下……你过来，这儿有水桶和抹布，这里的地板脏了，你就先把地板擦一擦吧，把别的房间的地也擦一擦。接下来就是洗痰盂和擦窗户。”

“这算是为革命效力吗？”小伙子问。

“是为革命效力。”维拉回答道。

利维拉用冰冷而狐疑的目光看了他们一眼，随即动手脱外套。

“那好吧。”他口中说道。

除此之外，他再没有说别的。之后，他每天都来干活——扫地、擦地板、收拾房间。在他们中最勤快的同志来工作前，他就已经清理掉炉灰，拿来了煤炭和引火柴，生着了炉子。

“我可以睡在这儿吗？”有一次，他问道。

啊哈！狐狸的尾巴终于露出来了——果然是迪亚斯的爪牙！睡在他们委员会的活动场所，就可以刺探情报，掌握墨西哥境内同志的名单以及地址！他的请求被拒绝了。此事利维拉也再没有提起过。他在哪儿歇宿、在哪儿吃饭以及如何糊口，大家一无所知。一次，阿莱兰诺提出要给他几美元的工钱，他摇摇头拒绝了。维拉过来帮着敲边鼓，劝他把钱收下，而他说：

“这是为革命工作，不取报酬。”

如今，发动一场革命是需要资金的，而委员会的状况总是捉襟见肘。委员们忍饥挨饿、埋头苦干，再苦再累也无怨言。不过，有的时候，革命的成败似乎也就是几美元的问题。有一次，那也是第一次，由于拖欠了两个月的房租，房东威胁说要赶他们出去。正是菲力普·利维拉——那个衣着寒酸而褴褛的打扫房间的小工，拿来了六十块金币，放在了梅·赛斯比的桌子上。这样的情形出现了不止一次。一天，几台打字机忙个不停，打出了三百封信（有求援信；有向劳工组织发出的呼吁书；有请求报纸编辑报道正义新闻的信件；有反对美国法院以高压手段对待革命者的抗议书），而这些信件由于缺邮资无法寄出。维拉父亲留给维拉的那块老式的金怀表不见了。梅·赛斯比中指上戴着的金戒指也是。真是到了山穷水尽的地步。拉莫斯和阿莱兰诺捋着他们的长胡子，苦于无计。这些信必须寄出去，可是买邮票，邮局却不愿意赊账。利维拉见状，戴上帽子出了门，回来时，将一千张两分的邮票放在了梅·赛斯比的桌子上。

“谁知道这是不是从迪亚斯那儿拿来的赃钱。”维拉对同志们说。

其他的人抬了抬眉毛，都有点说不准。就这样，为革命情愿当清洁工的菲力普·利维拉每当遇到这种情况，便拿出真金白银来供委员会使用。

可是，委员们还是无法喜欢上他。他们不了解他。他为人处世跟他们大不相同，从不跟人深谈，也不愿让别人打听他的事情。他虽然只是个毛头小伙子，他们也不敢冒昧地对他盘根问底。

“也许他是个伟大而孤独的人吧。谁知道呢，谁知道呢。”阿莱兰诺无奈地说。

“他有点缺乏人情味。”拉莫斯说。

“他的内心冷酷无情，”梅·赛斯比说，“他的生活中没有阳光和笑声。他像一个死人，却又充满了可怕的活力。”

“他肯定经历过许多磨难，”维拉说，“没吃过万千苦头的人，绝不会这个样子。说来，他还只是个孩子呀！”

不管怎样，他们还是无法喜欢上他。他从不多话，从不打听任何情况，也不献言献策。大家谈论革命，谈得慷慨激昂的时候，他总是站在旁边听着，脸上毫无表情，仿佛一个死人，唯有一双眼睛在冷冷地燃烧着。那双眼睛盯着发言人的脸，瞧瞧这个，再看看那个，目光似闪着亮光的冰锥般刺人，让人觉得慌乱和不安。

“他不是奸细，”维拉私下对梅·赛斯比说，“而是一个爱国者。请相信我的话，他是咱们中间最伟大的爱国者。我知道他是，能感觉得到他是，无论是从情感方面还是理智方面都可以感觉得到。只不过我对他的根底仍一无所知。”

“他的脾气很坏。”梅·赛斯比说。

“这我知道，”维拉打了个哆嗦说，“他曾用他那双眼睛盯过我，里面没有爱，只有威胁，野蛮得像猛虎一样。我知道，假如我做出对革命事业不忠的事情，他一定会杀了我的。他没有感情，如钢刀般冷酷，似冰霜一样寒气逼人。就像在冬夜里，一个人在荒郊野外快要冻死时看到的冷冰冰的月光。实不相瞒，我不怕迪亚斯和他的那帮杀人魔王，可是对这个小伙子，却有几分惧怕。他周身散发着死神的气息。”

不过，说服大家第一次信任利维拉的也是维拉。洛杉矶和下加利福尼亚(2)之间的通讯线被破坏。三个同志自投罗网，当局将他们枪杀了。另有两个同志也在美国被捕，被关进了洛杉矶的监狱。联邦军司令胡安·阿尔瓦拉多是一个恶魔，他破坏了他们所有的计划。无论是下加利福尼亚的革命积极分子，还是刚刚加入的新人，委员会再也无法跟他们取得联系了。

年轻的利维拉奉命南下。他回来的时候，通讯线恢复了，胡安·阿尔瓦拉多也死了。他被发现死在床上，胸口插了一把刀，只露出来个刀柄。此事已超出了利维拉所执行命令的范围，但委员会的人知道这是非常时期，也就没有追究。他什么也没说。大家相互交换了眼色，满脸猜测。

“我早就告诉过你们，”维拉说道，“迪亚斯最应该怕的是这个小伙子，而非别人。他下手狠，毫不留情，简直就是上帝派来的使者。”

梅·赛斯比曾说他脾气坏，大家也感觉到了，后来发生的情况亦证实了这一点。他露面时，不是嘴唇破了，就是脸青了一块，要不就是一只耳朵发肿。很清楚，他一定是在外边的哪个地方跟人打架了——那是一个他吃饭、睡觉、挣钱，以他们所不熟悉的方式活动的地方。过了一阵子，他开始为他们每周一期的宣传革命的小报排字。而有的时候，他则有些力不从心——因为他不是指节上皮破血流，就是大拇指受伤动弹不得，要不就是左臂或右臂耷拉下来使不上劲，脸上露出痛苦不堪的表情。

“真是个浪荡子。”阿莱兰诺说。

“看来他经常出入那些乌七八糟的地方。”拉莫斯说。

“可是，他的钱是从哪儿弄来的呢？”维拉说，“就在今天，我才刚刚知道，买纸的钱是他付的——整整一百四十块！”

“他常常说不来就不来，”梅·赛斯比说，“连个解释的话也没有。”

“应该派人调查一下。”拉莫斯提议说。

“我可不愿去盯他的梢。”维拉说，“要是去了，你们恐怕再也见不到我了，要见也是见我的尸体。他的脾气太可怕了，发作起来，就是上帝也别想拦住他。”

“在他面前，我觉得自己可怜得像个小孩子。”拉莫斯坦白地说。

“我觉得他代表着一种力量，简直就像是原始人、野狼、咬人的响尾蛇、蜇人的蜈蚣。”阿莱兰诺说。

“他是革命的化身，”维拉说，“是革命的火焰和灵魂，在厉声呼喊着人们起来复仇，但行动的时候却无声无息，静悄悄地置敌人于死地。他俨然就是一个惩恶扬善的天使，夜深人静时巡回于大地。”

“我真是为他感到难过，”梅·赛斯比说，“他身边没有朋友，他痛恨所有人，之所以能够容忍咱们，是因为咱们可以为他实现愿望铺平道路。他很孤独……一个人孤苦伶仃的。”说到此处，她的声音有些哽咽，泪水模糊了双眼。

利维拉的确行踪诡秘，有时一连一个星期都不见他露面。一次，他出外一个月未归。每次出外归来后，他都会拿出一些金币放在梅·赛斯比的桌子上，什么情况也不解释，什么话也不多讲。此后，他会一连数天或数个星期待在委员会，全身心地投入工作。过不了多久，他又会开始白天出去，只在早晨和晚上出现。这种时候，他一大早就到委员会来，晚上又待得很晚。阿莱兰诺曾发现他午夜时分还在排字，手上添了新伤，指关节肿肿的，要不就是嘴唇裂了口子，血还在流。

2

形势危急，快到关键时刻了。革命能不能发动起来，完全取决于委员会的作为了，而委员会经济情况窘迫。他们比以往任何时候都缺钱，可是弄钱却越来越困难。爱国志士们已经捐出了他们的全部钱财，再也拿不出一分钱了。养路工们（从墨西哥逃出来的苦役）拿出他们微薄的工钱，把一半都捐给了委员会。但这只是杯水车薪。多年的艰苦奋斗、运筹帷幄和秘密工作，眼看就要结出硕果了，时机已经成熟。一切的付出就像被放在天平上的砝码，只要再加一把劲，再做最后一次英勇的争取，革命会倒向胜利的一边。他们了解自己的祖国墨西哥。革命一旦爆发，星星之火便可以燎原。迪亚斯政权就会像纸牌屋一样垮塌。在边境，起义工作已准备就绪。一声令下，一个美国人就会率领一百名世界产业工人联合会的会员越过边境前去攻打下加利福尼亚。可是，他们需要一些枪支。纵跨大西洋，委员会跟美墨边境的相关人士保持着联系，他们也需要枪支——冒险家、雇佣兵、土匪、心怀不满的美国工会会员、社会主义者、无政府主义者、恶棍、墨西哥流亡者、挣脱枷锁的苦役，以及受尽鞭打，从柯达伦和科罗拉多的牢笼里逃出来的渴望参与战斗的矿工——这是些流离失所、生活无望的人，被当今错综复杂的世界所抛弃。枪支弹药！枪支弹药！他们无休无止地索求着这些武装。

只要让这支人员复杂、境况潦倒、复仇心切的队伍冲过边境，革命的大幕就拉开了。海关及北部的港口会一一被攻占，迪亚斯想拦也拦不住。鉴于必须守住南方，他不敢抽调精锐部队前来阻击。而在南方也会遍地烽火，人们会揭竿而起。他的防御会一个城池接一个城池地崩溃，他的政权将一个州接一个州地垮台。最终，高歌猛进的革命军会将墨西哥城——迪亚斯的最后一个据点围得水泄不通。

可当务之急，委员会需要的是钱。他们有人——有迫不及待地渴望拿起武器战斗的人。他们也认识枪械商，那些人愿意卖枪给他们，并会负责把枪运来。只可惜由于酝酿革命，委员会已经资财耗尽，花光了最后一美元，爱国者们囊空如洗，饿着肚子度日，革命的天平在摇摆不定。必须弄到枪支弹药！必须把这些来自五湖四海的队伍武装起来！可是，怎么做到这一点？拉莫斯哀叹道他的财产已被政府没收；阿莱兰诺悔不该少年时挥金如土，家财荡尽；梅·赛斯比觉得委员会如果在过去精打细算，也不至如此。

“想想吧，墨西哥能不能获得自由，居然要取决于区区的几千美元！”保利诺·维拉说道。

绝望蒙在了每个人的脸上。他们本来把最后的希望都寄托在了乔斯·阿马利诺身上，他最近才加入委员会，答应拿出钱来，可是他在奇瓦瓦的自家庄园不幸被捕，在他家的马厩墙边被枪毙了。这个消息是刚刚才传来的。

当时利维拉正跪在地上擦地板，听到这种情况，不由抬起了头，手里拿着刷子，两只光膀子上沾满了肥皂沫和脏水。

“五千块够不够？”他问道。

大家眼里露出了惊讶的神情。维拉点了点头，咽了口唾沫。他一时说不出话来，可就在这一瞬间他的心里升腾起了希望。

“下订单购枪吧。”利维拉说。接着，他面露愧色地又说了一通话——大家以前从未听他说过如此多的话。“时间紧迫。三个星期之内我就把五千美元拿来。这样反倒好。那时天气会暖和些，利于冲锋陷阵。我也只能做到这些了。”

维拉不敢抱太大的指望。这实在匪夷所思！自从他参加革命活动以来，不知有多少美好的愿望终成泡影。他相信这个破衣烂衫的革命勤杂工的承诺，现在却有点拿不定主意。

“你疯了吧。”他说。

“三个星期之内把钱拿来，”利维拉说，“下订单购枪吧。”

随后，他站起身，将卷起的袖子放下，穿上了外套。

“下订单购枪吧，”他说道，“我这就去想办法。”

3

一阵忙乱之后，打了许多电话，骂了许多脏话，凯利的事务所在晚上开了个会。凯利为生意上的事忙得不可开交，运气老是不好。他把丹尼·沃德从纽约请来，安排好了他跟比利·卡瑟的拳击赛，日期定在三个星期之后，不料卡瑟受了重伤，已经躺了两天，这件事他小心地瞒着体育记者。一时找不到个选手代替卡瑟上场。凯利差不多给东部的每一个有资格参赛的轻量级拳击手都发了电报，可那些人都签了合同，忙得抽不开身来。眼前倒是出现了一线希望，只是这希望有点渺茫。

“你简直是吃了熊心豹子胆了。”凯利见到利维拉，看了他一眼，劈头盖脸便来了这么一句。

利维拉眼里满是深仇大恨，脸上却不动声色。

“我能打败沃德。”他只说了这么一句。

“你怎么知道能打败他？你看过他的比赛吗？”

利维拉摇了摇头。

“他就是闭上眼睛，用一只手出拳也能打败你。”

利维拉耸了耸肩膀。

“对这你有什么可说的？”拳击事务所的老板大声问道。

“反正我能打败他。”

“你跟什么人交过手？”迈克尔在一旁问道。他是凯利的哥哥，经营着黄石赌场，靠拳击赛赚得盆满钵溢。

利维拉只是冷冷地瞪了他一眼，没有回答。

拳击事务所老板的秘书是个穿着很花哨的小伙子，见状不由轻蔑地哼了一声。

“哦，你和罗伯兹是熟人，”凯利打破了这充满敌意的沉寂，开口说道，“他马上就来。我派人去叫他了。坐下来等一会儿吧。从你的外表看来，你是完全没有胜算的。我可不能让这场比赛出洋相，坏了观众们的兴致。前排的座位一张票就卖十五美元，这你是知道的。”

后来，罗伯兹出现了，显然带着几分醉意。他是个瘦高个，慢慢吞吞的，无论是言谈还是举止都不慌不忙、懒懒散散。

凯利直截了当地说道：

“喂，罗伯兹，你自诩慧眼发现了这个墨西哥小屁孩。你知道，卡瑟的胳膊断了。这个面黄肌瘦的小家伙找上门来毛遂自荐，说他能代替卡瑟上场。你觉得怎么样？”

“这挺好的，凯利，”罗伯兹慢条斯理地回答道，“他可以打得很漂亮。”

“想来你接下来会说他能打败沃德喽。”凯利很快地顶了他一句。

罗伯兹沉吟良久，末了说道：

“不，我不会说这话的。沃德是一流拳击手，是拳王。不过，他一时半会儿是打不垮利维拉的。我了解利维拉，谁都别想叫他乱阵脚。我从未见他惊慌失措过。他善于使双拳，能够左右开弓，一个冷不防就可以将对手放翻。”

“开不开弓倒没什么关系。关键是，他能不能打出些名堂来？你这一辈子一直在培养和训练拳击手，你的眼力我是很欣赏的。他究竟能不能让观众觉得自己没有花冤枉钱？”

“他一定不会让观众失望的。他会让沃德饱尝一顿苦头。你不了解这个小伙子，而我了解。是我发现了他。他可不是任人宰割的羔羊，而是个魔鬼。如果有人问起，你也可以说他是个复仇天使。他的拳路神出鬼没，会叫沃德眼花缭乱，你们大家看了也会眼花缭乱的。我不敢断言他定能打败沃德，但他一定会叫你们大开眼界，让你们知道他不愧为后起之秀。”

“就这样吧，”凯利转过脸对他的秘书说，“你给沃德打个电话。我已经给他打过招呼了，说安排好就请他出场。他就在黄石赌场对面，此时正在对着媒体秀肌肉，出风头呢。”

凯利交代完，又回过头来对罗伯兹说：“喝一杯，怎么样？”

罗伯兹一边慢慢喝着掺了苏打水的威士忌，一边讲起了他发现人才的经历。

“我还没跟你说我是怎么发现这个年轻人的呢。话说几年前，他跑到了教练场来。当时我正在训练普雷恩，让他准备迎战德莱尼。普雷恩下手狠毒，对陪练员残酷无情，所以弄得我找不到愿意跟他合作的人。就在这时，我注意到了这个饿得半死的墨西哥年轻人，一时顾不了许多，便一把揪住他，给他戴上拳击手套，让他进场。他比生牛皮还结实，就是没气力，对拳击方面的事情一窍不通。普雷恩打得他一佛出世，二佛升天。他咬紧牙坚持了两局，最后还是昏了过去。全是因为饥饿过度，被打趴下了。他惨得都叫人认不出来了。我给了他半美元的辛苦费和一顿饱饭。他已经有两天粒米未进了，吃饭狼吞虎咽，你真该看看他的那种吃相。我心想他不会再来了。谁料，他第二天又跑了来，虽然身体僵硬、酸痛，还是想再挣半美元的辛苦钱和一顿饱饭。日子久了，他就打得好起来了。他简直天生就是当拳击手的料，顽强得令人无法想象。他残酷无情，冷得就像一块冰。自从跟他交往以来，他张口说过的话从没有超过十一个字。他只是埋头做事，从不多话。”

“我以前见过他，”那位秘书说，“他替你干过不少活。”

“有些名堂的拳击手都拿他练过手，”罗伯兹说，“他也从他们那儿获益匪浅。可以看得出，有些拳击手是打不过他的。不过，他的心思并不在这上面。我觉得他压根就不喜欢这一行。他只是擅长拳击，并靠此谋生而已。”

“最近几个月，他在小俱乐部里打过几场比赛。”凯利说。

“是的。不知道他为何那样做。好像是一时心血来潮吧。他一阵旋风般出场，把当地的那些小拳击手打得落花流水。他似乎缺钱，也赢了一些钱，只是在穿着上看不出来。他神出鬼没，没人知道他在干什么，也没人知道他把时间都花在了哪里。即便来拳击场干活，他也是来如风，去无影，一般都是活一干完就走人。有时候，他会一连几个星期不露面。有一点：他不听别人的劝告。他就像个摇钱树，如果有人当他的代理人，他肯定有钱赚，但是他压根不考虑。瞧着吧，你跟他谈条件，他肯定会坚持要现金的。”

话说到此处，丹尼·沃德来了，前呼后拥的，经理和教练也跟了来。他像一阵微风飘然而至，表情和蔼可亲，让人一见就喜欢。他见了大家好一阵寒暄，谈笑风生、妙语连珠，忽而莞尔一笑，忽而捧腹大笑。这是他为人处世的风格，虚情居多，真心则少，极会逢场作戏。他觉得在江湖上混，“热情”是最好的法宝。而在内心深处，他却是一个深思熟虑、冷血无情的拳击手，一个精明的生意人。其余的都是假面。那些了解他或者跟他谈过生意的人都说，一接触到金钱，他就会六亲不认、原形毕露。每逢谈生意，他必到现场，有人说他的经理完全是个傀儡，只是充当了他的传声筒。

利维拉则是两样。他的血管里流着印第安人和西班牙人的血液。只见他远远坐在一个角落里，一声不吭，一动不动，只有两个黑眼珠在转，看看这张脸，再瞧瞧那张脸，将一切都收入了眼帘。

“原来是这伙计，”丹尼一面说，一面用审视的眼光把他未来的对手上下打量了一番，“你好，老弟。”

利维拉眼里冒火，恶狠狠的，连理都没有理对方。他讨厌所有的美国佬，而这个美国佬更是叫他一见就恨得牙根痒痒——这种现象极为罕见。

“天呀！”丹尼对拳击事务所的老板半开玩笑地提出了抗议，“竟然找了个哑巴跟我交手。”大家哄堂大笑。待笑声平息后，他又继续挖苦说：“如果说这就是你们找来的精兵强将，那么，洛杉矶一定是人才匮乏了。你们是从哪家幼儿园把他找来的？”

“这小家伙并不简单，丹尼，听我的，”罗伯兹替利维拉圆场说，“他并不像表面看上去那么容易对付。”

“这场比赛的票都卖出去一半了，”凯利央求地说，“你必须出场跟他赛一赛了，丹尼。目前的情况也只能如此了。”

丹尼又看了一眼利维拉，目光漫不经心，显得很是轻蔑，然后叹了口气说：“那我就上场吧，拳头落得轻一点就是了。但愿他别一拳就给打死了。”

罗伯兹哼了声鼻子。

“还是谨慎一些为妙，”丹尼的经理警告道，“不了解对方的底细，就别轻易交手，免得生出些枝节来。”

“没关系，我会当心的，没什么了不起的，”丹尼微微一笑说，“一开始，我就悠着点，为了娱乐观众先慢慢奉陪着他。这样的表演打上十五局，最后来个撒手锏将他放翻，你看怎么样，凯利？”

“一言为定，”凯利回答说，“等你兑现承诺。”

“那就来谈生意吧。”丹尼说完停下来盘算了一番，然后才继续说了下去。“当然喽，跟上次和卡瑟的那场比赛一样，门票的六成半归我们。不过，这次拳击手之间的分成略有不同——我应该拿其中的八成。”他又转过来问他的经理道：“你看怎么样？”

经理点了点头。

“这样的分成，你明白吗？”凯利问利维拉。

利维拉摇了摇头。

“情况是这样的，”凯利解释道，“门票的六成半是分给拳击手的。你是个新手，又没有名气。你和丹尼之间分成，你拿两成，其余的八成归丹尼。这样公平合理，你说是吧，罗伯兹？”

“这是很公平的，利维拉，”罗伯兹赞同地说，“要知道，你现在还没有名气呢。”

“门票分成的六成半一共是多少钱？”利维拉问道。

“唔，也许五千块，也许可以多到八千块，”丹尼插嘴解释道，“大概就是这么个数目。分到你手里的大概有一千块到一千六百块。败在我这样的名将手下，还能赚到一些钱，是相当不错的了。这你还有什么可说的？”

利维拉的回答却惊得他们连气都喘不过来了。

“胜者拿全部的分成。”他斩钉截铁地说。

屋子里静悄悄的，掉根针在地上都能够听得见。

“这有点像欺负小孩，抢小孩的糖果。”丹尼的经理说。

丹尼摇了摇头。

“我在这一行混得时间太长了，”只听他说道，“在这里我并不想影射裁判或在场的任何一个人，也无心指责操纵比赛的人以及赛场上有时存在的猫腻，只想说这场比赛对我而言是划不来的。我打比赛不愿冒风险。谁知道会发生什么事呢。也许，我的胳膊会突然断了，或者被什么人下了药，谁都说不清。”说到这里，他摇了摇头，表情凝重。“不论输赢，我都拿八成。你说怎么样，墨西哥人？”

利维拉也摇了摇头。

丹尼火冒三丈，顿时露出了狰狞的面目。

“狗日的小兔崽子！我真想现在就揍你一顿，打得你满地找牙。”

罗伯兹身子一侧，挡在了两个势同水火的仇敌之间。

“胜者拿全部的分成。”利维拉阴沉着脸，把刚才的话又说了一遍。

“为什么非得如此呢？”丹尼问。

“因为我能打败你。”利维拉直截了当地回答。

丹尼摆出打架的架势，把外套脱下了一半。他的经理了解他，知道那只不过是吓唬人摆个花架子。由于众人劝解，外套最终并没有脱下来。此时他赢得了大家的同情，使得利维拉成了孤家寡人。

“给我听着，你这个小笨蛋，”凯利插嘴说，“你只不过是个无名小辈。我们知道你这几个月打过几场比赛，击败了当地的几个末流拳击手。可是，丹尼是一流的。这场比赛结束之后，下一场就是锦标赛，他将会成为冠军。而你仅仅是名不见经传的小辈，出了洛杉矶，就没有人知道你了。”

“这场比赛结束后，他们会知道的。”利维拉耸了耸肩说。

“你居然妄想着能打败我？”丹尼忍不住插嘴说。

利维拉点了点头。

“得了吧，你也该理性一些，”凯利恳求道，“想想海报上该怎么说。”

“我需要这笔钱。”利维拉言简意赅地说。

“你八辈子也别想赢我。”丹尼语气坚定地说。

“那么你为什么不同意呢？”利维拉反唇相讥，“既然你轻易便能把钱赢到手，为什么不赢呢？”

“好吧，那我就给你点颜色看！”丹尼突下决心，高声喊道，“我要在台子上打死你，小兔崽子！你竟然敢挖苦我！凯利，你把这条件写下来吧——胜者拿全部的分成。把消息登在报纸的体育专栏里，就说这是一场复仇之战。我要让这个初出茅庐的小兔崽子领教一下我的厉害。”

凯利的秘书默默地记着，丹尼制止了他。

“等一下！”他转过来问利维拉：“体重怎么个称法呢？”

“上台前称。”利维拉回答说。

“那是绝对不行的，小兔崽子。如果胜者拿全部的分成，就得在上午十点钟称体重。”

“胜者拿全部的分成？”利维拉追问了一句。

丹尼点了点头，将此事敲定。他要在精力最饱满的时候上台比赛。

“那就在十点钟称体重。”利维拉说。

秘书的笔落下，继续写了起来。

“你比他要轻五磅呢，”罗伯兹向利维拉抱怨道，“这样，你就吃大亏了，必输无疑。丹尼壮得像头牛，肯定会打败你的。你这个傻瓜，恐怕你连一丁点儿取胜的希望都没有。”

利维拉没吱声，只是用充满仇恨的目光扫了他一眼。以前他总觉得罗伯兹在美国人当中算是最正直的一个，现在就连罗伯兹他也蔑视了。

4

利维拉上台的时候，几乎没有人注意。欢迎他的，只是稀稀拉拉的几声鼓掌，冷淡、勉强。没有观众相信他会赢，都觉得他只不过是一只落在强大的丹尼手中的待宰羔羊。另一方面，观众们感到有点失望。他们原本指望能看到丹尼·沃德和比利·卡瑟的激烈对决，而今却必须委屈自己，看这个初出茅庐的小孩子出洋相。还有，他们在丹尼身上押了二对一，甚至三对一的赌注，以此表示他们对这种变动的不满。观众下赌注，历来都是投在自己喜欢的选手身上。

这个墨西哥小子坐在他的那个角落里等待开场。时间在一分钟一分钟地被拖延着。丹尼故意让他等着，虽说是老把戏了，但用在初上场的新手身上却屡试不爽。新手傻坐在那里，焦虑油然而生，看着那些冷酷无情、吞云吐雾的观众，心里的恐惧感会一点点增加。但这一次，这种老把戏却失败了。罗伯兹说得对，利维拉可不是好对付的。他比任何一个选手都从容不迫、泰然自若，比任何一个选手都有胆量，压根就没有慌乱的迹象。连他自己的那个角落里也弥漫着他必败的气息，可这些对他毫无影响。他的助手是几个素不相识的美国佬，都是些窝囊废，拳击赛上的不得志者，既无尊严又无本事。他们一个个垂头丧气，铁了心认为他们这一方必输无疑。

“现在你可要当心点，”领头的助手斯巴德·哈格蒂提醒他说，“凯利交代过，让你尽量把时间拖长一些。要不然，媒体会大做文章，说这又是一场狗屁比赛，在洛杉矶抹黑这场比赛。”

当时的情况没有一样对利维拉是有利的，但他全然不当回事。他鄙视拳击赛，认为这是可恶的美国人搞的一种可恨的把戏。他初入此行，在训练场给别人当“剁肉的砧板”(3)，只是因为肚子饿的缘故。后来参加比赛取得了骄人的战绩，他也全然不当回事。他痛恨拳击比赛。直到加入了委员会以后，他才为了筹集资金乐于与人交手，因为他觉得这样挣钱比较容易。按说，在自己厌恶的行业取得成功者，他并非第一人。

对于这场比赛，他没有考虑过多，只知道必须取胜，不允许有其他的后果。在他的身后有一种力量在推动着他，使他抱有必胜的信心，而这种力量是在场的观众做梦也想不到的。丹尼·沃德参加比赛是为了赚钱，因为钱能够使他在生活中顺风顺水。而利维拉则是为了一种在心里熊熊燃烧的愿望和可怕的幻象。此刻，他孤单单地坐在赛台的角落里，眼睛睁得大大的，一面等着他的那个诡计多端的对手，一面清清楚楚看到了一幕幕幻象，就好像是他已经亲身经历过此时此刻。

他看见了粉墙围起的里奥布兰科(4)水力发电站；看见了发电站的六千个工人，一个个忍饥挨饿、满脸菜色，其中有七八岁的童工，每天要干很长时间的活，却只能挣十美分；看见了脸色惨白如死人一般的染坊里的工人，记起曾听父亲把这种染房叫作“自杀洞”，进去做一年工就会死掉；看见了他家的那个小庭院，母亲在那里煮饭和操持繁重的家务，还会抽空跑过来搂搂他、亲亲他；看见了他那大胡子、虎背熊腰的父亲——天下最慈爱的父亲，他心胸开阔，爱所有的人，心里充溢着对母亲以及在庭院墙角玩耍的小家伙们的爱。想当年，他的姓名并不是菲力普·利维拉，而是随父母的姓费尔南德斯，名叫胡安。后来，他自己把姓名改了，因为他发现费尔南德斯是那些警察局长和宪兵所痛恨的姓。

魁梧的、好心肠的华金·费尔南德斯父亲呀！这位父亲在利维拉看到的幻象里占有重要的位置。当年，利维拉并不了解自己的父亲，后来回忆往事，才对父亲产生了深刻的理解。他仿佛看见父亲在那个小印刷所里排文字，看见他趴在堆满杂物的桌子旁奋笔疾书，写下一行行充满激情的文字；看见工人们在天黑的时候借着夜色摸到他家来，偷偷摸摸的，像干什么坏事似的，跟他的父亲促膝交谈，谈上很长时间，而他这个少不更事的孩子则躺在角落里，时常偷听他们的谈话。

此时，斯巴德·哈格蒂的话似从很远的地方飘了过来：“千万不要一开局就被打趴下。这是老板的命令。挨打就挨打，坚持住，最后才能有点钱挣。”

时间过去十分钟了，他仍坐在他的那个角落里，还是不见丹尼的身影——看来，丹尼要把他的那套鬼把戏玩到极致。

利维拉记忆的长河开了闸门，往事如河水涌现而来。那一次，里奥布兰科的工人为了声援在普埃布拉(5)举行罢工的兄弟们，自己也举行了罢工，或者说是老板不愿满足工人们的要求而导致了停工。工人们饥饿难忍，纷纷进山找野果、树根和野菜充饥，结果吃得肚子疼，胃如刀绞。接着，噩梦接踵而至——就在公司仓库门前的空地上，成千上万饥饿的工人遭到枪击。罗萨里奥·马蒂尼兹将军率领迪亚斯的军队对工人大开杀戒，枪口不停喷出死亡的火焰，似乎永远也不会停止似的，工人血流成河，仿佛只有用鲜血才能洗刷掉这些工人所造下的“罪孽”。那是一个多么可怕的夜晚啊！他看见一辆辆敞篷车上，遇害工人的尸体堆积如山，准备运往韦拉克鲁斯(6)，抛进海里喂鲨鱼。他爬到恐怖的死人堆上，寻呀找呀，终于找见了他的父母，发现他们被剥光了衣服，浑身血肉模糊。母亲当时的样子他记得尤其清楚——母亲被几十具尸体压在底下，只露出来一张脸。耳边又响起了迪亚斯士兵的枪声，他急忙跳到地上，就像一只遭到猎人追赶的幼兽一样跑掉了。

正在遐想之际，他的耳边响起了山呼海啸般的欢呼声，只见丹尼·沃德在一群训练员和助手的簇拥下从中央通道正走过来。全场观众为之沸腾，热烈欢迎他们这位必胜无疑的英雄。人们一边倒，都拥护他、赞美他。当他得意扬扬地钻过绳子走上比赛台时，就连利维拉的助手也兴奋了起来，甚至说见到他有点高兴。他脸上挂着永不消失的招牌式微笑，笑啊笑的，鼻子、眼全在笑，就连眼角的鱼尾纹和眼珠子都在笑。如此和蔼可亲的拳击手，你就是找遍天下恐怕也找不到第二个。他的脸仿佛就是一幅宣扬善心和友谊的流动广告牌。他好像跟所有的人都认识，隔着绳子和他的朋友们说笑，打招呼。那些坐得远一点的，也都抑制不住崇拜的心情，高声喊着：“你好，丹尼！”这一充溢着欢快气氛的欢迎式足足持续了五分钟。

利维拉被冷落在那里，观众谁也不去注意他，仿佛他不存在似的。斯巴德·哈格蒂俯下身子，把他那张浮肿的脸凑到利维拉的跟前说：“别害怕。记住老板的命令，必须挺住，万不可倒下去。假如你倒下去，我们奉命在身，非得在更衣室里揍死你不可。明白吗？你必须拼死一搏。”

比赛场响起了雷鸣般的掌声。但见丹尼横穿台子朝着利维拉走了过来。他弯下腰，用双手握住利维拉的右手，热忱地摇了几下，把他那张笑开了花的脸和利维拉的脸贴得很近。他落落大方的运动员风范赢得了观众阵阵的喝彩——他向对手表现出的是兄弟般的友谊。随后，他的嘴唇动了几下，观众听不见他说的是什么，都以为他在善意地鼓励对方，于是又是一阵喝彩。只有利维拉听见了他那张挂满了笑容的嘴压低声音恶狠狠地说出的话：

“你这个墨西哥小兔崽子，我要把你的屎都打出来。”

利维拉纹丝不动，他甚至都没有站起来，只是用眼神表达着内心的仇恨。

“站起来，你这条狗！”身后有个人隔着绳子喊道。

观众嫌他缺乏运动员的风度，发出了一阵嘘声，可他依旧一动不动。丹尼穿过台子回到自己的角落时，人群又爆发出了欢呼喝彩声。

丹尼一脱下衣服，便引来了一片兴奋的赞叹声。他的身体堪称完美，柔韧性十足，强健而有力，显得精神抖擞，皮肤白嫩、细腻，跟女人一样。动作优雅，富于弹性，拥有强大的力量。他前后参赛几十场，已展示了自己的虎威。几乎所有的体育杂志都刊登过他的照片。

而斯巴德·哈格蒂扒下利维拉的套头毛衣时，听到的则是一片嘘声。由于皮肤黝黑，利维拉显得很瘦。他也有肌肉，但是和对手的肌肉相比，是不具可比性的。但观众疏于观察，看不到他厚实的胸膛，也想象不到他那肌肉的纤维是何等坚韧，想象不到那肌肉瞬间会产生怎样的爆发力，不知道他身体的每一个部分都受到精密的神经系统的操纵，可以在赛场上将他变为一台出色的战斗机器。在观众的眼里，他只是一个棕色皮肤的十八岁的年轻人，一副孩子似的身材。丹尼则完全不同，他是一个二十四岁的男子汉，呈现的是成年人的身材。裁判一声令下，二人走到台子中央，站在一起，这时这种对比就更加鲜明了。

利维拉注意到罗伯兹就坐在报社记者的背后，好像比平日醉得还厉害，舌头僵硬，说话更慢了。

“你可别乱了方寸，利维拉，”罗伯兹慢声慢调地说，“他打不死你，记住就是了。一开始，他会猛攻猛打，你可别乱了阵脚。你只需稳住阵脚，扭住他，由他打吧，反正也要不了你的性命。你就权当自己是训练场上的陪练员，挨几下打怕什么。”

利维拉就像是没听见似的。

“这个小东西老是阴沉着脸，”罗伯兹对坐在他旁边的一个男子嘟哝了一句，“对人总是爱答不理的。”

利维拉沉浸在回忆中，面无表情，没有显露出往常的那种仇恨神色。他眼睛里只看得到无数的来复枪——一眼望去，从跟前一直到贵宾席，观众的每一张面孔都幻化成了一支来复枪。接着，他又看见了漫长的墨西哥边境，那儿寸草不生，烈日当空，热得难受，聚集着一群群衣衫褴褛的人，眼巴巴盼望着拿到枪支。

他回到自己的那个角落，站在那儿等待着。他的助手钻过绳子下了台子，顺手将帆布矮凳也拿了下去。在四方形的拳击台的对角，丹尼正虎视眈眈地看着他。锣声一响，战斗拉开了序幕。观众高兴得大呼小叫。他们从未见过如此激动人心的序幕。报纸上说得很对：这是一场复仇之战。丹尼求战心切，三步两步就蹿过了四分之三的距离，恨不得一口将这个墨西哥小屁孩吞进肚里。他左一拳右一拳，不知打了多少拳，双臂挥动如飞轮在转，大有摧枯拉朽的架势。利维拉无处躲藏，全无招架之功，被那位拳坛老将从四面八方打来的暴风骤雨般的拳头所淹没。他立脚不稳，被打得靠在了绳子上，裁判将他们分开，紧接着又被打得靠在了上面。

这不像是拳击赛，简直就是杀戮，一场血腥的屠杀。任何观众，特别是那些下赌注的人，一开局就激动到了极点。丹尼的确拿出了看家本事，表现出了他的八面威风。可能是因为太笃信丹尼，太兴奋，太偏心眼，观众居然没注意到那个墨西哥人依然挺立着，没有倒下。他们已经忘记了利维拉的存在，因为丹尼攻势凌厉，铺天盖地的拳头把他遮了个严实，几乎看不见他。一分钟过去了，两分钟过去了。裁判把两个拳击手分开时，观众才看清楚了那个墨西哥人——只见他嘴唇被打得裂开，鼻子流血不止。利维拉转过身，踉踉跄跄走上前，又和对手扭打在了一起，脊背由于紧靠绳子，上面出现了一道道血印，直朝外渗血。可是观众没有注意到他的胸脯没有一起一伏，没注意到他的眼里仍有蓝色的火焰在燃烧。过去在训练场的残酷战斗里，不知有多少雄心勃勃的拳击手都在他身上练习过这种凌厉的攻击。为了能挣到每次半美元到一星期十五美元的钱，他每次都咬牙挺了过来，并从中学到了本事。训练场就是一座严酷的学校，他在那里受到了严酷的训练。

接下来，惊人的一幕发生了。快如旋风、令人眼花缭乱的战斗戛然而止，利维拉仍站在那里，英勇无敌的丹尼却仰面朝天倒在了地上。就在他慢慢恢复知觉时，全身抖如筛糠。他刚才倒下时，不是摇晃了几下才倒下去的，也不是慢慢瘫倒的。利维拉一记右勾拳以雷霆万钧之势砸过来，打得他直挺挺地倒在了地上。裁判将利维拉推开，站在那位倒在尘埃里的英雄身旁开始数数。在赛场上，看见这种一拳便将对手打翻在地的场面，观众一般都会满场喝彩。可是，此时的观众席无人喝彩。出现这样的场面，太出乎人的意料了。所有的观众都在看着裁判数数，气氛紧张，鸦雀无声。突然，罗伯兹兴高采烈的一声喊打破了沉寂：

“我早就说过他是个能使双拳的拳击手！”

数到第五秒时，丹尼翻了个身，面朝下，数到第七秒，他单膝跪起来，准备在数到九和十之间的时候站起来。假如在数到十的时候他的膝盖还没有离开地面，就算“输”或者“退出”。一旦膝盖离地，就算“站起”，利维拉便可以再次出拳将他打翻。利维拉一点也不敢马虎大意，时刻准备着要在他的膝盖离地之际扑上前去。他围着丹尼逡巡，但裁判也围着转，挡在他们俩之间。利维拉发现裁判数数时数得很慢，所有的美国佬都站在他的对立面，甚至包括裁判。

数到九的时候，裁判猛地把利维拉向后搡了一把。这样做有失公平，使得丹尼趁机站了起来。丹尼嘴角又露出了笑容，把腰弓得像虾米，用两只胳膊护住脸和腹部，狡猾地蹒跚着步子走上前扭抱他。按照比赛的规则，裁判员应该将他们分开，可裁判只是袖手旁观，于是丹尼就像狗皮膏药一样死死粘在利维拉的身上，借此一点—点地恢复元气。这一局的最后一分钟在飞快流逝。他只要坚持到底，就可以安全地回到自己的角落，在那里有整整一分钟的休息时间。结果他如愿撑到了最后，尽管狼狈不堪、境况悲惨，却仍笑容满面。

“瞧呀，他总是笑得那么开心！”有人高喊了一声。观众们总算松了口气，哄堂大笑起来。

“那个墨西哥小子刚才那一拳实在厉害。”当助手们围着他忙乱的时候，丹尼坐在自己的角落里，气喘吁吁地对顾问说。

第二局和第三局均无波无澜。丹尼是个狡猾无比的拳坛老将，一个劲躲闪、招架、坚持，一心要从第一局使得他头晕目眩的那一拳的打击中恢复过来。到了第四局，他恢复了过来。他虽说仍有点狼狈和惊诧，但由于体质好，已恢复了充沛的精力。不过，他不再采用那种咄咄逼人的战术了，因为他发现那个墨西哥小子原来是根难啃的骨头。他转而采用自己最擅长的打法，表现出他所精通的谋略、技巧和经验，虽然一招一式并不能产生重大战果，但科学有方，以期用疲劳战打垮对方。利维拉打他一拳，他会还三拳，但每一拳只是搔搔痒，形不成沉重打击。这样的拳头不知要挥多少次才可以产生真正的效果。眼前的这个初出茅庐的小子擅使双拳，速度快如闪电，左右开弓，叫他很是佩服。

在防御的时候，利维拉打的是一种干扰式的左直拳套路。他一次又一次以左直拳挡开丹尼的进攻，同时将拳头落在了丹尼的嘴和鼻子上。不过，丹尼很会随机应变，恐怕也正是因为如此，他才有望成为锦标赛的冠军。他可以随心所欲地改变战术，此刻正专注于近战。这种战术可谓神机妙算，可以叫他躲开对方左直拳的攻击。全场的观众兴奋地为他欢呼，声浪一波又一波。紧接着，他发动漂亮的进攻，对准那个墨西哥人的下颚来了记上勾拳，打得他双足腾空，跌落在垫子上。利维拉单膝跪地，尽量利用数数的时间休息。他心里很清楚，裁判给他数数是数得很快的。

到了第七局，丹尼又恶毒地打出了一记上勾拳，这次只是打得利维拉踉跄了几步，但他利用利维拉毫无防御能力的机会又补了一拳，将对方打到了台下。利维拉的身体朝着报社记者们的头上砸了过去，记者们一把将他推回到台子旁的绳子外。他单膝跪在那儿，而裁判在飞快地数秒数。丹尼在台子上等着他，而他必须钻过绳子上台迎战。这回，裁判没有干涉，没有把丹尼推开。

观众欢声雷动，高兴到了极点。

“打死他，丹尼，打死他！”一个声音高喊道。

此起彼伏的声音在大喊大叫，就像群狼在嗥叫。

丹尼在虎视眈眈地等候着。而利维拉不等数到九，裁判数到八的时候，就已经出乎意料地钻过绳子上了台，和丹尼扭打在了一起。这时裁判却出面干涉了，把他拉开，让他只有挨打的份儿——这个偏心眼的裁判让丹尼占尽了便宜。

可是，利维拉挺住了。他现在头脑清醒了起来，知道眼前的这些人全都是一丘之貉。这些可恨的美国佬，都是些偏心眼。在他感觉最艰难的时刻，那些幻象又一幕幕闪现在他的脑海里——长蛇一般的铁路线蜿蜒于茫茫沙漠上；墨西哥的宪兵和美国的警察；监狱和拘留所；水塔旁边的流浪汉——这些都是他离开里奥布兰科和那次罢工之后，一路漂泊所看到的种种肮脏和残酷的现实。随后，他仿佛看见蔚为壮观的红色革命浪潮席卷祖国大地，散发出耀眼的光芒。革命所需的枪支就在眼前。那些观众，每一张可恶的面孔就是一杆枪。他在为枪而战，赢了就有枪了，赢了就有革命了。他在为全体墨西哥人而战。

观众开始对利维拉感到不耐烦了，怨他不认输，不乖乖就范。既然注定要失败，为什么还要这么顽固呢？只有极少的人对他有兴趣——这些人在下赌注的人群里占有一定的比例，他们喜欢将一部分赌注压在希望渺茫的选手身上。他们相信丹尼会胜，可是他们仍然以四对十和一对三的比例，把钱押在这个墨西哥人身上。这时，有相当一部分观众下赌注，赌的是利维拉还能坚持几局。赛台边曾经有人下了大赌注，赌的是利维拉坚持不了七局，甚至连六局也坚持不下来。见自己下的赌注赚了，赢的一方就放下心来跟着大家一道喝彩，为自己赌赢的那一位加油。

利维拉硬是不服输。在第八局里，他的对手又打了个上勾拳，结果落了空。第九局，利维拉又一次叫全场观众惊得目瞪口呆。和对手扭打在一起时，他泥鳅一般迅速脱离开来，就在两人之间那么小的空间将右拳从腰部举起，将丹尼放翻在地，躺在那儿靠裁判数数挽救他的命运。人群一下子愣住了。谁能料想到丹尼竟被自己的拳法给打翻了。他那闻名遐迩的右手上勾拳居然“以其人之道还治其人之身”地落在了他自己的身上。裁判数到九时，他站了起来，利维拉按兵不动，没有向他发动攻击，因为裁判公开阻止他那样做。假如颠倒一下，要站起来的是利维拉，裁判就会站在一旁作壁上观了。

在第十局，利维拉两次将右拳从腰部举起，用上勾拳击打对方的下颚。丹尼拿出了拼命三郎的狠劲，脸上虽然仍旧笑意浓浓，却又一次如饿虎扑食般发起了凌厉攻势。他挥拳虎虎生风，然而却无法对利维拉造成伤害，利维拉顶住了他那令人眼花缭乱、迅雷不及掩耳的攻势，一连三次将他放倒在了垫子上。现在，丹尼恢复元气没有之前那么快了。到了第十一局，他的境况已经非常不佳。不过，他硬着头皮一直鏖战到第十四局，把他步入拳击生涯的看家本事都拿了出来。闪展腾挪，他努力保持体力，不随便浪费一丝力气。除此之外，他还拿出了作为一个功成名就的拳击手所熟知的见不得人的套路。凡是小诡计、小动作，他无所不用其极，在打贴身战时假装无意，把利维拉的手套夹在他的胳膊同身体之间，并且用他的手套顶住利维拉的嘴，堵得他不能呼吸。两人扭打在一起时，他不止一次从他那破裂却仍在微笑的嘴里冲着利维拉的耳朵吐出脏话，句句下流并带有侮辱性。在场的人，从裁判到观众，无一不站在丹尼的一边，无一不帮衬他。他们了解他的计划，知道他的战略部署。那个无名小辈虽然冷不防地出击，占了上风，但丹尼正在积蓄力量，准备一举扭转危局。他摆出甘愿挨打的架势，有时虚晃一拳，有时佯攻，有时诱敌深入，时刻在寻找有利的战机，瞅准机会使出全身力气一拳打去，让局面彻底逆转。他采用另一位比他更有名的拳击手的套路，左右开弓，用双拳直击利维拉的心窝和下巴。众人相信他能将对手打倒，因为他以力大而闻名——只要他能站稳脚跟，就一定能做得到。

利维拉的助手在两局之间的休息中，一点也不用心照料他。他们挥动毛巾只不过是装装样子，并没有把多少空气扇到他那气喘吁吁的肺里。斯巴德·哈格蒂为他提建议，但他充耳不闻，知道那是误人的话。所有的人都在跟他作对，四面八方都是阴谋诡计。在第十四局，他又将丹尼打翻在地，裁判员数数的时候，他就垂着双手站在那儿休息。从对面的角落里，他留意到有人在可疑地说着悄悄话。他看见迈克尔·凯利走到罗伯兹那儿，弯下腰跟他耳语。利维拉的耳朵在沙漠里经过锻炼，跟猫耳朵一样灵敏，听到了几句不连贯的话。他想多听一点，于是，对手站起来开战时，他便跟对手打贴身战，身子靠在绳子上。

“必须这样做，”他可以听见迈克尔如此说，而罗伯兹点了点头，“必须叫丹尼赢……我押了一大笔钱进去，输是输不起的……那可是我的血汗钱。假如他撑过了第十五局，我就会破产……那孩子听你的，你去给他吹吹风。”

自此，利维拉眼前的幻象彻底消失了，意识到那班人企图算计他。接着，他又一次把丹尼放翻，垂手站在那儿休息。只见罗伯兹站起来对他说道：

“回到你的角落里去，别在这儿等了。”

罗伯兹用的是命令口气，就像平时在训练场上对他说话一样。而他只是用仇恨的目光瞪了罗伯兹一眼，依旧站在原地等丹尼站起来。后来在一分钟的休息时间里，拳击事务所的老板凯利亲自走过来跟他说话。

“你可不要敬酒不吃吃罚酒，”他恶狠狠地用刺耳的声音低声说，“叫你倒下去你就倒下去，利维拉。按我的话做，我就会让你前途光明。下一次，一定叫你打败丹尼。这一次你必须倒下去。”

利维拉瞥了他一眼，表示自己听见了，然而却未置可否。

“你为什么不说话？”凯利生气地问。

“你早晚也是个输，”斯巴德·哈格蒂在一旁帮腔说，“裁判会叫你想赢也赢不了。乖乖地听凯利的话，倒下去得了。”

“求你倒下去吧，孩子，”凯利央求道，“回头我帮你获得锦标赛的冠军。”

利维拉没吱声。

“我一定会帮你的。这次就算你帮我了，孩子。”

锣声一响，利维拉感到有点不对头，觉得有什么事情要发生。观众却没有这种感觉。究竟是什么事情，不得而知，反正就在这赛台上，和他息息相关，而且近在眼前。丹尼似乎又恢复了先前的那种自信，气势汹汹地扑来，叫他心头一惊，预感到对方要耍诡计。丹尼猛冲，而他避免交锋，只是一步闪开，避开锋芒。对方想打贴身战，便于施展阴谋诡计。利维拉连连后退，绕个圈子躲开，但他心里清楚，对方迟早还会贴上来施展诡计。他索性一不做二不休，决定引蛇出洞。当丹尼再次冲过来时，他假装要打贴身战，可是眼看二人的身体就要贴在一起的时候，他却敏捷地猛然缩了回去。就在那一刹那，丹尼的那个角落里就传来了叫喊声，指责他犯规。裁判犹豫了一下，正要判利维拉犯规，可话到嘴边，却听见顶层楼座上有个男孩尖声喊道“有鬼”，便只好作罢。

丹尼公开地咒骂利维拉，向他步步紧逼，可是利维拉跳开了。利维拉决计不再近距离交战，这样会失去一半取胜的机会，但他知道如果想赢得比赛，只有靠远距离进攻一条路了。给那些人哪怕一丁点儿的机会，他们也会诬赖他犯规的。丹尼忘乎所以，在接下来的两局里见利维拉不敢近距离交战，就跟在后边穷追猛打。利维拉挨了一拳又一拳，挨了几十拳也不敢冒险上前打贴身战。观众见丹尼最后终于占了上风，都跳了起来狂呼乱喊。他们并不了解内幕，只看得见他们的明星最终稳操胜券。

“为什么不敢打啦？”观众愤怒地厉声喝问利维拉。“缩头乌龟！缩头乌龟！”“拿出本事来，你这个狗东西！拿出本事来！”“揍死他，丹尼！揍死他！”“别留情！揍死他！”

全场沸腾，唯有利维拉保持着头脑冷静。论性情和血气，他是最容易激动的人，但他经历过的场面，比这不知要激烈多少倍——眼前人群沸腾，声浪一浪高过一浪，对他来说，不过是夏天黄昏里凉爽的微风罢了。

到了第十七局，丹尼虎威不减。利维拉挨了重重一拳，被打得狼狈不堪，蔫了下来，两手无力地垂下，连连后退。丹尼觉得时机成熟，认为这个墨西哥小子已在他的股掌之上。殊不知这是利维拉的缓兵之计。利维拉骗他放松了警惕，果断出拳，一拳打在了他的嘴上，将他打翻在地。他一起来，利维拉出右拳向下一劈，砸在他的脖子和下颚上。利维拉连着打了三拳。这样的拳路，裁判不可能说是犯规的。

“比尔！比尔！求求你了！”凯利央求裁判判他犯规。

“没办法，”裁判痛惜地说，“找不到他的破绽。”

丹尼被打得半死，但英雄气不减，仍一次次地站起来。凯利和另外几个靠近赛台的人大声喊警察，让他们中止比赛，可是丹尼的阵营硬是不肯认输。利维拉看见那个胖警官笨拙地钻过绳子爬上赛台，弄不清这是在搞什么名堂。这场美国佬举办的拳击赛中能埋藏的诡计不知道还有多少。丹尼站在他前面，摇摇晃晃、东倒西歪，像喝醉了酒一样。裁判员和警官一齐过来，正要拉开利维拉时，他已经打下了最后一拳。用不着中止比赛了，因为丹尼再也站不起来了。

“数数呀！”利维拉嘶哑着声音对裁判吼道。

裁判数完了数，丹尼的助手过来将丹尼扶起，搀着他回到了他的角落。

“谁赢啦？”利维拉喝问道。

裁判十分不情愿地抓住他那只戴着手套的手，把它举了起来。

场上没有人向利维拉表示祝贺。他孤零零回到了他的角落里，他的助手连凳子也没有给他摆。他背靠在绳子上，用仇恨的目光看着他的助手们，然后将目光移向在场的一万名美国观众。他双膝发抖，精疲力竭地抽噎了几声。那些可憎的面孔在他眼前晃过来晃过去，使他感到头晕而恶心。他突然想起那些面孔就是枪支，现在他总算拿到了枪支。革命的车轮可以滚滚向前了。

（全书完）

————————————————————

(1) 迪亚斯（1830—1915），墨西哥独裁者。

(2) 下加利福尼亚位于墨西哥西北部，地处墨西哥湾与太平洋之间，北邻美国，又称加利福尼亚半岛。

(3) 喻指陪练员。

(4) 美国科罗拉多州的一个县。

(5) 墨西哥中部偏东的一个州。

(6) 墨西哥东海岸最大的港口。

序言　写给第一版丹麦语版（匿名）

我，这本书的作者，很年轻、漂亮、富有，也很哀伤。

在我年轻的人生里，充满了恐惧。面对巨额财富，我也不知道如何处理。我的悲伤整日在我的耳边唱着同样的歌曲。这歌声在我裙摆里沙沙作响，在我胸中芬芳的花丛里叹息。漫漫长夜，我坐在床边，一遍遍推开那带着殷切期盼眼神的梦。

现在，我已写完的一切都不再真实。

在我写的当下，一切都是真实的；而现在，这一切都变得虚无。当我看到一切码成铅字，跃然纸上，我知道，我的青春就是我的力量和我的权利；我也知道，如果我面目丑陋，生来贫穷，我则无法存活。

现在，我很开心、知足。

这是我现在的状态。

但我不打算更改我所写下的词语，因为我知道，那样的时刻即将到来——很快——那一切都将又变成现实……直到再次成为虚无。

我的书会继续扩展，经历和平和动荡的年代，直到我再次成为现在的我。

但这本身也可能是个谎言。因为我一直都是我自己。

可是，会有他（上帝）看清我的那一天到来，那时候，我的书就会结束。因为那之后的事情，和其他书里的故事就没什么两样了，而且我也不太记得之后的事情。

尽管如此，这世界确实存在一间屋子，在那里，幸福之光在我眼前闪耀。然后，那光熄灭了，屋子的门也随之关上。

如果有任何人，基于我所写的，认为我是一个十恶不赦的卑鄙罪人，他一点儿都没错。但如果他认为我被这世界抛弃了，那他就大错特错了。

因为我跟别人一样能够昂首挺胸、心中充满平静地走在路上，且被最优秀的人爱戴。在高高的大厅里，灯光流泻在我的发丝上；男人用他们的欲望向我致敬，而女人则只赠予我她们的恶意。

他们之中，只有一个知道我的罪过，那个人诅咒我。

因为待在满是灯光的屋子里的是他，而那个走到大街上的她则是我。

第一章

从那屋子看出去便是广场，那广场如此巨大华丽以至于压根没人在那儿做生意。

白天的时候，在屋子里可以听到马车的声音，但这声响非常遥远，因为这屋子所在的房子远离街道，而且它的墙壁像城堡那样厚。傍晚，广场上闪耀起千盏灯光，夜里，你能听到喷泉的潺潺流水声，不知何时开始，也不知何时结束；还有哭声，没有人知道是谁在哭；更有孤独的脚步，来回交替。

屋子的位置比广场高出不少。它的窗户是一扇门，通向满是红色花朵的阳台。当风吹过，花朵的花瓣正好飞进广场的喷泉，在池水里起舞。

屋子又长又深。

有窗户的地方，阳光会穿过镶着有色玻璃的宽大窗格淌入房间；然而，房间里，那壁炉通向天花板的地方，却总是黑暗的。

从未有人见过窗户前的窗帘被拉开过。即使是太阳能直晒房间的时候，也从未有人出现在房间里。白天，这房间是死的。

屋子在这房子里的位置如此奇怪，看上去好像根本不是房子的一部分。日常生活在它之外展开；即使当整个房子都灯火通明，门前的马匹不断地刨着地面，玻璃杯叮叮当当，音乐声在庞大的会客厅回荡，那房间的门却依旧紧紧闭着。

除了这房子的主人和他的妻子，还有那最老的仆人之外，从来没人踏入过它的门槛。

因为这间屋子是这房子的灵魂，是这房子的传统和密室。

很早之前，建这房子的人给这间屋子预设了这样的用处。而且，他很聪明地做到不让人发现那里有间屋子，除非那人事先知道。当工程完成后，他让设计师起誓不泄露这个秘密，并给了设计师一笔丰厚的酬金，设计师遵守了他的誓言。

这房子的建造者按当时的方法极尽奢华地装饰着这屋子，不仅镀了金，还配备了有图饰的皮帘子，镶着有色玻璃的窗格，和昂贵的东方地毯。但他一直也没有摆放任何家具，直到最后，他带来两把从米兰定制的精致的扶手椅。

这两把椅子样子奇怪。它们可以在地面上自如地滑动，就连小孩子都能挪动。它们非常巨大，人坐在椅子里会显得很渺小。椅子的木制部分都被雕刻上鸟和其他动物，这些雕像的脸在黑暗中会露出奇怪的笑容，而当灯点亮时，这些笑容又都消失了。

当一切都布置到位以后，房子的主人叫来一位自幼住在这房子里的老仆人，并给了他一把这屋子的钥匙，让他虔诚地照顾这间屋子。每个傍晚，当黄昏来临，老仆人要点燃壁炉架上的蜡烛，即便他知道他的主人在远方旅行，老仆人也必须这样做。每个早晨，老仆人都要亲自整理屋子。除了老仆人，没人进入过这屋子。

房子的主人在正式拥有这房子的那天晚上，第一次带他妻子参观了房子，最后，他带她来到这间屋子。

妻子惊喜地环顾着屋子。她的丈夫让她坐在其中一把大椅子里，然后他坐在另外一把里，对她说：

“亲爱的，这间屋子是留给你和我的，不给世界上任何其他人。我把它设置在房子最隐蔽的位置，远离我们工作的账房，远离仆人们走来走去的走廊，远离我们会见客人的客厅，甚至远离我们的婚房，在这儿你将睡在我的身边。”

她拉起他的手，吻了吻，然后看着他。

“这将是我们婚姻的神殿，我们伟大的爱情使之神圣。在这儿，我们会向上帝祈祷，是他把我们带给彼此。在这儿，每个我们心灵相交的晚上，我们会开心真诚地交谈。当我们死去后，我们的儿子将带着他的妻子来到这里，继续做我们做过的事情。”

于是，房子的主人将这一切都记录在一个文件里，然后他和妻子共同密封了这个文件，并在封口处写下各自的名字。房主把这文件藏在墙里的一个秘密壁龛里。当这些全部完成，他们面对面跪下，紧握对方双手，向上帝进行了简单的祷告，之后便去休息了。

以上所讲的这对夫妻早已离开人世。但他们的儿子、儿子的儿子以及后代们都遵守了他们的遗愿，直到现在。

且不论这个家族财富如何变化，地产增加或减少，他们都一直拥有这所建在广场上的老房子。因为不管每一代房子的主人是如何生活的，他都会保住这栋祖宅。

那间屋子仍然保持原样，正如最初设计的那样，那个藏在墙洞里的文件开始褪色泛黄。每一代房子的主人一生中仅取出这份文件一次，那就是他第一次带他年轻的妻子来这间密室的晚上。之后，他们把自己的名字写在上面，继而把这文件放回原处。

但每一代房子的法定主人都习惯依据自己的品位脾性在这间屋子里添置一件家具。这些添置的家具在那个时期也都非常奇怪，围聚在那两把大而奇特的椅子旁。

有一位房子的主人，是一位一生和蔼可亲的人。他以他妻子的名义，将一架昂贵的、镶嵌着华丽饰品的纺车摆设在屋子里。这个纺车夜夜欢快地呼啦呼啦地飞转，这样进行了好多年。如今它依旧摆在那里，纺锤上还缠着线。

还有一位主人，他的脑子永远在天外遨游，从不安定，不过他死前变得糊涂了不少。他给这屋子带来一个精巧的天空系统模拟仪。当按键被按下之后，星体就亮了起来，沿着它们永恒的轨道前进。他就这样坐在那里摆弄他的星星，直到他生命的最后一刻。

还有一位主人，他的妻子害怕那屋子里的寂静，在第一次踏入那屋子后就再也不肯涉足。她丈夫等了五年，之后做了一个布娃娃女人，跟真人的实际大小一样，把它打扮得非常漂亮。他把这布娃娃放在阳台上的一把椅子上，这样光线就能照在布娃娃毫无表情的脸上。但是他的儿子很爱母亲，把这娃娃拽了回来，藏在了窗帘后。

还有一位，他的妻子每当伤心的时候就会唱歌，而且经常如此。她带来一架钢琴，音调细长柔美，就像妈妈唱歌哄孩子睡觉那样。有的时候，钢琴的声音变得非常尖细。当它在夜晚被弹起时，声音像空气中的嗡鸣传向广场。路过的人猜不出到底是什么在响。

还有一位，他请人给他妻子画了画像并挂在屋子的墙上。但他没有遵守他的婚礼誓言，于是他的孙子把这画像取了下来。而在这画像所悬挂的地方，留下了一个轻微的污迹，无法抹去。

书中故事发生之时房子的主人还没给这屋子添置任何东西。但他的妻子倒是带来一件在她旅途中最吸引她注意力的艺术品。这是一个形状滑稽的罐子，体积很大，发亮，颜色苍白。罐子的一边是一个在荆棘中扭动的裸体男人的画像。这罐子被摆在一个由耶路撒冷附近的石头凿制的台子上。

这个房间就是这样的。

傍晚，当夜色降临，这所房子里最老的那个仆人会点燃壁炉架上的蜡烛。清晨，在所有人醒来之前，他会亲自打扫房间，给阳台上的红花浇水。冬天，他会给聚集在栏杆立柱上叽叽喳喳的麻雀喂点儿面包屑。

现在，这房子的主人名叫科特，他的妻子是阿德尔海德。

第二章

科特坐在靠近壁炉的扶手椅上看书。

他穿着晚礼服，将礼帽和手套摆在膝盖上，快速地翻动书页，不停地从额头向后捋着浓密的头发，并不时看看背着手走来走去的阿德尔海德。

阿德尔海德身材非常高挑，脸蛋儿如同她的白色礼裙一般白皙。她的嘴巴非常红艳，眼睛看上去大而奇异。她在头发上和腰间别了鲜花。

“你并没有在看书，科特。”阿德尔海德说道，不过她从他身边走开了。

科特把书合上，放在一边。然后他挪了挪椅子，以便可以面朝阿德尔海德。科特的眼睛比她的还要大，但更沉稳，他的嘴巴也显得更坚毅。

“你可真漂亮！”他说。

她轻轻地笑了几声，拉起科特的手，吻了吻，说道：

“你可真迷人！”

说完这句，阿德尔海德又开始走来走去。科特则伸直了腿坐在那里，头靠在椅子上，但眼睛却一直注视着阿德尔海德。阿德尔海德有时会停下脚步，摆弄她的礼裙，或用手指滑过钢琴琴键，随后她又穿过开着的门走到外面阳台上。此刻，科特无法从他的位置看到阿德尔海德，但她裙子的白色拖尾留在了屋内，他转而注视着它。

不久，阿德尔海德返回屋里，坐在另外一把椅子的扶手上，晃着她的脚。

“我不喜欢你精神这么亢奋，阿德尔海德。”科特说。

她的眼睛闪着光，她注视着壁炉，壁炉里有根木头正烧得旺。

“你应该喝杯酒，科特。”

“我不稀罕酒。”

“我也不稀罕。但是我喜欢它能提神。它能使人快活，让万物都变得那么迷人。”

“你喝酒了吗？”

“可是，科特，为什么你这么问？”

“因为你现在这么快活，而我又这么迷人。”

阿德尔海德向科特走去，将她的脸颊靠在他的头发上，说道：

“为了我，不要毁了这一刻。你总是能用一个词就毁掉这样的时刻，这是极大极大的罪恶。你说我很漂亮，我很高兴，因为你会这样想我，因为我会陪着你出门，因为你英俊潇洒，而且属于我。我们会远离对方，但正是因为我们之间的一切，让我们彼此更加亲密。我们仅是对彼此点点头——就像我们经常做的那样——就能知晓对方的想法。”

科特轻轻地挣脱了她的拥抱，说道：

“坐一会儿，跟我聊聊。”

阿德尔海德吻了吻科特，坐了下来，立刻忘记了刚才的消沉，眼睛又像之前那样闪起亮光。科特拨弄着壁炉里的余火，然后添了一根木头。他们静静地坐着，看着木头燃烧，烟缠绕着木头，又缓缓上升。阿德尔海德的脚点着地毯，科特则用手遮住自己的眼睛，继续他的思考。

“我大学第一年，”科特说道，“我们五人关系非常要好，每周六晚上都会见面。通常都是在我的房间，因为我可以承担花费。我们就这样坐着，喝酒，直到天亮，然后互相搀扶着回家。”

“那你们一定喝了很多酒！”

“我不清楚，可能很多。我们大声讲话，深入地交流。酒让我们觉得自己更伟大、更勇敢，也更聪明。第二天，我们就很不一样了，变得冷静沉默多了。但是我们可以直视对方的眼睛，因为我们没有做错什么事情。我们是否允许自己沉迷于酒精而失去自控，这并不要紧。我们彼此熟悉，互相信任。”

阿德尔海德坐在那里，默默地看着讲话的他。沉思中的科特不断地往壁炉里加木头，直到阿德尔海德拿走他手中的木头，放在一边。

“你会把房子点着的！”阿德尔海德说。

“人不应该跟陌生人喝酒，”科特说道，“你知道，被剥得一干二净是多么丢人的事情。而这就是会发生的事。”

“你说得就好像喝醉了是被脱光一样。”

科特没有注意阿德尔海德的话，继续说道：

“人会自己宽衣解带，会自己暴露自己。看看你的眼睛和你的笑容。我亲眼感受过：上百次，他们一丝不挂地坐在桌旁，暴露无遗。”

“这是在上流社会吗，科特？”

“不然还能在哪儿？”

“我不明白。”她说，“我不认识你说的那些人。”

“你今晚会见到他们，阿德尔海德。”

她不满地耸了耸肩，脚轻叩着地毯。

“阿德尔海德。”

她望着他，眼神忧郁而愠怒。他拉起她的手，紧紧握着，“我在那些注视你的眼睛里看到过，阿德尔海德。”

她抽走了她的手，“这太可恶了，科特！”

她站起来，走向阳台的门。他的目光紧随着她移动，闪烁着微光，“阿德尔海德。”

她背对着他站着，倚在窗框上，戴上了手套。他微微前倾，用手抓紧了椅子的扶手，“我在你的眼睛里也看到了，阿德尔海德。”

她没有动，也没有说一个字。当戴好手套后，她拎起裙摆，走到阳台上。

五月的风冷飕飕的，她穿着薄薄的礼裙，忍不住打了寒战。路灯在薄雾中昏暗地发着光，众多马车从广场穿过。她能听到马具上的铃铛叮当作响；车夫也在下面走来走去。

她转了个身，站在窗户那里，看着科特。他此时已将椅子移到了离壁炉更近的地方。她只能看到科特的一个肩膀和一只手臂，还有他那浓密的头发和双腿。

“马车已经到了。”她说。

他站起来，走向她。

“请你别生我的气，”他温柔地说道，“我不太舒服。”

“你生病了吗？”

“是的，也许……不，不是。”

“好吧，虽然我不情愿，但是我们可以待在家里。你已经扫了我的兴。”

“是吗？”

“当然。为了你，我才打扮得如此漂亮，我是希望跟你一起出去。”

“是吗？”

他握住她的手，将她拉向壁炉，“坐下，阿德尔海德，好啦，就一分钟。我们今晚能不能待在家里，喝点儿酒，自己欢乐一番？”

“好吧，你心情很不错！”

“听话，阿德尔海德。你是我唯一的放纵，你知道你是，那数百个欢乐的日子足以证明这一点。如果今晚你跟我想的一样，我们就来证明这点。我们会为彼此美好，我们的眼睛会为彼此闪光。”

阿德尔海德并没有看科特，但她摇了摇头。

“我会待在家里，如果你希望这样。”她说。

他们静静地坐着。壁炉台上的蜡烛在过堂风中摇曳不定。

“好奇怪，”他说，“你记得在伦敦的那个夜晚吗，阿德尔海德？那晚我们要去参加那个盛大的舞会。那时我求你待在家里，你答应了，而且很开心。”

阿德尔海德深深地陷入她的椅子里，手臂搭在脖子后面。

“那晚我并不开心。”她说道。

他抬起头，听她要说什么。

“我屈服了，科特，但我并不乐意那样做。我在假装高兴，为了你。”

他们看向彼此。阿德尔海德的眼神安静、哀伤，她注视着科特说道：

“我那时很邪恶，科特。我心里恨你，对你撒了谎。当我坐在你身边，握着你的手，开心地笑的时候，我内心想的都是在舞会上跳舞，一小时接着一小时地跳舞。”

阿德尔海德从扶手椅上滑了下来，依偎着科特，双手抱着科特的膝盖，眼神谦卑地注视着他的脸说：

“不要用那么陌生的眼光看我，科特。那是我本来的样子。我爱你。但是我生活里不能没有其他人，我需要他们看到，看到我的快乐。我想要漂亮，想要他们都爱上我，而我属于你。只有我在被爱的时候我才想要美丽。哦，不要有那样的表情，科特。”

她紧紧地贴着科特，眼神里充满了乞求。

“我并不邪恶，科特，对吗？当我们的小宝贝生病的时候，我也日日夜夜都陪伴着他，难道不是吗，科特？”

“是的。”他说。

“没错，我的确在他身边。但我不能总是保持安静。”

科特将阿德尔海德从椅子上扶起来，手揽着她的腰穿过屋子，走到阳台。此时，一辆马车正迅速地穿过广场，不久，许多马车出现在广场上。这些马车从街道的各个方向涌来，但都朝着一个方向奔去，消失在街道的拐角处。马蹄踏在路面上发出咔嗒咔嗒的声响，路灯照着马车闪闪发光，车夫和男仆笔直地坐在他们的车厢上。

“走吧，阿德尔海德，”科特说道，“我们出发吧。”

炉架上的蜡烛燃尽了，巨大的椅子上，那些雕刻的脸庞在黑暗中开心地笑着。天色变暗，老仆人来到屋里，整理了房间。夜晚降临时，老仆人在屋里点燃了蜡烛。

老仆人日复一日地做着相同的工作。太阳升起，太阳落下。喷泉里的水花飞溅。路灯点亮，人们成群结队地走过广场。阳台上的红花鲜艳明亮，每个晚上，灯光穿过开着的门洒满房间。

但夏天过后，没有人再进入这间屋子。

第三章

阿德尔海德站在阳台上。她摘下红色的花朵，然后扔向下面的广场。她穿着长长的白色礼服，手套和白色的围巾搁在地上。刚刚从剧院回来的她，感到非常无聊。

阿德尔海德转向屋子。

科特缩成一团坐在壁炉前，眼睛盯着前方。阿德尔海德想看看科特的脸，于是喊了他的名字。科特向后推了推他的椅子，抬头看了看。

“我正在回想我们刚刚看的戏剧。”他说。

“没错，这戏太愚蠢了。”

阿德尔海德拽了拽另外一把椅子，这样她就能看到那个画着在荆棘中扭动的裸体男人的坛子。

“曾经有段时间，我非常厌烦法律，”科特说，“当诗人让我看到为了爱情而冲破婚姻的束缚时，我很开心。我曾以为通过爱，人们会变得更伟大，天堂会变得更高远，大地看起来更郁郁葱葱。”

她又打了个寒战，用裙子紧紧地包裹住她的脚踝。

“现在我非常厌烦无法无天的行为。我憎恨那些女人和她们的情人。”

“你现在也结婚了。”她回答。

“你说什么？”

科特抬起头。阿德尔海德能看出来，科特并没有听到她刚才说的话，她为此感到欣慰。

“肯定是有挣扎的，毫无疑问。”阿德尔海德说。

“当然，肯定有。有的。在过去，他们走到一起是不被允许的，而现在他们不被允许住在一起。”

阿德尔海德什么都没说，但她的手却慢慢地抚过那坛子。

“所有不忠贞的妻子都玷污了爱情。我能想象一个风雅的女人如何扼杀她的爱，因为她不会给这份爱任何生存的余地。”

“因为她害怕。”

“因为她风雅。”

他们默默地坐了一会儿，盯着白色灰烬里的余火看。

“你觉得会有很多人那么做吗？”

他抬起头。

“你觉得有很多不忠贞的妻子吗？”

“我不知道。为什么不会有？”

他把头靠在手上。阿德尔海德把玩着那坛子。

“但我无法理解人们要去戏院。”

“那你让他们去哪儿？”

科特向后推了推自己的椅子，以便能看到阿德尔海德。阿德尔海德一动不动，脑子里一片空白。

“阿德尔海德，”科特说，“我想今晚你应该不愿意待在家里吧？”

阿德尔海德躺回到椅子里，看着她自己的双手。

“哦，我想出去吃晚饭。”

“可是我很想跟你聊天。”

“但我确实从剧院回到家里了，亲爱的。”阿德尔海德答道，同时把手伸向科特。

而科特没有看到她的手，于是阿德尔海德把手放了下来。

“看完剧，我宁愿待在家里，阿德尔海德。”

“是的，我知道，”阿德尔海德答道，但她耸了耸肩，说，“可我无法理解。”

“但是在剧院你能理解，现在你又想去外面吃饭。”

科特向阿德尔海德俯下身，以便引起她的注意。阿德尔海德什么都不说，也不看他。

“阿德尔海德。”

阿德尔海德皱紧眉头。

“你看，我去戏院从来不是为了看戏，”她说，“看戏对于我来说一点儿意思都没有。但是，看那茫茫人海，听他们一会儿喧闹，一会儿安静，我觉得十分有趣。我喜欢他们听到台上精彩的对白时而鼓掌喝彩，时而沉静思考的样子。然后我的内心就会欢唱起来，这让我很享受。”

科特看了阿德尔海德一会儿，然后搓着双手大笑起来。阿德尔海德把椅子转向科特，她的膝盖几乎可以碰到科特。

“关于今晚，你到底想对我说什么？”她问，“难道不能等到戏演完？不能再等上一小时？我现在想出去吃晚饭。”

科特看着她，摇了摇头。

“到底是什么？或者你只是疲乏空虚，就跟我一样，以及跟那些不忠的妻子一样，还有那些现代诗人，还有……还有所有人？”

“不，阿德尔海德，”他说，“不。没什么。什么都没有。”

“我不知道你在说什么，”阿德尔海德突然狠狠地将自己抛回到椅子里，“你话里有话。”

科特点点头。

“你在生我的气。我做了什么？据我所知，我们跟圈子里的其他人没什么两样地活着。我们旅行，我们去戏院，我们去拜访朋友，我们在自己家里接待朋友，我们去结识有意思的人，艺术家……以及任何是个人物的人。”

“在这些有趣的人中间，你总会感到开心吗？”

阿德尔海德看着科特，带着些疑惑不解，“没有‘总是’这样的事。”

“是的，”科特说，“的确没有‘总是’这样的事情，所以就更值得怜悯。”

他们静静地坐着，陷入沉思。然后，科特捋了捋他额头的头发，平静地说：

“请你试着理解我，阿德尔海德。当一个女人出嫁，成为一个母亲，她通常会变得沉静。我是说，沉静一点儿。我的意思是，这世界上有女人无法赢得的胜利和无法获取的成就。一个已是母亲的女人不会为此烦恼。她不会想要试图征服这些，阿德尔海德，因为她已经升华了自己的生命，因为她已经属于一个男人，任何接触其他男人的想法都让她感到厌恶。这样她就会变得沉静……更加沉静。而这种沉静并不是空虚，它比其他任何感情都要丰富。”

阿德尔海德看着科特，她那愤怒的眼睛中闪烁着陌生而好奇的光芒。

“你嫉妒了吗？”她问。

科特摇了摇头，比了一个否定的手势。阿德尔海德从椅子里突然起来，站到科特面前，怒目圆睁，骄傲地说：

“你应该嫉妒，科特，你应该嫉妒。我是你的，而且我爱你。你曾赢得了我；但请你确保你知道如何一直拥有我。为我而战，科特。我还年轻，我很漂亮，这个世界上的男人多得是。”

科特不紧不慢地站了起来，一直看着阿德尔海德，阿德尔海德一度认为科特会伸手打她。

“下个月你就二十六岁了，”他说，“而且，我们家族的人不会为了保住自己的老婆而战斗。”

“科特！”

阿德尔海德坐了下来，脑袋一片空白。科特望着她，她也望着科特。她禁不住想科特好高啊，科特非常轻易地就能穿上他的衣服，还有就是科特的一个肩膀比另外一个低一些。

科特穿过房间，他走得太快差点儿被地毯绊倒。然后他费力地摆弄着老纺车，把它拉了过来。这期间，阿德尔海德一直注视着他。

“你会使用我曾奶奶的纺纱车吗，阿德尔海德？”科特问道。

阿德尔海德两只胳膊交叉在胸前，望着科特。

“难道你不会，阿德尔海德？那你不能学一学吗？如果我求你，你都不肯吗？”

科特把纺车径直拉到阿德尔海德面前摆放好，就如同阿德尔海德要立刻使用这纺车一样。做完这些后，科特又坐回到他的椅子里。

“你不觉得你能行吗，阿德尔海德？”

他们狠狠地直视对方。但不久，两人都有点儿尴尬，低下了头。

他们都想伸出手，但又不肯先做出这样的举动。两人渴望投入对方的怀抱，但却都坐得如同雕塑般一动不动。他们的嘴巴颤抖，但他们拒绝抬头看看对方，因此也并不知道对方心里想着什么。

“我在想，在这些大椅子里我们看起来这么渺小。”科特最终说。

他的声音非常冷静，阿德尔海德也立刻冷静下来。结束了，他们的灵魂重新平静。这不能算作和解，因为他们根本不记得任何争吵。他们信任地看着彼此。没有任何芥蒂，他们又重归于好了。

“我在想，我们是不是比不上我们之前曾坐在这里的人，”阿德尔海德说，“不同，是的。但是会比不上吗？”

两人都站了起来。

“差很远吧，”科特说，“而且远不如他们快乐。”

他们穿过房间，走到阳台上，这是他们睡觉之前的习惯。

九月夜晚的星空格外高远。大部分的路灯都已熄灭，广场上人烟稀少。一个酒鬼在远远的地方唱着歌。喷泉里流水的声音在寂静的夜里显得格外清晰。

“这里好美！”科特说。

“是的。”

“夏夜马上就结束了，而我们还没来得及享受。”

她把头靠在他的肩上，然后闭上了眼。

“我想世界上再没有一个广场如此美丽了。”科特说。

“哦，是有的，在佛罗伦萨。”

科特叹了口气，把她带进了屋子，“我们旅行得太多啦，阿德尔海德。”

她迅速地离开，打开房门，而科特还在阳台上站着。

那股怒气重新在科特的胸中凝聚。他想将其平息，但毫无效果。

“你进来吗，科特？”

阿德尔海德站在走廊上看不到科特的位置。

“走你的吧……我一会儿就过来。”

科特努力使自己的声音听起来尽可能平静，但是即便在他自己的耳朵里，听起来都非常不自然。他静静地站着，听着走廊上的动静。阿德尔海德站了一会儿，好像在考虑什么。

然后她关上了门，离开了。科特能听出来，她走得很急。

第四章

入冬以来的第一场雪降临了，静静地染白了阳台，麻雀在积雪上面绣着图案。

红色的鲜花摆在温暖的房内，看上去很是可怜。一张大桌子被放在房间靠里的位置，桌上摆了一盏台灯和一堆书。

科特很早就来了。

他径直走到桌子旁，坐了下来，打开一本书。一会儿，他又站到窗户前向外面望。

天色渐暗。这是一个潮湿而雾蒙蒙的夜晚，一束单薄微红的灯光在透着寒气湿漉漉的屋顶后闪烁。广场上的雪已融化成雪泥。喷泉悄无声息，掩埋在一堆木板和废松木下。

科特再一次坐下开始阅读。不久他又站起来，看了看手表，走向窗户那里，然后开始在房间里不断徘徊，最终再次坐了下来。他点了支雪茄，又把它掐灭了。然后他离开了，一个小时后又回来，重复做着这些事情。

快到午夜的时候，有马车穿过了大门，五分钟后，阿德尔海德站在屋里，高挑而白皙，大大的眼睛扑闪着。

“你玩得开心吗，阿德尔海德？”

阿德尔海德知道，科特并不在乎这问题的答案，因此她也就没有直接回答。

“我快冻死了。”她说。

阿德尔海德把自己的那把椅子使劲拖向壁炉旁，然后把自己蜷缩在椅子里，把脚搭在了壁炉的围栏上。

“他们都在询问你的近况，科特。”

“当然。”

科特翻了翻书页，然后合上了书，把自己的椅子拉向阿德尔海德。他坐下来，手托着脸，看起来很疲倦。

“科特，你打算成天都坐在这间屋子里吗？”

“不，只在晚上，当我没什么事可做的时候，我就爱待在这间屋子里。”

阿德尔海德双手紧握，闭上了眼睛。

“我讨厌这屋子，”她说，“我们之间所有的不愉快都来自这里。”

科特没有回应，他走到桌子那里拿雪茄。当科特重重地盖上雪茄盒时，阿德尔海德突然感觉到了什么，整个人不舒服起来。

“科特，你打算跟我们的熟人都断绝联系吗？”

“没有，”科特说道，“我不会的。但刚才我不想出去。”

“你觉得我们的朋友会怎么说啊？”

“他们想怎么说就怎么说吧。”

“难道你就不想想，这一切让我很不愉快吗？”

“当然。但是我目前不愿意出去。”

科特用壁炉架上点着的蜡烛点燃了雪茄，之后他坐了下来，静静地抽着雪茄，望着火炉。阿德尔海德看着科特，叹了口气。

不知怎么的，阿德尔海德突然感到心被触动了，她的眼睛湿润了，“你不快乐吗，科特？”

科特抬起头，注视着她，“是的。”

“这是我的错吗？因为你的妻子是一个愚蠢的女人，整天就想着出去交际？”

“你不是那样的，阿德尔海德。”

“因为我是一个轻浮不安分的现代产物吗？”

“你不是那样的。”

“那我是哪样的，科特？”

他牵起了她的手，吻了吻，然后朝她笑了笑，“你是我的妻子，阿德尔海德。我们还有个孩子，将来我们可能还会再生一个。”

“不，”阿德尔海德抽回了自己的手，“不，科特。我不会再要了。”

科特什么都没有说。他的手无力地垂了下来，他的脸色从未像现在这样苍白。阿德尔海德注意到科特的反应，她担心科特是生病了，于是弯下腰来，轻轻地呼唤着他的名字。

但科特没有看她，也没有听她的呼唤。

阿德尔海德无法将视线从科特身上挪开。她心里想到，就是他们的孩子死掉，科特的反应也不过如此了。阿德尔海德为自己在这件事情上感到开心而觉得极其羞耻。她害怕极了，唯恐科特会看她。

就在这时，科特望向阿德尔海德，并捕捉到了她心里的想法。

阿德尔海德看到科特越来越沮丧，她内心的开心就越发不可收拾。她不能理解自己这样的情绪反应，并深深地为此感到困扰。

科特的眼睛里，并没有一丝愤怒，阿德尔海德在脑海中搜寻着，想要想出一个词能让科特说点儿什么或是动一动。

但是科特就一直静静地坐在那里，慢慢地扭转了头，不再看阿德尔海德。而阿德尔海德也不知道要说些什么。

她站了起来，走到窗户那里，在那里站了一会儿。之后她又走回来，坐到了一把椅子里，“你在想什么，科特？”

“想你。”

屋子里的两人再次陷入沉默。

“阿德尔海德。”

他温柔平静地喊着她的名字，但是她却被吓到了。

“我会为你而战，阿德尔海德，我是说我会去争夺你，原本我们未来的孩子应该能帮我，但现在我只能孤身奋斗了。”

阿德尔海德隐约记得这句话似乎在什么时候被说过，但那时她并没有理解科特的意思。

“我会以生命和快乐作赌注去为你而战，”他说，“我会跟你聊天，一直纠缠你并征服你。我会把你抱在怀中，把你的后路阻断，然后去追逐你，原谅你。”

“那如果你没有赢得我呢？”

“我会赢得你的。”

“但如果没有呢？”

她看着科特的嘴巴，等待他的答案。这答案来得异常平静，科特甚至都没看阿德尔海德，自顾自地说道：

“如果没有，那我就抛弃你。”

阿德尔海德紧紧地闭上眼，又大大地睁开，“最好能立刻抛弃我，科特。如果你能做到的话。”

“我做不到。我们有个孩子，而且我们还喜欢着对方。”

“我不确定。”阿德尔海德说。

“你不确定什么？”

阿德尔海德没有再回答，只是摇了摇头。

“你将得到你想要的自由，”科特说，“你可以尽情地去外面玩，尽情开心，邀请客人都来家里做客。随你的性子去开心去忧伤。你现在就可以去了，如果你想的话。”

“那你再也不会跟我一起了吗？”

“不可能了。我不会在那种地方追你了。我曾在那里得到了你，而且我也不担心你……那方面。无论怎样，我不会再费力在那样的场合去追你了。”

“那之后呢？”

“你知道你可以在任何夜晚在这间屋子里找到我。这里是我将长久生活的地方。”

科特站起来，慢慢地穿过屋子。阿德尔海德从椅子上滑到了地板上，脸靠着壁炉围栏，眼睛死死地盯着前方。她看着科特走了过来，站在她身边，然后又走了回去。

“科特，”阿德尔海德说，“我永远都不会再来这里。”

“你随意。”

科特坐了下来，双手托着头，说道：

“我的祖先，在他富丽堂皇的新房子里建造了这间神圣的婚姻密室时，他很清楚地知道他当时在做什么。这屋子高高在上，远离日间和夜晚的工作生活。他看得非常深远。”

“这屋子是一个折磨人的地方，”阿德尔海德说，“我敢肯定，很多女人都曾在这里痛苦地流泪。”

科特欠身，手放在了前额。

“我害怕极了，科特。你想虐待我。我没办法照你希望的去做。我们去别的地方聊天，去你的房间吧，科特？”

“不，”科特说，“我们就在这里。我们注定要在这里。”

他站起来又立刻坐下，眼里闪着光，“他们都曾坐在这里，那些在这座房子里生活的男主人和他们的妻子荣辱与共。他们注视着我们，他们的低语在这周围回荡，你难道听不到我曾祖母的纺车声吗？你听不到钢琴的声音吗？”

“是的，科特。”

“在这里，我们的言语在这静谧中变得更重大。在这里，我们的爱和愤怒都更有力量。我们不论做什么，都可以在这里完成。他们明白，那些年老的男人和女人是明白的。”

阿德尔海德起身站在科特面前，倚着壁炉上的架子，高挑而白皙，“他们知道如何在这房子里遵守规则。”

阿德尔海德看着科特，她红艳的嘴唇和陌生的眼神中显示着骄傲、害怕和愤怒。

“他们确实做到了这一点，”科特说，“上帝保佑已经身葬坟墓里的他们！”

阿德尔海德坐了下来，抱着那个陶罐，罐子上的男人仍在荆棘中扭动着。她盯着那男人的脸，就好像她跟他在一起，一并感受到了荆棘的刺痛。

“也是在这里，阿德尔海德，我们注定要跟彼此永远在一起。那晚我们把我们的名字写在那张古老泛黄的纸上，封在墙里，你向这个屋子起过誓，虽然你很讨厌那么做。而且，不久之后，我们的儿子也将带着能给他幸福的女人来到这里。”

科特走到阳台又走了回来，身上落满了白雪。寒气入室，阿德尔海德打了个冷战。他静静地在火炉旁站了一会儿，又开始在屋里踱步。阿德尔海德听着他的脚步声，想要说点儿什么，却一句话都说不出来。

然后她走向那架古老的钢琴，坐在钢琴前，开始唱：

我的丽诺尔，白昼带来的负担，
是多么忧郁而悲伤！
我听不到悦耳的钟声，
也没有小鸟在日光里歌唱。
亲爱的丽诺尔，哦，我的女神，
你眼睛如此明亮，白昼都显得暗淡，
一定要给我金色的美酒，
是夜晚从她那芬芳的罐子中倾倒。
紫罗兰看着我们，草原上的蓝色，
我们的秘密不会错过任何一颗星星。
亲吻我吧，丽诺尔，再次亲吻我，
千万次地亲吻我。

轻柔的旋律穿透屋子，然后阿德尔海德停了下来。

她仔细听了听，已经听不到科特的脚步声。此时科特坐在其中一个大椅子里，一动不动。

阿德尔海德扭过头看了科特一会儿，然后她站起来，合上钢琴，故意弄出很大的声响，“晚安，科特。”

“晚安。”

阿德尔海德脸色一阵白一阵红，眼睛湿润，生气地离开了屋子。

第五章

阿德尔海德浑身冰冷地坐在靠近壁炉的地方。

壁炉里，火苗旺盛。红色的火焰炙烤着她的脸庞和她白色的礼服。但她依旧继续往壁炉里添木头，总也暖和不过来。

科特坐在另外一把椅子里读书，但他的书却放在膝盖上，手托着头。书很大，书页泛黄，字体老旧。

阿德尔海德沮丧地看了看科特。她非常后悔自己来到这间屋子，如果她有力气的话，她肯定早就离开了。她叹了口气，眼神疲惫地望着炉火。

“阿德尔海德，听着。”

科特双手捋了把头发，读道：

但，当泰王后知道奥拉夫已经死去的消息后，她陷入了昏迷，在那里躺了很久。当她醒过来的时候，她的悲伤如此沉重，以至于屋子中的人都为她感到难过。当白昼过去，她来到一个住在附近的德高望重的修士的家里。她问这位修士，自杀是否违背上帝的意志。因为她的主人、她的丈夫已死去，她对人生无可眷恋。但这位修士告诉她：

“自杀确实是一种罪过。因为上帝给予我们生命，并且会在他认为合适的时候收回。”

之后，这位王后流下眼泪，因为她即将犯下深重的罪孽。但第二日清晨，她又来到修士这里，问道，一个人能吃多么少而不会惹上帝生气？这次，修士怜悯她，说：

“如果你一天吃一个苹果，这就足够了。”

之后，泰王后在她的躺椅上躺了下来，命令所有的侍女退下，这样她便可以和她的悲伤独处，并命令她最信任的一个侍女每日早晨用金色的杯子为她送上一枚苹果。这样过了八天，第九天早晨，当侍女来到王后身边，发现王后已经随她的丈夫去了天堂。

科特合上书。他的嘴唇动了动，就好像他在对自己重复刚才说过的话。阿德尔海德若有所思地看着炉火，然后说：

“那些去世的老一辈人真幸运。他们都有一位圣人，每当他们感到沮丧，就可以向他倾诉。”

科特听到这话，摇了摇头。

“你扭曲了事实，阿德尔海德，”他说，“并不全是那样。王后想要死去，她就死去了。她去修士那里只是想要洗清罪过，虔诚地遵从他的命令。”

“那时候他们还相信上帝。”阿德尔海德说。

“是的，他们相信。古老而强大的上帝掌握着他们的命运。”

此时，科特很快地起身站到壁炉旁。

“你信上帝吗，科特？”

“不，”科特说道，“我不信。但我相信上帝曾经是存在的。而且我觉得，如果他此刻在的话，绝对是件好事。”

“我也觉得是。”

科特抱着自己的膝盖，脚踩在壁炉围栏上，说道：

“上帝仍然存在于某些地方。我并不畏惧上帝。如果我有机会直视他的脸，我敢说我一生荣耀高贵，坦坦荡荡。”

阿德尔海德笑笑，“你说的是那个古老而强大的上帝吗？”

科特瞥了一眼阿德尔海德，但却没有生气。他走到阿德尔海德身边，说道：

“就是那个古老而强大的上帝。没有他，我自己可以过得很好。但我需要他在我家里。”

阿德尔海德把头靠向了椅子，大笑道：

“确实如此，科特。你确实需要他在你的家里。”

她继续大笑，然后说道：

“如果他在的话，我敢肯定楼下那个，叫什么来着，再也不敢在账房抢你的钱了。你是这么想的吗，科特？还有，你的妻子每个早晨都会亲吻你的手，然后卑微地询问她那严厉的主人的命令。”

科特在屋里踱着步，没有说话。

阿德尔海德以为科特并没有在听她的调侃，因为她的话语不值得科特思考，她开始对自己不满，而且还生科特的气，“但是，要说到故事，当然还有哈格巴斯和西涅，更不用提罗密欧和朱丽叶，还有玛利亚·韦克则拉和埃尔韦拉·马迪根。”

科特自顾自地走着。

“我并没有说任何反对这故事的话。这是个美好的故事，说不定还是件真实的事情。不管怎样，应该给年轻人树立个正确的榜样。但就泰王后来讲，她对丈夫的爱肯定多多少少取决于他们结婚的时间。”

科特没怎么看阿德尔海德。阿德尔海德觉得自己被当成了孩子一样对待——无须费心去回答，这激起了她的斗志，她在努力寻找正确的词语，以伤到科特。

“每一段爱情都会消逝，”阿德尔海德说，“我们都知道这点儿。那些在爱情消逝前就死掉的人是很幸运的。他们美好地出现在历史里，但这并不能证明他们就要好过我们。”

科特仍旧不停地走来走去，然后他站在窗前向外看了看，继而又开始走。

“科特。”

科特在她的椅子前停下并看着她。

“你知道奥拉夫国王和泰王后结婚多久了吗？”

“问这个有什么意义呢，阿德尔海德？”

阿德尔海德向后推了推自己的椅子，站了起来。她一时没有组织好语言，无法表达自己想要说的意思，只是向科特跨了一步，又坐回了椅子里，她感到无力。

此时，科特眼神中的某种东西帮助了她，然后她站了起来，坚定地看着科特：“这意味着，你整天坐在这里，在你的旧书、旧物件和无聊的故事里生锈发霉，而真正的生活却绕过你在你的身边进行。用不了多久，你的胡子就会长到这桌子，这期间你根本不会说话，即便偶尔说那么一词半句，也过于深奥，没有人能够理解。”

“阿德尔海德，不会发生你说的那种情况的。”科特说。

“但是我不希望成为泰王后，也不希望成为西涅或者他们中的任何一个，”阿德尔海德的声音如此生硬，科特内心一阵酸楚，“我想成为现在的我，那个你爱上并拥入怀中的女人。我不生活在书里。不会有女学生在她们的书本里读到我的故事。我没有时间浪费在无聊的老式恋爱上，我无法理解这种爱情，所以也不相信这样的爱情。我想要疯狂的、激情的爱情。”

当她说话时，科特的视线已从她身上离开，这会儿又重新望着她，说道：

“难道你还没得到它吗，阿德尔海德？”

阿德尔海德重新坐到椅子上，用很陌生的眼神望着科特。科特从未看过这样的双眼。像是层层纱幕遮住她的双眼，阿德尔海德的眼睛非常暗，突然，她的眼睛里有一丝光闪现，但转瞬即逝，纱幕再次落下。“我不知道。”她回答。

她的声音那么轻，科特差点儿没听到。科特停了一会儿，看她是否还有别的要说。

然后，科特低下头，他那浓密的头发落到前额，然后他又把头发向后耙了一下，脸色惨白，“难怪。”

科特慢慢地穿过屋子，走向窗台，额头抵着窗户栅栏。阿德尔海德先是慢慢地转向科特，又转了回来，面向壁炉。

阿德尔海德似乎说了什么，然后，她就听到了科特压抑的回答，看到了科特惨白而严肃的脸。她知道那并不是她想要说的，同时，她所说的也都是真实的。看着她爱着的男人受伤，她有一些懊悔，因无法去做任何弥补而感到内心泛起一阵绝望。

这些情愫酝酿成了阿德尔海德对科特的愤怒，是科特激得她说了那样的话。最终，愤怒消散，留下的是阿德尔海德对自己深深的怜悯。

阿德尔海德从未像现在这样看透自己的灵魂，她变得茫然，被一阵疯狂而奇特的渴望笼罩。随即她感到俯身在井口，自己快速地跌落，她紧紧地抓住椅子的扶手，关节处都已发白。

在这恐惧之外，远处有只小鸟在金色和绿色的草地上歌唱，阿德尔海德从未在自己的梦中见过这样的景象……

科特来到阿德尔海德的面前，伸出手。

“晚安，阿德尔海德。”科特说。

阿德尔海德坐直了身子，迷惑地望着科特。

“你打算离开这里吗？”她问。

“不。我希望你去上床睡觉。我会在这里多待一会儿，读读书。”

科特坐了下来，拿起了书。阿德尔海德慢慢地穿过屋子。

到达门口的时候，她停了一会儿，看了看科特，他的脸很平静，但感觉很遥远。阿德尔海德在想，他会不会抬头，然后再说一遍晚安，或者仅是点点头。

然而科特既没有抬头也没有点头，他就静静地在那里看书。

第六章

壁炉里的火将要熄灭，蜡烛也快要燃尽。屋里屋外一样安静。

科特仍坐在他的椅子上。他坐在那里已经很久了，一动不动，思考着什么。他的手指插进头发里，仔细听着阿德尔海德的脚步声。

阿德尔海德此刻待在家里，她已经在家里待了整整一个星期了。但在过去的两周里，她都没有去过那间屋子。

科特看看时间，然后他站起来离开了屋子，走出了房子。

不久之后，阿德尔海德来到屋子里。

她在门口站了一会儿，惊奇地发现屋子里竟然没人。她冲阳台喊了喊科特，没人回应。她迟疑地走向窗户朝外望去，那里也没有人。

她迅速地转身离开。科特不在屋里让她有点儿小懊恼，尤其是想到为了来这屋子她付出了什么样的代价。但这懊恼仅持续了一小会儿，随即她又为没有和科特正面相遇而感到开心。比起前些日子，此刻她心情舒畅了不少。

她好奇地看了看这屋子。她从未独自在这里待过，也似乎从未仔细地观察过这里。

阿德尔海德在那对古老的椅子前站了许久，对着椅子上雕刻的怪异脸庞陷入了沉思。她极尽所能地摆弄那对椅子，一会儿让它们面对面，一会儿让它们并排挨着，然后她坐下来，好像要试试看是什么感觉。她回想起所知道的那些曾坐在这里的人，想象他们的对话，觉得很有意思。

然后她走到天球仪那里，按下按键，于是星星动了起来，闪耀着光芒。她高兴地看着这个奇怪的玩具，一遍遍地转动这玩具的发条。

她拉出了那台老旧的纺车，开始纺起布来。纺车的轮子在安静的屋里有力地转着，那呜呜的声音让阿德尔海德快活极了。她甚至希望那位曾祖母此刻来到这里，表扬她如此勤劳。

她从纺车边站了起来，站在屋子的中央，环视屋子。她想到了一个场景，她站在一座印度寺庙里，极度冷静地审视那里的每一件古老物件，也冷静地审视这印度教圣地。

阿德尔海德感到如同站在一座停尸房里一样，古老有趣的物件摆放在这屋里，但一张张充满愚蠢想法和荒谬迷信的木乃伊的脸却盯着她。她并不害怕，因为她知道他们都已死去，再也回不来了。

她的视线落在了墙上的那浅浅的污迹上，那里曾挂过一幅肖像。

“可怜的莱克！”她大声感叹道，“你被关在了这神殿之外了，因为你的丈夫欺骗了你。”

她抬起双臂，欢呼雀跃，她出生在平和的年代，生活在平和的年代，她依旧能感受到温热的血液在她心中涌动。

阿德尔海德在屋里转了一圈，放声大笑，她如此轻易地便破除了这老屋子的魔咒。她拍拍那大椅子硬邦邦的后背，友好地跟它们对话。她曾经忌恨这椅子：曾经每当她坐在椅子里时，就感觉她的血液变得冰冷。而现在，这椅子只不过就是两把时髦的、价值不菲的椅子而已。

她把那“神圣之地”的薄纱撕了下来，后面什么都没有。

她跑向窗户，猛地拉开了窗帘。

那洋娃娃僵硬可笑地坐在那里。

她把她的脸贴近洋娃娃的蜡制脸颊，用她那红艳的唇吻了吻它。

哼着小曲，她又坐在那古老的钢琴边。她在寻找一首圣歌以庆贺她的胜利。

但刚弹奏第一个音符，她突然就害怕起来。

她感到屋子里还有其他人。

阿德尔海德跳了起来，弄倒了椅子，她四处张望。

没有人。

蜡烛还剩一支就全部熄灭了，屋子里一片漆黑。终于，剩余的那只蜡烛也摇摇曳曳，坚持了一会儿，也熄灭了。

然后，屋里传来一阵令人毛骨悚然的喃喃声和低语声。

有人走过地板……好多重重的脚步声。纺车开始旋转，钢琴也在她背后唱起歌来。星星疯跑，闪烁光芒，洋娃娃也摇晃起来。那些雕刻在老木椅上的脸庞伸长了脖子要啄她，诡异地发出笑声。

罐子上那个在荆棘中穿行的男人喊着救命……她能听到他的喊声。他越来越大……越来越近……她看到他裸露的肢体上滴下的鲜血……

阿德尔海德颤抖着爬到了门口，眼中充满了恐惧。

第七章

阿德尔海德伸手放在科特的书上，说道：

“我能和你谈谈吗？我能告诉你一件事吗？我能跟你说，你现在所做的是愚蠢的行为吗？”

科特挪开阿德尔海德的手，抬起了头。

“坐下，阿德尔海德，”他疲倦地说，“坐在那椅子里。”

阿德尔海德从科特手里夺过书，扔到了地板上，“你病了，科特。你在这间可怕的屋子里得了病。”

“那你有家庭良方吗？”科特问。

“你怎么还有心情说笑？”

“如果是笑话，也是个冷笑话，”他说道，“但这并不是笑话。我相信传统的治疗方法。”

阿德尔海德坐在她的椅子里，无助地看着前方。

“你当然会信，”她说，“你还信老书本，以及所有死去的东西。”

科特没有回应，疲倦地打着哈欠。

“上帝会回到他的宝座上，我呢，会坐到纺车上，然后我们会有幸福的婚姻，从此过上美好的生活。”

科特双腿交叠，看着他的指甲。

“是的，这是我的计划，”他静静说道，“差不多就是那样。你刚刚真挚动人地表述了这个计划。”

“科特，你怎么还有这样的心情？”

阿德尔海德晃来晃去，她的手放在膝盖上，她的眼睛湿润了。她想再说些什么，但又说不出来，泪水让她哽咽。她无法理解他为什么不帮她。然后她说道：

“科特，我们的关系很糟糕。”

科特依旧沉默。阿德尔海德努力让自己镇定，她闭上转来转去的眼睛，说道：

“我们必须遵循我们所处的这个时代的规律，不是吗，科特？毕竟，我们是现代人，我们俩都是。或许你觉得现代人是疲倦的、空虚的，但我们的感受和想法毕竟与你喜欢的那些人不一样。并且，我们无法改变自己。但像我们这样的人，就是现在，我们可以尽可能地快乐……我们有什么不开心的呢，科特？”

“我不开心。”

“哦，科特！”

阿德尔海德双手合十，十指交叉，紧紧握着，她低下头，眼泪滴在手上。然后她泪流满面地转向科特，问道：

“那么，我是不是不再漂亮了，科特？”

科特站起身来，亲吻了她那雪白的额头。

“你依旧非常漂亮，”他说道，“但这对于我们糟糕的关系已没什么作用了。”

科特开始来回踱步。阿德尔海德默默地、狠狠地哭泣着。一会儿后，她说：

“你在逼我离开你，科特。我想趁着还有时间，告诉你这些话，如果我能找到合适的言语。你能坐下来吗，科特？我的头疼得很。”

科特坐在椅子里，然后阿德尔海德站起来，往壁炉里添了些木头，继而又坐下，说道：

“每当我们一起说话的时候，科特，我就很害怕我自己，这不仅仅是因为我有点儿邪恶，总是说一些不是我本意的话。是的，我也总是口是心非。但你那么好，你让我看到我脑子里的想法，这些想法在你没有说出来的时候并不存在。但当你说出来的时候，我会意识到你是对的，并且这正是我所想的。科特，这可真糟糕。”

沉默再一次降临。阿德尔海德闭上眼睛，科特不安地在椅子里挪动。

“阿德尔海德，”科特说道，“那晚你告诉我……”

“你不要说那个，你不要说出来。”

“你还记得吗，你说……关于那狂野、激情的爱情，你说我们所拥有的不是这样的爱？”

阿德尔海德摇了摇科特的手，然后紧紧握住。

“就是这样的，”她说，“我感激你，因为你这么好，还因为你不会生我的气。但是，一开始我并没有意识到我内心的想法，科特。我当时不知道。但你说了那些话，然后使得我说了我所说的。但是就在那一刻，我明白，我说的是真的。这让我感到很难过，我从未那么难过过。但同时我也觉得我似乎比以前更加富有。我不再害怕未来，因为女人在她们还年轻的时候有时会想到那种爱情，科特。而当这一切都已成过去，一切将变得空虚。”

科特面向壁炉，静静地听着。

“我敢肯定，世界上没有一个男人能够理解我刚才说的话。”她说道。

然后，阿德尔海德平躺在地板上，头靠在壁炉的围栏上，眼睛里充满光芒。

“女人年轻的时光太短，”她说，“而且女人总是在担心时光会匆匆流逝。当她突然怀疑：还有比她本以为是最好的爱情更好的。然后，她或许会突然意识到这一切还没有结束，难道你不能理解那时她所经历的悲伤害怕吗？”

科特大笑，“本以为已经拥有最好的了，结果却发现还有更好的，这实在不是什么愉快的事情。”科特说。

但阿德尔海德摇摇头，说道：

“不是那样的，科特。”

科特向后推了推椅子，站了起来，开始在屋里踱步，沉默又一次笼罩了这间屋子。然后他在她身边坐了下来，“你所说的是真的。但它的确在你的骨子里，我很高兴是我让你看清了它。当我意识到这一点时，我就无法再做别的选择。我无法静静等待另外的男人打开你的心扉，给你那最伟大的爱情。”

阿德尔海德脸靠着围栏看着科特，“不，科特。如果是那样的话，我所说的就是错的。”

他摆摆手，不耐烦地摇摇头，“或许不是今天或者明天。但可能会是一年、两年后，或是十年后。如果没有发生，那也只是因为意外。”

阿德尔海德向科特靠近，将自己的头放在科特的膝盖上。她抬头看了看科特是否介意自己这样。但科特迷失在自己的思绪中，并没有注意到。

阿德尔海德突然感到内心平静且满足。她很开心说出了自己想要说的话。她感到似乎这件事情已被远远地移开，甚至消失了，她不能明白为什么科特还要继续谈论它。

科特所说的另外一个男人，在阿德尔海德看来如此遥远，毫无可能。她像思考别人的事情一样想着此事，说道：

“我爱你，科特。如果有一天，有另外一个男人出现了，并且我爱上了他，难道我能控制住吗？”

科特猛地站起来，靠在他膝盖上的阿德尔海德赶紧抓住椅子的扶手以免摔倒。

“不，”科特讽刺地说，“你当然控制不住。”

他在屋子里疾速穿行，将自己的话重复了三四遍。阿德尔海德从地板上站起来，坐到了她的椅子里，闭上眼睛。

“想到这个借口的人真是个天才，把人生活下去的一大部分力量都驱散了。”

科特一头扎进他的椅子，然后静静地坐了很久。看到科特安静下来，阿德尔海德很欣慰。

“为什么一个人控制不了他的心？”科特最终说道，“假设我有一个妻子和一个孩子，我的妻子是我自己选择的伴侣。有一天，我遇到另外一个女人，她勾起我的欲望。我与她在舞会上相识，那里有灯光、美酒和音乐，我们并非真实的自己，她与我，我们有着与平常不一样的心情，所做的一切都是为了让我们从日常的烦琐中脱离。但我难道不应该跳出这个游戏，衷心地感谢我所拥有的一切吗？”

在科特说话的时候，阿德尔海德睁开了双眼，然后又闭上。她听到了科特所说的，但却没有意识到这话是对她讲的。

“是谁把爱情置于法律之外？如果我脑子里想着为了爱情杀死同类，毫无疑问我在进行犯罪幻想。如果我说出了我的誓词，然后想着将来可以不履行，我就不是一个绅士。但我的心可以肆意而为。”

“是的。”阿德尔海德附和道。

她说这话的时候脑子一片空白，科特也没有听到她的话。

“我们知道，有些人，他们有权利让成百上千的人去死；有些人，他们的激情像赤红的火焰一样直冲天空并照亮大地，吞噬一切挡路之物。诗人歌颂这样的激情，每个人心中都供奉着这样一座神龛。但，如果有人在市政厅广场大街上扮演拿破仑，我们会绞死他。那为什么每两个女人中就有一个会把自己视为海洛薇姿(1)？”

科特陷入自己的椅子里，盯着眼前，“我不知道，是否一次伟大的焰火抵得上成千的微小灯光。我在想，有人知道答案吗？有人能够测量出来吗？”

阿德尔海德挪了挪位置，科特转头看着她，专注地看着她。她的眼睛温柔梦幻，她淡淡地笑了下，好似一个昏昏欲睡的孩子。

“如果真是那样，”科特声音压抑地说，“如果我真的无法控制我的心，”科特让自己的头重重地抵向椅子扶手，“如果爱情真的让我开心、自信，让我将自己和自己家庭的生活都建立在此基础上；如果我的爱情会在我不知不觉的情况下终止，我不得不在另外一个男人的床上寻找我孩子的母亲，那我为什么还要我的妻子出去见人？为什么我不把她锁起来，就像土耳其人那样？或者，在她生下小孩后，我就杀了她？”

科特站起来，开始在屋子里走来走去，渐渐地，他平静下来，“但不是这样的，让那伟大的爱情保持它们的伟大，让诗人歌颂它们，让那微不足道的现代人卑微地模仿它们。希望还是有女人一生只奉献于一个男人，而这些男人也会永久爱着她们。”

他站在壁炉边，看过整个屋子。四下都很安静，教堂的钟敲了两下。

“你看，阿德尔海德，生活会越来越多地进入法律的管辖内。每一天，一方的自由都是以侵犯另一方的权利为代价。国家，与法律无关，但却受法律的制约。没有园丁的同意，花儿不会开花。家畜不能随便选择它们的伴侣。但没有人能控制自己的心，然后人类就像狗一样在大街上交配。”

当科特从他的沉思中醒来，壁炉里的火已几近熄灭。

他看到阿德尔海德已经睡着了。他在她身前站了很久，充满了对她和自己的同情。

然后，科特轻轻抚摸了阿德尔海德的头发，说：

“太晚了，阿德尔海德。”

————————————————————

(1) 法国国王路易十六的王后，生活奢靡，艳名远播。

第八章

“真希望我们没有结婚，科特。”阿德尔海德说。

她双臂交叉在胸前，那双深邃的黑色眼睛望着科特。

“我希望我是你的情人。做情人的话，我们的关系会在黎明时分结束，不会有这些不愉快，也不会有恐惧。而我们享受的快乐会更美好。”

科特站在壁炉旁，摆弄着他口袋里的钥匙。

“那样，你会有光滑的额头，明亮的眼睛，因为你会跟我做爱。”

科特抬头望着阿德尔海德，温柔地说：

“难道我跟你不做爱吗，阿德尔海德？”

阿德尔海德叹气，没再说什么。科特坐了下来，过了许久，问道：

“阿德尔海德，你听到我刚才说的了吗？”

“我更希望听到你接下来要说什么。”

“我最近在一本书里看到跟你刚才说的类似的话，”科特说，“我忘记那书叫什么名字。书中作者痛责婚姻，以及它所象征的安全感，它的习俗等等。这样的观点在好多书里不断重复。”

“是的，那些作者总是唱老调，”阿德尔海德回答道，“这观点当然并不讨好，但我敢说，它有它合理的地方。”

科特轻轻地拍了拍双手说：“如今的诗人想象力贫乏得可怜，这真奇怪。就好像世界上就那么几个女人，他们还跟这些女人结了婚，然后又从她们身边跑开了。我很惊讶，歌颂传统这件事从来没在他们脑子里出现过。”

科特向前拉了拉他的椅子，双手抱头，看着壁炉说：

“如果我是个诗人，我会歌颂赞美神圣的传统。”

“你会吗，科特？”

“是，是的，我会。”

此刻，科特背靠在椅子上，听着烟囱里大风的呜呜声，说：

“你看，阿德尔海德，两个人被这世界上最强大的力量驱使而拥抱彼此。白昼与黑夜，时间与地点对于他们而言都已不存在。整个大地都充满紫罗兰的芬芳。他们的快乐是一种恐惧，这恐惧又充满了狂喜的欢乐。之后，一个小婴儿会躺在女人的膝盖上，她眼里的光芒更加深邃。时间流逝，大地上的紫罗兰越来越少。她承受分娩之痛给予孩子生命，这种痛损耗了她的容颜。孩子吸干了她的乳汁，她的眼睛由于经常熬夜而干涩。路过的陌生人只会看到一个青春已逝的女人。但他，那个被女人年轻时的眼睛迷倒、亲吻过女人坚挺的乳房的男人，他眼里的女人不是那样的。他早已习惯了女人的存在。她平息了他年轻的欲望，取而代之，她给了他平静的快乐。”

科特沉默了一会儿。然后，他转向阿德尔海德，接着说：

“他再不会像过去那样渴望那些激情约会的时刻了，而会寻找她身边那个他早已习惯的睡椅。习惯已将两人捆成了一个家庭。这难道不美好吗，阿德尔海德？”

“是的，很美好，正如你说的那样。但那不是青春。”

“那什么是青春，阿德尔海德？”

“青春是不安稳。”

“那人们不应该在年老之前结婚，因为婚姻就是安稳。深沉的，有力的，快乐的……带来安稳。”

“确实不应该，”阿德尔海德回答，“这也正是为什么我希望我是你的情人。”

阿德尔海德说这些话的时候看着科特，科特也看着她。

然后科特站起来，手放在阿德尔海德椅子的后背上，俯下身对她说：

“我们之间已经变得太陌生了！”

阿德尔海德伤心地点点头，科特穿过屋子，站在壁炉旁，“我从各个角度说明我的想法，都是徒劳。我祖先搭建的这间屋子毫无益处，他的后代在这里，一代又一代的见证，没有任何意义。”

一阵疾风吹来，将阳台门吹开。

阿德尔海德打了个寒战，看向阳台，科特走了过去，关上了阳台门。之后，他站在天球仪旁，按下了按键，“我经常想起那个把这玩具放在这里的可怜人。他的社交圈无法满足他，于是他失去了理智，将自己的精力全部放在摆弄这些星星上。对于我们现代人来讲，正好是相反的，我们发疯是因为社交圈太大了。我们把这些星星留给孩子们玩了。我们去摆弄更大的玩具。当然，要是有兴趣，我们可以与上帝较量一下……如果我们还没玩腻那玩意儿的话！我们不敢说爱，我们嘲笑婚姻。我们蔑视勇气，不相信诚实，对于道德，我们每个人都有自己的一套说辞。”

阿德尔海德漫不经心地听着，如同人们听音乐那般，并不介意是否听清楚了每个音符。

“然后，碰巧我们渴望在我们生活中有一个固定的点。只是那么一个点，无法被批驳被讨论，无法成为过去。”

科特坐了下来，在他的椅子里挪来挪去，无法安定。

“如果我能在这屋里放置任何东西的话，”科特说，“我打算从远方的乡下挪一座小房子放在这里。这幢小房子有一个门，两个窗户。夜晚，烟囱里炊烟袅袅。房子要尽可能地小，但那是为了显示屋内无法容纳任何疑虑。丈夫和妻子会一起进进出出这个房子，直到他们生命的最后一天。”

现在，阿德尔海德终于听清了科特的话，她望着科特。

“那才是我应该有的婚姻，阿德尔海德。如果我有任何才能，如果我得为了生活而工作，我敢说我对婚姻的期待会有所不同。我跟其他男人没什么两样，既没有更加强壮，也没有更加勇敢。我不了解上帝，对人类也没有过多的信仰。”

科特降低了自己的音量，说话的时候并没有看着阿德尔海德。但阿德尔海德知道，科特希望听到她说点儿什么，然而她的心在哭泣，因为她没有任何能对科特说的话。

“我的固定点。”科特说。

之后，他沉默了一会儿。但不久，科特就站了起来，手臂搭在阿德尔海德的椅子上，说道：

“我曾经在家里经常看到这样的场景。父亲和母亲非常和蔼，非常坚强。他们现在就在我眼前，就像以前那样在晚饭后相互亲吻对方，不管周围还有多少客人在场。他们会互相亲吻对方问候早安和晚安，直到他们死去。当我父亲和他的哥哥在大街上遇到，他们总是亲吻对方。人们总是大笑。这曾是多么美好的习惯。”

当科特说话的时候，阿德尔海德试图打断他。

“我对家人的感情一直很强烈，”科特说道，“直到现在也是这样。不过，我也曾有过一位情人。”

科特停了下来。阿德尔海德坐起来看着他。她的眼睛闪烁着光芒。

“或者只是一种肉体关系，如果你喜欢这样归类的话。”

“你从未告诉过我这些！”阿德尔海德说。

科特抬头看着阿德尔海德，而阿德尔海德垂下了眼睑。

“没什么可说的啊。”科特说。

然后，科特没再说什么，他向窗户那边走去。

阿德尔海德又一次在这巨大的古老的椅子里感到渺小而局促。

第九章

科特站在门槛处，等待。但随后他又关上屋门，走向壁炉那里。

科特穿着正装，疲惫而脸色苍白，但他的眼睛因为喝过酒显得明亮。在壁炉旁坐了一会儿后，科特觉得燥热无比，于是他把椅子挪到了阳台门那儿，坐在那里摆弄那些红色的花朵。

当阿德尔海德走进来时，并没有看到科特。

她缓缓移动到了屋子正中央，看到科特并没有在壁炉旁，感到十分惊奇，但不久就忘记了这一点，沉浸在夜晚消遣的欢乐和兴奋中，满脑子都是那些机灵、讨巧的话语，灯光在她的眼睛里闪闪发光。

阿德尔海德坐到钢琴前，前额抵在键盘上。她内心正在欢唱，她的一只脚随之轻轻地在地板上打起拍子。

然后，阿德尔海德找了个小调，唱了起来：

丽诺尔，我心如刀绞。
你如此大胆年轻。
告诉我，丽诺尔，让事实坦白；
（我从来都猜不到）：
你灵魂的泉水何时喷涌？
大山在哪里下沉，溪谷在哪里高耸？
告诉我，让事实坦白；
向我打开你年轻的门。

丽诺尔，我心感悲伤。
你如此开心如此坚定。
教给我你那平静的步态；
教给我欢笑和伤悲。
我的心是一片沙漠，荒凉贫瘠；
我的心属于你，你在那里低语。
一个明天将要喷涌的泉水，
一轮将要镀上上帝光辉的太阳。

阿德尔海德一只手放在一份乐谱上，另外一只手弹着钢琴，又哼了一遍。

此时，科特赞赏地鼓起掌来。阿德尔海德吓了一跳，手重重地落在键盘上。

“吓死我了，科特！”

科特走了过来，站在钢琴旁。阿德尔海德看着他的脸，叹了口气。然后她站起来，不再弹奏钢琴，坐到了壁炉旁的椅子里，“科特，你不到这边来吗？”

科特在屋里不停地走来走去。

“在这里坐一会儿。”阿德尔海德说。

“为什么我要坐下来？”科特问，“你并不在这里，你知道的。”

阿德尔海德望着科特那沉静的眼睛。

“你还在楼下客厅里，在我们那群客人中间。难道你没有意识到吗，阿德尔海德？走出大门的那些马车都是空的。因为，每当有客人来跟你说再见时，你都会要求他们再待一会儿。”

阿德尔海德叹了口气，双手交握放在膝盖上。科特站在壁炉旁，想要看到阿德尔海德的脸。

“当你进来时，我就坐在那儿，在那些花的中间，我都看见了。你进来的时候带着微光和沙沙声，伴随你的是那一大群客人……你是他们中最漂亮的。你旁边走着马顿斯，灵活帅气。后面远远地跟着的是他的妻子……那个眼神总是很疲惫，笑容充满苦涩的女人。她都没看到她的丈夫在向谁献殷勤。”

她皱了皱眉头，生气地看着科特。

“然后，马顿斯恳求你再唱一遍这首歌，客人们全都簇拥着你，跟他一样哀求你。你穿过屋子，步子缓慢而自信。你总是这样走路，阿德尔海德，好像一个无法被阻止的人。你白色的裙摆在你身后拖行，屋子里全都安静下来。”

科特停顿了一会儿。阿德尔海德将头靠回椅子里，闭上了眼睛。

“然后你唱了他要求你唱的歌，就是那首几分钟前你在老钢琴上边弹边唱的歌。是的，你听到我鼓掌了，阿德尔海德。马顿斯站在你身旁，看着你，无比恭敬开心。你望向他的眼睛，在那里反射出你是多么的魅力无敌。”

“你把这一切说得真邪恶！”阿德尔海德说。

科特向她弯下腰说：

“看着我，阿德尔海德。”

她看着他，感到害怕。

“你怎么敢带着你的追随者们进这个屋子？”科特问，“来这儿？来见我？在这间屋子？看着我，阿德尔海德。这房子其他地方的空间还不够大吗？这城市里你能随意玩你喜欢的这类游戏的地方还不够多吗？”

阿德尔海德向他伸出手：

“科特！”

但科特怒目圆睁，她不敢直视。

然后，她在科特面前站起来，低着头。

“我能走吗，科特？”她轻声地问。

科特没有回答，径直穿过屋子。阿德尔海德坐在大椅子的边缘，就好像她并不是在自己家一样。

“是的，马顿斯。”科特说。

“你今晚对他非常不友好，科特。”

她说这话仅仅是为了说些什么，当她想都没想地脱口而出时便后悔起来，可怜兮兮地看了一眼科特。但科特做了个手势，平静地说：

“事实上我对他已经很友好了，尽他所愿地友好，甚至比我想象的还要友好一些。”

科特站在壁炉架旁，低头看着前方。阿德尔海德拉着他的手，放在自己的脸上。

“马顿斯对我来说什么都不是。”她说。

“不，”科特否定道，“不完全是。不是特指那个男人，而是男人们。现在还没有发展成那样，但已经向前发展了。”

“我不明白你在说什么。”阿德尔海德伤心地说。

“不是一个男人，一个好男人或坏男人，在向你求爱，赢得了或正在试图赢得你的心。马顿斯不是我的敌人。他不爱你，他也没有试图要让你相信他爱你。他并不撒谎。不撒谎这种品质，除了在下等阶级中，已经不被提倡了。我们这群人中，连丑闻的影子都看不到。我们应该从何处获取力量，让我们可以与这社会割裂、隔离或者从这里逃离？是从一位告诉他的女孩她是他唯一的挚爱的士兵那里；是从一位杀死不忠诚的爱人，名叫史密斯的工匠那里；是从一个被爱人抛弃，跳水自尽的农场女孩那里。”

科特抽走了他的手，双臂交叉在胸前。

“马顿斯不是唐璜。让女人着迷的并非他的激情，也不是他男儿的勇气和力量。他将欲望发泄在后街那里，他的妻子是用来陪他吃饭的。他无法去爱。他觊觎的女人全部会属于他，但他从未属于任何女人。他的眼睛，他的话语，他歌颂爱情的小曲儿，再加上他那迷人的略带忧伤的气质，没什么女人能够抵挡。然后他把头放在女人的膝盖上，向女人诉说他那亘古不变的渴望和失望。他向女人吐露心声，求她不要背叛他。之后，女人便会爱上他。女人就成了他的囊中物，任他摆布。”

阿德尔海德试图插话，但科特摇头示意不让她说话，她只好叹口气，继续沉默。

“马顿斯不再年轻，但这不会有任何影响。他从未年轻。他那不受约束的多情，他时刻准备为爱献身，这让他在那些女人的眼里显得年轻，就好像他是一个穿着男人衣服的女人。他那软弱无力、贪图感官享受的气质渗透了他身体和灵魂的每一处，以至于他所说的话、他的眼神和想法都受到了影响。他毫无意志，乏味至极，且没有诚信。他虽从不感到饥饿，却贪得无厌。他吞下女人，然后又把她们吐出来，让她们带着病态的欲望、消沉的意气和所剩无几的力量继续过她们的生活。”

“科特！科特！他对于我来说是什么？对于我们来说是什么？”

科特看着阿德尔海德，沉默了一会儿，接着说道：

“马顿斯照看那个你会摘花的花园。他是首席园丁。但他仅仅是千万人之一。总的来说，这些追求激情的人都差不多。需要我把他们介绍给你吗？”

“不，科特。”

“我能告诉你他们的名字，这样就不会伤害到他们。当你见到他们，你会认出他们来，你会立刻认出他们。”

“科特！”

但科特并没有在听。

“你将记得那个男人，虽然我们都知道他有众多的情人，但我们无法当着他的面说什么。他经常带新人来，所以他的情人越来越多，因为他也从不放走那些旧相好。”

“够了，科特。”

“还有个男人，他告诉他那些漂亮的朋友，这一生他只爱过一个女性，那就是他母亲。你有没有注意过母亲在这些筋疲力尽的男人的想象中所扮演的角色？在他们的记录里，他们的爱情中，母亲象征了他们早晨的头痛和性障碍。母亲就是用来抚平他们那堕落的思想的。他们轻轻呼唤着他们母亲的名字，当他们亲吻怀中那甜美的人儿时。我不知道这对谁来说是更大的侮辱，这吻是给母亲的，还是给情人的？”

阿德尔海德试图站起来，但恰巧这时经过的科特离她太近以致她无法移动。于是，阿德尔海德继续坐在那里，疲惫而痛苦，而科特满屋子走，说话的时候一会儿站在这儿，一会儿站在那儿，“我们的妻子属于这些男人，他们并不把这些妻子带走，所以我们无法为她们的离去而伤心，也无法娶新的妻子将她们替代。这些男人咀嚼了我们精心呵护、使其茁壮成长的爱情之树的顶冠。”

此刻，阿德尔海德在科特面前站了起来，满眼泪水，嘴唇颤抖，“科特！”

但科特苍白的脸上满是怒气，阿德尔海德竟说不出一句话。

“我让你想笑吗，阿德尔海德？”科特问。

阿德尔海德回到自己在烟囱旁的位置，再次坐了下来。

“你熄灭了我所有的灯。”阿德尔海德说。

科特穿过屋子，自顾自地继续说道：

“当这些人看上了某个人的妻子，那个人的真爱将付之东流。然后，他就降级为简单的丈夫，一个无聊笨拙的人，一个名不符实的拥有者。然后，在我妻子的脑海里出现了对一些她没有拥有的事物的渴望。她的平静转化成疲倦，婚姻所带给她的爱变成了空洞的习惯。她放弃。那些愚蠢的书里的愚蠢话语在她耳朵里唱歌。她知道，没有什么爱能够长久，婚姻是可憎的。烦躁的叹息在她的灵魂处升起，让她日也苦闷，夜也忧伤。她把真爱的黄金兑换成一把把小硬币，然后在灯光亮起、音乐响起的地方随意挥霍一空。”

科特双手扶着脖子，站在阿德尔海德的椅子附近，看着前方。

“阿德尔海德，”科特说，“我无法理解引起这种情况的男人还能在我们中间自由走动，而且我们还敬他们为尊贵的客人。当我们看到一个可怜的瘸子，我们会抑制不住要打个冷战，难道我说的不对吗，阿德尔海德？我们讨厌看到一张充满痛苦的脸。但与那些男人相比，我们眼前这些本该让人避之不及的人却闪耀着光芒，展现出无人能比的美丽。”

科特来来回回走了一会儿，时间流逝，屋子里充满寂静。

之后他坐在他放在阳台门旁的椅子上，被红色的花朵包围。

科特觉得疲乏无力，于是闭上了眼睛。时不时，有一辆马车驶过广场或一阵叫喊声划破夜的寂静，他睁开眼睛。然后他再次闭上眼，陷入充满烦躁且痛苦的困倦中。

然后，他突然坐起来。

阿德尔海德躺在他前面的地板上，她的脸靠着他的膝盖。她的泪水浸湿了他的手掌。

“请不要生我的气，科特！”

科特看着她，但什么都没有说。

“科特，你说的那些，都是真的。我也很认同，这一切都那么美好。”

科特向后推了推椅子，站了起来：

“阿德尔海德，小心你所做的事情。我不是一个时髦的说教者，激怒你然后又去安慰你。我也不是一个诗人，在给你朗诵他最后的作品。我是你的丈夫，现在要求你解释。”

科特穿过屋子，然后又走回来，抚摸阿德尔海德的头发。

“这已超出了我们的能力，阿德尔海德，”科特悲伤地说道，“上帝帮帮我们！”

阿德尔海德托着科特的手，用力地盖住自己的眼睛，弄得她生疼。

“如果那个过时的上帝还在这里，我们不妨跪下来，双手合十，就像盖起这屋子的人那样，向他祷告。这样难道不好吗，阿德尔海德？”

“是的。”

“我向上帝求告，向超出我个人力量的一切神明求告，向楼下的我们的孩子求告。”

第十章

阿德尔海德躺在她椅子前的地板上，将她花环上的花朵撕成碎片。科特头倚着手，坐在旁边，看着那些花。

“但愿你能说点儿什么，科特，但愿你能问我点儿什么。你为什么不问我点儿什么呢？”

“我能问你什么？”

“问问我在想什么。我为什么回来得这么早。为什么我这么久都没有来过这里。”

“我都知道，阿德尔海德。”

阿德尔海德双手交叉放在她的膝盖上，身子摇来摇去，用那双黝黑的眼睛生气地望着科特，“有什么是你不知道的吗，科特？”

“没有。”

“我也这么觉得。你知道这大千世界里所有一切事情的对错。你从不疑虑，也从不觉得迷茫。你立刻就能辨别一切的对错，然后你会毫不犹豫地做正确的选择。”

科特摇摇头，什么都没说，而阿德尔海德变得更加生气，“只有你无所不知。那些不顺从你意见的人都消失了。这房子里，除了你和那些为你服务的人，根本没有给其他的人预留一点儿空间。”

科特将阿德尔海德从地板上提了起来。

“安静一会儿，阿德尔海德，”科特说，“安静一小会儿。”

但阿德尔海德再次滑倒在地板上，蔑视地看着科特。

“我不会坐在那把椅子里，”她说，“再也不会坐那椅子了。我不配这样的荣誉。你并不是什么都懂，科特。你不了解我。”

科特用手摸了摸阿德尔海德的头发，强迫她抬起头。

“那么，让我了解你。”科特说道。

阿德尔海德挣脱科特的束缚，眼睛变得湿润起来：

“你千万不要对我好。你不了解我。我不是你想象的那个女人。”

然后阿德尔海德把头靠在椅子上，轻轻地说：

“我是如此悲伤，科特。”

“你会开心起来的。”

“我敢说，”阿德尔海德回答道，“我会长久地悲伤。”

阿德尔海德捡起毁掉的花环放在椅子上，她的脸贴着椅子，眼睛闭着。科特看着她——她看起来如此疲惫——他们俩陷入长久的沉默。然后，阿德尔海德说：

“这里可真冷。”

接着，沉默再次降临。

“科特！”

阿德尔海德坐在地板上，背靠着椅子，眼睛盯着壁火，神情诡异，说道：

“科特，你知道吗？有时，当我在外面正开心的时候，我好像听到了小孩子的哭声。”

科特仍旧沉默。

“我听到小孩子们的哭声，科特。有时在我跳舞的时候。有时在我唱歌的时候。有的时候在剧院，灯光明亮，人流涌动，我很开心，然后，我就经常听到……我听到小孩子们在哭，远远地，但我还是可以清晰地听到，我不自禁就会听到。科特，你知道是为什么吗？”

“是的，我知道，阿德尔海德。”

阿德尔海德看着他，眼睛再次转向壁炉说：

“有时，发生的情况不一样。当我听到一个孩子在哭……确实是一个孩子在哭……一个陌生的孩子，跟我一点儿关系都没有，我对他什么都不知道，我甚至不需要看他，科特，但之后我自己也禁不住哭起来。”

阿德尔海德沉默了一阵，然后转向科特，问道：

“你知道那是什么吗，科特？”

科特平静地看着她，说道：

“是的，我知道，阿德尔海德。”

“我不知道，”阿德尔海德说道，轻轻地摇了摇头，“我爱我们的儿子，也非常乐意他跟我在一起。难道不是这样吗，科特？”

“是。”

“但他跟老玛丽在一起的时候更快乐。他更喜欢跟她在一起。当我进来的时候，他向我伸出他那双小手。但当我抱了他一会儿，他就想去找老玛丽。他还那么小。”

“是。”

“有时他无论怎样都不肯亲我，但他总是亲吻老玛丽。”

“当老玛丽去世的时候，我们会给她的坟墓立块碑。在这碑上，我们就写‘这里躺着孩子们曾愿意亲吻的人’。”科特说道。

阿德尔海德双手搂着脖子，仰头看着天花板，“曾经，你总是跟我讲你的母亲。那是很久很久以前的事了，科特。那时，你那么爱谈她，为什么你现在不这么做了？”

“我现在只想你。”

阿德尔海德向科特这边挪了挪，把头靠在了他的膝盖上，“我能这样躺着么，科特？”

科特轻抚她的头发，他的手留在了她的肩头。

“这样很好。”阿德尔海德说。

科特看着她的头发，又摸了摸。阿德尔海德闭上眼，依偎在他身旁。

“这儿很安静，”阿德尔海德说，“现在我想去睡觉了。”

但突然，她又变得焦躁不安起来。阿德尔海德跪在地上，双手撑着膝盖。她的头发散落在肩膀上，眼睛盯着壁炉里的火苗，“你曾告诉我，你还是小孩子的时候，你的母亲会每晚给你脱衣服，每个早晨会给你穿衣服。”

“是的。”

“你说，这总会造成她去剧院迟到。或者，当餐桌上还有客人的时候她就会离开。你父亲曾为此生她的气。”

科特点点头。

“我觉得你父亲是对的，”阿德尔海德说，“我觉得你母亲有点儿怪，有点儿……有点儿不自然。”

科特将额前的头发捋到后面，什么都没说。

“我知道，你想让我做同样的事情。但是我做不到。我做不来老玛丽所做的，我也不觉得只有那样才能是个好母亲。你还告诉我，有一天晚上，当你母亲不得不出门，你一直不停地哭泣，直到她回来。”

“是的。”

“但如果你母亲像我一样，如果是老玛丽天天哄你睡觉，那么你将会为老玛丽而流眼泪了。”

“没错，”科特回答，“但由妈妈做这件事情对于我和她自己都是有益的。”

“我不理解。”阿德尔海德说。

但随即，她抬起头，用她那大大的充满骄傲的眼睛看着他说：

“哦，我懂了。我明白了，这样对一个男人是好的，让他看到他的妻子被她的孩子拴住，能够让他更加自信。”

“没错，阿德尔海德。”

科特静静地、伤心地看着阿德尔海德，那眼神立刻让她那点儿反抗的念头土崩瓦解。

“你说得好奇怪，科特。”

然后她重新将头倚靠在科特的膝盖上，两人沉默了一阵子，之后，阿德尔海德说道：

“我记得我去第一场成人舞会的那个晚上。一位女士来我家为我梳妆打扮。我对此非常郑重，那位女士却滔滔不绝。她告诉我，我很漂亮，一定会很快就嫁出去，因此，我必须抓紧时间一刻不停地跳舞。因为，一旦一个女孩嫁了出去，她就不得不放弃跳舞。我问她说这话是什么意思，因为我认识很多结婚的女士都依然跳舞。然后她告诉我，确实有很多女人婚后继续跳舞，但她们跳死了自己的孩子，因此那是极大的罪过。”

科特在椅子上动了动。阿德尔海德抬了抬头，说道：

“你相信我们能跳死我们的孩子吗，科特？”

科特没有回答，摸了摸她的脸。但阿德尔海德把他的手推开，转向科特，“你信吗，科特？”

科特点了点头。

之后，阿德尔海德笨拙地从地板上站起来，站在科特面前。她缓慢地抬起胳膊，双手压在自己的太阳穴上。

科特迅速站起来，紧紧地握住阿德尔海德的手，把她抱入怀中。但阿德尔海德挣脱了科特的拥抱，眼神空洞地看着科特。

“阿德尔海德！”

“那些是你和我的孩子，科特，当我开心的时候，那些小孩子就开始哭泣，那些因为母亲跳舞而死去的孩子。”

“阿德尔海德！”

科特的声音和眼神都极其温柔，阿德尔海德盯着那双眼睛，在那深邃中看到一丝光芒。她明白，科特心里很开心，因为他认为他以自己想要的方式得到了她。

科特向阿德尔海德伸出手，他的眼睛、他那沉默的颤抖的嘴巴都在对阿德尔海德诉说着情话。阿德尔海德僵硬地站着，冷眼望着科特。

当他的手触碰到阿德尔海德时，阿德尔海德从他身边缩了回来，把自己的椅子向后推了很远，就好像她要为自己找到足够的空间。

“你不懂我。”阿德尔海德说。

阿德尔海德穿过屋子走到阳台门那里，然后又折回到壁炉旁，科特在那儿坐着。她看科特的眼神似乎是在看一个陌生人。

“那些哭泣的小孩，”阿德尔海德说，“他们在哭什么？”

科特抬起手，放在椅子的扶手上。

“他们为什么哭？”阿德尔海德重复道，“是因为他们没有出生在一个看到其美丽的同时却被拒之门外的世界，还是因为他们不是生来就注定要死的？”

阿德尔海德在房间里走了一圈又坐回到椅子里，神情严肃，就好像她不得不向一个理解迟钝的人解释什么。

“没有用。”她说道。

阿德尔海德的声音冷酷。她的身体摆来摆去，脑子里搜索着词语，以便可以一次性表达清楚她的意思，不会被误解。

她的眼光落在科特身上，科特坐在她的旁边，筋疲力尽地闭着眼睛，双手无力地垂着。她看到了她带给科特的痛苦。她希望能够解除这痛苦，修复他们的关系，想着这些，眼泪潸然而落，“科特！”

阿德尔海德握住科特那双毫无力气的手。

“难道你不能帮帮我吗？”

“不能，阿德尔海德。”

听到这回答，阿德尔海德的心情再次发生了变化。她狠狠地坐回到椅子里，双臂交叉在胸前。

“那么，我必须自我拯救，”她说道，“你，或者，一个老……是的，一个像你这样的老人？”

科特没有回答，没有反应，没有看她。

“一个像你一样的老人，”阿德尔海德重复道，“只渴望着平静、安详，对其他毫无欲望。那样，你耗尽了最棒的快乐，也是最便宜、最易得的、最适于家庭的快乐。”

科特坐直了上身，手紧抓着膝盖，眼睛充满怒火。

“你把你爱的女人放到你母亲的坐榻上，也是你祖母还有你曾祖母的坐榻上。”

科特从椅子上跳了起来，双手叉腰，紧咬着嘴唇说道：

“闭上你的嘴！”

阿德尔海德吓了一跳，双眼惊恐地看着他，说道：

“你没有权利对我说这话。”

科特重新坐回到椅子里，脑袋靠着椅背，脸扭向另外一边。阿德尔海德如此疲惫，她找不到她想要的词语，所表达的意思都不是她想要表达的，口气也不是她所想象的那样。

当科特在她身边渐渐冷静下来，阿德尔海德的思维也清晰了起来，她意识到，除非她说出最狠的话，似乎没有别的方法了。然后，为了给自己鼓劲，她握紧拳头，闭上眼睛，一口气说道：

“你必须知道事情的真相，科特。你所看到的，所说的，都是真的。我欺骗了你，科特。我撒了谎，每次我来这里，和你坐在一起，我都会撒谎。”

阿德尔海德看着科特。科特费力地抬起头，看着阿德尔海德的眼睛，然后，他转头看向别的地方。

“你现在还在撒谎。”他说。

阿德尔海德张开嘴，又闭上，上下牙齿撞了一下。

然后，她双手交叉放在膝盖上，弯下腰，哭泣道：

“我自己都不知道。”

科特站起来穿过屋子，缓慢而又疲惫不堪，头脑一片空白。阿德尔海德的泪水不断落在她的膝盖上。

他们虽然同在这屋子里，却又独立于彼此，丝毫不怜悯对方。他们的心已死去，他们的思想瘫痪。他们不再是彼此相爱一起追求幸福的两个人，他们甚至不为即将到来的分别而感到生气或遗憾。他们仅仅是被判了死刑的两个人，碰巧被关在同一间牢房里，除此之外，这两人再无共同之处。

科特首先回过神来。

他站在阿德尔海德椅子的背后，阿德尔海德发丝的香味唤醒了他。他向阿德尔海德弯下腰去，记起了她是谁。科特看着阿德尔海德的手已被眼泪浸湿，此刻，科特的心也碎了。

那一刻，科特突然意识到，如果他不想跟阿德尔海德分开，他必须给予她怜悯。而当他明白这一点时，他立刻知道，他已永远地失去了阿德尔海德。

科特坐在自己的椅子里，搜索着他应该说的话。他感觉自己好像一个演员，要在这场表演中诉说结束语，然而观众已经开始离席，因为这场演出的结局已然明朗，表演的张力已经消失。

“阿德尔海德！”科特喊道。

这是他唯一能说出口的。阿德尔海德明白科特内心的想法，无言以对，默默地流着眼泪。

夜晚悄无声息地降临。

阿德尔海德又一次躺在了地板上，她的脸靠在科特的膝盖处。她急切地说着，断断续续地，并不在乎说了什么，只求把想要说的都说出来。

科特头倚着手，他浓密的头发散落在额头上。科特闭上眼，又睁开，对阿德尔海德的话，左耳朵进，右耳朵出，时不时做出回应，心里只有一个念头，就是这一切结束了。

“除了你之外，还有其他男人。你说的是真的，都是真的。哦，科特，我能跟你说吗，尽管这事很邪恶？你会温和地对我吗？你能理解吗，那不是不忠诚。”

阿德尔海德紧握双手，绝望地摇头说：

“是的，是的，是不忠，科特，是这样的。我现在明白了。我能告诉你吗，科特，我可以吗？我爱他们眼中的渴望，我对那渴望很好奇，我不觉得有什么耻辱，我在那眼神中觉得开心，我甚至试图点燃那眼神。”

“这些事情，不该跟你的丈夫诉说，阿德尔海德。”

阿德尔海德看着科特，“那么，我应该对谁说？”

“这些事情应该埋藏起来。”

“哦，好吧，但我要把它们说出来。我会说出来。因为我面对的是你，还因为，你询问我这些事情，科特，你看到了这些事情，想要拯救我。这就是你跟我讨论这些的原因，不是吗？我以前不知道，现在我知道了，现在我没有撒谎。但是我以前不知道，在你说之前。而且，对于我来说，这并没有更丑陋，反而是更好的。科特，科特，这并没有那么丑陋。”

阿德尔海德将脸埋在双手中，抽泣到无法说话，“哦，科特，实际情况比我说的还要糟糕。你为什么不把我逐出家门？要是你不在世了就好了，科特！为什么你要这么不快乐？为什么是我让你这么不快乐？如果你抛弃我，这是我罪有应得。可我知道我爱的是你，我从前不曾明白，但我现在意识到，你才是我命中注定的人。”

阿德尔海德抓着科特的衣服努力站了起来，她那苍白的脸贴近科特：

“科特，难道你不能等等我吗？我已经赶来了。”

说完这话，阿德尔海德松开了抓着科特衣角的手，瘫到了地板上。

“不，不，我做不了你期望我做的事。”

科特站在阿德尔海德面前，望着壁炉里的火苗，说：

“阿德尔海德，是你的意志出了问题。”

科特穿过屋子，站在阳台门那里，望向外面。然后他又走了回来，坐到自己的椅子上，说道：

“你知道那伟大的欢乐在哪里。你知道，我们会沉浸在这伟大的欢乐里，如果你能够得到它。但是你不能。你没有自己的判断力。一切事物对于你来说就是很近或很远，很小或很大。你就像马顿斯以及其他那些人一样。你是他们中的一员，因为你的意志脆弱，和他们一样。你正在转变成他们那样的人。”

“不，科特。”

“是的，你跟他们一模一样。你是个女人，优雅大方，因此你害怕深陷泥潭。但你属于他们。你和我是不共戴天的敌人。如果你是我儿子选定的妻子，我会为他的幸福极其担忧。你有你要找的幸福。不，全世界的幸福都是你的。当你足够年轻能够抵挡酒精而又足够成熟知道它的好处时，你才会把酒杯端到唇边。”

科特捋了捋额头的头发，向四周看了看，说道：

“没什么可说的了。你是这个时代的孩子，这个时代养育了你。以后，再带你来这房间也没有什么意义了。”

“不，科特。”

“但你很聪明，你有教养，你已经看到了这房间伟大而无声的美丽。有一天，你会明白，快乐就在你原来待过的地方，但你却执意去远方寻找。”

“是的，科特。”

“你会看到那一天的到来。但那时一切都太迟了。到那时，时光都已流逝，老钢琴的琴键已经生锈不能发声，纺车轮子布满灰尘，壁炉里的火也都熄灭。那时，你的想象陷入惶恐，困惑不堪，就像那只不停冲着窗户栅栏扑打翅膀的鸟。你会丢失信仰，你的谦逊化为不贞。”

科特站起来走到阳台门处。阿德尔海德脸靠着壁炉栅栏，双眼紧闭。

房间里的空气仿佛凝结，被沉默吞噬。他们彼此都感受到了这沉默所带来的痛，然而当死亡即将来临，痛感已经变得麻木。他们不再抗拒命运，不再抗拒胜过他们的力量。他们疲惫不堪，甚至都没有想过所遭受的溃败，而是在得到的平静中微笑起来。

夜晚飞逝。

科特和阿德尔海德坐在稀奇的古董椅子里，看着余火在壁炉中熄灭。蜡烛也几乎燃尽。

两人温柔安静，好像上次有不同意见的时候是好多年以前了。两人表情镇静，当他们彼此相望，眼神清澈而悲伤，但不再渴望，也没有愤怒和痛苦。

他们看着彼此，聊着刚刚结束的一切。

他们的话语不再带着锋芒。科特握着阿德尔海德的手，像好朋友那样。阿德尔海德甚至像对一个孩子般给科特捋了捋额头的发丝。

“如果有人看到我们坐在这里，他肯定不会明白我们之间发生了什么。”科特说道。

“没错。”

“如果有人听到我们在屋子里说的每句话，他可能会觉得我们是一对傻瓜。”

阿德尔海德摇了摇头：

“还好没有更糟糕的事情发生在我们身上。”

“我不确定。”科特回应道。

然后他放开阿德尔海德的手，挺直身体，说道：

“有时，我觉得，如果要是有什么具体行为需要被宽恕，或许会更容易些，一些可以忘记的事情，那么就不会结束了。”

“并没有结束，”阿德尔海德说，“我们错过了快乐，因为我没有遵守我应该遵守的标准。但我们还有儿子，他能娶到一位配得上坐在这里的妻子。”

“不。老屋子的作用已经消失了。它不再适应这时代，更不适应未来的时代。我们的儿子不会在这里目睹他的快乐支离破碎。”

说完这些之后过了一会儿，科特用手压住自己的太阳穴，非常小声地说：

“因为要一个人做令自己不快乐的事太难了。”

蜡烛终于熄灭了，一支接着一支。

“很晚了，阿德尔海德，我们走吧。”

“好的。”

但他俩谁都无法离开。

他们互相看了一眼彼此，陷入同样的沉思中，害怕结束这平静的夜晚，因为之后迎接他们的将是灾难的日子。

最后一根蜡烛燃尽。

科特的台灯仍旧亮着，但房间里的一切似乎都在灯光的摇曳下移动了位置。原来明亮的地方被黑暗替代，一大片黑影在墙上显现。

两人似乎都感受到神秘的力量，不由自主地靠近了一些。

“唱歌给我听吧，阿德尔海德。”

阿德尔海德走向钢琴，看着琴键。

“唱丽诺尔系列的最后一首。”

阿德尔海德转头看了看，但却看不清科特脸上的表情。

然后她唱道：

当死亡来临，来临，丽诺尔，
你是生命那红色的灯塔；
那光芒从你快乐的大眼睛中四射；
就在那一刻，死神也死去。
我从不属于死神，而是属于你；
我不流眼泪，也不曾抱怨；
将你那红唇放在我的唇上，
再带走你的灵魂。

我将最后一次看到，
我珍爱的光芒四射充满爱意的双眼；
是什么样的歌曲什么样的罪过，
我让他人去权衡考量。
但你不要忘记，
当夜色爬过窗格，
那羞涩的蓝色紫罗兰之香气，
甜美了一切简单朴素。

当阿德尔海德唱完时，科特站在她椅子背后。阿德尔海德并没有感觉到，她坐在钢琴前，手放在琴键上，不断地重复最后一句歌词。

科特看着她的头发，她的手，还有她那白色的连衣裙。他似乎刚刚意识到他失去了什么，也明白他再也不会拥有了。科特双手颤抖，眼睛发烫。他觉得他一定会杀了阿德尔海德还有他自己。

然后他念着她的名字。

阿德尔海德抬头看着他。

她忘记了一切，眼中只有他。科特从她那大而奇特的眼睛中、她那红艳的嘴唇里看到了这一切。

阿德尔海德跳了起来，开心地大叫，科特把她拥入怀中，带走了她。

第十二章

当科特讲完老屋子的故事，他站在窗户旁，望着广场远方，刚刚亮起的路灯旁暮色渐浓。

仆人悄无声息地进入房间，点燃吊灯，又悄无声息地离开。灯光照亮了屋子的每一处，散落在科特身上，此刻坐着的科特看着眼前的芬，而芬的眼睛也盯着科特。

但芬和科特的注意力却不在灯火阑珊处。

他们早已神游于老屋子的美好神秘中。他们听到外面寂静的广场上喷泉的潺潺声，看到阳台上如烈焰般的红色花朵。钢琴清爽的音符在他们的耳畔回响，阿德尔海德白色的礼裙轻轻滑过地板。

科特转身面向芬，在芬眼里，科特已是暮年；而在科特眼中，芬依旧是那个在摇篮里大笑着挥舞起一对小拳头的小孩子。

科特站起来，抓着芬的胳膊，一起走来走去，沉默不语，他们被看到的景象征服，生怕一说话那脑海中的梦就破碎了。

他们走了一会儿，最后，停在了窗户前，玻璃上满是水汽，挡住了他们的视线。科特想起来，还有一些事情应该让芬知道，且这些事情芬无从问起。

科特看着芬，回忆起他是如何爱过芬的母亲。

芬长着他母亲的眼睛，但是眼神更显平和；嘴巴也随了母亲，但要苍白一些，稍显疲倦，似乎他试过千百次要说出那从未说出口的事情。芬随了他母亲那纤细的腰身，他比科特还要高，但身高对于他来讲更像是负担一般。他脸庞苍白，亦随了母亲，但头发却随了科特，甚至更加浓密乌黑。

“芬！”科特喊道，并把手搭在芬的肩膀上。

芬被这喊声吓了一跳，无法直视科特。但科特抓住了芬的下巴，让他抬起头。科特看着芬那双受惊的眼睛，脸上浮现出伤心的笑容，“还有一件事情没有告诉你，芬，阿德尔海德并没有情人。”

当看到儿子脸上突然显现的巨大喜悦，科特不由得也开怀笑了，他把芬拥入怀中，亲吻了他。

但突然间，科特离开了芬，在屋子里某处背对着他坐了下来。芬紧随其后，在科特身旁站了一会儿，心里对他充满深情和喜爱，却不知该说什么。

科特思绪万千。

他又重新经历了一遍，多年的沉默在他的意志里结成的疤又裂开了。他的眼神渐渐充满怒气，他想要像曾经那样说话，那时他还在为阿德尔海德做无谓的斗争。

然后，他看到了芬。

芬以他最喜欢的姿势坐在那里，头垂着，手掌摊开放在膝盖上。

于是科特内心又恢复平静，柔声说道：

“你当然高兴，因为她是你的母亲。”

科特穿过房间又走了回来，手搭在椅子后背上，瞧着沉浸于思考的芬。屋里如屋外一般沉寂，因为是周日的缘故。他们能听到晚间祷告的钟声响起。

“她从来没有得到过红色的花朵来取代那些她不喜欢的蓝色花朵。”科特说道，“我不知道，我经常想……”

祷告结束的钟声响起。

有一处钟声很近，有一处很远却更响。还有远处的钟声分不出彼此，在空中响成一片。

由于他们都在注意听，这钟声听起来比以往要响，巨大的喧闹盈满整个房间。

然后，房子大门处传来一阵隆隆的声音。马车驶进了软绵绵的雪地里，没了声响。“这是阿德尔海德要去教堂。”科特说道。

他坐在他儿子身边，开始低声说话，他并没有瞧着芬。

钟声突然停止，更加凸显了随之而来的寂静。

“有一个晚上在兰德克，钟声勾住了她，那是一个继充满阳光、欢乐和人群的白天之后的夜晚。她是所有人中最开心的那个，但傍晚时，她突然变得沉默疲惫，这样的状况据我所知经常毫无理由地发生……你和我们在一起。你那时十岁，你躺在那里睡着了。我们站在你的小床旁看着你，她突然开始哭泣，而我除了握住她的手不再说话外什么都做不了。”

芬听着科特讲话，就好像他听那钟声一般，不去管这些词语对他的意义是什么。他仅知道，他的母亲没犯任何错误，而他的父亲把一切都告诉了他，并让他最终决定他们之间的对和错。芬心中充满喜悦，这让其余一切都变得轻松且无关紧要起来。

科特继续说道：

“然后我拿着烟走到阳台上，她站在门廊处，听着小教堂的钟声回响在山间，我们白天刚参观过教堂回来，在那里，我们还听到了一个关于教堂的故事。曾经，一个虔诚的人为了赎罪修建了这座教堂，自那之后，教堂的钟声每天午夜后两小时都会响起……她问那钟声会不会就这样一直响到世界的尽头，然后我们开始谈论世界上的一切钟声，白天响的，夜里响的，日出响的，日落响的，还有抚慰疲惫的世人的。有时她会沉默。那钟声总会响起，她也总会重新开始讲话，而且经常是关于一件事情，关于世界上的钟是如何亘古不变地发着一致的声音。还有那些第一次听到钟声的人，他们像狂野的异教徒一般在无尽的树林里跑着。关于那些在现代社会里意志突然崩塌的人，他们跪了下来，爬着离开钟声召唤他们的地方。”

芬抬起头。科特的话终于引起了他的注意，把他从梦里拽了回来。

“我仍旧能回想起她站在夜色下，把自己灵魂交给上帝的样子。她那奇异的眼睛望着星空，她那苍白的脸，她的双手，还有她的话语，来得如此快，就好像她的生命全都依赖于她的话语，如此沉重，就好像每一个词语都给她带来痛苦。她根本没有考虑到我在那里：她讲话的样子就好像她在教堂里做忏悔，然后她就宣布结束了。她周围的一切都变得空洞、冷漠、黑暗，四处都是痛苦和绝望，在那里她笑意盈盈的眼睛曾见证过节日的灯光和人群。绝望绵延不绝，她不得不闭上眼睛以抵制绝望的侵袭。绝望越来越近，越来越强，她逃命一样地逃开。现在，绝望就在那里，充满天地，在她身体里，在她周围，远远近近。如果那钟声无法抗击绝望，那她就得死。”

科特声音如此轻柔，芬几乎听不到他的声音。

“然后，那钟声停止了。不久，天亮了，阳光照耀在她那雪白湿润的脸颊上。她一动不动，保持沉默，但她的思绪依旧。当我们周围的事物开始动起来时，她离开了旅店，我不知道她去了哪里，但我敢打赌她去了教堂。夜晚的时候，她才回来。午夜，我们又一次坐在阳台上，继续听教堂的钟声。就这样，一周过去了。我经常会担心她失去理智。她总是讲述同样的事情，她沉默的时候则更糟糕。我让老汉斯带着你先回了家，第二天我们也离开了那里，但我们并没有回家。她想把我们旅行的路线再走一遍。她说她想去她寻欢路上曾路过的每一个教堂里祈祷。”

芬在他的椅子里直起身来，“那你去了吗？”

“我做了她所希望的。旅途最后变成了去往每一个生活无拘无束的地方的朝圣。我们不断地从一个地方赶往另一个地方。她不肯错过任何一个教堂，唯恐有罪名她没有祈祷到，唯恐将来那钟声无法抵达她的坟墓。”

“那之后你们回家了吗？”

科特看着他的儿子，好像他早已忘记他还待在这屋子里。他突然意识到那些日子和当下生活的不同，他的神情变得忧郁不堪，他的眼神严肃起来，让芬觉得害怕。

“之后，我们回到家里。再之后……”

科特迅速站起，双臂交叉在胸前，看着芬，“之后我们回到家里。随着时间推移，阿德尔海德也慢慢地恢复了精神上的平静。她又找到了昔日的自己。她的思绪变幻莫测，她的欲望永远也无法满足。现在她的马车还像从前那样经常在大街上走动，只不过马车会停在教堂门口，而不是剧院。”

芬想说话，但又说不出口，因为科特就站在他面前，眼睛盯着芬看，还朝他点了一次头，就好像在说他知道芬想要说什么，而且他所说的毫无意义。

“她去参加上帝的欢宴了，”科特说，“而且上帝也会参加她的聚会。”

芬坐回到椅子里。

他既不为他父亲所说的感到伤心，也不为他的母亲苦恼，如果这一切都是真的，这让他既惊讶又羞愧。他知道他应该有抗拒之心或者怜悯之情，但却没有，因为他对这一切太了解了。

科特大步跨过屋子，“天堂不是阿德尔海德想要的，也不是她寻找的。你可能得需要再过几年才能理解我的话。但是，芬，这一生，我所看到的上帝在那些否定他的人身上最能显现。在他们的责任感里，他们的人性里，在他们的骄傲中，我看到了上帝的光芒。其他人，那些不断向他忏悔，把他摆满屋子的人，当他们应该歌颂他的伟大荣耀时，他们却让我更无法看清上帝，他们赞美他的全能，实则使他变得很渺小。”

科特讲了好一阵子。芬无聊且无助地坐在椅子里，希望他父亲能停下来。他感觉自己好像不小心见证了他不该看的事，又好像得到了不该有的信任。

在芬的内心深处，对他父亲滔滔不绝所说的话不屑一顾。

但此刻，科特就坐在他面前，紧握芬的手，眼神温柔忧郁，话语温柔谦卑，好像一个罪人那样祈求内心的平静，“我不知道，芬。我无法解释这一切给你听。我无法跟你讨论这些事情。父亲是可怜的生物，芬，我是个可怜的父亲。我无法告诉你森林是绿色的，鸟儿会歌唱，这蓝色的天空后面一无所有。我不敢，芬。我认为我没有这样的权利。我也无法跟你一起去教堂，甚至当你和你母亲一起去教堂时我也无法开心。”

科特紧张地摁了摁芬的手。芬的手一动不动，他亦不知道该如何回应他父亲的眼神。

“但是，我必须要告诉你一点，就这一次，今天，我向你坦白，以弥补我们作为父母的责任。如果你愿意试着理解我，宽恕我，宽恕我们，因为我们没有我们的孩子所期望的那样富有，因为我们有一个孩子。你爱这钟声，芬。当钟声一响起，你就会进入梦乡，这钟声送你去遥远的地方。自你是小孩子时起就是这样。我非常能理解，我也很爱听这钟声。我很高兴，因为有这钟声在那儿。但是，芬，芬，除了这些召唤我们去教堂的钟声外，世界上还有很多其他的钟声。每个人都有只属于他自己的钟声，只有他自己能听到，只会召唤他本人。有些富有、帅气的人，不论他们走到哪里，钟声都会为他们响起。他们过着比我们更有权势、更得意的生活。他们让我们……我们之中那些爱他们的人遭受痛苦。但世界上没有人渺小到不会有钟声召唤他。钟声存在于一个人的工作中，在他的孩子身上，在他的爱情里。对有的人来说，他的钟声在他母亲居住的干净的小屋子里，可能他只有在星期天的时候在那里待一个小时……每个人的情形都不一样，芬，但钟声一直都在。当人们走上了不该走的路，钟声就会把他们叫回来，如果来不及，钟声会敦促他们忏悔。不论举办宴会的时候，还是疲倦伤心的时候，他都会有钟声相伴。但教堂的钟声，它们只为那些耳朵被生活震聋的人发出。生活会发出可怕的噪音。那些钟声在周日响起，就是为了提醒我们过去一周所忘记的，有它们在那儿可真好。但是，芬，当教堂的钟声把那些曾经都有属于自己的神圣之地的人逼到一起，这是多么悲伤啊。那就好像当一个家庭破碎后，家里的老人不得不在济贫院找到一处避难所。阳光穿过窗户，室内温暖，窗扉上的花朵鲜艳。芬，你母亲和我之间，我们有过更好的时候，我们的那个钟声，曾经也在老屋子里响起。”

科特沉默，不再看芬。芬也放松下来，最终找到他想要说的话，“我能使用那个房间吗，父亲？我能把它重新布置一下吗，跟原来一样，然后跟我的书一起搬进那里？”

科特松开了他儿子的手，他脸上的神情让芬后悔说出那样的请求。此刻，两人都站了起来，科特脸上浮现出一丝微笑说：

“可以。亲爱的孩子，你从未要求过任何事情。这屋子就当作我送给你的礼物吧。”

那一天，科特的儿子刚刚过完他的二十一岁生日。

第十三章

芬站在老屋子里，手里拿着泛黄的文件，上面写道：

上帝把我带到这里，让我能盖起这座漂亮的房子，它将长久屹立，见证我和我家族的力量。在这里，他们将正直地生活，慷慨地给予。这房子会被一代一代的父子忠诚守护。善良的男人女人会坐在那大厅里，伴着笛声和提琴起舞。

我将这屋子设置在整个房子最秘密的部位，除了房子的设计师和我最老的仆人外，没有人知道它的存在。我给了房子的设计师一笔封口费，让他发誓不会把这秘密泄露出去。而我的老仆人则对我无比忠诚。

我不仅给屋子镀了金，还配备了有图饰的皮帘子和昂贵的东方地毯。我有两把从米兰定制的精致的扶手椅，木质部分那里被雕刻了鸟和动物的图案，黑暗中，它们好像露出奇怪的笑容，但打开灯的时候笑容就消失了。

我给了仆人一把房间钥匙，告诉他要诚心诚意地照料房间。每天傍晚，暮色渐浓时，他就会点燃壁炉架上的蜡烛，即便他知道他的主人正在远方旅行，他也照做不误。每个早晨，他会亲自收拾房间。除了他自己，没有其他仆人曾进入这个屋子。

因为这个屋子是为我和我的妻子准备的。因此我把这屋子设置在房子最为隐秘的地方，远离我们工作的账房，远离仆人们走来走去的走廊，远离我们会见客人的客厅，甚至远离我们的婚房。

这将是我们婚姻的神殿，因为我们的爱情使之神圣，而这爱情比我们所知的任何一切都要伟大。在这儿，我们会向上帝祈祷，是他把我们带给彼此。在这儿，每个我们心灵相交的晚上，我们会开心真诚地交谈。当我们死去后，我们的儿子将带着他的妻子来到这里，继续做我们做过的事情。

今晚，是我在这所新房子里度过的第一个晚上，我带着我的妻子来到这里，告诉了她我的心愿。她充满爱意地倾听了我的想法，我在这里记录下事情的经过，并签上我们的名字，让后人见证。

芬读着他们的名字，还有后来房子主人和他们妻子的名字。最后，科特和阿德尔海德的名字浮现在眼前，但又被划去了。

然后，芬把这份文件放回了原处，环顾四周。

老屋子又恢复了以前的样子，高高耸立在广场上，深幽而寂静，好似一个没有生命存在的地方。

阳台被雪覆盖，麻雀在雪里跳来跳去。屋子里，在那彩色的窗格后面，是红色的花朵，极度渴望阳光。皮革挂帘上的灰尘已被扫去，重新恢复了以往的亮度。东方地毯在地上铺展开来，好似流放归来的贵族重新掌管了他的家园。

所有以前的老家伙事儿都又一次找回了各自的位置，合法安心地站在那里，就好像一切从未改变过。钢琴、画着在荆棘中扭动的男人的罐子、星星不仅发光还会移动的天球仪，所有这些由不同的主人带来的家具都又一次出现在屋子里。

在壁炉前面摆着两把硕大奇特的扶手椅。

芬觉得他好像在天主教堂里，每一面飞舞的旗帜都是一位名人的墓志铭。他吸吮着过去时光的味道，他想象出来满屋子的男男女女坐在那里，或强硬或温柔地交谈，他们周围的一切已经进入梦乡。

芬陷入了对那对最后在这屋子里坐着的夫妇的沉思，这两人给予他生命，但他却不知应该做什么。

他看到他们年轻时的爱和挣扎。他听到他们的声音，他看到阿德尔海德的红唇和科特那沉稳的眼神。他看到科特带着自己的妻子来到这里，这里是房子的灵魂、传统和密室，向她展示他祖先留在这里的稀奇古怪的物件。

他看到那天科特独自站在壁炉旁，在空荡荡的房间里，将他和阿德尔海德的名字从那份文件上划掉，然后门也不关地离去。

他看到所发生的一切。但他们并不是他的父亲和母亲。他们是两个他从书本上读来的、并逐渐喜欢上的惹人喜爱的人，他对他们的喜爱就如同对艺术的喜爱一样，是苍白的，没有任何探寻的欲望。

芬将其中一把大椅子拉到窗户边上，长久地坐在那里。

当他坐在那里时，阿德尔海德走了过来。

她站在门廊处，穿着白色的裙袍，满头银发的她向他点头。然后，阿德尔海德转头看了看屋子四周。

然后，一切就好像梦的影子一样发生又随即消失：屋子里的一切都恢复了生机。

钢琴开始歌唱，古董椅子上的怪脸伸出了长脖子，屋内的每个角落都有低语声。

阿德尔海德缩了回去。她没有看到芬，忘记了他还在那里。

但是芬看到了她。

他从椅子上站起来，他的眼睛泛着光芒，“你点亮了这屋子，母亲，这屋子也点亮了你。”

芬握起阿德尔海德的手亲吻了一下，阿德尔海德被芬牵着，走进了这个容不下她年轻欲望的屋子。

童话故事结束了，连同对这屋子的恐惧一起。但那光芒仍旧在阿德尔海德身上显现，她看上去美极了。她的脸如同小姑娘那般粉嫩，她的步伐轻盈，她的眼睛湿润而羞涩。她轻轻地、开心地笑着，一边观看这些老家具，一边讲关于它们的故事，不时抚摸着它们。

她讲了那个每当悲伤时便唱歌的女人的故事，是她带来了这架老钢琴。当她在钢琴上弹出和声时，她的手都在发颤，那轻柔美妙的旋律响彻房间。她还讲了老纺车的故事，这老纺车曾夜夜不停地呼啦呼啦地转了一整年。她还讲到了天球仪，那曾是那个智力衰退的人的玩具。还有那带着一张空洞的脸的布娃娃，让人想起那个害怕这屋子的寂静而从来不敢踏入这里的女主人。但她的儿子，因为非常爱她，把布娃娃藏在了窗帘后面。还有莱克，她的画像曾挂在墙上露出污渍的地方，但是后来被取下来了，因为她的婚姻解体了。

还有那个画着在荆棘里扭动的男人的坛罐，这是她带给这房间的礼物。阿德尔海德轻轻拂过这坛罐，沉默不语。

芬的眼睛紧追着阿德尔海德。

他从未看过他的母亲如此美丽。他不认识那样的眼神，那样的笑容，那样清澈的声音。

有时，芬会在她讲的基础上加一点儿东西，他说话内涵丰富，让她感到惊讶和害怕。现在，他可以在阿德尔海德说话前就猜到她要说的事情。然后，她从未怀疑过他会知道这些事情。

阿德尔海德内心的恐惧与日俱增，因为不晓得科特对他都说了什么。

但芬已沉浸在自己的欢乐中。

陶醉于阿德尔海德的美丽，痴迷于屋子里这些奇怪的东西，还有那深深的寂静中，他想让这游戏进行得更加生动，却忘记了老屋子的封印已被打破。

芬将另一把椅子也拉到窗户那里，让阿德尔海德坐下，然后他自己坐到另外一把椅子里，说道：

“现在，你不是我的母亲，你是我年轻的新娘。我带你来到这个神圣的地方，我现在要告诉你它的秘密。”

听到芬的话，阿德尔海德突然脸色苍白，芬内疚地握起她的手，说：

“我伤害到你了吗，母亲？”

阿德尔海德摇摇头，强挤出一点儿笑容。

然后芬再次走进屋子里，开心地拥抱这屋子的一切，但阿德尔海德依旧坐在那里，眉头紧锁。

她心情沉重，因为在她看来，当他们坐在这房子的密室里聊天时，她突然就不是他的母亲了。旧时光强有力地冲击着她的大脑，把她带到另外一个世界里去了。

老房子充满了回音，科特的言语，科特的爱……那坚定的信念，还有这在优良的传统之下发芽且在过往时日里不断壮大的家族的巨大幸福，都融为一体。

有那么一刻，阿德尔海德在想，如果一切按照科特所想的那样发生应该会很好。

但同时，又有一个想法抓住了她，让她变得叛逆而年轻，就如同很多年前她最后一次站在这屋子里一样。

她狠狠地将自己的椅子向后推了推，环视着充满敌意的屋子，眼里满含泪水。

阿德尔海德看向芬，他站在天球仪旁，试图将其启动，但却因为开关生锈而卡住了。

阿德尔海德想，当芬到了娶妻的年纪，他会想要恢复传统，将他的妻子也带到这里，和她坐在这对古董椅子里吗？

之后是芬的儿子，以及儿子的儿子，他们都会读到那泛黄文件上被划掉的她的名字。她会像其他那些在这个家族里被标上标签的人一样，关于她爱出去玩和猎寻根本不存在的快乐的流言蜚语会越来越多。

“来帮帮我，母亲。”芬说道。

阿德尔海德走了过去，用力地按下了开关，天球仪又开始转动起来。

“瞧，你泄露了魔法的秘密。”芬说道。

他自顾自地说着话，看到天球仪能发亮、能转动的星星非常高兴。

“芬，来我身边坐。”

等芬坐了过来，阿德尔海德又顿了一会儿，就好像她在找她想要说的话，而且，她说话时并没有看着芬。

“芬，”阿德尔海德把手放在他肩头，然后又立刻抽开，“芬，有一次，很多年以前，有一天晚上，我独自待在老屋子里。你知道，我以前经常会和你的父亲来这里，我被老屋子的权威控制，从来没有在这里真正开心过。我当时还很年轻，芬，这一切和我的憧憬和快乐都格格不入。我当时无法理解这些，也无法减轻或者克服这屋子带给我的不适感。因为你的父亲是属于这屋子的，而这屋子还有屋里的古怪东西都是属于他的，而且它们都在抗拒着我。每次我来到门前，我的心脏都停止跳动。而一旦我在这里面，就好像……就好像我不能再诉说我的想法，而是说着别人安排好的话。哦，都是些好话，但不是我的。但当我鼓起勇气，说出我自己想说的，我的话听起来又好像我在诋毁老屋子还有你父亲以及上帝。之后……”

阿德尔海德感到，她正在背叛放在她手上的一些伟大而美好的事物。她看看周围，似乎在害怕屋子里还有其他人，或者整个屋子会跳起来用它根深蒂固的力量反对她。

但屋里没有其他人，也没有声音。

然后，她转头看着芬，高兴地说道：

“但是那一晚，芬，我解除了老屋子的咒语。我把神龛上的那块薄纱扯了下来，薄纱后面什么都没有。第一次，我感到我可以在我的家里自由呼吸。”

阿德尔海德并没有说明后来她如何又被恐惧笼罩，继而狼狈地逃离了这屋子。但是，她没有达到她撒谎想要达到的目的。芬悲伤地看着她，说道：

“你怎么能那么做，母亲？你怎么能那么想它？”

“你也受了咒语的控制吗？”阿德尔海德问道。

她的语气中透露出嘲笑的意味，比她预期的要浓烈许多，这让她惊吓不已。但芬并没有注意到。

“那老屋子已经不存在了，仅仅是一个意象，一个纪念碑，是我依据父亲所说编造的幻象。”芬说。

阿德尔海德扭过头去，继续听着。

“但若我也经历过老屋子还存在的那段时光，它肯定也会控制住我。”

“是的，你一直都在跟你父亲谈话。”阿德尔海德轻轻地说。

“是的。”

然后，芬在阿德尔海德面前躺了下来，如以往那般将脸放在她的手里。

“是的，”芬重复道，“还有，母亲，我爱你。你如此美丽。但我们再也不会讨论那老屋子了……因为我认为那老屋子是我所知道的最精彩、最美丽、最强大的事物。可是，一想到我没有完全随了你，或继承了父亲的所有，我无法专一地分享你们俩任何一人最强烈的感情，我就会心痛。我无法跟父亲讨论这一点，也没法跟你讨论，对吗？”

阿德尔海德没有回答他，而是温柔地抚摸着他的头发。两人都没有再说话，屋子里静极了。

沉默中，阿德尔海德又做回了自己。许多已定型的时光回到了本来的状态，钟声单调又激烈地响着，从外界曾淹没它们的噪音中脱离出来。

她惊叹老屋子在她心里所引起的兴奋。熄灭的，是让她成为老屋子女主人的爱，同时也是让屋子无法承载的赤红欲望。她想到科特，想到科特曾为在她看来不值得拼搏的事情而拼搏。她哀伤地看着她高挑沉静的儿子，他那疲倦的思绪和她如出一辙。

阿德尔海德双手叠放在膝盖处，她眼神里的光芒退去，老屋子的光辉也从她脸上消失，她的话语变得如同她的思绪一般平静。

芬看着她，但是却没有看到这些变化。而对于芬而言，这童话故事也已经结束。他低着头坐在古董椅子里，手在膝盖处摊开。

无意识地，两人又恢复到日常的交流方式，没有思想上的交汇，更算不上是观点的碰撞。他们说着几乎同样的事情，不论其中一个人的思绪如何漂游，另外一个总是能找得到。他们的话语总是很郑重，却并没有威胁感。很多次，他们坐在那里，虽然什么都没说，却以为已经跟对方说了一切。

“看，”芬指向窗外，“多可怕！”

一架灵车正穿过广场。

芬一边挪动自己的椅子，一边说：

“灵车应该用步行的速度行驶，庄重地，有仪式感地，就好像他们只是要赶马去饮水一样。战士应该保持身姿笔挺，走路的步伐、节拍都一致，即便他们鞋子该去修鞋匠那儿修了也要保持一致。这样的话，一切就简单了。”

芬安静了一阵。然后他转过头，看着阿德尔海德，“那天我在跟父亲聊天，我正好说了类似的话。”

阿德尔海德惊讶地看着芬。

“我不知道为什么突然讲起了这个。但父亲大笑，说我应该写一篇关于这事儿的文章或者组织一个社团，专门维持正确的灵车速度。”

阿德尔海德微笑，低头看着放在腿上的双手。

“然后，他突然变得严肃，走到我身边，手搭在我肩膀，说：‘灵车应该被开得再快些，用眨眼的工夫将死人带走，让生命成长开花！’”

“父亲是权威。”阿德尔海德说。

芬点点头。

然后他们开始讨论科特。他们总是这样做。他们总是急于寻找漂亮的词汇来赞美他。但内心里，他们都知道，科特比起他俩，显得更粗糙一些。

他们从来不这么讲，但他们都可怜科特，那感觉就好像看着一个明明静静坐着就可以，却偏要不断奔跑的人一样。

但是，当他们一起交谈时，阿德尔海德知道，在芬的灵魂深处，他崇拜也害怕父亲那威严的一面。

虽然这种感情如此弱小，不过只是一个苍白的映象，映出她年少时的爱情，一个遥远的回音，回响着当科特追求她时，她心中为科特辩护的声音。

但这足以让她受伤。她想，她仅仅短暂地拥有过她儿子。她在他给予她的亲密中察觉到一丝不屑。她想，在芬身上，有一些比芬所给予她的更加强大的东西，这些东西来自科特或将要变成如此。

而且，阿德尔海德意识到，争夺芬的斗争将要比重新打开老屋子还要艰难。

一整天，芬都专注于他脑子里的那些事情。现在，他在想象他母亲打破屋子咒语的那一晚。

“我就是不能理解，你怎么忍心。”他说道。

阿德尔海德立刻知道他的意思，但是什么都没有说。

“应该有一些法则，就好像童话故事里的，那个掀起面纱的人就必须死掉，”芬说，“而且，应该有一层又一层的面纱，面纱叠面纱，母亲，你能忍受直视太阳吗？女人应该戴着面纱且从不……从不掀起它，除非是非常重大的场合，大到一切都变得伟大，而且人不应该去看那玩耍的人群。”

阿德尔海德在她的椅子里直起了上半身。

她想告诉芬，在那个晚上，因为她的鲁莽，她遭受了人生最强烈的恐惧。但是她说不出口。一会儿后，她望向广场，极其平静地说道：

“假设有人无法戴上面纱，假设那纱会让人窒息。”

此刻，芬也望向远处，说道：

“纱叠着纱，纱盖着死人。”

阿德尔海德叹了口气，什么都没有说。

“那样，人就可以生活了。”芬说。

第十四章

从那天起，芬只在迫不得已时离开那间屋子。

春天融化了屋子前的喷泉，芬欣喜于那无休无止的潺潺水声。红色的花朵也被放到了阳台上：当风吹过，花瓣会被正好吹到楼下的喷泉里，漂在水面上。他看着花瓣从空中飞舞而下，猜测它们能否到达目的地。

傍晚，当广场上千灯齐亮，这是芬一天中最美好的时光。

他喜欢那即将消逝的白昼。

他知晓每盏熄灭的灯光，熟悉每个停止的声音。而他最中意的便是那刚刚戛然而止的声音和骤然熄灭的灯光。在他心里，披着夜色游荡的人们是另外一类人，好过于那些走在太阳底下的人。他跟这些人都不认识，没有任何关系，但他莫名地更喜欢那些夜行的人。

当夜晚来临，喷泉划破夜空的沉寂，大声地歌唱，远处传来哭喊声，没有人知道这哭声来自哪里，孤独的脚步由远及近，又由近及远，然后芬会点燃壁炉架上的蜡烛，在其中一个老椅子上坐下，在那儿，曾坐着房子的主人和他们的妻子，整栋房子入睡后，他们会坐在那里聊天。

芬环视屋子，屋里的一切都在黑暗的角落里歌唱，他不敢相信自己以前竟然不知道老屋子的存在。

比起任何其他地方，老屋子更让芬觉得无拘无束：在这里，他可以躲开外面令他烦心的世界，因为那个世界需要他展现他所没有的品质。在这里，每一个点、每一件物品都在诉说以往的事情，芬好奇地听着，为老屋子那不可思议的美丽感到欣慰。

有时，芬会陷入梦境，并一直静静地坐着，直到灯都熄灭了。

“他睡眠不够。”阿德尔海德担心地说。

科特心里也在想着一样的问题，他穿过房间，停在了阿德尔海德坐着的地方，说：

“我在想，他有没有醒过，阿德尔海德？”

白天，芬会坐在窗户旁向外望去，无所事事，双手摊放在膝盖上。

当科特穿越广场，他总是认为，他能看到在窗格后面的芬。科特会停下来，冲他点点头。

但芬从未看到过科特。因为他从不积极主动地观察任何事物。

科特进进出出房子，总是期望老屋子强壮的气息能够晕染他儿子的脸色，唤醒他的意志，科特总是相信，这一切迟早都会发生。

自从科特和老仆人把老屋子整理如初后，他便再也没有去过那里。

对此，芬非常开心。他非常担心科特会来这屋子瞧瞧他，以至于每当听到有脚步声靠近，他都需要极力克制自己的恐惧。当芬从恐惧中恢复平静，他意识到，科特来这屋子里是迟早要发生的事情，而那一天将是不愉悦的一天。

其实芬很清楚科特眼中一直都有的充满爱意的疑问，这问题让他担惊受怕。他害怕科特对他的渴望，这种渴望比一个父亲应有的热切得多，更像是一国之主对即将继承王位的继承人的期盼。

而芬那无力的双手根本无法掌控一个国家，也承受不住头顶皇冠的压力，仅仅是有这样的想法都已让他头痛不已。

但阿德尔海德经常来老屋子，他们两人会惬意地坐在那里。

阿德尔海德对芬没有什么期盼。而且，虽然她多疑不安，自芬搬到老屋子后她就总是这样，但当屋子的门在她身后关上，她就会安静下来。

安静得像芬，像硕大的古董椅子和画着在荆棘中扭动的男人的罐子，像那辆曾经好多年夜夜发出欢快的呼呼声、纺线仍旧穿在纺锤上的纺车一般安静。

当阿德尔海德说话时，芬会看着她微笑点头。芬自己也会讲话，长久地，然后突然停止，不过这不会有什么影响，然后他会听那喷泉的汩汩声，老屋子里的声音，这些声音总是在对他讲话，而当阿德尔海德和他在一起时，讲的话最通俗易懂。

芬告诉阿德尔海德，当她来到这里，这屋子就不再是他一人的了。

他觉得自己像个陌生人，来自另外一个年代，他会突然发现自己住在一个充满各种危险和冒险的废墟城堡里，和最后一个享受过城堡里富足生活的人面对面站着。

有一次，在阿德尔海德进入屋子的那一刻，他大声地喊出了她的名字。那时，房间里极暗，他的声音和身形像极了科特，这让阿德尔海德脸色苍白，惊恐不已。但芬没有注意到这一切，阿德尔海德逼自己笑了笑，很快就忘记了这件事。

逐渐地，当他们两个都在老屋子的时候，那奇妙的肃穆消散在背景里，他们在那里度过越来越多的时间，到最后变成，只有在老屋子里时，两人才算陪伴彼此。

他们过去会一起读书，而且是用这种特定的方式读书，他们中的某个人会发现一本书，一个安静又满是歌声的宝藏，这是他们觉得唯一可以与之相比的，然后读完这本书的人再给对方，而对方则会于他们在一起的时候来读这本书。

大部分书都是外语书，书多得好像无穷尽。正是因为用外语书写，书变得更为珍贵，因为异国语言能把他们带到更远的地方去。

当他们读完一本书，他们会沉浸在书中。并不是沉浸在它的情节或它的角色里，而是在它的音乐里。他们把书中的思想和话语转化为音符。

那时，他们好似体验了一些经历，或者好像他们在旅行。

“艺术家会名留青史，”芬说，“他把天空描绘成蓝灰色，为了他自己……为了他自己也为了我们所有人。他用手擦掉所有东西，然后又重新建立，建立更大的，至今为止最大的事物。他是主宰者。他是上帝。”

一天，芬要求阿德尔海德唱首歌。

阿德尔海德许多年都未曾唱过歌了，除非在教堂里，因而当芬提出这个要求时，阿德尔海德很诧异。

“我已放弃唱歌了，芬。”

芬在她面前躺下，看着她的脸朝她微笑，“我清楚地记得你唱歌的时候。当我还是小男孩时你总是唱歌给我听。但是有一次，有一次我记得很清楚，家里有很多客人，我早已上床，但我并没有睡着。因为老玛丽答应我当客人们用晚餐，你要唱歌的时候，会带我到宴会厅里。她告诉我，当有客人时，所有的灯都被点亮，你是最漂亮、最光彩照人的，那时，你会唱得比以往好听一千倍。”

阿德尔海德把视线从芬的脸上移开，躺回椅子里。

“我一直醒着，直到老玛丽来了，我等了好久，但我听到了你歌唱，还从门缝里看到了你。”

“有那么好吗？”

“我不记得了。但我记得有很多张脸。如果再见到他们我应该能认得出来，幸运的是，我记得父亲的脸。”

阿德尔海德站起来。

“我应该唱什么呢？”她问道。

芬满意地笑了，走到钢琴前，打开钢琴，然后他选了一首曲子。

“看我找到了什么，”他说，“这是那个把钢琴放在这里的人所唱的歌曲。瞧，这里是她的名字，她自己写了词和曲。瞧这笔迹可真模糊，但同时又这么明显。”

阿德尔海德站在那里，手里拿着那泛黄的曲单。她哼着小调，敲打着琴键。

然后她坐在钢琴前，边弹边唱了起来：

白天正在消逝，亲爱的少女：
你知道吗，夜晚来临；
警示的风，满载香气，
带来凉气寒灯。
我们必须分开：时间促使这样！
白天正在消逝，黄昏正在到来。
听！你母亲正在喊你：
亲爱的少女，我必须离去。

我们必须分离，亲爱的少女，悲伤漫溢！
白天一定会消逝。
唉，但到明日，
我们错失了数不清的快乐，
少说了数不清的话语。
我们从浪费的机会中抢走时间，
眼睛充满彼此的影子，
数不清的亲吻被我们忘记。

快乐的微笑萦绕着做梦的你，
在纯洁的白色躺椅上；
我脑海中你的身影摇曳，
我将要快快过完夜晚。
让绯红的太阳起程！
你的脸上明亮的阳光，
回忆中故地的阳光，
爱情的阳光在你的心里。

唱完后，她在钢琴前坐了一会儿，手里拿着曲单。芬问道：“那女人曾唱过这歌。你觉得她快乐吗，母亲？”

“她经常伤心，”阿德尔海德说，“每当她伤心时，她就会唱歌。”

阿德尔海德放下曲单，拿起手边的一本乐谱，但又立刻扔在了一边，好像乐谱烫到了她的手指。

乐谱上是丽诺尔系列，她曾经给科特唱过。

阿德尔海德站了起来，坐回到芬旁边。然后她又突然站起来，双臂交叉在胸前，又坐下，大眼睛盯着窗外，“芬，如果我唱歌给你听，你还能辨别出老玛丽带你下楼听我唱歌时的那曲子吗？”

芬回过神来，惊讶地看着阿德尔海德，“那首歌，不，我应该不能。为什么这么问？你记得那首歌吗？”

“不。”阿德尔海德回答道。

他们长久沉默地坐着。黄昏来临，屋子里变暗了。

“母亲，”芬问道，“女人是什么样的？”

阿德尔海德慢慢地扭头看着芬。而芬并没有看着她。他的眼睛看着远处，阿德尔海德意识到，他已经忘记他刚刚问的问题，或者，他根本没有意识到自己问了那样的问题。

第十五章

阿德尔海德裹着披肩站在窗户旁望向外面。马在下面的门廊处跺着脚，车夫站在马车门旁边等候着。

他们准备去车站接芬。

整个夏天，芬都在国外。

这是芬第一次独自离家，他并不喜欢独自在外的日子。从佛罗伦萨，西班牙，到巴黎，他一直都在写信问可不可以回家。但科特决意芬应该在国外待够原定的时间。

芬经常写信给阿德尔海德，语气尴尬无比，因为他知道父亲会首先读到这些信。科特注意到了这一点，但什么都没说。他快速浏览信件，似乎想要找到一些积极向上的东西，但当他放下信件时，脸上总是露出一副失望的表情。

科特会把他收到的信递给阿德尔海德，虽然阿德尔海德从未要求过。

阿德尔海德急躁地看了看自己的手表，然后坐了下来，闭上眼睛，头抵着窗格。

她心里想，整个夏天家里是多么空虚无聊。

关于老屋子，科特没有说过一言半语，但从芬搬到老屋子那一刻起，他俩之间的关系发生了改变。一些不确定的、无法言说的事情发生了，但这些事情也是注定要发生的。

当芬在国外时，这些微妙之处在他们之间不断扩大……而两人也没有做任何事情加以阻止或助长。两人都过着各自的生活，在各自对芬的期盼中渐行渐远。白天对于他们来讲显得尤为漫长，他们的房间非常冰冷。

然而，阿德尔海德内心里对科特的焦虑与日俱增，科特变得更加沉默，眼神中充满忧伤。

门开了，她猛站起来，“我们要迟到了，科特。”

“完全不会，”科特平静地说，“你叫的马车来得太早了。”

“我们走吧，科特。可以去了那里等。”

科特坐下来，帽子放在膝盖上，看着阿德尔海德。阿德尔海德低头站在那里，扣着手套的纽扣。

“坐下等一会儿。”科特说道，推了推旁边的椅子，示意阿德尔海德坐下。

“你想跟我聊天？”

“坐下，阿德尔海德，”科特不耐烦地讲道，“等一会儿。”

阿德尔海德倚着椅子仍旧站着。

“我们很久都没有聊天了，阿德尔海德，很多很多年了。你知道吗？”

阿德尔海德耸了耸肩。

“是的，”她说道，声音坚定无比，“但我们现在能平静相处。”

科特点点头，指头不断地拍打帽子，看向窗外，“是的，是的，毫无疑问。我们老了，阿德尔海德。老得不行了。”

“这就是你想对我说的吗？”

“我担心芬，”科特说，“他回家时跟当初他离开时不会有什么变化，一样地脸色苍白，一个可怜的上帝缔造的幻想家。明天，他又会坐在那里，看着外面的生活而自己却不敢参与其中。”

“是的，他为什么会去老屋子里？”

“是他问的我，”科特平静地说，“我不能拒绝本来就属于他的遗产。他有权力了解他出生的地方。”

“那然后呢？你觉得你能够追回已流逝的时光吗？”

“不，”科特说，“我不那么认为。我也不想那样做。”

科特沉默了一会儿。阿德尔海德没有把眼神从科特身上挪开。然后科特说道：

“如果他喜欢，芬可以给自己盖一座新房子。或者，他可以重新装饰他老祖宗的房子，装上平板玻璃窗和宽大的楼梯，以及任何适合他，还有他的时代的东西。但他得知道，墙壁很坚固，塔楼很高耸，他得为此而感恩。”

阿德尔海德把她靠着的椅子往后推了推，说道：

“在你的安排里，似乎没有给母亲留下任何空间。”

她的声音颤抖不已，怒目圆睁。科特站了起来，像以往一样平静地说道：

“是你离开了，阿德尔海德。你不希望在那里生活。”

阿德尔海德没有回答。她知道，科特并没有要问她意见的意思，也未曾想要她帮忙。

“阿德尔海德，现在，芬快回来了。”

“然后呢？”

“我很担心他，阿德尔海德。我请你自己注意自己的言行，不要给他带来伤害。我觉得有的时候，你扑灭了他原本就可怜的精神气。你所得到的平静，可能这本身是件好事，对你的作用也不错，但他还年轻，你得记住这一点。他才刚刚开始他的人生，他不需要平静或顺从。对你是恩赐的事物对他可能意味着死亡。”

阿德尔海德向科特走了一步，抬起头说道：

“已经到了这样的地步，科特，为了芬，你把我当作敌人。”

“可能确实会这样。”科特说。

“你会把我逼成这样，科特。”

科特抓起阿德尔海德的手，紧紧地抓着不让她抽走。

“不，不，阿德尔海德。我仅仅是想警告你。”

第十六章

阳台门大敞着，他们之前忘记了关门。但天气温和，几乎没有什么风。不时地，会有一片黄叶飘落在栏杆附近。天色渐暗。

阿德尔海德手托着头望向外面。

科特的话一直在她耳边回响。她觉得芬和以前不一样了。他变得焦躁不安，无法静静地坐着，甚至絮絮叨叨。

“不论我去哪里，我都能感觉到外面的喷泉，”芬说，“它每时每刻都跟着我。没什么比喷泉的潺潺水声更响亮了，它让夜晚显得如此静谧，那潺潺水声在我耳边歌唱乡愁，又陪伴我回到了老屋子……我在想，是不是哪一位房子的主人建造了这个喷泉？”

“我不这么想。”

“是的，”芬说，“一定是这样的。我非常确定。可能是房子的建造者。你瞧，它是老屋子的组成部分，它是老屋子的象征。如果这里只剩下喷泉，其他一切也会依旧保持一样。我必须去问问父亲。”

阿德尔海德打了个寒战，芬关上了门。

“我们都不喜寒冷。我们俩都是。我们不像父亲那样。昨晚我去他卧室说晚安的时候我想关上窗户，他却嘲笑了我。‘不要，芬，秋天的空气凛冽健康，让人变得年轻，坐在风口那儿，别担心，你是大人了！’父亲这么说。”芬说。

“是的，你父亲很强壮。”

芬偷偷地看了一眼阿德尔海德。

他立刻明白，在他出国期间，他的父母已经渐渐疏远，而他却是这个结果的承受者。他如同以往那般挚爱他的母亲，但不论他们在讨论什么，他总是会想到科特。

“父亲很伤心。”芬说。

“我没有注意到这一点。”

阿德尔海德说完这句后变了脸色。但芬此刻没有看着她，几乎没有听到她的回答。

“很奇怪，母亲，在外面，在我的旅途中，很多次我有一种感觉：我会遇到父亲。不论我去哪里，我会突然听到他的声音，然后，他会离我很近。我会跟他一起散步，让自己和他步调一致，并同他讲话。”

芬把头靠回椅子里，闭上眼睛，“就好像他去过我在的地方，为我准备好了一切，以至于处处都有他的身影。有时，我甚至觉得为了等他的到来，我必须推迟我起程的时间。”

“那他来了吗？”

“他总会出现。这难道不奇怪吗？”

“是的。”

阿德尔海德想，芬的声音不同于以往了。虽然芬如往常那样讲话时并不看阿德尔海德，但他的思绪并没有跟阿德尔海德在一起。

“你和父亲今天去了哪里？”她问。

“我们去了小树林，走了很长一段距离。父亲不怎么说话，但是不如在家里那般无聊。外面风景可真不错，但又很陌生。几乎什么都看不到了，只能看到叶子不停地落。”

“是的。”阿德尔海德说。

然后，阿德尔海德低头看着芬的脸，比起出国前，芬瘦了许多，也苍白了许多。

“芬，”阿德尔海德说，“当你……当你在外面旅行的时候，我没有和你在一起吗？”

芬笑了，点点头，说：

“你存在于你的信里。父亲从来不写信。但大部分时候，你待在家里，而这是我最想要去的地方。”

芬说这些时并没有握着她的手，这让她感到有些不适。

猛然间，她意识到，她沉浸在芬从她身边离开的恐惧中。

如果芬被超乎他们平静生活的事物吸引，她要对芬说些什么？如果他离她而去，她还剩下什么？

阿德尔海德觉得科特似乎就站在这屋子里，召唤芬去外面的黄树林里转悠，那里空气凛冽清新。芬欢快地跳跃，他们一起离开，头也不回。

阿德尔海德觉得科特比她要强大，这让她对科特心存恨意。她在寻找一件能保护自己的武器。她多么期望那么爱她的芬现在能放松地躺在她面前，就如同他以往那样，脸放在她的手心里。但她知道，此刻芬不会那么做。

阿德尔海德觉得极其委屈、孤独，她变得害怕起来，对赤红幸福的旧日渴望又燃烧起来。要是那快乐能够带走她就好了，这样她就有可能和拥有一切的科特保持对立。

“母亲，给我唱首歌吧。”芬说。

“好。”阿德尔海德回答道。

她穿过屋子，脚步声大于平常。阿德尔海德脸色红润，眼睛散发着光芒。她双手坚定地放在钢琴上。芬注意到了这一点，颇为讶异。但光线太暗，他并没有看到阿德尔海德脸上的表情。

你爱上在那舒适茅舍角落里的农民？
你和他一起生活，食宿共享；
你平静地酿酒，快乐地做饭；
生锈的轮子、生锈的针在你的照料下光可鉴人；
你感恩上帝赐予的阳光雨露。
但不爱任何人的她会悲伤哭泣！

你爱上拥有金制竖琴的诗人？
你倾慕于他在弦丝上弹奏的歌曲；
你在花簇满地的荒原和他相遇；
你的微笑是他来去的指令，
他的思绪沉浸于你的快乐。
但不爱任何人的她会悲伤哭泣！

你爱上在果园里打猎的小公子？
你向你母亲提出请求离开她的监护；
你献给他你的初吻你的爱；
当他高高在上驱使骏马和猎犬的时候，
你将在地上匍匐，承受他抛来的荣耀与食物，
但不爱任何人的她会悲伤哭泣！

阿德尔海德坐在那里没有动，低着头。

这歌曲击碎了她的骄傲。她浑身颤抖，大颗的泪珠滴到手上。她努力振作自己，但她感到前所未有的无力渺小。

阿德尔海德想到了芬，惊慌地看了看周围。但芬看不到她，她默默地流着泪。阿德尔海德头抵着钢琴，然后她的手坠落在了键盘上，她被琴声吓了一跳，从座位上站了起来。

“真是首奇怪的歌。”芬说。

屋子里如此闷，阿德尔海德几乎无法忍受。

“我好多年都没有唱这首歌了，以前，我经常唱它。”

“当你遇见父亲的时候，他是什么样子？”芬问道。

阿德尔海德背朝芬站着，颤抖的手不断翻阅着乐谱。

“他像现在这样帅气吗？”

“是的，不，我不知道他帅不帅。”

芬静静听着。

“他……他很有魅力。”

“他的确是那样，的确是，”芬像孩子听到好故事那样开心地拍着手，“他也很有主人派头，不是吗？所以所有人都注定要追随他？”

“是的。”阿德尔海德说。

“父亲是一个国王。”

阿德尔海德的心脏抽搐着，她全神贯注地听着。她感到芬站在离自己很近的地方，并且做了一件足以毁灭她的事情。她无法转身，无法靠近他，恳求他停下来。

“我希望我有个弟弟。”芬说。

“你觉得孤单吗？”

“不，不是那样。如果有个弟弟，那他应该继承这个王国。”

第十七章

那时，芬交了一个朋友，然而，这朋友不是他自己选择的，而是处在焦虑中的科特给他安排的，因为在科特看来，芬自己交不到更好的朋友了。

他的名字叫汉斯，他和芬从小就认识。汉斯比芬大一岁，没有芬高，但更强壮，金黄色的头发，明亮的眼睛，性格也非常活泼。

汉斯的父亲是个小个子男人，在账房里做最普通的工作。他和他的妻子生活中没什么运气可言，除了他们的儿子。但有时，他们也为汉斯的未来担心，因为汉斯的想法很明显而且很广泛。

虽然汉斯已经长得比他父亲高，但他对自己的各个方面都很不满意。

首先，他不想坐在办公室里，而是想去外面的世界闯闯。从他还是小男孩的时候起，他就确信，外面的世界要比别人口中的大很多。

现在汉斯已长大成人，对自己的需求和能力非常了解，但却哪里都不能去，于是他勇敢地找到房子的主人，跟科特说了说事情的情况。

科特很喜欢汉斯，希望留他在家里做事，但科特很快发现，没什么工作能引起汉斯的兴趣。科特问汉斯，他将来想成为什么样的人。汉斯说他想成为一名工程师。

科特看着他，心里不禁感叹，汉斯的眼神足以炸裂岩石。

科特答应会帮助汉斯，但当汉斯唱着歌儿走下楼梯时，科特却仍旧陷在自己的沉思里。

时间流逝。汉斯一直坚持自己的梦想，他和其他所有人都明白，汉斯正有条不紊地为梦想奋斗。科特一直都在注意汉斯，当汉斯再次拜访时，科特显得很高兴。但阿德尔海德不喜欢汉斯，因为汉斯说话聒噪，走起路来脚步沉重。

一天晚上，科特站在汉斯的屋子里，用一种前所未有的方式跟汉斯聊天，“我是你父亲的老板，我父亲是你祖父的老板。我儿子则永远不会成为你的老板。因为你决意要走自己的路，成为你自己的老板。即便没有人帮助你，你也会那么做。没错。但你可能会变得愤世嫉俗，在使用你的才华力量时变得疑心重重，心胸狭窄。我把你从这一切中解救出来，给你帮助。现在，我希望你能回报我。”

汉斯握住科特向他伸出的手，不舒服地站着，没有理解科特的意思。科特疲惫地坐下来，很久没有说话。

最终，科特从他的沉思中回过神来，看着眼前这个无法洞晓他的年轻人，科特被那眼神感动，“我并不希望你是我的儿子，我有一个儿子，他是个好孩子，我很爱他。他没有你的意志力，但他也不需要。他的未来平坦无比。他可以给你很多你没有的东西。”

科特听着自己说的话，这些话不断变成对芬的道歉，祈祷芬的原谅。科特痛苦不已，而汉斯，看到了他的难过，以为这大房子里发生了可怕的事情。

“你能试着成为芬的朋友吗？”

汉斯非常愿意。

科特看着汉斯，估量着他的力量。科特环视了汉斯那狭小的、屋顶很低的房间，除了汉斯工作需要的工具就别无他物。他望向窗外，蓝天下一片脏兮兮的灰色屋顶交织交错，成百上千的烟囱里炊烟袅袅，院子和街道上的噪音填满了这间屋子，窗户的玻璃已碎，用纸糊着。

然后，他看着坐在这样嘈杂环境中强壮的汉斯。科特知道，站在这里的他，绝不是扮演汉斯的慈善家或是他父亲的老板的角色，对汉斯打开自家富有的门。站在这里的科特，仅仅是一位恳求者。

“你知道你们小的时候曾一起玩耍。”

当科特说完这句，他竟激动起来，因为他想起，芬从来没有玩过什么。汉斯也想着同样的事情，但在这种情况下却不知道该说什么。此刻，沉默对于两人而言变得沉重而煎熬。

为了打破沉默，汉斯问道，芬是不是生病了。

科特立刻明白，汉斯一定很久没有注意到这位脸色苍白、生性沉默的房子的继承人了。

科特站了起来，厌烦了谨慎地回答。他搭着汉斯的肩膀，看着汉斯，那眼神让汉斯一辈子都不会忘记，“请你作为大卫(1)，带着你的竖琴来我们身边，当你自己愿意的时候，或者当我们请你的时候。”

————————————————————

(1) 《圣经》中，大卫被神称为“合我心意的人”。

第十八章

为了迎接汉斯，芬做的第一件事就是重新整理他之前的房间，这样，汉斯来看芬的时候就有地方待了。

这样的安排没什么不正常的。因为理所当然，老屋子不能让陌生人踏入。但科特立刻觉得他寄托在汉斯身上的希望破碎了。

有时，芬对汉斯的到来感到很开心。

但他们无法在一起聊天。

虽然身在芬的房间里，但汉斯却一直在想着他工作的计划和所遇到的困难，其中最简单的对于芬来说都是无法被逾越克服的，而且，芬对他朋友脑袋里的想法一无所知。他跟所有人讲话的方式都一样，他说的话不是问题，就是答案或者他的意见。

因而，大多数情况下是汉斯讲话，而且当他讲话时会完全沉浸在自己的世界中，根本没有注意到芬开始白日做梦了。

当芬让汉斯做他自己的计算或是其他事情时，他会愉快地坐在一旁，看着汉斯与那些数字和绘图缠斗。

汉斯皱起的额头，还有那急切的、不耐烦的动作，都让芬觉得好笑。他好像坐在赛马场，或是人们参加竞技的地方，充满期待地等候着这位工程师在解决问题的那一刻将铅笔一扔并发出的兴奋的吼声。

芬的脸上洋溢着欢乐，就如同是他自己赢得了胜利那般喜悦，而他并不知道那是哪种胜利，也不知道这胜利意味着什么。

但有时，越来越频繁地，芬感到对他而言汉斯过于活跃急躁。

于是，有那么几日，当汉斯拜访芬时，芬会躲起来，而仅仅是汉斯的露面都会引起芬身体上的疼痛。汉斯那强大的眼神，那洪亮欢快的声音，还有他充满意义的话语，都让芬觉得晕眩。

芬坐在那里，满是痛苦和委屈，因为他无法让汉斯离开。而汉斯也很少会注意到这一点。当他注意到芬的情绪时，汉斯总是会陷入无限的自责和郁闷中；而芬必得说服汉斯，不是他想的那般。

然后，芬就屈服了，就像一个无助的病人屈服于一项新的治疗方法一样，然而随着这方法而来的必然有新的折磨。当他在备感折磨的时候，他不停地想起他的父亲，父亲承受的痛苦更多，而他却帮不了父亲。

芬最喜欢的时间是他们一起出去的时候。

他们驾车或者骑马。然而，两人却从未达成过一致，芬想要慢慢地骑马，快快地驾车，而汉斯则恰恰相反。他们总是渴望顺从对方，但每次都会依着芬的喜好。

芬虽然不喜欢外出，可一旦他真的去了，便会开心起来。而且他总是希望汉斯可以和他一起。芬在人群面前总是很羞涩，有他的朋友在场，会让他安心许多。

他们总是会在大街上走，因为如果出城，芬会觉得太冷。他会搂着汉斯的胳膊，跟随汉斯的步伐，心里默默地为他骄傲。芬喜欢在嘈杂的街道上听汉斯洪亮的声音，还有那有力的脚步声，以及他的拐杖点在路面上发出的声音。

芬有的时候会开口讲话。

大部分是关于他的旅行。他总是能把他的想法准确地表达出来，像他对他母亲讲话那样。似乎这样的生活，还有几乎淹没掉他声音的嘈杂声让他感到更自由安全。

虽然汉斯并不关心芬旅行中的所见所闻，但芬的语言带着色彩和微光，让他迷恋不已。

但当街上的噪音戛然而止，芬会立刻沉默并显得非常害怕。而且，若两人在人群中彼此分开一小会儿，且汉斯没有听到芬所讲的话，要求芬再重复一遍，或者他仅听到了只言片语，要求芬进一步解释或予以确认，芬会突然变得疲惫，心情立刻就变了。

芬会被街头生活吸引而停下脚步。他会指给朋友看，并以此作为聊天的话题。汉斯会接着芬的话讲，说一些挑逗的观察给芬听，这让芬觉得很有意思，但不久芬就觉得很懊恼，因为汉斯的话破坏了芬所看到的景色。

他们从来不讨论女人。

芬会沉默，因为他的想法模糊而保守。而汉斯的生活也不值得总被提及。而且，他们本能地知道，在这一话题上他们的共同点少之又少，且都不希望过分介入彼此的生活。

只有一次，芬去了汉斯的家里。

那是那间小屋里的一次常规宴请，芬很高兴去参加。

他欣然地看着两位矮小的老人，他们不论站着还是坐着都双手相叠微微鞠躬，不知如何向这房子的小主人表达敬意和感激。他们认定芬一定生气了，因为汉斯坏了规矩，选择了自己的未来，他们替汉斯百般解释。

然而他们的解释中无不透露着对自己小心呵护着的儿子的骄傲，好似如果不紧紧捧着他，他会掉下来摔得粉碎一样。

芬非常理解他们，被他们感动了。他把汉斯夸得不得了，预言汉斯将有大作为，当看到汉斯双亲眼中的欢乐时，芬自己也开心极了。

芬与汉斯的父母进行深入的交谈，听着他们表达自己对汉斯的爱，这情景让汉斯彻底困惑，而芬看着满脸迷茫的汉斯觉得十分可笑。

当芬停止讲话时，然后整个屋子都陷入沉默，情形尴尬。

后来，芬和汉斯站在房间里望向窗外。

芬的眼睛游荡在成百上千的屋顶之间，太阳照在石板上，还有那红色的瓦片上和发亮的电话线。每一面上，小小的阁楼窗户都自成一格，有的挂着印花棉布窗帘，种着天香竹和天竺葵，还有黄色的小鸟在白色的笼子里跳动。

有一个地方挂着一个有精美绘画的长着蕨类植物的木盒子，植物已经变成了铁棕色，但依旧骄傲挺直地站着，中间的地方还有一棵冷杉。在另一个地方，窗帘直接飘出窗外，挥舞飘荡如同一面旗帜。有两只麻雀在水槽里跳来跳去。还有一只关在笼子里的鸟在尖声而甜蜜地唱歌。

“这一切是多么美好！”芬说道。

汉斯并没有这么觉得。

但，在那个时候，芬注意到了靠旁边的一个窗户，这窗户离他那么近，好似他一伸手就可以够到。

窗户是打开的。房间里有鲜花，还有一只鸟在笼子里，安静而不停地从一处跳到另一处。在这些鲜花后面坐着一位缝纫的姑娘。芬可以看到她的后背，和一点儿她的脸蛋，还能听到缝纫机的声音。

“看。”芬压低声音说。

汉斯走了过来，立刻朝那个方向看去。

“那是玛丽，”他说，“她是个裁缝。”

其实，不论是这对话的内容，还是汉斯说话的语气都没什么不对劲的地方。但汉斯说得如此大声且毫无顾忌，以致伤到了芬。女孩此刻也闻声抬头看着他们，笑了笑。

于是，充满鲜花、小鸟以及温暖的屋顶的整个画面都被阴影遮住。芬叹了口气，从窗户旁走开了。

晚饭时，汉斯一家人和芬坐在一起，吃完饭，他们从芬身上感到一种不可抑制的忧伤。

芬看着他们每一个人的脸，知道他们都在为了他而克制各自的快乐。他想，如果他不在场，这一家子会忙碌而开心地沉浸在工作和对彼此的信任中。

在他们友好的话语和善良的微笑后，芬不禁开始为他这位安静的客人感到可怜。但他觉得他们更加为科特感到惋惜，而他自己则应当受到责备。

然后，芬匆匆地辞别了汉斯一家。

第十九章

当汉斯和芬在树林里驾车时，一条小狗钻到了车轮底下，伤得很严重。

他们两人都立刻从车上跳了下来。汉斯跪在地上，将大口喘气的小狗抱在怀里。

“给我你的手帕。”汉斯说道。

但汉斯没有收到手帕，他烦躁地抬头看芬。

芬无动于衷。

他俯身看着小狗发光的眼睛，眼神奇怪而专注。芬并没有在想受伤的是动物还是人，也没有想小狗能不能被救或者他自己要做些什么。

“芬！”

芬依旧没有反应。他看着死神那张伟大的脸。黑房子的门被狠狠地甩开，芬看向黑暗深处。他的灵魂满是虔诚的敬畏。他没有感觉，看不到任何事物，但生命正在他眼前消逝。

汉斯无语地盯着芬，被芬脸上的表情吓到了，他不知道如何理解这表情，变得越来越不安。

“把你的手帕给我，芬。”

芬抬头，把自己的手帕递给了汉斯，说：“我没想到要这么做。”

汉斯没有回答，不久，小狗死了，汉斯将小狗狠狠地扔到树丛里，这让芬几乎要打他。

他们回到车上，沉默地继续前行。芬满脑子都是他所看到的一切，对汉斯的不安没有丝毫察觉。突然，芬让车夫停下。

“你一定不要介意，汉斯。”芬说道。

“我打算在这里下车，我能自己走回家，我想独自待会儿。”汉斯跳下车，连再见都没有说就离开了。芬并没有介意。他让车夫关上门，自己缩到一个角落里，然后回家了。

阿德尔海德去老屋子里看芬，却无法让芬说出自己脑中的想法。她朝他笑笑，握着他的手，开始为他唱歌。

但芬沉默地坐着，心不在焉。

一些日子后的一个晚上，芬和汉斯穿过街道沿着运河散步。河上，小船排成一排，河岸另一边，是一座古老的城堡，城堡的玻璃都已破碎，但绿色的屋顶却散发着魅力。

“让我们在这里坐一会儿。”芬说。

他们坐在码头上。河流在他们的脚下愤怒地暗涌。河上的船只撞到一起又漂开来。汉斯用自己的拐杖敲着堤坝。

“威尼斯像这样吗？”他问道。

“不，”芬说，“那里要更美好。因为那里更陌生。”

汉斯开心地笑了，芬什么都没说，低头看着河流。

然后他们听到一声喊叫。

他们立刻站起来，向发出叫喊声的地方跑去，当他们走近一点儿，在河里看到一个溺水的小孩。

“这里，芬，帮我。”

汉斯跳进一艘船，笨拙地摆弄船桨。但芬径直跑向那孩子的方向，想都没想立刻跳进河里。

芬不会游泳，汉斯不得不先救他。然后，极度艰难地，汉斯又救起了小孩。当他们回到科特那里，大家先是被吓了一跳，然后发现芬没什么大碍，于是大家都坐在客厅里，开始讨论起这件事。

阿德尔海德双手握着芬的手，时不时拍拍它，或者用力压一下。科特情绪高涨地在客厅走来走去。

“你怎么会想到要跳下去？”汉斯问，“你知道你不会游泳。”

“我都没有想这么多。”芬安静地回答。

科特站在芬面前，对他点点头。阿德尔海德眼睛闪烁着泪珠，亲吻芬的额头。

汉斯看着他们一家人，气红了脸。

他想到，芬可能会淹死，或者那小孩可能会淹死，或者他们两人都可能淹死。然后他又想起在小树林的场景，当小狗死去的时候。他无法理解这些人的想法。汉斯没有看这一家里的任何一人，他努力让自己的声音趋于平静，说道：

“你没有权利做出那样的行为。那是非常愚蠢的。”

“是的。”芬说。

但此刻科特把手放在汉斯的肩膀上，看着汉斯，那眼神让汉斯突然想到他那怯懦的父亲。

“是的。”科特说，“芬竟然不会游泳，真是太愚蠢了。”

然后，科特的儿子被决定应该去学习游泳。

第二十章

阿德尔海德坐在那里，手里捧着书，但并没有阅读。

天色已晚。芬一直和她待在一起，直到他道了晚安然后去休息。科特不在家中。房子里外都一般寂静。

她有一种感觉，好似这世界上只有她一个人。

阿德尔海德并不快乐。

那段长久单调的日子所带给她的内心的平静已从这房子里消失。她无法看清自己未来的路：和芬在一起的时候不行，她自己一个人的时候也不行，更不用提当科特在这屋子里的时候。

甚至在教堂里，她都无法感到安稳。有时，她离开教堂时的心情比她进入教堂时还要沉重；有时，她根本不敢踏入教堂，当听到教堂走廊里风琴的召唤时，她却转身离开。

她长久地坐着，目视前方，白皙的手叠放在膝盖上。她想试试看她能否把这事情想清楚。她之前也曾这样努力过，但从未成功。

首先，是回到老屋子。

这是所有事情的开端，她禁不住想，老屋子是所有事情的源头，因为，事实上，她内心里从未真正地战胜它。与之关联的回忆汹涌地袭来，她根本无力抵挡，这让她血液沸腾，双眼模糊，而她却不知为了什么。

她承受着绵长的恐惧，而这恐惧她既无法解释从何而来，亦无法驱散。有时是芬，芬那苍白的脸让她害怕。有时是科特，科特变得越来越沉默，总是在酝酿他那些想法。

她陷入一阵令人绝望的懊悔中，而她却不知道自己如何犯下了罪过。然后她内心充满对复仇的恐惧，而她知道没有人想要伤害她。她感到她住在一幢墙体充满密格的房子中，而一旦密格之中的文件曝光，将毁灭现存的所有一切。她感到好似走在神秘的地窖上，那地窖掩盖着诡异的罪过的痕迹。

阿德尔海德疲倦地用手托着头，又把手放下。她在椅子里直了直上半身，将脸靠近摆在她身前桌子上的玫瑰。然后她拿起书，不久又再次把书放在一边。

然后，科特来了。

科特朝阿德尔海德点了点头，算是打个招呼，然后走到房间里较远的那一边，拿了本书坐了下来。

阿德尔海德怯懦地看着科特。她听到科特在翻书，于是想知道他读的是什么书。阿德尔海德开口问科特，科特头也不抬地回答了她，沉默加倍地充斥着房间。

阿德尔海德叹了口气，站起来准备去睡觉，“晚安，科特。”

科特合上书，随手扔到桌子上。阿德尔海德停下脚步，看着他。然后他问道：

“今天汉斯来了吗？”

阿德尔海德又坐回到椅子里。此刻，科特已站了起来，在屋子里踱步。阿德尔海德一边等待一边听着科特的脚步声，直到她无法忍受，“科特！”

科特停了下来，看着她。

“科特，芬会死的，如果汉斯一直和他在一起。”

“是的，”科特说道，声音轻轻地，充满悲伤，“芬会死掉，你会死掉，我也将死掉，但汉斯会活着。”

“你想拿芬怎么办，科特？”

“难道你已经忘记我想要什么了吗？”

科特看着她，那眼神伤到了她。

“不知你的愿望是不是同我的一样，科特。”她问道。

“不。”

科特冷静地回答道，口气里没有怒气，但毫不犹豫。

听到这样的回答，阿德尔海德从椅子里跳了起来，“你的愿望从来都跟我不同。从不！你成功地说服我，威吓我，强迫我。但我从来都不想那样，科特，从不！即便是我同意的时候。”

“阿德尔海德，不要再谈陈年旧事了。”

“现在呢，科特？现在我离你越来越远，而你越来越不能理解我。在我身上，有一种力量比那时将我们分开的东西强大一千倍。”

科特看着阿德尔海德，眼中闪过一阵愤怒，“阿德尔海德，我身上也有。”

科特站在她面前，她感到科特比平常似乎要高一些，而他的脸看着出奇地年轻。

“芬来了。”科特说道。

阿德尔海德无法站立，于是坐回到椅子里。

“你说话的方式就好像他只是你的儿子，不是我的。”阿德尔海德说道。

阿德尔海德盯着科特的脸。她无法摆脱科特看上去如此年轻的想法。他的头发没有一点儿变白的迹象，他走路轻盈挺拔，眼睛充满力量和自信，和以往无二。

阿德尔海德身体前倾，盯着科特的脸，寻找蛛丝马迹。她当然应该能找到悲伤留给他的伤口，岁月带给他的痕迹。

科特没有看她。他双手交叉搂着脖子站在那里，眼神迷离，“阿德尔海德，你说对了，就像你说的那样，现在我们身上有种力量比当初分开我们的强大千倍。我们凡人总是认为，当不幸来临，后面就会是好运，不幸一定会终结。而且，失去爱人的男人和失去洋娃娃的孩子没有什么不同。除了时间，来来去去，熄灭了一盏灯，点燃了一堆柴，然后又熄灭了柴。”

科特放下胳膊，无声地站了会儿，“阿德尔海德。”

他没再说什么。他环视了屋子，又看了看她，就好像他刚从他的思考中醒过来一样。然后他走向窗户，望向广场，那里的灯已经全部熄灭了。

阿德尔海德大睁着双眼盯着科特站立的地方。

很多年了，她都忽略了他的存在，这些年她都去了哪里？她都在做些什么？

她现在又注意到了他，起初遥远而模糊，当她又一次站在老屋子的时候，就好像一次吵架、一种伤痛的回忆那般。然后，他靠近了一些，就是在那次他警告她芬不能像她那样活着。再然后，一点儿一点儿，通过芬，通过他的恐惧和他的爱，通过他每句话，他接近了她，越来越近，影响也越来越大。

她把椅子的扶手握得那么用力以至于她的关节都泛白了。

现在，那神秘的地窖之门的铰链嘎吱作响，罪过显现。现在墙体里秘密的暗格都被打开，老旧的文件都公布于众。

现在，她和他之间的一切都消失了，而他们之外的一切也都不存在了。他站在她身旁，她伸伸手就能触摸到他。她失去了儿子也失去了上帝。他的话像暴风雨般扫过她的心灵，他的眼睛注视着她。

她想要站起来逃走，但却无法动弹。她感到一阵晕眩，脚下的大地似乎在后退。

她听到许多说话的声音，向她诉说一个很久以前早已被人忘记的故事，一个记录在家族档案里用于娱乐和对后人进行指导的传说，而后人大约会对这传说加以不同于原作者的评论。

还有其他话语，嘲笑和兴奋的声音，都在向她耳语，这一切都是幻想。芬是属于她的，而不是他，他所有的自信、力量都会在遇到那深爱着母亲、苍白而安静的男孩时变得粉碎。

话语中还有圣歌、赞美诗、风琴声和令人难忘的对罪恶、宽恕和基督的荣耀的话语。教堂地窖的凉风吹过她滚烫的额头。所有的钟一起敲响，就好像是为了一个灵魂之需。

她听到了这一切，而这一切就像空中任意的声音一样消失了。

所有的话语在她混乱的思绪前混成一团，演绎成旧时光里的一个夜晚，一个充满灯光和欢乐的夜晚。她看到那时的人们，她听到她自己的声音。

然后，突然地，所有的声音都被老屋子里的寂静镇压。

蜡烛在壁炉架上燃烧。她坐在那里，盯着红色的壁炉。科特在说话……那是以前的科特，“我会用生命和快乐作为赢得你的心的赌注。我会和你说话，强求你，征服你。我会拥抱你，拒绝你，然后追求你，宽恕你。如果我没有赢得你，我将抛弃你。”

她站起来，双手拍着她的脑袋说道：

“科特，科特。”

科特转过头，看着她苍白的脸。

阿德尔海德抬起头看着科特，在科特的眼睛里寻找自己的影子，或者仅仅是过去时光的一丝念想儿，一点儿记忆。

但她找不到。对于科特，这世界上除了他的快乐、他的恐惧、他的挣扎之外就再无其他，以往如此，现在亦如此。只是，这一切都不再围绕着她。

“阿德尔海德，你生病了吗？”

“没有，没有。”

阿德尔海德大声笑起来。科特握着她的手，把她领到一把椅子前。阿德尔海德任科特摆布，眼睛却一直看着科特的脸。

然后，她突然猛推开科特。

她微笑着，对自己的愚蠢摇摇头，然后在屋子里走了一圈。她说她很好，让科特离开，快点儿离开。

然后科特走了。

她看着科特离开时关上的门，好似那是她最后一次看到科特。然后她转身，看着镜子，镜子里呈现出她整个人。

慢慢地，她走向镜子，坐了下来，手托着头，眼睛盯着镜子里自己的脸。

教堂尖塔里的钟敲了一下，两下，她都没有听到。然后有人在广场上尖叫。她站了起来，拿了一支蜡烛，离开了屋子。

她穿过长长的走廊，走上楼梯，小心翼翼地，好像她是小偷一样。她站在科特和芬的卧室门前，听里面的动静。然后她站在老屋子门外。她凝神听着，没有任何声音。她微微打开老屋子的门，里面一片漆黑。

她迅速走进去，径直走到墙上的暗格处，打开暗格，双手颤抖地拿出那泛黄的文件。

然后她盯着科特和自己的名字，写在文件最后面，又被划掉的名字。

第二十一章

芬站在科特房间里的窗户边上，头倚着窗户框，看着楼下的院子，看门人的孩子们正在那里玩耍。

芬是按照惯例前来向科特道早安的，科特让芬等一会儿，等他写完手头的那封信。此刻，科特早已封上信封，但芬没有注意到。他在观看楼下孩子们玩游戏，为了看得更清楚，他还往前探了探头。

不久，孩子们被喊进屋子了。于是，他头倚着窗框望着灰色的天空。他想起汉斯，那天早晨汉斯去了巴黎，并且将要在那里待两年。

科特静静地坐着。他看着芬的侧脸，芬的额头是那么白皙，芬的眼睑如此沉重地抬着，芬的嘴巴疲惫而软弱。

“芬！”

芬惊了一下，转过身来。

“你去送汉斯了吗？”

“去了。”

芬坐在他刚刚站过的窗户旁的位置，低着头，双手摊在膝盖上。他把百叶窗的绳子卷到自己手指头上，然后又解开。

“你会想汉斯吗？”

“哦，会的。”

“我会想念汉斯的，”科特说，“汉斯属于新秩序中最棒的那些人，是现代诗歌的英雄……工程师，你知道的，没有人能够原汁原味地将他展现在舞台上，因为他从来不会表演单一的一个角色。他很强大，有勇气去挥洒他的力量。对于我们来说，他似乎缺乏教养，而他也无法认同我们。他没有祖先，因为他就是祖先，他建立了他自己的朝代。”

“是的。”芬附和道。

然后他们沉默地坐了一阵子。

科特心中没有任何疑虑。他知道他想要的是什么，然后索要他想要的。他不会说温和的话，而是富有力量的话。芬对此很清楚。他坐在那里就像个囚犯，等待着他的判决，每一分钟对他来讲都是煎熬。

然后，他们抬起头，看着彼此的眼睛。

两人相互估量对方的力量。芬的绝望如此强大，就像科特无法放弃的希望那样强大，这希望是科特唯一所能依赖的。

“你知道你是天生的艺术家吗，芬？”

芬伤心地笑笑，摇摇头。

“你是的，”科特说，“关于这一点儿毫无疑问。当你在国外旅行时，你的信中充满你对所见美景的喜悦。你的旅程是一段穿越高贵画廊的漫长的过程。在海边，在街道上，在山里，在每一处你都捕捉到生活，把它挂在你的墙上，然后你会坐下来慢慢欣赏。”

“是吗？”

“要不是你出生在富有的家庭中，你会不可救赎。你可能成为个画家，不，一个作家。”

“成为画家或作家有那么糟糕吗？”

“文学对于我们现代人来讲有什么用？”科特说道，“文学能带领我们去哪里？文学如何影响我们的生活？如果那些老诗人活到今天，他们早就变成商人，或电工，或北极的领航员。看看你身边，芬，我们读的书，看的画，上演的戏剧，难道不是都像街头的交响乐队，在人们散步的时候表演一个小时？那都是些疲惫的人们，在上床睡觉前想听一点儿音乐。乐队演奏完小曲儿，得到钱和掌声，而我们乐于看到这表演恰如其分地完成。但是，诗人，芬，是那响彻山冈的孤独号角。我们会扔下手中的犁，静静地听，抬头看，因为那些文字对于我们来说如此稀有而又如此强大，我们从未听到过这些音符却又对它们如此熟悉。然后我们眼中闪过光芒。然后，那些压弯我们脊梁的伤痛，那些让我们挺拔的欢乐，还有我们的希望，瞬间都拥有了颜色和光芒。我们渐渐衰老，号角召唤我们，在山的那头，去那新的绿地，那里有更好的生活。”

“父亲。”

芬抬起头，但却不知如何表达自己的想法。

“难道你不认为诗人首先应该是一个……一个跟他人一样的男人，胸中充满勇气，腰上挎着利剑？他用诗歌欢送人们去战场或去婚礼，去跳舞或者战死疆场。他是世俗的一部分，首先出现在群体中。”

“诗人也会坐在女士的闺房里唱歌。”芬说。

科特点点头说：

“是的，但我们如今的诗人却只会坐在女士的闺房里唱歌了。只要有闲逛的女人，还有经历过两场战争，两个国王，有两个丈夫的女人在；只要星星游离在天空，孩子们抓不住灌木丛中的飞鸟，就会有许多光阴的游荡者存在。但是，不必在意这些，芬。不必在意。你就看看今天坐在交响乐团中的那些人，你会坐在他们中间吗？他们都是些病态的人，吟唱他们各自的病魔。有人犯了相思病，有人淫秽，还有人嗜酒。有人吟诵他那写在羊皮纸上的信仰，有人出售有关他疑虑的六便士的书。他们那懦弱的意志在愚蠢的诗句中颤抖，还有人借用旧时代的血腥恐怖来陶醉他那苍白的想象。你觉得一个自由意志的人会选择把自己放在这些艺术家中吗？”

芬抬起头，用他那安静的眼睛望着科特，“父亲，谁是有自由意志的人？你吗？”

科特将手放在芬的肩膀上，并看着他，“你是啊，芬，你是有自由意志的人，如果你愿意的话。”

“父亲。”芬伸出手，好似小孩子向大人索要东西那般。但科特无情地看着芬。科特的眼神充满力量和光芒，芬试图躲开那灼人的眼神，却无法做到。他试图说些什么，但却保持着沉默。

然后，科特在屋子里走来走去，步伐稳重有力，他一会儿说话，一会儿沉默，但从不肯让芬从他那严厉的掌控中逃离一步。

科特用话语抓住芬，把芬托到一个一切都很伟大、美丽但有点儿冷酷的地方，再把他摔回到他自己那个黑暗的角落里。然后重新又抓住他，把他带到高处。

然而，当科特停下来时，对于芬来讲，就好像听到号角齐鸣，宣告其他话语紧接着要来了，更加宏大、严肃，充满爱意但却承受不起。

“你是对的，芬，我不是一个有自由意志的人，我从来都不是。我被筑成我的房子、养育我家族的传统束缚，当我无法再支撑这些传统，我的世界就会崩塌，但依旧无法让我自由。那是很沉重的时光，芬。我无法理解这些，你看，我一直战斗到了最后。那时我很年轻，身强力壮，而且我在恋爱中。你喜欢那间老屋子，你能听到那些传奇人物在那屋子里动人忧伤地歌唱。记住，芬，我也是那些人中的一员。我也曾经平静而骄傲地站在那里，在那儿，没有人能看得到我，除了房子的建造者和他的妻子，总是遥远又封闭地躲藏在老屋子古老的威力中。对房子建造者毫无保留地打开心扉，我像一个被打倒的人。但我无法躲入角落独自神伤，因为我还有你，芬。那时你还是一个小孩子，我不知道你未来的路是怎样的。我只知道一件事情，就是你永远都不会和你的妻子坐在那里，坐在那硕大的、立刻让人显得渺小的椅子上，那里一切总是很舒适很安心。我是最后一个坐在那里的人。老屋子的传统在我这里终结。后来我不得不试着在这个我无法理解的世界中找到我自己的路。我不得不经历一切我极其讨厌、并让我的快乐消失殆尽的事物。对我自己而言，已无所求，我是一个被束缚的、受过伤的人。但我还有你，芬，我得知道在一切虚无的跳舞、调情、唱歌背后，他们是不是在诚实、正确地筑建这个世界。或者这世界于我眼前的没什么两样，那我是不是不应该尽全力将我的孩子带到这险山恶水中，让野兽把他撕成碎片，这一切考量中我都独自一人。你母亲搬去这房子旁边的老房子住了，因为在这里，她无法快乐。在那里，她找到了平静。但我不需要避难所。不论我在哪里，我都是在家里：我只是想看到你，还有你的孩子能够幸福安康生活成长的地方……我不遗余力地寻找，南部北部，东边西边。我读了他们的书……那些轻松的书在我手中像肥皂泡一样破裂，而那些富有力量的书我理解起来很费劲。没有什么他们的绿色远景是我没有在自己的房间里看到过的，也没有什么亮剑没在我眼前闪过光。我没有被自己的苦楚蒙蔽双眼，被流行话欺骗，也没有害怕那些谩骂声。只要我还能看到路，我就顺着我的路一直往前走，芬。我凝视着最远处，在那里我所看到的只有恐惧和疯狂。芬，我不知道，可能是你母亲的上帝救了我。也可能是我那个自己开船驶入港湾然后在新大地上盖起房子的祖先。或许是在那些充满焦虑孤独的日子里，你来向我道早安和晚安时，你完全信任地放在我手掌中的那双小手。我说不清楚。我敢肯定，是我对你的爱让我得到了升华。我爬到了凡人所能爬到的山峰高度。一切在我脚下都像一片云，憧憬、幸福、生计和苦恼。我看不到我的房子所在的山谷。但在白云之外，越过山峰，我看到我们一代又一代忙碌努力的地方，一天一天朝着目标前进，虽然这目标我们看不到，但它就在那里，因为路就在那里。我还看到土地，从我站的山峰之处，看到你还有你的子孙后代的乐土。那是一片我所不知道的土地，一片我看着陌生的土地，那里的人们有不一样的习惯和信仰，有不同形式的爱情和荣耀。我在那场将老屋子的门猛地推开的暴风雨中看到这一切，芬，那是很神奇的时刻，是我一生中最强大、最快乐的时刻。”

科特站在窗边，双臂交叉在胸前。他看着他的儿子，遗憾地笑笑。芬静静地坐在椅子里，仰着头，闭着眼。

“然后，我就让你为你的旅行做好准备，芬，我无法给你指路，因为我是被束缚的人，我无法和你同行。我带给你书籍和指引者，他们帮你打开世界之门。我让你知晓你想骑行穿越的迷雾。我已没有任何顾虑，因为我无所求，我已看过那片雾霭。你长大了，你健康聪明。之后我便慢慢地等待，渴望当我从自家阳台向你挥手，看你去征服世界的那一天尽快到来。我就是在等待着那一天。啊，我看到过那些穷鬼，饥饿难耐，伤痕累累，盲目地冲向新世界，因为那世界不可能比旧世界更加糟糕。我听到他们号召建立新的法律，因为他们违反了旧的。他们被赶出他们的茅屋，带着他们的包裹，还有对新世界的一丝希望，坐上了移民的船舶。但你，你没有做错什么，也没复仇的理由。你有国王的儿子一样的自由身，你和你的随从骑过桥梁，横穿世界，把你的横标插在任何你想要的地方。你生于你母亲对兴奋的渴望，生在你父亲堡垒一般的房子里，有老屋子里的劲风充满你的肺，而没有它对你的束缚。一个高贵无瑕的君子，追逐他的自由意志，在革命的潮流中占有一席之地。”

科特安静下来，他的脚步声则显得更加沉重。

“芬，你在听我讲话吗？”

“是的，父亲。”

“过来。”

芬站起来。科特搂着芬的肩膀，同他一起在屋里踱步。

“我曾有好多的梦想，芬。我收获了很多自信，我的快乐已经支离破碎，但我还有你。我虽是个老人，但我的思想却不迟钝。我经历过海难，但我不惧怕大海。我相信生命，相信上帝。”

科特和芬无法步调一致地肩并肩走路，于是科特挪开了他搭在芬肩头的胳膊。芬又坐回到他的椅子里，听着他父亲继续说道：

“然后就到了你知道的这些时光，现在的日子，你长成为一个安静的人。你沉重地看着生活，胆小的你害怕世界上的硝烟火海。你的衣服总是一尘不染，但这很容易做到，因为你从来不打架。你从不会在别人不希望你出现的地方出现。你从不踏出家门，芬，从不。你的血液中没有热血，你的思想中没有欲望。你总是很累，芬，仅仅是累。我渐渐为你担心起来，随着时间流逝，你对我来说已不仅仅只是儿子，不仅仅是我的血肉，你是人类链条上的一节，穿越年华，一直向前。你的生命比我的更加宝贵。因为你得挑起新的负担进入新的时代。记住，芬，我曾去过山顶，看过森林。这不再只是传承的问题，不再只是家族骄傲和家族忠诚的问题。你和我在这场战斗中结盟。我拿着眼前的地图，紧随战斗的脚步，像年迈的士兵，自己无法再征战疆场，但他还有他的儿子，他的族群，他的帝王，记住我是如何到达我所在的地方的。记住我失去了什么，我放弃了什么，我是如何全心全意为你付出的。我拥有你，芬，除了你，我还有什么？那时，我开始为你担忧，我倾尽所有培养你。我告诉你老屋子的故事，希望它会让你穿上戎装。我告诉你你父亲和母亲的命运，是为了让你明白人们如何努力去获得幸福。我把你送到外面的世界，让你开眼界，看看更加伟大、强壮的生命力，是为了让你成为一个男人。但我从不……从不给你套上任何限制。我从不利用我作为抚养者的角色要挟你。而你，你翻着画册，带着比以往更加苍白的脸色回到家里。老屋子只是一首漂亮的诗，它让你陷入更沉的梦里。而在外面的世界，身强力壮的男人遇到他们的妻子。当太阳西下时，他们真诚而开心地交谈。而你，整天坐在那里，一个人，双手倦怠无力。”

讲到这里，科特重重地拍了下芬的肩膀。芬抬起头看着科特，双眼模糊，嘴巴一直在颤抖。

“今天，芬，我把一切交给你来继承。从今天起，我把你当作成年人对待。别人无法强迫你。而且，也没有人愿意那样做。也没有人能对你生气。你没有情绪，始终都那个样子。今天，这一切都将成为过去。出去给自己买座房子，娶个老婆，跟她生一群孩子。记住，我们家族里虽然有人失败，但没有胆小怯懦之徒。”

“父亲，我理解你所说的，但我做不到你想让我做的。”

“你们这些胆小鬼总是理解一切，因为你们根本没有任何信仰。你们以为你们都那么亲切聪明。说你们宽容，那是因为你们根本不做决定，你们知道，真理无处可寻又处处都在。你们替一切愚蠢的想法辩护，你们永远都在盘算肚子里那点儿东西却从不行动，然后你们放走了杀人犯，让小偷逃之夭夭。上帝啊，帮帮这些可怜虫！那些最愚蠢、最无知的恶魔都比你们这些人更聪明、更和蔼！”

芬想说话，但科特做了个手势，不让他说话，“一个男人，不应能够理解一切。他必须选择、判断、拒绝。如果他不这么做，那世界上就不存在幸福，也就没有和平和忠诚。如果他无法恨，那么他也就无法爱。”

科特走到窗户前，向外望去。此刻，芬走到他身边，抓住他的手，哀求地望着他，“我做不到你想让我做的那样。”

科特抽回自己的手，站得离芬远了些，“你没有权利对我说那样的话，芬。我不听。因为我想要的，只不过是让你去生活。拿着我给你的财产，随你的意愿使用它。有一天，你会为你的儿子负责，现在，是我对你负责的时候。”

芬满脸悲伤地笑笑，说道：

“我永远都不会有儿子。”

科特没有听到芬说的话。他陷入了回忆的挣扎中。科特用手抹了一把脸，目视前方。他看到阿德尔海德，那一晚在老屋子里，说了跟芬刚才说的一模一样的话，绝望无力。“我做不到你想要的。”

科特坐下来，躺回到自己的椅子里。

过去的绝望再次向他袭来，他陷入巨大的疲惫中。他无法抵御那一句“我做不到你想要的”。

然后，他从椅子上跳了起来，双眼冒火地看着芬，“如果是你的母亲摧毁了你的意志，那你立刻离开她，恨她，抛弃她。”

“父亲，父亲！”

“恨她，她沉迷于她年轻时的毒害。跟你一样，她理解一切。对于她来说，没有渺小伟大，没有远近之分。她的意志已经消失，就跟你一样。她知道荣耀在哪里，但她够不到。她汲取这个时代的精髓，她也成了这个时代的人。她总是病怏怏的，病得快死了。”

他穿过屋子，没再说什么。

科特和芬两人脸色苍白，都渴望独处。他们彼此都不想再说什么。

芬并不是为了他母亲而感到生气。他脑子里只有一件事情，那就是他做不到科特希望他做的，而且他也无法平息科特心中的悲伤，也无法告诉科特，他有多么爱他。他渴望静静地坐着，在老屋子里，和他母亲一起。

“你生我的气吗，父亲？”

科特长久地看着芬，然后说：

“是的。”

当芬离开后，科特把脸埋在手中，默默地哭泣。

第二十二章

科特打扮成要出门的样子，急匆匆地穿过客厅。

阿德尔海德坐在那里写信。当科特走进来时，她抬头看了一眼，然后又继续写信。

“芬在哪里？”

“楼上吧，在他自己房间里。”阿德尔海德回答，眼睛并没有看科特。

科特站在窗户旁待了一会儿，然后他坐到椅子上，又站起来，走到阿德尔海德写信的书桌旁说：

“你今天跟他在一起吗？”

“没有。”

她合起笔记本，转了转她的椅子，她的脸隐藏在阴影下。

然后她说道：

“芬太孤独了。”

“是的。”

科特点点头，又说了声“是的”；然后低着头，站在那里，陷入沉思。

“这里太安静了。”阿德尔海德说，“你不开心，芬注意到了这点。汉斯也离开了。”

“是的，是的。”

阿德尔海德双臂交叉，沉默地坐在那里，眼睛看着脚尖。

“阿德尔海德，”科特站直了身体，“我们会让这房子充满欢笑，”他说，“我们，你，我，还有芬，明天去拜访一下我们的新老朋友。我们邀请有活力的年轻人来家里做客，邀请漂亮的女人和聪明的男人，让屋子充满灯光和音乐。”

阿德尔海德抬头看着他。他笑笑，然后把手放在她的肩头。

“好的。”阿德尔海德回答。

关于这样的安排，科特又继续讲了一阵，然后就急匆匆地出去了。

阿德尔海德长久地坐在那里，客厅里渐渐暗了下来。大门前的灯亮了起来，灯影在天花板上摇曳。壁炉里的火苗在堆积的灰烬下闷闷地燃烧。阿德尔海德所坐的位置没有被灯光照到，她身上的白色裙子反射着微微的光亮。

她想到科特的微笑。他那样跟她说话，就好像是他在要求办公室的某个人做一件为难的事一样。她想到芬，芬看着她时那奇怪的眼神就好像他们之间的母子关系改变了，而且他无法理解。

她想到她自己。她感到自己像秋天里树叶凋零的树，一棵一直认为自己常青美丽的树，直到现在，她却看到了自己的青春在风中摇摆。

日复一日，每时每刻，她都在重建老屋子的旧日辉煌。

她重建老屋子的神坛，用七道封印封住门。她把时间调回到以前，想象她抱着她的孩子坐在那里，嫉妒老玛丽给他脱衣服，唱歌哄他入睡。她又想象未来，开心地描画着芬带着他的妻子踏入老屋子，并将两人的名字写在黄色文件上的那一天。

阿德尔海德苦涩地笑笑。

她想到，她好像那个把天球仪放在老屋子的那个人，那个神志不清坐在那里一直摆弄那些星星到死的人。

但当黑夜降临时，她的想法总是殊途同归。

她想，如果现在让这房子充满欢乐，还有用吗？还是会在宴会结束后，潜伏在房子每个阴郁角落的黑暗都会迸发出来，逼得他们三个人以各自的方式隐藏起来，焦虑而孤独？

她不知道。但她经常会想到这些。然而，不论是在她的希望里、她的恐惧中还是在她的遗憾里，都没有任何激情存在。

阿德尔海德现在非常平静。

第二十三章

广场上那幢富丽堂皇的房子里再次灯火通明，喜气洋洋。

一时间门庭若市，仆人在铺着地毯的楼梯上跑上跑下。巨大的会客室成了灯和花的海洋，音乐此起彼伏，人们翩翩起舞。

那光鲜亮丽甚至超过往日，因为房子的主人变得比以往更加奢华。他的身影遍布整个房子，他亲自负责料理一切，他穿梭于客人之间，热情地招待他们。

科特房子里举行的宴会成了传说。一切富有美丽高贵聪明的人们都受到科特的邀请并前去赴约，他们甚至抱着感激感谢的态度。

男人们聚集在房子女主人的身旁，陶醉于她的白色礼服和她的银发。

那些在她年轻时对她崇敬万分，如今已是满头白发的人们目不转睛地望着她那依旧高挑的身形，眼睛重现火光。而那些年轻的人，当被老人告知她曾经比现在美丽一千倍时，竟无力勾画那样的画面。

被她眼睛看到的每一个男人都变成了她的追随者，她的眼神也被永久地刻在那些男人的脑海中。

现在，她的笑容拒人千里之外。

她的眼神更加深邃，但又好像什么都看不到一样。她红色的嘴唇不再像以前那样充满欢乐。而人们依旧觉得，如果能赢得她，那是莫大的幸福。但没人觉得那是能够做到的事情。

他们猜想着这些年发生在这房子里的一切，为何它关闭了这么久，又为何突然敞开大门，夜夜笙箫。

他们的猜测并没有任何恶意。

他们邀请她唱歌。当她坐在钢琴前，用她那大而奇特的眼睛环视整个屋子，她的老朋友回忆起她年轻时热情洋溢的歌声，让他们热血沸腾，让他们在欲望和爱慕中潸然泪下。

当她的歌声响起，年轻的人侧耳倾听，忘我地沉醉在她的嗓音里，那声音明亮清澈，宁静悠远：

那是如今地球上最狂野的激流，
（上帝给予我他那令人心安的恩惠）
花朵布满深邃沉默的灰色峡谷，
但却只有它们才能诉说，
是谁搅动起这波涛汹涌。

从未有船漂流至此，
从未有花开放在此，
从未有鸟儿从这里飞走，
从未有星光从天堂
照耀至它的黑暗中心。
它从眼睛涌出，带着痛苦
（上帝保护我免于一切灾难！）
当一个男人把自己的幸福，
像破布一样撕成两半，
从不曾是他自己命运的主宰。

一曲之后，屋子里短暂沉默，然后，人们蜂拥至钢琴旁，向她表达钦佩赞赏，邀请她再来一首。

阿德尔海德起立，她微笑着感谢她的客人，但她的眼神则越过眼前对她而言毫无意义的人群，看着屋子另一端站着跟别人讲话的科特，显然，科特没有注视她也没有听她唱歌。

但芬听过她的歌声，看到过她优雅、低微、痛苦的样子。

芬的眼睛一刻不离地紧随着阿德尔海德，奇怪的想法在他脑袋里涌现。他现在明白，这房子里究竟发生了什么。他知道阿德尔海德为什么最近很少去老屋子里找他。为什么她会沉默地坐着，陷入深深的沉思，为什么她的眼神闪烁怯懦，说话犹豫不决，双手毫无力气。

他感到，他与人类连接的最后一根线也断掉了。

芬失去了他的母亲，因为他追得太紧。现在，阿德尔海德来到芬的身边，实际上是为了找科特。若是现在芬主动去找阿德尔海德，像以往那样躺在她身边，把脸放在她手中，阿德尔海德会把芬扶起来，撵他去外面的世界过生活。

他有一种被背叛的感觉，但同时，他在心中和阿德尔海德一同哭泣。他看着他的父亲，觉得科特比阿德尔海德想象的男人得多。他看着他的母亲，产生了一种奇怪的既爱又轻视的感觉，就好像男人对向他们索要一文不值的东西的女人的感觉。

然后，芬不得不走进冲他微笑的人群。

他内心的孤独感如此强烈，以至于毫无困难地就跟客人们混在一起，显得无比愉快，开朗健谈。

他很开心在这些屋子里走来走去，如同他在别的地方那样，因为这里已经不再是他的家。他甚至还跟一些穿着时髦的先生女士说几句俏皮话，因为他不得不说话，因为他无法告诉任何人他内心的想法，因为没有人能对他说他想听的话。

女人们聚集在他的身旁，如同男人们聚集在阿德尔海德身旁那样。一圈圈白色的胳膊和热切明亮的眼睛围着这房子的继承人，他如此白皙，如此帅气。女人们对他说迷人的漂亮话，对他微笑，但他会毫不犹豫、毫无可惜地冲破围绕在他身边的人群。

男人们向他献上友谊，芬和他们握手、讲话，但转眼就忘记了他们的样子。科特总是能从他躲清闲的地方把他找出来，然后继续带着他回到人群中。芬朝他父亲微笑，跟在他身后，但依旧孤独。

芬看到且只能看到他自己。他抓住每一个在他脑海中涌现的想法，对其进行讨论，就如同这个想法是由别人想出来的一样。他品读每一种在他灵魂中出现的心情，好像这心情是他在书里读到的。

他爬到人们无法居住的高山之巅，人们要么将其踩在脚下，要么死在白色的冰霜里，因为那里没有声音、空气，没有白天，没有路。只有灯，永远只有灯。

但是，当科特的眼神落在他身上，不知道为什么，他所感到的孤独立刻烟消云散。

然后，他便知道他是谁，他在哪里，生活的痛苦正在侵蚀他的灵魂。因为他经常在他父亲的眼睛中看到那个永恒的、无望的、天真的问题。他意识到他早已忘记的事实——这房子之所以重新开门迎客，全部都是为了他。每一声奏响的音乐，每一朵开放的玫瑰，每一位漂亮的女人：他们都是他父亲的仆人，都在向他一遍遍传递着信息，人生的盛宴随时都能举行，只要他在餐桌旁落座，喝光他金色酒杯里的美酒。

然后芬想到他那内心平和、容貌美丽的母亲，她已从自己身边离去，投入到现实的生活中，而他对这样的生活却无动于衷。芬想，要是他们能静静地坐在一起聊会儿天该多好，听着广场上的喷泉发出汩汩的声音，还有老屋子里的物件发出的低声细语。

哦，那样不仅对他有好处，对阿德尔海德也有好处，芬心里想，甚至对科特都会有好处。

芬的想法最终化为对科特的爱，他看到科特在自己无望的斗争中拼死挣扎。他感到他的父亲像是战争中的英雄，他渴望自己是父亲身边卑微的仆人，能够为他征战疆场，为他抚平伤口，为他坚守睡榻，吹奏长笛。

然而，宴会如往常一样进行，当最后一辆马车驶出房子大门时，已是深夜。

大门关闭时发出沉重刺耳的声音，好像在怒气冲冲地驱逐客人。大门的链条嘎吱嘎吱地响着，好像它再也不会打开，决意要把外面的世界永远地关在那老房子外面。而房子里愈来愈多的阴霾聚集，那是无论多少灯光或多少欢乐的号角都驱逐不走的。

然后，他们三人在一起坐了一会儿，这三个老房子的常居者，坐在一起说着空洞的话，睁着无神的眼睛。

阿德尔海德第一个停了下来，因为她的想法是最强烈的。芬说得最多，好似在弥补之前的过错。

但科特是最痛苦的。冷漠的言语在这亲密的三人中传递，他们害怕沉默，但彼此之间又无话可说。

然后，科特和芬相继道了晚安。阿德尔海德让仆人退下，自己一个人待在客厅，伴随着燃尽的蜡烛。

她不安地在房间里走来走去，回忆逝去再也无法返回的时光。她欣然地沉浸在自己的幻想里，因为现在的她只有一个希望，一个信仰，一次忏悔。

她幻想着宾朋满座的愉快夜晚结束时，科特和她眼神交融，而只有他们俩才能懂得那眼神的意义。

然后她走进婴儿房看看她那睡得小脸红扑扑的儿子。之后，她会拿一枝最红艳的花朵，爬上那段隐秘的楼梯，走向光辉满堂的老屋子。

科特已经在那里坐着，等待着她。

她进门的时候看到科特，科特向她点点头，然后又回到自己的沉思中。她在窗户旁安静地站了一会儿，那里红色的鲜花在她双脚前绽放，楼下广场上一片漆黑，只有喷泉的汩汩声有规则地响着，没有开始亦不会有结束。

然后她穿过屋子，听到科特在对她讲话，永远都是那一些，对跳舞的偏见，对伟大婚姻的赞美，还有充满激情、富有爱意的祷告。让那些无所事事的人继续跳舞，她坐在科特示意的那把古董椅子里，就在他旁边，这是一个庄严的位置，坐在上面的人显得渺小但坚强，因为他们的脚踩在一个由信仰搭建保护的神坛上。

壁炉里火苗跳跃，蜡烛在角落里发着微光，科特站在壁炉旁说话。她会在窗户那里站一会儿，屋子里一片寂静，她看着科特，这是她生命里的男人，一直都是。然后，她会走向科特，缓慢地，轻轻地，因为她尊重她脚下的大地。然后她跪在科特坐着的地方，用那双迷人的、科特曾经爱过的眼睛望着他。

然后她会告诉他，她对他的爱是怎样的，是怎样强烈又怎样沉静，“科特，你这个坚强不可战胜的男人，我爱你，而你应该这样被爱。我感谢你，因为你陪我聊天从不感到厌烦。因为你总是恳求我。因为你等待我，且相信老屋子里的沉默终有一天会变成愉快的歌声，其他的一切声音会像树林里遥远的嗡嗡声那般。如今，我在这里，科特，你这个坚强不可战胜的男人。现在我是属于你的，如同以前一样，在老屋子里，我是你的。老屋子里那些过去留下来的物件没什么可让人郁闷或害怕的。我能对着老钢琴唱歌，这样就不会有琴键突然断裂，不会有回忆被惊扰，因为我只唱有关你、有关我们的孩子和我的快乐的歌曲。我能珍爱曾祖母留下来的老纺车，因为我已在自己的房间里编织我的幸福。我能爱意满满地把蜡制娃娃藏到窗帘后面，因为我爱这老屋子，能够长久而满足地待在里面。但那个画着在荆棘中扭动的裸体男人的罐子，我在还不成熟的时候把它放在那里。它将纪念阿德尔海德的灵魂所经历的那段黑暗时光，那段欲望被广场上的声音吸引的时光。我们的儿子，睡觉的时候小脸红扑扑的，有一天他将有男人魁梧的身材，在你和我去世之后，也将来到这里，和他的妻子一起坐在我们曾经坐过的地方。他会知道，他的母亲曾受到欲望的引诱，但并没有被摧毁。”

阿德尔海德坐在角落里，在空无一人的房间里想象这一切。

她白色的礼服在地板上铺开。她的眼睛闪着光芒。

而在楼上，芬站在老屋子的阳台上，盯着远处的夜晚，夜如同漆黑无浪的海一样在他周围延伸。

好静。他没有思考，没有幻想。他的灵魂和黑暗交融，既不邪恶也不美好……只是悄无声息。

他像一个被放在高楼边缘巡逻的死人一样，静静地站在那里，目无神采。喷泉咕咚咕咚，就好像水从池盆的边缘升起，一直到那死人站立的地方，为了把他冲走。

此刻，广场上有一个行人在走路。

那人边走边唱，直到看到阳台上的芬，耸立在黑暗中一动不动。那人停了下来，看着芬，喊了几句。

阳台上的芬朝着那人喊了一声。那人害怕极了，跑了起来，迅速消失在黑暗中。

第二十四章

科特看着阿德尔海德所在的房间问道：

“芬在哪里？”

“我想他应该在老屋子里。”

科特关上房间门，迅速下了楼梯。阿德尔海德坐在窗户旁，看着下面的广场，科特站在那里，抬头望着这房子。然后，他走远了，从他走路的方式阿德尔海德就知道，科特并没有什么事情要去办。

仆人点燃房间里的蜡烛。阿德尔海德坐在壁炉旁，手放在膝盖上，听着静得出奇的房子里发出的每一个声响。

不久，科特返回家里。

阿德尔海德听到他在走廊上说话的声音。

然后他走进自己的房间，又走了出来。她知道，科特要去找芬。但一扭头，科特走进她所在的房间，和她隔着一段距离坐下来，“你今天去见他了吗，阿德尔海德？”

“没有。”

科特在他的椅子上不安地动来动去，站起来又坐下。阿德尔海德挣扎着要不要走到科特面前，握住他的手跟他讲讲话。此刻，科特说道：

“芬最近很奇怪。比平常开朗，但心不在焉。虽然他没有假装什么，但他也不是他自己。”

科特接着讲芬的事情，没有看阿德尔海德一眼，他讲这些不是为了讲给阿德尔海德听，而是他没有办法保持沉默。阿德尔海德看清楚了这一切，转过脸，悄悄地哭了起来。此刻，科特问道：

“你注意到这一点了吗？”

“我觉得他跟平常一样。”

科特站起来，穿过房间。他在壁炉旁站了一会儿，盯着壁炉里的火苗。阿德尔海德抬头看着科特，眼含泪水。然后科特又走回到他原先坐的地方，说道：

“我在想，阿德尔海德，你是不是该上去看看他？”

科特听不到阿德尔海德的回答，于是朝她看了一眼。此刻，阿德尔海德站了起来，正在朝他走来。科特看得出阿德尔海德脸色十分苍白，知道她在哭泣，但并没有太在意。

阿德尔海德在科特身边坐下来，她离科特那么近，她的礼服遮住了科特的脚。她双手合十放在腿上，然后又把手分开，低着头说道：

“科特。”

当她喊他的名字时，阿德尔海德开始颤抖，不得不双手握紧。

“嗯？”

“你应该上楼看看他，科特。”

科特沉默了一会儿，然后低声说道，就好像房间里还有其他人，而他不希望其他人听到他要讲的话，“我不敢。我已经让他害怕了。他会站在我房间门外，等到鼓足勇气才进屋和我道早安。我打算远离他一阵子，可能去旅行，直到他内心平静下来。”

阿德尔海德看着科特，想象着他在外面四处晃悠，为了能让芬恢复宁静。她想象着科特在遥远的城镇漫步，一个人，内心无法平静，牵挂着他的儿子。既渴望早日回家和他团聚，又害怕看到他不好的样子。

阿德尔海德坐在科特面前的地板上，把脸放在他手掌里，眼泪顺着脸颊慢慢流下。

科特没有看到阿德尔海德的眼泪。他目视前方，眼神紧张又充满痛苦，“他不喜欢我们的聚会，阿德尔海德，我们这么做，对他有害无益。”

“是的。”

“但，如果你上楼去找他，阿德尔海德，悄悄地，陪他坐一会儿，让他说说他的想法。你们两个总是相处得很好，你知道的，每当你去找他，他总是很开心。”

“现在他见到我已经不再开心了，科特。”

科特惊奇地看向阿德尔海德，看到了她泪光闪闪的眼睛。

“如果我现在上去，科特，我无法像以前那样陪他坐着。因为我跟以前不一样了。”

“唉，好吧！”

科特说得平静冷漠，好似原本他就对这个解救芬的办法也没有抱太大的希望，必须再去找其他的方法。

“科特！”

阿德尔海德尖叫道。

科特吓了一跳。然后，就好像他刚刚看到阿德尔海德跪在他面前一样，他往后推了推椅子，站了起来。

科特穿过房间又走了回来，站在阿德尔海德身旁看着她，眼神中的嫌恶每一分钟都增加一分。阿德尔海德爬到科特刚才所坐的椅子那里，把头放在椅子上。她闭上眼睛，静静地抽泣。

“你？”科特缓慢地说道。

阿德尔海德像被这个词打击到一样，无法呼吸，她睁开眼又立刻闭上，脸色苍白，一动不动地躺在了科特的脚下。

科特眼里充满怒气和嘲笑，“自从我们相识，都这么多年了，阿德尔海德，这是多么痛苦难熬的岁月啊！”

“没错。”阿德尔海德抬起头，然后又靠在椅子上。

“你离开，追寻你充满激情的幸福。你不满足于你爱着的且深爱你的丈夫，你必须让所有的男人都拜倒在你的脚下，你必须看到他们眼中的欲望之火燃烧，看到他们那不洁的手抽搐，因为他们不敢触碰科特的妻子。”

“是的。”阿德尔海德说道。

“那么，你找到让你心甘情愿的情人了吗？当他看穿你那双迷人的眼睛，他是不是一脚把你踢开了？或者，你选择离开他，去寻找你那更有激情的爱人？”

“我没有情人。”阿德尔海德低声说道。

科特将额头的头发甩到脑后，握紧了拳头说：

“是的，你没有。那是你的耻辱和你的审判。”

“科特，科特，假如我有……”

“是，如果你有情人，且他现在就在这里，那我应该握着你的手，把你带到我们儿子的面前，告诉他，‘这是你的母亲，她一直都不幸福。她爱过你的父亲，但当她遇到这个对她意义更大的男人的时候，她对你父亲的爱就死去了。这么多年她都没有过一天开心，因为她的命太硬。现在她又回来了，渴望你的喜爱并且需要它。’”

科特穿过房间又走回来，“站起来，阿德尔海德。”

阿德尔海德从地板上站起来，坐在她的椅子里，她洁白的双手交叉放在腿上，沉默无语。科特看着她，好似阿德尔海德谦卑的遵从更加激怒了他，“当你结束你的婚姻时你去哪儿了？是老屋子的空气对你来说太纯洁太强大了吗？自那以后你都去哪儿了？”

“我去上帝那里了。”

科特大声笑道：

“给我看看你的上帝。”

科特俯下身去看着阿德尔海德的脸，说道：

“我不相信你的上帝。”

阿德尔海德看着科特的眼睛，伸出她哆嗦的双手，她红色的嘴唇颤抖着说道：

“那么，我也不相信他，科特。”

科特转过身。阿德尔海德静静地低下头，她的眼泪滴在她的手上，她聆听着科特暴风雨般的话语，且渴望更多。

科特坐在窗户旁，看着窗外的倾盆大雨，路灯的光辉在风雨中闪烁。此刻，科特的怒气已经消逝。他已经不记得他们刚才一直在谈论什么。他脑子里一直在想芬，其他的什么也没想。

突然，他站了起来，双手按着太阳穴，看着阿德尔海德，眼中充满恐惧地说道：

“阿德尔海德，你觉得芬今天晚上会不会不下来跟我们道晚安？”

阿德尔海德知道，一切都已经晚了，无可挽回地晚了。阿德尔海德无法告诉科特她灵魂深处的煎熬。科特永远都不会知道，她无法回到他身边是因为她太疲惫，因为她害怕，但她诚恳地改正她生命中堕落的时光，如今又以科特会喜欢的样子站在科特面前。

“他会来跟我们道晚安的。”阿德尔海德平静地说。

阿德尔海德双手合十放在嘴边。

她可以等，如果能让她在科特的家里找到一个她可以停留的地方，即便要求她赤脚穿过石子地也无妨，她想，那里总会有一条路通向科特。

夜色深了。

阿德尔海德坐在科特身旁，握住科特的手，科特没有反对，这让阿德尔海德开心不已。她想把科特的头发从他那满是皱纹的额头上拨开，想把手放在科特那疲惫的眼睛上，但却不敢。

他们讨论着芬的事情，阿德尔海德像个孩子那样温柔地对科特讲话，愿意顺着科特。阿德尔海德的话语变得那么温柔，让人印象深刻，她脸上又有了笑容。阿德尔海德扭头看看科特，看到科特的脸上闪现的笑容，就像从乌云深处透出来的一束阳光，转眼就消失了。

科特几乎没有听到阿德尔海德在讲什么，但她说话的声音让科特安静下来。阿德尔海德柔柔的嗓音，窗外的细雨声，让科特感到温暖平静。

那每时每刻都驱使笼罩着他的每一滴想法的恐惧，在这安静的一小时里，变得麻木。他坐在那里，像个经历太多痛苦的老人一样，好似他的身体机能都麻木了。

科特看着阿德尔海德，像年轻时郁郁寡欢的他看着母亲一样。在他眼里，他母亲好似一个小女孩，对他的父亲知之甚少，且对他没有任何亏欠，但母亲会亲自把玫瑰花送到父亲手上，这样家里的气氛就变得令人愉快一些。

科特又一次在椅子里很不自在地挪了挪身体，神情异常地看着阿德尔海德说：

“阿德尔海德，为什么我除了他再没有其他的孩子？”

科特平静地说道，顿了一会儿，又重复了一次，而这次，他不是说给阿德尔海德听，而是他自己。阿德尔海德啜泣起来，因为她知道科特没有在看她。

夜色笼罩大地。

他们安静地坐着。然后阿德尔海德说：

“科特，让我们一起上去找他吧！”

“我们两个？”

阿德尔海德焦躁地等待科特会不会继续说些什么，会不会突然反应过来她是谁，然后狠狠地将她推开。

但科特并没有这样做，他沉默地坐在椅子上，眼睛盯着壁炉里的红色火焰。

然后阿德尔海德站起来，向科特伸出手，“走吧，走吧，让我们赶紧走。我们跟他一起聊会儿天，平静地，愉快地，直到那些阴影消失。然后我们就下楼来，那些阴影会再次笼罩他。但我们每天都去陪他一会儿，和那些阴影斗争，直到他好起来。”

科特沉重地站起来，握住了她的手。

阿德尔海德像带着孩子一样带着科特在房子里穿行。他们穿过长长的走廊，走上那段隐秘的台阶，阿德尔海德在科特前面一点儿。她的眼睛充满了欢乐。她灵魂深处的钟声响起，她紧紧地握着科特的手，再也不愿松开。

两人来到老屋子门前，敲了敲门，静静地听屋内的动静。阿德尔海德看着科特，又俯身吻了科特的手，她双眼满含泪水。

然后，阿德尔海德轻快地推开门，拉着科特昂首挺胸地走进屋里。

窗户旁坐着科特的儿子，在其中一把大椅子上。他用枪结束了自己的生命。

PREFACE　TO THE FIRST (ANONYMOUS) DANISH EDITION

I who write this book am still young and fair to look upon and rich and very sad.

My youth and my beauty fill me with horror and I know not what to do with the wealth which I possess. Daily my sorrow sings the same song in my ears. It rustles in the folds of my train; it sighs in the fragrant flowers at my breast. Through the long nights I sit on the edge of my bed thrusting away the dream that comes with glaring eyes.

Now what I have written is a lie.

When I wrote it, it was the truth: now, it is a lie. When I saw it set down on paper, I knew that my youth was my strength and my right; that, if I were ugly, I could not live; and that, if I were poor, I should die.

And now I am glad; and there is nothing on earth but my gladness.

I am in this case.

But I let the words stand as I wrote them, for I know that the time will come—and that soon—when all of them will be true again…until they once more become a lie.

And so my book will grow, through still and stormy times, until the day comes when I am again what I now am.

But that, too, is itself a lie. For I was always the same.

But there came a moment at which HE saw me as I am; and there my book will end. For after that there was but little that differed from the stories in other books and less still that I remember.

Be that as it may, it is true that the world contains a room in which the radiant light of happiness famed up before my eyes. And the light went out and the door closed upon me.

And, if any one, from what I have here written, comes to think me a great and abject sinner, then he is indeed right. But, if he thinks that I have been cast off by the world, then he is at fault.

For I go with head erect and peacefully along the road that others go; and I am welcome among the best. The lights in the high hall stream down upon my hair; the men honour me with their desire, the women with their ill-will.

Their lives only one who knows my guilt and he has condemned me.

For it was HE that stayed in the room where the light burns. And she that went out into the street was I.

Chapter 1

The room looks out upon the square, which is so big and so fashionable that there is no business done in it.

By day there is a sound of carriages, but at a distance; for the house that contains the room is thrust a long way back and its walls are as thick as the walls of a castle. In the evening, the square shines with a thousand lights; at night, you can hear the rippling of the fountain, which never begins and never stops, cries, no one knowing what they are, and solitary steps that approach and retreat again.

The room is built high over the square. Its window is a door and leads to a balcony flled with red fowers. When the wind lashes them, their petals fly right over into the basin of the fountain and rock upon the water.

The room is long and deep.

Where the window is, the light streams in through the wide, stained-glass panes; but, inside, where the fire-place rises to the ceiling, it is always dark.

No one has ever seen the curtain drawn before the window. But, even if the sun could shine right into the room, it would never have seen a human being there. By day, the room is dead.

It is placed so strangely in the house that it seems to form no part of it. The life of every day passes outside it; and, even when the whole house is lighted up and the horses paw the ground in thegateway and glasses clink and music sounds in the great drawing-room, the door of the room remains constantly closed.

No one has ever crossed its threshold but the master of the house and his wife and the oldest servant in their employ.

For the room is the soul of the house and its tradition and its secret chamber.

It was destined for this purpose long ago by the man who built the house; and so cunningly did he contrive it that no one could guess that it was there, unless he knew of it. Then, when the work was ended, he sealed the architect's tongue with a solemn oath and a heavy fee and the man kept his sworn word.

And the builder of the house decorated the room as richly as was possible according to the means of those days, with gilt and fgured leather hangings and stained-glass window-panes and costly carpets from the East. But he placed no furniture in it until the very last. Then he brought two splendid armchairs which he had had made for him in Milan.

They were odd-looking chairs. They glided so smoothly over the foor that a child could move them, and were so large that people became quite small when they sat in them. Their wood-work was carved into birds and animals, whose faces grinned strangely in the dark but ceased to do so when the lights were lit.

When everything was thus ordered for the best, he called an old servant, who had been in the house since he was a child, gave him a key of the room and told him to care for it faithfully. Every evening, when it grew dusk, he was to light the candles on the mantelpiece and he was to do this even if he knew that his master was travelling in distant lands. Every morning, he was to adjust the room with hisown hands. None but himself was ever to cross the threshold.

On the evening of the day when he took possession of his house, the master, having first shown her all its other beauties, brought his wife to the room.

She looked round in wonder. But he made her sit in one of the great chairs, seated himself in the other and spoke to her in these words:

“Sweetheart, this room is for you and me and for none other in the world. I have placed it in the most secluded part of the house, far from the counting-house, where we work, from the passages, along which our servants go, and from the drawing-room, where we receive our guests, ay, even from our marriage-bed, where you will sleep by my side.”

She took his hand and kissed it and looked at him.

“It shall be the temple of our marriage, hallowed by our love, which is greater than anything that we know. Here we will pray to Him who gave us to each other. Here we will talk gladly and earnestly every evening when our hearts impel us to. And, when we come to die, our son shall bring his wife here and they shall do as we did.”

Thereupon he wrote down in a document how all this had happened and they both sealed it with their names. He hid the document in a secret recess in the wall. And, when all this was accomplished, they fell upon their knees and, folding their hands together, offered a simple prayer to God before they went to rest.

These two are long since dead. But their son complied with their will and his son after him and so on and so forth until the present day.

And, however riches might increase or diminish with the varying fortunes of the times, the old house in the square continued in the possession of the family. For he who was its head always lived in such a way that he kept his ancestral home.

The room stood untouched, as was appointed, and the document grew old and yellow in the secret recess in the wall. Once only in the time of each master of the house was it taken out; and that was on the evening when he first brought his young wife to the secret chamber. Then they wrote their names upon it and put it away again.

But it became the custom for each of them that took lawful possession of the room to adorn it with a piece of furniture after his own taste and heart. And they were strange objects that, in the course of time, gathered round the two great, strange chairs.

There was one of the owners of the house who was kindly and cheerful to the end. He placed in the room, in his wife's honor, a costly spinning-wheel, richly inlaid, which whirred merrily every evening for many a good year and which stood as it was, with thread upon the spindle.

There was one whose thoughts were always roaming and never at rest and whose intellect was obscured before he died. He presented the room with an ingenious representation of the heavenly system. When a spring was pressed, the spheres lit up and ran their eternal courses; and he sat and played with the stars to his last day.

There was another whose wife dreaded the deep silence of the room and never entered it but once. He waited for five years and then had a doll made, a woman, life-size and beautifully dressed. He put it on a chair in the window, so that the light fell on its vacant face. But his son, who loved his mother, drew the doll back, so thatit was hidden in the curtain.

There was one whose wife was in the habit of singing when she was sad, as she often was. She brought a spinet, with slender, beautiful notes, which sang like a mother singing her child to sleep. In time, its sound grew very thin. When it was played upon in the room at night, it sounded over the silent square like a humming in the air; and none that passed knew what it was.

There was also one who had his wife's portrait painted and hung the picture on the wall. He broke his wedding-vows and his grandson took the picture down. But, where it had been, a light stain remained that could not be removed.

The man who was master of the house at the time when that happened which is related in this book had brought nothing as yet. But his wife had set up a thing that had caught her eye more than all that she had seen in the way of art on her long travels. This was a jar of a preposterous shape, large and bright and of a pale tint. On one side was the fgure of a naked man writhing through thorns. It stood on a stone pedestal hewn from a rock near Jerusalem.

That was how the room was.

Each evening, when it grew dark, the oldest servant in the house lit the candles on the mantel-piece. Each morning, before any one was awake, he cleaned the room with his own hands and watered the red flowers on the balcony. When winter came, he strewed bread-crumbs for the sparrows that gathered on the baluster and twittered.

But the name of him that owned the house was Cordt. And his wife was Fru Adelheid.

Chapter 2

Cordt sat in one of the arm-chairs by the chimney, reading.

He was in evening clothes and held his crush-hat and his gloves on his knees. He turned the pages quickly. Every moment, he swept his thick hair from his forehead; every moment, he looked at Fru Adelheid, who was walking up and down the foor with her hands behind her back.

She was very tall and slender. Her face was as white as her white gown. Her mouth was very red, her eyes looked large and strange. She wore fowers in her hair and at her waist.

“You are not reading, Cordt,”she said; but she passed with her back to him.

He closed the book and laid it aside. Then he moved the chair so as to turn his face towards her. His eyes were larger than hers and steadier, his mouth frmer.

“How beautiful you are!”he said.

She laughed softly and took his hand and kissed it:

“How charming of you!”she said.

She began to walk again. He stretched out his legs and lay with his head back in the chair, but followed her all the time with his eyes. Now and again, she stopped, smoothed her gown, let her fingers stray over the keys of the spinet and then went out on the balcony through the open door. He could not see her from where hewas sitting, but the white train of her dress lay inside the room and he looked at that.

Then she returned, sat on the arm of the other chair and swung her foot to and fro.

“I do not like you to be in good spirits, Adelheid,”he said.

Her eyes shone. She looked at the fireplace, where a log lay glowing:

“You should drink a glass of wine, Cordt.”

“I do not care for wine.”

“No more do I. But I like its exhilaration. It makes one so light-hearted. Then everything becomes so charming.”

“Have you been drinking?”

“But, Cordt…what makes you ask that?”

“Because you are so light-hearted and I so charming.”

She went up to him and laid her cheek against his hair:

“Now don't spoil it for me,”she said.“You can, with a single word, and that would be a great, great sin. You say I am pretty; and I am glad because you think so and because I am going out with you and because you are handsome and belong to me. We shall be far from each other and close together for all that. We shall nod to each other, as we always do, and know what we know.”

He released himself from her gently:

“Sit down a little,”he said,“and talk to me.”

She kissed him and sat down in the chair and then and there forgot her despondency. Her eyes shone as before. He raked out the embers and threw a log upon them. They sat and watched it catch fre and saw the smoke surround it and rise up. Her foot tapped the carpet; he shaded his eyes with his hand and pursued his thoughts:

“In my frst year at the university,”he said,“there were fve of us who were chums and we used to meet every Saturday evening. It was generally at my rooms, for I could best afford it. We used to sit and drink wine until bright daylight and then take one another home.”

“You must have drunk a great deal.”

“I don't know. Perhaps we did. We talked so loud and deep. The wine made us feel bigger, braver and cleverer. Next day, we were quite different, more reserved and cool. But we could look one another boldly in the face, for we had nothing to repent of. It did not matter if we had allowed ourselves to be carried away. We knew one another so well and trusted one another.”

She sat and looked at him as he spoke, but said nothing. Lost in thought, he continued to throw logs on the fre until she took one out of his hand and put it aside:

“You'll set the house on fre!”

“One should never drink wine with strangers,”he said.“You see, it is so degrading to be stripped bare. And that is just what happens.”

“You say that as if it meant getting drunk.”

He paid no attention to her words, but went on:

“One unbuttons one's self, one reveals one's self. Look at your eyes and your smile. I have felt it in my own eyes: hundreds of times, I have suddenly seen them all naked together round the table.”

“In good company, Cordt?”

“Where else?”

“I don't understand that,”she said.“I do not know the people whom you speak of.”

“You will be with them this evening, Adelheid.”

She shrugged her shoulders discontentedly and tapped her foot on the carpet.

“Adelheid.”

She looked at him and her eyes were dark and angry. He took her hand and held it fast in his:

“I have seen it in eyes that were looking at you, Adelheid.”

She drew her hand away:

“This is hideous, Cordt!”

She rose and went to the balcony-door. He looked after her and his eyes gleamed:

“Adelheid.”

She stood with her back to him, leaning against the window-frame, and buttoned her gloves. He leant forward and gripped the arms of his chair with his hands:

“I have seen it in your eyes, Adelheid.”

She did not move, uttered not a word. When she had fnished buttoning her gloves, she gathered up her train and went out on the balcony.

The May air was cold and she shivered in her thin gown. The lamps shone dimly through the mist; many carriages drove across the square. She could hear the tinkling of the harness-bells in the gateway; the footman was tramping up and down below.

She turned and stood at the window and looked at Cordt. He had moved his chair round towards the fireplace. She could see nothing of him but one shoulder and arm, his thick hair and his legs.

“The carriage is there,”she said.

He rose and went to her.

“You must not be angry with me,”he said, gently.“I am out of sorts.”

“Are you ill?”

“Yes…perhaps.…No, not that.”

“Well, for all that I care, we can stay at home. You have spoilt my pleasure.”

“Have I?”

“Of course you have. It was for you I made myself look so nice…it was with you I wanted to go out.”

“Was it?”

He took her hand and drew her to the fre:

“Sit down, Adelheid…there…only for a minute. Shall we stay at home to-night…get some wine…have a party of our own…?”

“Yes…you're in such a festive mood!”

“Now be good, Adelheid. You are my only dissipation…You know you are…there have been hundreds of delightful days to prove it. If you are of my mind to-night, we will do this. And you will be beautiful for me and I for you and our eyes will sparkle together.”

She did not look at him, but shook her head:

“I will stay at home, if you wish it,”she said.

They sat silent. The candles on the mantelpiece flickered and guttered in the draught.

“It is strange,”he said.“Do you remember the evening in London, Adelheid, when we were to go to that great ball? Then I begged you to stay at home and you did and you were glad.”

She lay far back in her chair, with her arms behind her neck:

“I was not glad that evening,”she said.

He raised his head and listened.

“I submitted, Cordt, but I was not glad to. I was acting a part, for your sake.”

She met his eyes. Hers were still and sad and she did not remove them while she spoke:

“I was wicked, Cordt. I hated you. I told you a lie. I was dancing at the ball, hour after hour, while I sat and held your hand and laughed so gaily.”

She slipped from her chair and crouched before him, with her hands folded round his knee and her eyes fxed humbly on his face:

“Do not look at me so strangely, Cordt. That is how I am. I love you. But I cannot live without the others…without having them to see it, to see my happiness. I want to be pretty and I want them to fall in love with me and I want to belong to you. I only care to be pretty if I am loved. Don't look like that, Cordt.”

She clung to him with eyes of entreaty.

“I am not really wicked, Cordt…am I? I was with our little baby day and night when he was ill…wasn't I, Cordt?”

“Yes,”he said.

“Yes…I was. But I cannot always be quiet.”

He lifted her from her chair and crossed the room with his arm round her waist. They went out on the balcony. A carriage came across the square at a brisk trot, followed soon after by a multitude of others. They came from the streets all round, but drove away in the same direction and disappeared round a street corner. The horses' hoofs clattered against the pavement, the lamps shone on the glittering carriages, coachmen and footmen sat stiff and black on their boxes.

“Come, Adelheid,”he said.“Let us go.”

The candles on the mantelpiece burnt down and the faces in the big chairs grinned in the darkness. When day dawned, the old servant came and arranged the room. When it was evening, he lit the candles.

He did this the next day and the next and many days after. The sun rose and the sun set. The water splashed in the fountain. The lamps shone and the people swarmed over the square. The balcony was bright with its red flowers and, every evening, the light fell through the open door.

But the summer passed and no one entered the room.

Chapter 3

Fru Adelheid stood on the balcony. She plucked the red fowers and threw them into the square below. She wore a long, white gown; her gloves and her white boa lay on the ground. She had just come from the theatre and had been bored.

Now she turned towards the room.

Cordt sat huddled together before the fireplace and stared in front of him. She wanted to see his face and called to him. He pushed back his chair and looked up:

“I was thinking of the play we have been to see,”he said.

“Yes, it was stupid.”

She drew the other chair over the foor, so that she could look at the jar with the naked man writhing through thorns.

“There was a time when I was tired of law,”said Cordt.“I was glad when the poet showed me a marriage that was broken for love. I used to think that people grew greater through it and that Heaven seemed higher and earth more green.”

She shuddered again and wrapped her skirt closer about her feet.

“Now I am so tired of lawlessness. I loathe these women and their lovers.”

“You are married yourself now,”she answered.

“What do you say?”

He looked up. She could see that he had not caught her words and she was glad.

“There must be a struggle, no doubt,”she said.

“Of course there must. There is. In the old days, they were not allowed to come together and now they are not allowed to stay together.”

She said nothing, but let her hand glide over the jar.

“All these faithless wives have lowered love. I could imagine a woman of refnement stifing her love, because she would not give it scope.”

“Because she was afraid.”

“Because she was refned.”

They sat silent for a time and looked at the live embers in the white ashes.

“Do you think there are many who do that?”

He looked up.

“Do you think there are many faithless wives?”

“I don't know. Why shouldn't there be?”

He leant his head on his hands. Fru Adelheid played with the jar.

“But I can't understand that people care to go to the theatre.”

“Where would you have them go?”

He pushed back his chair so that he could see her. She remained sitting as she sat and thought of nothing.

“Adelheid,”he said,“I suppose you wouldn't care to stay at home to-night?”

She lay back in her chair and looked at her hands.

“Oh,”she said,“I wanted to go out to supper.”

“I should so much like to talk to you.”

“But I did come home from the theatre, dear,”she replied and put out her hand to him.

He did not see it and she let it fall.

“I would rather have stayed at home after the theatre, Adelheid.”

“Yes, I see,”she answered and just shrugged her shoulders.“I did not understand.”

“But you understood it in the theatre. And now you want to sup out all the same.”

He bent over to her to catch her eyes. She said nothing and did not look at him.

“Adelheid.”

Fru Adelheid knit her brow:

“I don't go to the theatre, you see, for the sake of the play,”she said.“That does not amuse me. But it amuses me to watch that sea of people and to hear them clamor and then fall silent. I like the way they clap and the way they are quite still when anything good is being said on the stage. Then something sings inside me and I enjoy it.”

He looked at her for a moment; then he laughed and rubbed his hands. Fru Adelheid turned her chair towards him, so close that her knees touched his:

“What is it that you wanted to talk to me about this evening?”she asked.“That couldn't be postponed until the theatre was over? That couldn't wait for an hour, now that I feel like going out to supper?”

He looked at her and shook his head.

“Was it anything? Or were you only tired and empty, as I was…and as the faithless wives are…and the modern poets and…and everybody?”

“No, Adelheid,”he said.“No. It was nothing. Nothing at all.”

“I don't know what you mean,”she said and suddenly flung herself violently back in her chair.“There is something behind your words.”

Cordt nodded.

“You are angry with me. What is it that I do? We live no differently, that I know of, from other people in our circle. We travel, we go to the theatre, we go out and we receive our friends at home. We meet amusing people, artists…everybody who is anybody.”

“Are you always amused among amusing people?”

She looked at him a little doubtfully:

“There is no such thing as always anywhere.”

“No,”he said,“more's the pity. There is not.”

They sat silent, both steeped in thought. Then he pushed his hair from his forehead and said, calmly:

“Try if you can understand me, Adelheid. When a woman marries and becomes a mother, she usually becomes quiet…quieter, I mean. I mean that there are victories which she cannot win, triumphs which she cannot achieve…which she does not trouble about. She does not trouble about them, Adelheid, because she has deepened her life…because she has come so near to one man that the approach of other men is distasteful to her. Then she becomes quiet…quieter. And this quietness is not empty, but just richer than all the rest.”

She looked at him with a strangely inquisitive fash in her angry eyes:

“Are you jealous?”she asked.

He shook his head and made a gesture of denial with his hand. But she sprang from her chair and stood before him with great, proud eyes:

“You ought to be, Cordt,”she said.“You ought to be. I am yours and I love you. You won me once: see to it that you know how to keep me. Fight for me, Cordt. I am young, I am pretty and the world is full of men.”

He rose deliberately and looked at her till she thought for a moment that he would strike her.

“You will be twenty-six next month,”he said.“And, besides, we in our family don't fght to keep our wives.”

“Cordt.”

She sat down without knowing what she was doing. He looked at her and she looked back at him. She could not help thinking how tall he was; and how easily he wore his clothes; and that one of his shoulders was a little lower than the other.

Then he crossed the room, so quickly that he nearly tripped over the carpet. He struggled with the old spinning-wheel and pulled it over the foor. She followed him with her eyes.

“Can you spin on my great-grandmother's wheel, Adelheid?”he asked.

She crossed her arms on her breast and looked at him.

“Can't you, Adelheid? Couldn't you learn? Not if I begged you to?”

He pulled the spinning-wheel right in front of her and placed it as if she were to use it then and there. Then he sat down in his chair again.

“Don't you think you could, Adelheid?”

They looked hard at each other. Then they became timid and shy and dropped their eyes.

They both thought of holding out their hands, but neither could see the other's. They longed to throw themselves into each other's arms, but they sat as stiff as statues. Their lips trembled; but they did not look at each other and neither knew anything of the other's thought.

“I am thinking how very small we look in these big chairs,”he said, at last.

His voice was calm and she grew quite calm at once. It was all over; there was peace in their souls. It was not a reconciliation, for they remembered no quarrel. Their glances rested confdently upon each other.

There was nothing between them and they were friends.

“I wonder if we are inferior to those who sat here before us,”she said.“Different, yes; but inferior?”

They both rose.

“Much inferior,”said Cordt,“and much less happy.”

They crossed the room and went out on the balcony, as was their custom before they went to bed.

The stars of the September night rode in a high sky. Most of the lamps were extinguished and there were but few people in the square. A drunken man was singing far away. The sound of the water falling in the fountain swelled up in the silence.

“How beautiful it is here!”he said.

“Yes.”

“And now the summer nights are over and we have not enjoyedthem.”

She laid her head on his shoulder and closed her eyes.

“I do not think that in the whole world there is a square so pretty as this,”he said.

“Oh, yes…in Florence…”

He sighed and led her into the room:

“We have travelled too much, Adelheid.”

She crossed the foor quickly and opened the door. He remained standing on the balcony.

It had all seethed up in him again. He fought against it, but to no purpose.

“Are you coming, Cordt?”

She was outside in the passage and could not see him.

“Do you go…I will come presently.”

He forced his voice to be as calm as possible, but it sounded very unnatural in his own ears. He stood quite still and listened. She remained standing for a moment, as though she were considering.

Then she closed the door and went. He could hear that she went hurriedly.

Chapter 4

The frst snow had fallen and lay fne and white on the balcony, embroidered by the feet of the sparrows.

The red flowers stood indoors, in the warmth, and looked pitiful. And a big table had been placed at the back of the room, with a lamp upon it and a pile of books.

Cordt came early.

He went straight up to the table, sat down and opened a book. Soon after, he stood at the window and looked out.

It was growing dusk. A damp and misty evening, with a thin, reddish light behind the mist and cold feet and dripping roofs. The snow on the square had melted into slush. The fountain was silent, covered with boards and pine-faggots.

He sat down again and read. He stood up, looked at his watch, went to the window, walked up and down the floor and sat down again. He lit a cigar and let it go out. He went away and came back in an hour and began all over again.

A little before midnight, the carriage drove in through the gateway and, fve minutes later, Fru Adelheid stood in the room, tall and white, with large eyes.

“Have you enjoyed yourself, Adelheid?”

She could hear that he did not care to know and she did not answer:

“I am freezing,”she said.

She drew her chair close up to the fre, nestled into it and put her feet on the fender.

“They asked after you, Cordt.”

“I daresay.”

He turned over the leaves of his book a little, then closed it and drew his chair beside hers. He sat resting his cheek in his hand and looked tired.

“Do you intend to sit in this room all day, Cordt?”

“No, only in the evening. When I have nothing else to do, I love this room.”

She pressed her hands hard together and closed her eyes.

“I hate it,”she said.“All the unkindness that has come between you and me comes from here.”

He said nothing to this, but rose and went to the table for a cigar. Something went through her as he slammed the lid of the box.

“Are you going with me to-morrow?”

He shook his head.

“Do you want to cut off all our acquaintance, Cordt?”

“No,”he said.“I do not. But I don't care to go out just now.”

“What do you think our friends will say?”

“Let them say what they like.”

“Don't you consider how unpleasant it is for me?”

“Oh, yes. But I don't care to go out at present.”

He lit his cigar at the candle on the mantel-shelf. Then he sat down again and smoked quietly and looked into the fre. She looked at him and sighed.

And, without knowing how it happened and without intendingit, she suddenly felt her heart touched and her eyes grew moist:

“Are you not happy, Cordt?”

He looked up and gazed at her:

“No.”

“And it is my fault? Because your wife is a silly woman, who wants to go out every day?”

“You are not that, Adelheid.”

“Because I am an empty, restless, modern creature?”

“You are not that.”

“What am I then, Cordt?”

He took her hand and kissed it and smiled to her:

“You are my wife, Adelheid. And we have a little baby, we two, and perhaps will have another.”

“No,”she said and drew her hand away.“No, Cordt. That was only my nonsense.”

He said nothing. His hand fell down slackly and he turned paler than she could remember ever having seen him. She was afraid that he was ill and stooped over him and called to him.

He did not see her, did not hear her.

She could not take her eyes from him. She thought he could not look more distressed if their boy were dead. She felt it as an appalling shame, that she herself was glad of it; and she dreaded lest he should look at her.

Then he did and read her thoughts.

And she grew worse and worse the more she saw him grieve. She did not understand it, felt troubled by it.

And, as there was no anger in his eyes, it grew worse for her still. She cast about for a word that could make him move and saysomething, no matter what.

But he sat still and silent and slowly turned his face away from her. And she could fnd nothing to say.

She rose and went to the window and stood there for a while. Then she came back and sat down in a chair:

“What are you thinking of, Cordt?”

“Of you.”

Again they sat silent.

“Adelheid.”

He spoke her name quite calmly and gently, but she was frightened.

“I will fght for you, Adelheid; I mean to fght for you; and the new little baby would have helped me. Now I shall have to fight alone.”

She remembered vaguely that this phrase had once been uttered between them, but she did not understand him.

“I will stake life and happiness to win you,”he said.“I will talk to you and importune you and conquer you. I will take you in my arms and close my door against you and run after you and forgive you.”

“And, if you don't win me?”

“I shall win you.”

“But if?”

She looked at his mouth, while she listened for the answer. It came quite calmly; he did not even look at her:

“Then I shall cast you off.”

Fru Adelheid closed her eyes tightly and then opened them wide:

“Better cast me off at once, Cordt. If you can.”

“I can't. We have the baby. And we are fond of each other.”

“I don't know,”she said.

“What don't you know ?”

She did not answer, only shook her head.

“You shall have your liberty,”he said.“Go out as much as you please, amuse yourself, fll the house with guests. Be gay and melancholy the whole day long, as your fate decides. Go away, if you feel inclined.”

“And will you never go with me?”

“As little as possible. I will not fght for you out there. I won you there once and I am not afraid for you…that way. There, in any case, I need not trouble to win you again.”

“And then?”

“Then you will know that you can find me here any evening. Here is where I shall live.”

He rose and walked slowly through the room. Fru Adelheid let herself slip to the foor and lay there with her cheek on the fender and stared before her. She saw him return and stand beside her and go and come back again.

“Cordt,”she said,“I shall never come here.”

“You can do about that as you please.”

He sat down and rested his head on his hand:

“My ancestor well knew what he was doing, when he built this sacred nuptial secret chamber in his rich, new house…high above the street, far from the day's work…and the night's. He saw deep and far.”

“It is the torture-chamber of the house,”said Fru Adelheid.“Iam certain that many women have wept bitterly in here.”

He half rose in his seat and passed his hand over his forehead.

“I am frightened, Cordt. You want to ill-use me. I can't do what you wish. Shall we talk somewhere else…in your room, Cordt?”

“No,”he said.“Our place is here. Here we are bound to be.”

He stood up and sat down again at once. His eyes glittered as he spoke:

“Here they all sat, the men who lived in the house and their wives…in joy and in sorrow. Their faces look at us from every corner, their words whisper all around…. Can you not hear my great-grandmother's spinning-wheel?…Do you not hear the spinet singing?”

“Yes, Cordt.”

“Here our words become greater and weightier in the stillness. Here we grow more powerful in our affection and our anger. Whatever we can do we can do here. They knew something, those old, big men and women.”

She rose and stood before him, leaning against the mantel, tall and white:

“They knew how to keep discipline in their house,”she said.

She looked at him and there was pride and fear and anger about her red mouth and in her strange eyes.

“That they did,”he said.“God bless them for it in their graves!”

She sat down in the old chair and put her arms around the jar, where the man writhed through thorns. She stared at the man's face and it was as though she were with him and felt the thorns in her fesh.

“Here also it was that we two bound ourselves to each other forgood and all, Adelheid. That evening when we put our names to the old yellow paper there, in the wall. Then you pledged yourself to this room, which you hate. And, when the time comes, our son will come here with the woman who shall be his joy.”

He went out on the balcony and came back, white and wet with snow. He brought the cold in with him and she shivered. He stood silent by the fre and then began to walk about again. She listened to his step and waited for a word and could fnd nothing to say.

Then she went to the old spinet and sat down and sang:

My Lenore, how dark and drear
The burden of daylight's bringing!
No music of chiming hours I hear,
No birds in the sunlight singing.

Sweet Lenore, O lady mine,
Bright-eyed, as the day wanes weaker,
Now pledge me deep in the golden wine
Night pours from her fragrant beaker.

The violets watch us, blue in the plain,
Not a star our secret misses.
Kiss me, Lenore, and kiss me again
And give me a thousand kisses.

The slender tones sang through the room, when she stopped.

She listened, but could not hear his footstep. He was sitting in one of the big chairs and did not move.

She looked at him for a moment over her shoulder. Then she rose and closed the instrument, with as much noise as she could:

“Good-night, Cordt.”

“Good-night.”

Then she turned very red and very pale and went away with moist and angry eyes.

Chapter 5

Fru Adelheid was icy cold and had drawn her chair as near the chimney as she could.

It blazed and fared in there; the red glow scorched her face and her white gown. But she kept on adding logs to the fre and could not get warm.

Cordt sat in the other chair reading, with his book on his knees and his head leaning on his hands. The book was a large one, with yellow pages and old-fashioned characters.

Fru Adelheid looked at him despondently. She regretted that she had come up to the room and would have gone away, had she had the strength to. She sighed and looked into the fre with tired eyes.

“Adelheid…listen.”

He pushed his hair with both hands from his forehead and read:

But, when the tidings came to Queen Thyre that Olav Trygvasson was dead, she fell into a swoon and lay thus for long. And, when, at the last, she came to herself again, she was so sorrowful that it was pity for those of her house to behold. When the day was over, she went to a monk who dwelled near by and was known in all that land for a holy man. Him she asked if folk who died by their own hands sinned against God's law; since her lord and husband was dead and she had no more liking for life. But the monk answered and said:

“Indeed it is a sin. For God has given us life and will take it back again when He thinks right.”

Then the queen wept, because she must sin so grievously. But, early the next morning, she came again and asked the holy man how little one was allowed to eat without angering God. And the monk took pity on her and said:

“If you eat an apple every day, that will be enough.”

Then Queen Thyre lay down on her couch and bade all her handmaidens leave her, so that she might be alone with her dule and sorrow, bidding them that one of her maidens, whom she best loved, was to bring her each morning an apple in the golden cup from which she was wont to take her morning draught. And so it fell that, when the maiden came on the morning of the ninth day with the apple in the golden cup, the queen was in Heaven with her husband.

He closed the book; his lips moved as though he were repeating the words to himself. Fru Adelheid looked thoughtfully into the fre. Then she said:

“It was all very well for those old, dead people. They always had a holy man to whom they could go in their distress.”

But Cordt shook his head.

“You distort the chronicle, Adelheid,”he said.“It was not at all like that. The queen wanted to die and she died. She went to themonk to be released from sin and piously subjected herself to his command.”

“They had God, in those days,”said Fru Adelheid.

“Yes, they had. The old, strong God held them in His hands.”

He rose quickly and stood by the chimney.

“Do you believe in God, Cordt?”

“No,”he answered.“I do not. But I believe that He once existed. And I think that it would be a good thing if He were here now.”

“I think so too.”

He put his foot on the fender and folded his hands over his knee:

“God is somewhere still. And I do not fear His mighty face. If ever I come to look upon it, then I daresay I shall see all that was high and glorious for me in my days, all that made my blood red and my back straight.”

Fru Adelheid smiled:

“Is that the old, strong God, I wonder?”

He glanced at her face, but there was nothing there to rouse his anger. Then he crossed the room and stood beside her again with the same expression in his eyes:

“The old, strong God,”he said.“I myself can do well enough without Him. But I need Him in my house.”

She laid her head back in her chair and laughed:

“Yes, indeed, Cordt. That you certainly do.”

And she kept on laughing and said again:

“Then I daresay that wouldn't have happened with…what was his name, who robbed you down below, in the counting-house? Doyou think so, Cordt? And then your wife would kiss your hand every morning and ask to know her stern lord's commands.”

He walked up and down and did not answer.

Fru Adelheid understood that he paid no attention to her sally, because her words were too small for his thoughts and she was displeased with herself and angry with him:

“But, to come back to the story, surely there are also Hagbarth and Signe,”she said.“Not to speak of Romeo and Juliet. And Maria Veczera…and Elvira Madigan.”

Cordt continued his walk.

“I don't say anything against it. It is a beautiful story. And perhaps it is true besides. In any case, it is right to place a good example before the young. But, as for as Queen Thyre, it surely depends a little upon how long she had been Fru Trygvasson.”

He did not so much as look at her. She felt that she was being treated as a child whom one does not trouble to answer and she worked herself up into a steadily increasing passion and sought for words to wound him:

“Every love passes,”she said.“That we know. It is all very well for those who die frst. They show up prettily in history; but there is nothing to prove that they were better than the rest of us.”

Cordt was still walking. Now he stood over by the window and looked out. Then he began to walk again.

“Cordt.”

He stopped before her chair and looked at her.

“Do you know how long King Olav and Queen Thyre were married?”

“What is the point of all this, Adelheid?”

She pushed back her chair and stood up. She was not able to say at once what she wished, but took a step towards him and sat down again and felt quite powerless.

Then there was something in his glance that helped her. And she drew herself up and looked him frmly in the face:

“It means that you are sitting here and growing musty in old books and old stuff and nonsense, while life is taking its course around you. In time, your beard will grow fast to the table and you will never speak a word, except once every ten years, and then it will be so wise and deep that no one will understand it.”

“There is no danger of that, Adelheid,”he said.

“But I don't want to be Queen Thyre or Signe or any of them,”she said; and her voice was so hard that something gave a wrench inside him.“I want to be the woman I am, the woman you fell in love with and took in your arms. I am not in a book. They will never read about me in the girls' schools. I have no time to spare for this endless old drab affection beyond the grave. I don't understand it, I don't believe in it. I want the wild, red love…”

Cordt had turned his face from her, while she was speaking. Now he looked at her again:

“Haven't you got it, Adelheid?”

She lay back in her chair and gave him a strange look. He had never seen those eyes before. Veil after veil fell over them, till they were quite dark, and then there suddenly lighted in them a gleam that was gone at the same moment and the veils fell again.

“I do not know,”she said.

She said it so softly that he could only just hear. He listened a moment whether she would say any more.

Then he bowed his head, so that his thick hair fell over his forehead, and threw it back again and turned very pale:

“Indeed?”he said.

He slowly crossed the room to the window and stood with his forehead against the panes. And slowly Fru Adelheid turned her face to him and back again to the fre.

It did not seem to her as though she had said it; and then, the next moment, she heard his quiet answer and saw his face, which was so terribly stern and white. She knew that it was not what she meant to say and she knew that it was true. She felt a bitter remorse at having hurt the man she loved, a senseless despair at not being able to make amends.

Then all this was dissolved in anger that he had led her on to speak like that. And the anger died away in a profound, soft pity for herself.

She saw deeper into her own soul than she had ever done before and turned dizzy with what she saw. She was seized with a wild and curious longing and bent lower over the well. Then it seemed to her as though she were falling and she gripped the arms of the chair so tightly that her knuckles turned white.

And behind the terror was the distant bird, that sang…a green and golden land, which she had never seen in her dreams…

Cordt stood before her and put out his hand:

“Good-night, Adelheid,”he said.

She sat straight up and looked at him in bewilderment:

“Are you going?”she asked.

“No. But I should like you to go to bed. I shall stay here a little longer and read.”

He sat down and took his book. Fru Adelheid rose slowly and went across the room.

At the door, she stood for a moment and looked at him. His face was very still. It seemed to her as though he were far away. She wondered whether he would look up and say good-night once more. Or only nod.

But he was reading and turning the pages of his book.

Chapter 6

The fre in the hearth was nearly out and the candles had burnt quite low. It was quiet in the room and quiet outside.

Cordt sat in his chair. He had been sitting there long and had not stirred, only pondered, with his fingers buried in his hair, and listened for Fru Adelheid's footsteps.

She was at home, had been at home the whole week. But she had not set foot in the room for the last fortnight.

Cordt looked at his watch. Then he rose and left the room, left the house.

A little later, Fru Adelheid came.

She remained standing at the door, surprised to fnd the room empty. She called to the balcony, but no one answered. Lingeringly, she went to the window and looked out. There was no one there.

She turned quickly to go. Then the thought came to her of what it had cost her to come up here; and she was annoyed that Cordt was not there. But that was only for a moment; then she was happy again at escaping the encounter. She felt in a lighter mood than she had for many days.

She looked about her curiously. She had never been alone in the room and she seemed not to have seen it properly before.

She stood long in front of the old chairs, lost in contemplationof the strange faces in the woodwork. She pushed them round the foor, placed them opposite each other and beside each other and sat down in them as though to try what it was like. She summoned up in her memory all that she knew about those who had sat in them and amused herself with imagining what one had said and the other.

Then she went to the celestial globe and looked at it. She pressed the spring, so that the stars ran and shone. She looked with delight at the queer plaything and, when the clockwork stopped, set it in motion again.

She pulled out the old spinning-wheel and sat down beside it and set it going. The wheel whirred lustily in the silent room and its whirring put Fru Adelheid in a very cheerful mood. She wished the great-grandmother would come in at the door and praise her for being so industrious.

She rose from the spinning-wheel and stood in the middle of the room and looked round. She thought of an occasion when she had stood in an Indian temple and refected that she was examining these singular old things just as calmly as she had contemplated the Hindu sanctuary.

It seemed to her as though she were standing in a mortuary chapel, where old and interesting, but foolish ideas and preposterous superstitions stared at her from the sunken faces of mummies. She felt no terror, for she knew that all that was dead and gone and could never return.

Her eyes fell on the light stain on the wall, where the portrait had hung.

“Poor Fru Lykke!”she said, aloud.“You were shut out of the temple, because your husband deceived you.”

And she lifted her arms in the air in jubilant gladness that she was born in gentler times and still lived and felt the warm blood beating in her heart.

Fru Adelheid went round the room and laughed aloud to think how easily she had broken the spell of the old room. She patted the big chairs on their stiff backs and talked kindly to them. She used to hate them; her blood had turned to ice each time she sat in them. Now they were two handsome, valuable chairs and nothing more.

She had torn the veil from the Holy of Holies. There was nothing behind it. She ran to the window and pulled the curtain aside with a jerk.

There sat the doll…stiff and stupid.

She laid her face on its waxen cheek and kissed it with her red mouth.

Humming a tune, she sat down to the old spinet. She sought for a hymn that should celebrate her victory over the ghost.

But, when she struck the first notes, she suddenly grew frightened.

She had an uncomfortable feeling that there was some one in the room.

She sprang up, so that the chair upset, and looked around her.

There was no one.

The candles were all burnt out but one and it was dark in every corner. Now the last candle flickered up and struggled a little and went out.

And then there came a treacherous and threatening muttering and whispering all round the room.

People passed over the foor…many and heavy footsteps. Thespinning-wheel whirred, the spinet sang behind her back. The stars ran and shone, the doll rocked at her. The faces in the old chairs raised themselves on their long necks and pecked at her and grinned uncannily.

But the man who writhed through thorns called for help…She could hear him call. He grew bigger…he came nearer…She saw the blood drip from his naked limbs…

Fru Adelheid crept to the door with quivering hands and fearful eyes.

Chapter 7

Fru Adelheid laid her hands over Cordt's book:

“May I talk to you a little? May I tell you something? May I tell you that what you are doing is madness?”

He moved her hands from his book and looked up:

“Sit down, Adelheid,”he said wearily.“Sit down in that chair.”

But she took the book from him and threw it on the foor:

“You are ill, Cordt. You have become ill up here in this dreadful room.”

“Have you a household remedy?”he asked.

“How can you have the heart to make a jest of it?”

“It would be a bitter jest, if it were one,”he said.“But it was not a jest. I believe in the old household remedies.”

Fru Adelheid sat down in her chair and stared helplessly before her:

“Of course you do,”she said.“And in old books and in everything that has ceased to exist.”

He said nothing, but yawned wearily.

“And God shall be set on His throne again and I shall sit at the spinning-wheel and we shall enjoy a blessed married life and be happy ever after.”

Cordt crossed his legs and looked at his nails:

“Yes…that is my programme,”he said quietly.“Something likethat. And you have stated it in your usual affectionate manner.”

“Cordt, how can you have the heart?”

She swung her body to and fro; her hands lay folded in her lap, her eyes were moist. She wanted to say something, but could not, because the tears prevented her. She could not understand that he did not help her. Then she said:

“Things are going badly with us, Cordt.”

And, as he was still silent, she pulled herself together with an effort and spoke with closed eyes, constantly rocking to and fro:

“We must obey the law under which we were born…must we not, Cordt? After all, we are modern people…both of us. Tired, empty people, if you like. But we do think and feel otherwise than people did when…when they were the sort of people whom you like. And we cannot alter ourselves. But we can be as happy as it is possible to be…nowadays, being what we are. Why should we not be happy, Cordt ?”

“I am not happy.”

“Oh, Cordt!”

She pressed her hands together and wrung them and bent over them so that her tears fell upon them. Then she turned her wet face to him and asked, softly:

“Then am I no longer pretty, Cordt?”

He stood up and kissed her white forehead:

“That you are,”he said.“But that won't help us any longer.”

He began to walk up and down. Fru Adelheid wept hard and silently. A little later, she said:

“You are driving me away from you, Cordt. I do so want to tell you this, while there is still time, if only I could fnd the right words.Won't you sit down a little, Cordt? My head aches so.”

He sat down in the chair. Then she rose and put some wood on the fre and sat down again:

“I am so afraid of myself when we talk together, Cordt,”she said.“It is not only that I am wicked and say what I do not mean. I do that, too. But you are so good. And you show me thoughts in my mind which are not there before you utter them. But then they come and I think that you are right and that they have been there always. That is so terrible, Cordt.”

They sat silent. Fru Adelheid closed her eyes; Cordt moved restlessly in his chair:

“Adelheid,”he said…“You told me that evening…”

“You must not say that…you must not.”

“Do you remember, you said…about the wild, red love…that it was not the love which you have?”

She shook his hand and pressed it:

“That is just it,”she said.“I am grateful to you because you were so good. And because you did not take it ill. But that was not in me, Cordt. I did not know it. But then you said it…and made me say…what I said. But then, at that very moment, I understood that it was so. And that made me feel so terribly bad…as I did. But then I felt a sort of secret joy…a secret treasure. It seemed to me that I was richer than before. I was no longer afraid of what may come…for women sometimes think of that, Cordt, while they are young, how empty everything will be, when that is past.”

He listened, with his face turned to the fre.

“I am sure that there is not a man who can understand that,”she said.

And then she lay down on the floor, with her chin on the fender…and her eyes shone:

“A woman is young for so short a time,”she said.“And she is always dreading that it will pass. Can't you understand, when she suddenly suspects that there is something greater than the greatest…and then, when she is sad and afraid…that then it may suddenly dawn upon her that all is not over yet?”

Cordt laughed:

“It is a poor pleasure to be the greatest when there is something greater still,”he said.

But Fru Adelheid shook her head:

“It's not like that, Cordt,”she said.

He pushed back his chair and walked up and down many times and it was silent in the room. Then he sat down again beside her and said:

“What you say is true. But it was in you and I am glad I showed it to you. I could not do differently, when I once saw it. I cannot go and wait until another man knocks at the secret door of your heart and offers you the greatest of all.”

She laid her cheek against the fender and looked at him:

“No, Cordt,”she said.“If it is like that, then what I said was not true.”

He waved his hand and shook his head impatiently:

“Not to-day or to-morrow,”he said.“But in a year, or two years, or ten. And, if it does not happen, then it is only an accident.”

Then she moved nearer to him and laid her head on his knee. She looked up to see if he minded. But he was far away in his thoughts and did not notice it.

She suddenly felt peaceful and contented. She was glad that she had got it said. She felt as if it was removed to a distance…perhaps it was quite gone…she could not understand why he continued to speak of it.

And what he said about another man seemed so far to her and so impossible. She thought about it as though it concerned somebody else:

“I love you, Cordt,”she said.“And, if, one day, another man came and I loved him…could I help it?”

He sprang up so suddenly that she had to seize the arm of the chair lest she should fall:

“No,”he said, scornfully.“You could not.”

He rushed through the room and repeated his words three or four times. Fru Adelheid rose from the floor and sat down in her chair and closed her eyes.

“The man who hit upon that excuse did a fne day's work,”said Cordt.“He drove out of the world a great portion of men's strength to live their lives.”

He threw himself so violently into his chair that Fru Adelheid started. Then he sat long quiet and she was glad that he was silent.

“Why should one not be able to control one's heart?”he said, at last.“Suppose I have a wife and child; and my wife is she whom I myself chose. Then, one day, I meet another woman, who rouses my desires. I meet her at a party, where there are lights and wine and music…we are not ourselves, she and I…we are in another mood than usual…everything is done to lead us from the way by which we go on ordinary days. But why should I not be able to step aside, in loyal gratitude for that which I possess?”

She opened her eyes at intervals and closed them again. She heard what he said, but did not realize that he was speaking to her.

“Who is it that placed love outside the laws? If I take it into my head to kill a fellow-creature, there is no doubt but that I am indulging a most criminal fancy. If I have given my word and think of breaking it, I am no gentleman. But my heart may do as it pleases.”

“Yes,”said Fru Adelheid.

She was thinking of nothing when she spoke and he did not hear her.

“There are people, we know, who have the right to send thousands to their death,”he said.“There are people whose passion rises skywards in red fames and devours the poor chattels that stand in its way and lights up all the land. Poets sing about it and a wax taper burns before its image in every human heart. But, if a man plays the Napoleon in the Store Bröndstræde, we hang him…Why should every second woman be entitled to look upon herself as an Héloïse?”

He sank into his chair and stared before him:

“I am not sure either whether the radiance of the one great fame makes up for the thousand tiny lights that are put out. Does any one know, I wonder? Can any one measure it?”

Fru Adelheid moved and Cordt turned his face to her and looked at her attentively. Her eyes were soft and dreamy; she smiled faintly, like a drowsy child.

“And if that be so,”he said, in a subdued voice,“if it be the case that I am not able to control my heart…”He let his head fall heavily on the arm of the chair.“If it be the case that love makes mehappy and confdent, so that I build my life and the life of my family upon it…if it can then expire, without my knowing how or why, and I have to look for the mother of my children in a strange man's bed, then why do I let my wife go out in the street unveiled? Why do I not lock her up, as the Turk does? Or why do we not kill the mother when the child is born?”

He rose and walked round the room and grew calmer as he walked:

“But it is not so,”he said.“Let the great keep their greatness…let the poets celebrate them and the puny moderns ape them in their wretched way. And may there always be women who cannot give themselves more than once and men who love them.”

He stood by the fre and looked through the room. It was still on every side; the church-clock struck two.

“See, Adelheid,”he said,“how life passes more and more into law's domain. Every day, the liberty of the one is taken for an encroachment upon the rights of the other. Every day, land, hitherto free of law, is regulated by law. Flowers beget no fowers without the gardener's consent; animals no longer select their own mates. But no one can control his heart; and human beings pair like dogs in the street.”

The fre had burnt out when Cordt woke from his musings.

He saw that Fru Adelheid was asleep. He stood before her a long time, sick with compassion for her and for himself.

Then he stroked her gently on the hair:

“It is late…Adelheid.”

Chapter 8

“I could wish we were not married, Cordt,”said Fru Adelheid.

She laid her arms across her breast and looked at him with deep, dark eyes:

“I could wish I were your mistress. If it meant that, all would be over and done with in the morning. Then there would be no more of this unpleasantness. And no fear, either. And the joys we have would be all the fairer.”

He stood by the fre and played with the keys in his pocket.

“Then your forehead would be smooth and your eyes bright, Cordt, for then you would be making love to me.”

He looked up and said gently:

“Don't I make love to you, Adelheid?”

She sighed and said nothing. Cordt sat down in his chair and time passed. Then he asked:

“Do you hear what I say, Adelheid?”

“I am longing to hear what you will say next.”

“I read something similar to what you have been saying in a book lately,”he said.“I forget what the book was called. I was looking into it…just where the author railed against marriage, with its security and its habits and all that. I have read exactly the same thing in a hundred books, I think.”

“Yes…they all sing the same song,”she replied.“It is notparticularly entertaining. But it is true enough, I daresay.”

Cordt struck his hands together lightly:

“It is curious how little imagination the poets have nowadays,”he said.“One would think there were only half a dozen women, whom they have all kissed and married and run away from. I wonder that it never occurs to one of them to glorify custom.”

Cordt pulled his chair forward and sat with his head in his hands and looked into the fre:

“If I were a poet, I would sing a song in honour of sacred custom,”he said.

“Would you, Cordt?”

“Yes, yes…that I would.”

He laid his head back and listened to the gale whistling in the chimney:

“Now just look, Adelheid, at two people thrown into each other's arms by the strongest power on earth. For them there exists neither day nor night, neither time nor place. The whole earth is fragrant with violets. Their joy is terror and their terror is full of exultant gladness. Then a child lies in her lap and the light in her eyes is deeper than before. And then the years go by…there are fewer violets on the earth as the years go by, Adelheid. She bears her children in pain. And the pain sears her cheek. The children have sucked her breast dry; her eyes are weary with the night-watches. The stranger who passes the house sees only the faded woman. But he who drank intoxication from her young eyes and kissed the strength of her bosom…he does not see it. He has grown accustomed to that woman. She has quenched the longing of his youth and given him peaceful happiness instead.”

He was silent for a while. Then he turned his face towards her:

“He does not live in his frst eager longing for the trysting-hour, but confdently seeks his accustomed couch by her side. Custom has gently bound the two people into one family. Is that not beautiful, Adelheid? And good?”

“Yes,”she said.“It is beautiful, as you tell it. But it is not youth.”

“Then what is youth, Adelheid?”

“Youth is not rest.”

“Then one should not marry before one is old,”said Cordt.“For marriage is rest. Deep, powerful, happy…generating rest.”

“No more one should,”replied Fru Adelheid.“And that is why I could wish I were your mistress.”

She looked at him, as she said this, and he at her.

Then he stood up and laid his hand on the back of her chair and bent close down to her:

“How far estranged from each other we have become!”he said.

And Fru Adelheid nodded sadly and Cordt crossed the room and stood by the fre again:

“In vain I pitch my call in every key,”he said.“It has availed me nothing that my ancestor built this room…his heirs have borne witness here, generation after generation, to no purpose.”

A gust of wind came and blew the balcony-door open.

Fru Adelheid shuddered and looked that way, while Cordt went and closed it. Then he remained standing by the celestial globe and pressed the spring:

“I so often think of the poor man who placed this toy up here,”he said.“He was a man who could not be content with the circlein which he moved. So he lost his reason and devoted himself to playing with the stars…For us modern people it is different…the other way round. We go mad because the circle in which we move is too large. We leave the stars to the babies. We play ball with bigger things. We try a fall with God Himself, if the fancy takes us…provided that we have not outgrown that plaything too! We dare not speak of love and we smile at marriage. We despise courage and do not believe in honesty and each of us has his own opinion about virtue.”

She heard what he said even as people listen to music when it does not so very much matter if they catch every note.

“Then it happens that we long for a fxed point in our lives…just one point. Something that cannot be pulled to pieces and discussed. And something that is not past.”

Cordt sat and moved about in his chair and could not settle down:

“If I were to put anything in this room,”he said,“it would be a little tiny house…from far away in the country. There would be only one door and two windows and it would be evening and the smoke would rise up gently from the chimney. The house would have to be as small as could be; but that would show that there was no room for doubt inside it. Husband and wife would go in and out of the door to the end of their days.”

Now she heard what he said and looked at him.

“That is what my marriage ought to be, Adelheid. If I had had any talent, I daresay it would have been different. Or if I had to work for my bread…And I am no different from other men of today…no stronger, no braver. I know nothing about God and I have noexcessive belief in men.”

He had lowered his voice and spoke without looking at her. But she understood that he was listening for a word from her and her heart wept because she had nothing to say to him.

“My fxed point,”he said.

Then he was silent for a little. But, soon after, he rose and stood with his arm on the back of her chair and spoke again:

“There was also something in what I used to see at home. Father and mother were so kind…and so strong. I see them before me now, as they used to kiss each other after dinner, however numerous the company might be. And they kissed each other good-morning and good-night until they died. And when father and his brother met in the street, they always kissed…people used to laugh…and it was such a pretty habit.”

While he spoke, she sought for an opportunity to interrupt him.

“My family-feeling has always been too strong,”he said.“Until now. And yet…I once had a sweetheart…”

He stopped. Fru Adelheid sat up and looked at him. Her eyes shone.

“Or a connection, if you like…”

“You never told me about that!”she said.

Cordt raised his head and looked at her and she lowered her eyes.

“There is nothing to tell,”he said.

Then he said no more, but went to the window and stood there.

And Fru Adelheid again felt small and ill at ease in the big old chair.

Chapter 9

Cordt stood on the threshold and waited, but then closed the door and went to the fre.

He was in dress-clothes and tired and pale and his eyes were bright with wine. When he had been sitting for a little while, it grew too warm for him and he drew his chair to the balcony-door. There he sat and let his hands play with the red fowers.

Fru Adelheid did not see him when she entered.

She moved slowly and stopped in the middle of the room, when she discovered that he was not by the freplace. She was surprised at this, but soon forgot it, in her gaiety and her lingering excitement at the evening's entertainment, with her mind full of bright and clever phrases and the lights gleaming in her great eyes.

She sat down to the spinet and laid her forehead against the keys. Something was singing inside her; her foot softly beat the carpet.

Then she sought among the music and sang:

Lenore, my heart is wrung.
Thine is so dauntless, thine is so young.
Tell me, Lenore, the truth confessing
(Which never were mine by guessing):
Whence do thy soul's fresh fountains pour?
Where the mountains dip or the valleys soar?
Tell me, the truth confessing;
Open to me youth's door.

Lenore, my heart is sad.
Thine is so constant, thine is so glad.
Teach me thine equable gait to borrow;
Teach me laughter and sorrow.
My heart is a desert, sterile and bare;
My heart is thine: do thou whisper there
Of a fount that shall flood to-morrow,
Of a sun that shall gild God's air.

She put one hand on the music-sheet and played with the other and hummed the tune again.

Then Cordt clapped his hands in applause. She started and her hand fell heavily on the key-board:

“How you frightened me, Cordt!”

He came and stood beside the spinet. Fru Adelheid looked at his face and sighed. Then she stood up, put the music away and went and sat in a chair by the freplace:

“Won't you come here, Cordt?”

Cordt walked to and fro again and up and down.

“Sit down here for a little,”she said.

“Why should I?”he asked.“You are not here, you know.”

She looked up and met his calm eyes.

“You are still down below, among the crowd of our guests. Don't you know that, Adelheid? They are all empty carriages thatdrove out at the gate. For, as each one came to shake hands and say good-bye, you entreated him to stay a little longer.”

Fru Adelheid sighed and crossed her hands in her lap. He stood up by the freplace so that he could see her face.

“I was sitting over there among the fowers, when you came in, and I saw it all. You entered with a gleam and a rustle, accompanied by the whole throng…you were the fairest of them all. By your side went Martens, supple and handsome. A long way after came his wife…the woman who wears those tired eyes and that painful smile. She did not even look to see to whom he was offering his homage.”

She puckered her forehead and looked at him angrily.

“Then he begged you to sing the song once more and they crowded round you and added their entreaties to his. You crossed the foor…with your slow, sure gait…You always walk in the same way, Adelheid…like one who is not to be stopped. Your white dress trailed behind you; there was silence in the room.”

Cordt ceased for a moment. Fru Adelheid laid her head back in the chair and closed her eyes.

“Then you sang…his song…the one you were singing a minute ago at the old spinet…Yes, you heard me applauding, Adelheid. He stood beside you and looked at you…deferentially, happily. And you looked at him to read in his eyes how charming you were.”

“How wicked you make it all seem!”she said.

Cordt bent over her:

“Look at me, Adelheid.”

She looked at him and was afraid.

“How dare you come up here with your retinue?”he asked.“Uphere…to me…in this room? Look at me, Adelheid. Is there not room enough in the house besides? Are there not a hundred houses in the town where you can play the game you love?”

Fru Adelheid stretched out her hands to him:

“Cordt!”

But his eyes were large and stern and she could not bear to look into them. Then she rose and stood before him with bowed head:

“Shall I go, Cordt?”she asked, softly.

He did not answer, but crossed the room. And Fru Adelheid sat down on the edge of the big chair, as if she were not at home in the room.

“Yes…Martens,”he said.

“You were not at all friendly to him this evening, Cordt.”

She said this in order to say something and without thinking, but regretted it at the same moment and looked at him dejectedly. But he made a gesture with his hand and answered, calmly:

“Indeed I was. As friendly as he could wish and a great deal more so than I feel.”

He stood by the mantel and looked down before him. She took his hand and laid her cheek against it:

“Martens is nothing to me,”she said.

“No,”said Cordt.“Not really. It is not the man…it is men. It has not gone so far as that. But it has gone farther.”

“I don't understand you,”she said, sadly.

“It is not a man, a good man or a bad one, that is wooing your heart and has won or is trying to win it. Martens is not my rival. He does not love you and he is not trying to make you believe that he is. He does not lie. That is not called for nowadays, except amongthe lower classes. With us, we rarely see so much as the shade of a scandal. Whence should we derive the strength that is needed for a rupture, a separation, a flight from society? It's a soldier that tells his girl that she is his only love…a journeyman smith that kills his faithless sweetheart…a farm-girl that drowns herself when her lover jilts her for another.”

He drew away his hand and folded his arms across his chest.

“Martens is no Don Juan. It is not his passion that infatuates women, not his manly courage and strength that wins them. He carries his desires to the backstreets; he takes his meals with his wife. He cannot love. The women become his when he covets them, but he has never belonged to any woman. His eyes, his words, his ditties sing love's praises with a charming, melancholy languor which no woman can resist. Then he lays his head in her lap and tells her of his perpetual yearnings and his perpetual disappointments. He unbosoms himself to her and begs her not to betray him. Then she loves him. And she is his…to any extent he pleases.”

She tried to speak; but Cordt shook his head in denial and she sighed and was silent.

“He is no longer young. But that makes no difference. He was never young. His unbounded susceptibility, his eternal readiness make him young in the women's eyes, as though he were a woman in man's clothing. His limp sensuousness has permeated every fbre of his body and his soul…so much so that it affects his every word, look and thought. He is destitute of will and insipid and sickly and untrustworthy. He is never hungry and he is insatiable. He swallows women and spits them out again…with morbid longings and a despondent temper and a diminished strength to live their lives.”

“Cordt!…Cordt!…What is he to me?…What is he to us?”

He looked at her and was silent for a moment. Then he said:

“Martens tends the garden in which you pluck your fowers. He is the chief gardener. But he is only one of a thousand. In the main, these passion-hunters are all alike. Shall I introduce them to you?”

“No, Cordt.”

“I can do so without hurting the feelings of any of them by mentioning their names,”he said.“You will recognize them all. You will recognize them at once.”

“Cordt!”

But Cordt did not hear.

“You will remember the man of whom we all know that he has many mistresses, even though we can say nothing to his face. He often takes a new one. Then he has one more…that is all…for he never lets go the old ones.”

“That will do, Cordt.”

“Then there is the man who tells his fair friends that he has only loved one woman in his life and that is his mother. Have you ever observed the part which the mother plays in these worn-out men's imaginations? In their books…in their love…she is the emblem for their morning headaches, their impotent compunctions. Her business it is to soothe their worm-eaten thoughts…they whisper her name while they kiss their lady-loves. I don't know which is the greater insult: that offered to the mother or to the mistress.”

Fru Adelheid tried to rise, but just then he passed so close to her that she could not move. So she remained sitting, weary and racked, and he went round the room and stopped here and there while he spoke:

“These are the men to whom our wives belong,”he said.“And they do not take them away, so that we can bemoan their loss and get new wives in their stead. They are content to nibble the crest of the tree of love, which we have planted in our garden, and to leave it to stand and thrive as best it can.”

Fru Adelheid stood up before him with moist eyes and quivering lips:

“Cordt!”

But Cordt's face was white with anger and she could not fnd a word to say.

“Do I amuse you, Adelheid?”he asked.

She went to her place by the chimney and sat down again:

“You are putting out all my lights,”she said.

He walked across the room and went on talking:

“A man's honest love goes for nothing, when one of these gentry has laid eyes on his wife. Then he is degraded to the mere husband…a dull and clumsy person…the owner of something which he cannot own. Then there awakes in my wife's mind a longing for something which she does not possess. Her peace has turned into weariness and the love which her marriage offered into an empty custom. She resigns herself. And the silly words of every silly book sing in her ears. She knows that no love endures for ever…that marriage is odious. Impatient sighs rise up in her soul, embitter her days and sadden her nights. Then she changes the gold of love for small coin and fritters it away, while the lights shine forth and the music strikes up.”

He folded his hands about his neck and stood by her chair and looked before him:

“Adelheid,”he said…“I cannot understand that the men who occasion this state of things are allowed to go free among us. And we honor them as the most distinguished of mankind. When we see a poor cripple, a shudder comes over us…am I not right, Adelheid? We are disgusted with a face full of pain. But these lepers beam before our eyes with a radiance and a beauty that know no equal.”

He walked up and down for a while and time passed and there was silence in the room.

Then he sat down in his chair, where it stood by the balcony-door, among the red fowers.

He was tired and closed his eyes. Now and then, he opened them, when a carriage drove across the square or a cry sounded. Then he closed them again and fell into a drowsiness in which everything was present to him and painful.

And then suddenly he started up.

Fru Adelheid was lying before him on the foor, with her cheek against his knee. His hand was wet with her tears.

“Don't be angry with me, Cordt!”

He looked at her, but said nothing.

“Cordt…when you speak like that…it is true…true for me also…It is all so good and so beautiful…”

He pushed back his chair and rose to his feet:

“Be very careful what you do, Adelheid,”he said.“I am not a fashionable preacher, working up your nerves and quieting them again…not a poet, reading his last work to you. I am your husband, calling you to account.”

He crossed the room and then returned and stroked her hair:

“It is beyond our strength, Adelheid,”he said, sorrowfully.“Godhelp us!”

She took his hand and laid it over her eyes, so frmly that it hurt her.

“If the old God were still here, then we could go down on our knees and fold our hands together, as they did who built this room. Would that not be good, Adelheid?”

“Yes.”

“I call upon Him, Adelheid…. And upon everything in the world that is greater than my own power…. And upon the little child downstairs…”

Chapter 10

Fru Adelheid lay on the floor before her chair and pulled the fowers of her bouquet to pieces. Cordt sat with his head leaning on his hand and looked at the fowers.

“If only you would speak, Cordt…If only you would ask me something. Why don't you ask me something?”

“What can I ask you?”

“Ask me what I am thinking about. Why I have come home so early. Why I have not been here for so long.”

“I know all that, Adelheid.”

She crossed her hands on her knee and swayed to and fro and looked at him with dark and angry eyes:

“Is there anything you do not know, Cordt?”

“No.”

“I don't think so either. You know the right and the wrong of everything between heaven and earth. You are never in doubt and never at a loss. You know at once what is good and what is bad; and then you go away and do what is good.”

He shook his head and said nothing and she grew still more angry:

“You alone know. Whoever does not obey you is lost. There is no room in the house for any but you and those who serve you.”

Cordt bent over her and lifted her up in the chair.

“Be silent for a little, Adelheid,”he said.“And stay quiet for a little.”

But she slipped to the foor again and looked at him defantly:

“I will not sit in that chair,”she said.“Never again. I am not worthy of the honor. You do not know everything, Cordt. You do not know me.”

He stroked her hair with his two hands and forced her head back:

“Then show yourself to me,”he said.

She released her head and her eyes grew moist:

“You must not be good to me,”she said.“You don't know me. I am not the woman you think.”

Then she laid her head on the chair and said, softly:

“I am so sad, Cordt.”

“You will be glad again.”

“I daresay,”she said.“But I shall always be sad.”

She took the ruined bouquet and laid it on the chair and her cheek upon it. She closed her eyes. Cordt looked at her—she seemed so tired—and they were long silent. Then she said:

“It is so cold in here.”

And then silence fell upon the room again.

“Cordt!”

Fru Adelheid sat with her back against the chair and stared into the fre with strange eyes:

“Cordt…do you know…that sometimes, when I am merriest…outside…it is as though I heard little children crying.”

He sat silent.

“I hear little children crying, Cordt. When I am dancing…andsometimes when I am singing. And at the theatre…when there are many lights and people and I am happy…then it comes so often. Then I hear little children crying…far, far away, but still I can hear them distinctly…I can never help hearing them…Cordt…do you know what it is?”

“Yes, I know, Adelheid.”

Adelheid looked at him and turned her eyes to the fireplace again:

“Sometimes it happens differently,”she said.“When I hear a child crying…when it is really a child crying…a strange child, which has nothing to do with me, which I know nothing at all about…I needn't even see it, Cordt…but then I have to cry myself.”

She was silent for a little. Then she turned her face to him and asked:

“Do you know what that is, Cordt?”

And he looked at her calmly and said again:

“Yes, I know, Adelheid.”

“I do not know,”she said and shook her head softly.“I love our little boy and love to have him with me. Don't I, Cordt?”

“Yes.”

“But he is much happier with old Marie. He prefers to be with her. He puts out his little hands to me when I come in. But, when I have had him in my arms for a while, he wants to go back to Marie. He is so small still.”

“Yes.”

“Sometimes he will not kiss me on any account. He always kisses old Marie.”

“When she comes to die, we will put a tombstone on her grave,”he said.“And on the stone we will write,‘Here lies one whom the children in the house kissed.’”

Fru Adelheid folded her hands behind her neck and looked up at the ceiling:

“At one time, you used to tell me about your mother…that is long, long ago, Cordt. You talked of her so often, in those days…why do you never do so now?”

“I think only of you.”

She moved nearer to him and laid her head on his knee:

“May I lie like this, Cordt?”

He stroked her hair and left his hand lying on her shoulder.

“That's nice,”she said.

Cordt looked at her hair and stroked it again. She closed her eyes and nestled up against him:

“It is so quiet here,”she said.“Now I will go to sleep.”

But then she grew restless again. She half raised herself and lay on her knees, with her hands folded in her lap. Her hair had become undone and slipped down over her shoulders. Her eyes stared into the fre:

“You used to tell me that your mother undressed you every night when you were a little boy,”she said.“And every morning she dressed you…always.”

“So she did.”

“You said that it so often made her late when she was going to the theatre…or else she would get up from the table when there were guests. And your father used to be so angry with her.”

He nodded.

“I think your father was right,”she said.“I think it was odd of your mother…not quite…not quite natural.”

Cordt pushed the hair from his forehead, but said nothing.

“I could see quite well that you would have me do the same. But I couldn't do it. I can't do it as well as old Marie does and I can't see that that is necessary in order to be a good mother.…Then you also told me that, one evening, when your mother had to go out, you cried without stopping until she came home again.”

“Yes.”

“But, if your mother had been like me and if old Marie had undressed you every night, then it would have been she whom you would have cried for.”

“So it would,”he replied.“But it was good for me and good for herself that it was mother.”

“I don't understand that,”she said.

But then she raised her head and looked at him with great, proud eyes:

“Yes…I understand,”she said.“I understand that it is good for a man and gives him confdence to see his wife chained to her baby's cradle.”

“That is so, Adelheid.”

He looked at her quietly and sadly and her defance was broken then and there:

“How strangely you say that,”she said.“Cordt…”

Then she laid her head on his knee again and they were silent for a time. Then she said:

“I remember the evening when I was going to my frst grown-up ball. A lady came to dress my hair. I was so solemn and the ladyso talkative. She told me that I was pretty and that I was sure to be married soon; therefore I must lose no time and dance as much as I could; for, once a girl was married, she had to give up dancing. I asked her what she meant and said that I knew many married women who danced. Then she told me that that was true enough and that there were many fne ladies who did, but then they danced their children dead and therefore it was a great sin.”

He moved in his chair. She raised her head and laid it on his knee again:

“Do you believe that we can dance our children dead, Cordt?”

He did not reply, but stroked her cheek. But she pushed his hand away and turned her face and looked at him:

“Do you believe it, Cordt?”

He nodded.

Then Fru Adelheid rose awkwardly from the floor and stood before him. Slowly, she raised her hands and pressed them against her temples.

Cordt sprang up and took her hands frmly in his own and drew her to him. But she tore herself away and her eyes stared vacantly into his and did not see him.

“Adelheid!”

“Those are your children and mine, Cordt…the little children who cry when I am merry…the children who died because their mother danced . . .”

“Adelheid!”

His voice was very soft and his eyes very gentle. She stared into them and saw a gleam in their depths. She understood that he was rejoicing within himself, because he thought that he had her as hewanted her.

He put out his hands to her and his eyes and his silent, quivering mouth spoke a thousand loving words to her. She stood stiff and cold and looked at him stiffy and coldly.

And, when his hands touched her, she drew from him and pushed her chair far back, as if she could not fnd room enough:

“You do not understand me,”she said.

She crossed the room to the balcony-door and stood there. Then she came back to the freplace, where he had sat down, and looked at him as though he were a stranger:

“Those little children who cry,”she said,“what do they cry for?”

He raised his hands and let them fall on the arms of his chair.

“Why do they cry?”she repeated.“Because they have not been brought into a world which is closed to them at the very moment when they see its beauty?…Because they are not born to die?”

She went away again and came back and sat in her chair with a strained expression on her face, as though she had to explain something to one who was slow of comprehension:

“It's no use,”she said.

Her voice was harsh. She swung her body to and fro and her thoughts hunted for words in which she could say what she wanted in such a way that it would be settled once and for all and could not be misunderstood.

Then her looks fell on Cordt, as he sat there by her side, shattered and tired, with closed eyes and nerveless hands. She saw the pain she was giving him. She wished to undo and repair it and the tears broke out in her:

“Cordt!”

She took his hand and it lay lifeless in hers.

“Can't you help me?”

“No, Adelheid.”

Then her mood changed about. She pushed herself back in her chair and crossed her arms over her breast:

“Then I must help myself,”she said.“How could you, either, an old…yes, an old man like you?”

He did not answer, did not stir, did not look at her.

“An old man like you,”she repeated,“who long for peace and quiet and nothing else. Then you give out that that is the best happiness which is the easiest and the cheapest and the best adapted to domestic use.”

Cordt had raised himself upright in his chair. His hands lay clenched about his knee, his eyes blazed.

“Then you put the woman you love in your mother's chair…your grandmother's and your great-grandmother's chair…”

He few up and stood before her with his hands on his hips and his lips pressed close together:

“Hold your tongue!”

Fru Adelheid started and looked at him with frightened eyes:

“You have no right to speak to me like that,”she said.

He sat down again and threw his head back in his chair, with his face turned away from her. She was so tired, could not fnd the words she wanted, said everything differently and in another tone than that in which she thought it.

And, as he quieted down beside her, she began to think more clearly than usual and it seemed to her that there was nothing to bedone but to say her worst. Then she clenched her fsts, to give herself strength, and closed her eyes while she spoke:

“You must know things as they are, Cordt. It is all true, as you have seen it and as you have said it. I have lied to you, Cordt. I lied in my words…I lied every time I came up here and sat with you.”

Now she looked at him. He raised his head with an effort and met her eyes. Then he turned his face away again:

“You are lying now,”he said.

She opened her mouth and closed it again, so that her teeth struck together.

Then she crossed her hands in her lap and bent over them and wept:“I don't know that,”she said.

Cordt stood up and walked across the foor, slowly and wearily and without thinking. Fru Adelheid's tears fell into her lap.

They were in this room, each independent of the other, each without sympathy for the other. Their hearts were dead, their thoughts paralyzed. They were no longer two people who loved each other and who strove to be happy, not even two who were angry or sorry because they were to be parted. They were just two people under sentence of death, whom chance had imprisoned in the same cell, but who had nothing else in common.

Cordt was the frst to come to his senses.

He was standing behind her chair and the scent of her hair awakened him. He bowed deeper over her and remembered who she was. He looked at her hands, which were wet with tears, and his heart wept with her.

Then, at that moment, he saw that he must spare his sympathy if he wished to keep her. And, when he saw this, he at once realizedthat she was lost to him for ever.

He sat down in his chair and sought for the words which he should say. He felt like the actor who has to deliver the last sentence in the play, while the audience is already leaving, because the end of the performance is there and the tension over.

“Adelheid!”he said.

That was all he could say. She understood what was passing within him and was speechless too and wept softly.

And the night sped on.

She was lying on the floor again, where she had lain before, with her cheek upon his knee. She talked…hastily, by fts and starts, without troubling what she said, as long as she could get it all said.

Cordt leant his head on his hand and his thick hair fell over his forehead. He closed his eyes and opened them again, heard what she said and forgot it again, answered from time to time and knew only that it was over.

“There are other men for me besides yourself…it is true…it is all true…Ah, Cordt, may I say it, wicked as it is?…And you will be kind…you understand that it is not that…that it is not infdelity…”

She pressed her hands together and shook her head in despair:

“Yes…yes…it is infdelity, Cordt…it is.…It is, because it's you…and because I understand it now. May I tell you, Cordt…may I?…I love the desire in their eyes…I am curious about it…. There is nothing in it that insults me…. I am happy in it, I even try to kindle it…”

“Those things are not said to one's husband, Adelheid.”

She looked at him:

“To whom shall I say them, then?”

“Those things are not said.”

“Ah…well…I say them. I will say them. Because you are the man you are. And, also, you asked me about it, Cordt…you saw it and wanted to save me…that was why you spoke to me about it, wasn't it?…I did not know what it was…now I do know…I am not lying now…but I did not know, before you said it. And it is no uglier for me…it is better for me…Cordt, Cordt…it is less ugly so.”

She hid her face in her hands and wept so that she could not speak:

“And it is worse still, Cordt…it is worse than I have said…why do you not turn me out?…Ah, if you were only dead, Cordt!…Why should you be so unhappy and why should it be I that make you so? If you cast me away, it will be only what I deserve. For I know that it is you I love…I know it now as I never knew it before…you are the man that was destined for me…”

She seized his clothes with her hands and half raised herself, so that her white face was close to his:

“Cordt…can't you wait for me?…I am coming…”

Then she released her hold and sank in a heap on the foor:

“No…no…I cannot do what you wish.”

He rose to his feet and stood before her and looked into the fre:

“It's your will that is sick, Adelheid,”he said.

He walked across the room and stood at the balcony-door and looked out. Then he came back and sat in his chair again:

“You know where the great joy lies. And you know that it would be yours and mine, if you could reach it. But you cannot.There is no sense of perspective in your life…everything to you seems quite close or quite far, quite small or quite big. You are like Martens and the others. You belong to them, because your will is weak, like theirs. You are becoming like them.”

“No, Cordt.”

“Yes, you are like them. You are a woman and you are refned and therefore you dread the mire. But you belong to them. You and I are mortal enemies. If you were she whom my son had chosen for his wife, I should tremble for his happiness. And you had the happiness which you seek…nay, the happiness that exists. You set the cup to your lips when you were young enough to stand wine and old enough to know that it was good.”

He pushed the hair from his forehead and looked round the room:

“There is nothing more to be said. You are a child of the time and the time claims you as its own. There was no sense in bringing you to the old room.”

“No, Cordt.”

“But you are clever and you are refned and you have seen its great, silent beauty. And, one day, you will see that happiness lay in the land where you were and you sallied forth to fnd it in distant climes.”

“Yes, Cordt.”

“You will see that, one day. But then it will be too late. Then the years will be gone. Then the strings of the old spinet will be rusted and mute and the spinning-wheel will have fallen to dust and the fre died out in the chimney. Then your fancy will be frightened and bewildered, like the bird that keeps on fapping against the window-pane. Your faith will be lost and your modesty turned to unchastity.”

He rose and went across to the balcony-door. Fru Adelheid lay with her cheek on the fender and with closed eyes.

A silence hung over the room greater than it had ever known before. They both of them felt it and felt it as the silence when pain is dumbed at the approach of death. They no longer fought against the inevitable, against what was stronger than themselves; and they were so tired that they no longer thought of the defeat which they had suffered, but only smiled in the peace which they had won.

And the night sped on.

They were sitting again in the quaint old chairs and looked at the embers that were expiring in the hearth. The candles were nearly burnt out.

They were both of them very gentle and very still. It seemed years since they had last differed. Their faces were calm, their eyes clear and sad, when they looked at each other, but without longing, without anger or bitterness.

And they looked at each other and talked together…of that which was over.

Their words had lost all sting. He held her hand in his and pressed it as that of a good friend. Once, she pushed his hair from his forehead as she would have done to a child.

“If any one saw us sitting here, he would not understand what has happened to us,”said Cordt.

“No.”

“And, if anyone had heard every word that fell between us in this room, he would perhaps say that we were a pair of simpletons.”Fru Adelheid shook her head:

“It is well that nothing more has happened to us,”she said.

“I don't know,”replied Cordt.

Then he let go her hand and drew himself up in his seat:

“Sometimes I think it would be easier if there were an action that had to be forgiven,”he said.“Something to be forgotten. Then it would not be over.”

“It is not over,”she said.“We have missed happiness, because I did not keep the measure by which I should be gauged. But our boy down below lives and he can win a wife who shall sit in the old room with honor.”

“No,”said Cordt.“The secret of the old room is out. It does not suit these times and still less the times to come. Our son shall not see his happiness shattered here.”

And, a little later, he pressed his hand hard to his temples and said so softly that she just heard it:

“For it is hard to decrease one's own happiness.”

The candles went out…one after the other.

“It is late, Adelheid,”he said.“We had better go.”

“Yes,”she said.

But neither of them was able to.

They looked at each other and sat steeped in the same thoughts, afraid to end this still night, which was to be followed by bad days.

Then the last candle went out.

Cordt's lamp still burnt on the table, but it was as though everything in the room was displaced in its glow. There wasdarkness where light had been before and great shadows on the wall.

They both felt it as something uncanny and involuntarily moved closer together.

“Sing to me, Adelheid,”he said.

She went to the spinet and sat down and looked at the keys.

“Sing the last of the Lenore songs.”

She looked over her shoulder, but could not see the expression on his face.

Then she sang:

When death comes, come, Lenore, too:
Thou wert Life's beacon rosy-red;
And, by those glad, great eyes shot through,
In that same instant, Death were dead.
So am I never Death's, but thine;
No tears shed I, nor once complain:
Set only thy red lips to mine
And take thy soul again.

I shall have seen for the last time
The radiant, loving eyes I treasure;
And what of song and what of crime
I wrought let others weigh and measure.
But thou sometimes wilt not forget,
When evening creeps across the pane,
The scent of shy blue violet
That sweetened all the plain.

Cordt was standing behind her chair when the song was fnished. She did not perceive it, but sat with her hands on the keys and softly repeated the last lines.

He looked at her hair and her hands and at the white dress that hung over her shoulders and her lap. He knew as he had never known before what he had lost and knew that he would never win it back. His hands trembled, his eyes burned. He thought that he must kill her and himself.

Then he spoke her name.

She looked up and looked at him.

She forgot everything, saw nothing but him. He could see it in her great, strange eyes and in her red mouth.

And she sprang up with a cry of happiness and he took her in his arms and carried her away.

Chapter 11

The candles on the mantelpiece were lighted and their gleam fell through the balcony-door over the square, as it had done every evening since the house was built.

Outside, the square shone with a thousand lights. There was a sound of carriages, but at a distance, for the house was thrust a long way back and its walls were as thick as the walls of a castle.

And, when time passed and night came, the noise died away and you could hear the rippling of the fountain, which never begins and never stops, and cries, no one knowing what they are, solitary steps that approach and retreat again.

Cordt stood by the freplace of the empty room.

He stared at the places where the quaint old things had stood which had seen his race pass through the room.

He remembered every single piece that had been brought there and looked at the empty spot where each had stood. He closed his eyes and saw everything in its place again…the spinet sang…Fru Adelheid's white train rustled over the carpet.

He thought of the man who had built the house and the room and who had called it the soul of the house and its tradition and its secret chamber. Of all those after him who had brought their wives in here…of the day when he himself stood in the room for the frst time.

And he went and opened the secret recess in the wall which hid the old, yellow document on which each of them who took possession of the room had written his name and his wife's.

He read the report of the builder of the house, with its plain, homely phrases.

And, when he had read it and read it again, he struck out his own name and Fru Adelheid's and went away and left the door open behind him.

Chapter 12

When Cordt had fnished telling the story of the old room, he sat by the window and looked across the square, where the dusk was gathering about the newly-lighted lamps.

The servant entered noiselessly and lit the chandelier and went out noiselessly again. And the light flled the whole of the room and fell upon Cordt, who sat and gazed before him, and upon Finn, who stood by him with his eyes fxed on his face.

But Finn and Cordt were not where the light found them.

They were in the wonderful mystery of the old room. They heard the rippling of the fountain outside in the silent square; they saw the blaze of the red fowers on the balcony. The slender notes of the spinet sounded in their ears; Fru Adelheid's white gown rustled over the foor.

And, when Cordt turned his face towards his son, he appeared to Finn as a very big, old man; and Finn seemed to Cordt the little child that once lay and laughed in the cradle and fought with its little fat fsts.

Then Cordt stood up and took Finn's arm and they walked to and fro, silent, overcome with what they had seen and afraid lest they should shatter the dream by speaking.

They walked for some time. And, when, at length, they stopped before the window, which was dewed with the heat, so that theycould see nothing through it, Cordt remembered that there was still something which Finn ought to know and which he could not ask about.

He looked at Finn and remembered how he had loved his mother.

It was her eyes, but more restful-looking; her mouth, but paler and tired, as though it had tried a thousand times to say something which it never could. He had her slender waist and he was taller than Cordt, but carried his height like a burden. Then he also had Fru Adelheid's pale cheeks and forehead, but Cordt's hair, only thicker still and blacker.

“Finn,”said Cordt and laid his hands on his shoulders.

Finn started and could not look at him. But Cordt took him under the chin and lifted his head and looked with a sad smile into his frightened eyes:

“There is only one thing left to tell you, Finn…Fru Adelheid did not take a lover.”

His smile widened when he saw his son's sudden and great joy; and he drew him to him and kissed him.

But then he suddenly left him and sat down somewhere in the room, with his back to him. Finn followed him and stood by him for a while and thought kindly and fondly of him and could fnd nothing to say.

The thoughts rushed through Cordt's head.

Now that he had lived through it all anew, the scab broke which the silence of many years had placed upon the wound in his will. His eyes grew hard and angry, he wanted to speak as he used to speak when he fought his hopeless fght for Fru Adelheid.

But then his glance fell upon Finn.

He sat as he liked best to sit, with bent head and his hands open upon his knees.

And Cordt grew gentle again and said, softly:

“You are glad, of course. For, you see, she is your mother.”

He crossed the room and came back and stood with his arm over the back of the chair and looked at Finn, who was lost in his thoughts. It was silent in the room and silent outside, for it was Sunday. They could hear the bells ringing for evening service.

“She never secured the red flowers in the place of the blue which she valued so little,”said Cordt,“I don't know…I often thought…”

The bells rang out.

There was one that was quite close and one that was farther away, but louder, nevertheless. And there was a sound of distant bells which could not be distinguished from one another, but which sang in the air.

It sounded louder than it was, because they were thinking of it; and the ringing grew and flled the room with its deafening clamor.

Then there came a rumbling in the gateway. The carriage drove out in the soft snow, where they could not hear it.

“That's Fru Adelheid going to church,”said Cordt.

He sat down by his son and began to talk in a low voice and without looking at him.

The bells rang and then suddenly stopped and increased the silence a hundredfold.

“There was a night at Landeck when the bells caught her, a night following upon a day of sunshine and merriment and manypeople. She was the gayest of us all and, in the evening, all at once, she became silent and tired, as so often happened, without any cause that I knew of…. You were with us. You were ten years old then; you lay and slept. We had been standing together by your bed and looking at you and she began to cry and I could do nothing but hold her hand in mine and stop speaking.”

Finn listened, as he had just listened to the bells, without making out what the words had to tell him. He only knew that his mother was without blame and that his father had been able to tell it him all on that day and to leave it to him to pronounce judgment between himself and her. His joy at this sang within him and made all the rest easy and light and indifferent.

And Cordt continued:

“Then I went out on the verandah with my cigar and she stood in the doorway and listened to the bell of a little chapel up in the mountains, where we had been during the day. We had heard the story when we were there. Once, in the old days, a pious man had built the chapel in expiation of a sin and, since then, the bell had rung two hours after midnight every day…She asked whether it would go on ringing till the end of the world and we came to talk of all the bells that ring over the earth, by day and by night, sun up and sun down, and comfort weary mortals…. Sometimes she was silent. But the bell rang up there constantly. And she constantly began to talk again and constantly about the same thing. About the bells that sounded so eternally and so identically over the whole world…about those who heard them for the first time, one day when they were running like wild heathens in the endless wood…about those whose will suddenly broke in the midst of the modern crowd, so thatthey fell on their knees and crept away where the bells summoned them.”

Finn looked up. The words now caught his mind and he woke from his dreams.

“I see her before me still, as she stood on the night when she carried her soul to God. Her strange eyes lifted to the stars…her white face…her hands…and her words, which came so quickly, as though her life depended upon their coming, and so heavily, as though every one of them caused her pain. She never gave it a thought that I was there: she spoke as though she were doing public penance in the church-porch…. And then she declared that it was over…. It had become empty around her and cold and dark to anguish and despair, there where her glad eyes had beamed upon the lights and the crowd of the feast. Despair had come long since and slowly and she had closed her eyes to it and denied it. It had grown and come nearer to her and she had run away from it, as though she were running for her life. Now it was there and reached from earth to heaven, in her, around her, far and wide. And, if the bells could not conquer it, then she must die.”

Cordt spoke so softly that Finn could hardly catch his words.

“Then the bell up there ceased. Soon after, the day dawned and the sun shone on her white, moist cheeks. She was still now and silent, but her thoughts were the same. When things began to stir around us, in the town and at the hotel, she went out, I did not know where, but I daresay she was at the chapel. Towards evening, she returned and, at midnight, we sat on the verandah again and listened to the church-bell…. A week passed thus. I often feared for her reason. She always talked of the same thing and it was almost worsewhen she was silent. I sent old Hans home with you and, the next day, we left. But it was long before we reached home. She wanted to travel by the same road which we had taken on the journey out. She said she wanted to pray in every church which she had passed on her hunt for happiness through the world.”

Finn half raised himself in his chair:

“And did you?”he asked.

“I did as she wished. It became a pilgrimage to every region where life lies nakedest in its pleasure. Restlessly we travelled from place to place. She omitted none, afraid lest there should remain a single sin which she had not prayed away, a single memory which the bells had not rung into the grave.”

“And then did you come home?”

Cordt looked at his son as if he had forgotten that he was in the room. He suddenly awoke to the consciousness of what lay between those days and these; and his face became so gloomy and his eyes so serious that Finn was frightened.

“Then we came home. And then…”

He rose quickly and stood with his arms crossed on his breast and looked at Finn:

“Then we came home. And the years passed and Fru Adelheid recovered her peace of mind. She found herself again and became the same as in the old days. Her thoughts waver restlessly, her desires yearn insatiably. Her carriage now rattles through the streets as before…only it stops at the church instead of the theatre.”

Finn wanted to speak, but could not, because Cordt stood in front of him and looked at him fxedly and nodded to him, once, as if to say that he knew what it was and that it was no use.

“She goes to Heaven's table,”said Cordt,“and Heaven comes to her parties.”

Finn sank back in his chair.

He was surprised and ashamed that he was not grieved with his father for saying that, nor with his mother, if it were true. He knew that he ought to rouse himself to protest or sympathy, but could not, because he understood it all so well.

But Cordt crossed the room with a frm stride:

“Heaven is not what Fru Adelheid thinks, nor where she seeks it,”he said.“Perhaps you will not understand me until you have lived longer in the world; but look here, Finn…what I have seen of God in my life I have seen most in those who denied Him. In their sense of responsibility, in their humanity…in their pride I have seen God's splendor. The others, those who confess His name and fll His house…they masked Him from me so closely, when they ought to glorify Him, made Him so small, when they praised His might…”

He talked about this for a time. Finn sat dumb and helpless in his chair and wished his father would cease. He felt like one who has inadvertently witnessed something he ought not to see, or like one who is receiving a confdence under a false pretence.

And deep down within him lay a little ironical astonishment at the fre and authority with which his father was talking.

But, at that moment, Cordt sat down in front of him with both his hands in his own and sad and gentle eyes and words as soft and humble as though he were a sinner begging for peace:

“I don't know, Finn. I cannot really tell you anything about it. I can never talk with you about these things. A father is a poor creature, Finn, and I am a poor father. I cannot tell you that the forestis green and that the birds sing and that there is nothing behind the blue sky. I dare not, Finn. I do not think I have the right to. I cannot go to church with you, either…nor even be glad when you go with your mother.”

He pressed Finn's hands nervously. They lay dead in his and Finn did not know what to do with his eyes.

“But I must talk to you a little…just this once…to-day, when I have confessed to you and made up your parents' accounts. If you will try to understand me…and to forgive me…to forgive us, because we are not so rich as our child could expect…since we have a child…You love the bells, Finn. When they ring, you fall a-dreaming; they ring you far away from where you are. You were like that ever since you were a little boy. And I can well understand it. I love them, too. I am glad because they are there. But…Finn…Finn, there are so many bells in the world besides those which summon us to church. Every man has his own, which are his and his only…which he alone can hear, which call no one but him. There are men, opulent, charming men, for whom the bells ring wherever they set foot. They lead more powerful lives than we and prouder lives. They suffer us…those of us who love them. But there is not in the world a man so small but that the bells call him. One has them in his work, Finn. And one in his child…and one in his love. For one they hang in a neat little room where his mother lives and where he can only come for an hour, perhaps…on a Sunday…It is not the same for the one as for the other, Finn, but the bells are there always. They call their man back when he has strayed from the way he should go, or, if that is too late, they ring for his remorse. They ring to the banquet and they ring their music when he is tired andsad…But the church-bells…they ring for the man whose ears life has deafened…and life makes such a terrible noise. They ring on Sundays to remind us of that which we have forgotten throughout the week…. And it is well that they are there…. But…Finn…it is so tragic when the church-bells drive and tumble people together who once had each his own sacred church. It is just as when a home breaks up and the old fnd a refuge in the workhouse. The sun shines through the windows and it is warm indoors and there are fowers in the casement. But there was once something that was better…For your mother and me, Finn…for us the bells used to ring in the old room.”

He was silent and no longer looked at Finn. And Finn was at ease again and at last found words for what he had long wanted to say:

“May I use the old room, father ? May I set it up again…all as it was…and live there with my books ?…”

Cordt released his son's hands and his face wore a look that made Finn regret his request. They both rose to their feet. And, at that moment, Cordt's face lit up with a smile:

“That you may,”he said.“You dear child, who never asked for anything. Let this, then, be my present to you today.”

This happened on the day when Cordt's son completed his twenty-frst year.

Chapter 13

Finn stood in the old room with the yellow document in his hand:

God brought me thus far, that I was able to erect this fair house, which shall stand till distant times, a witness to my might and that of my race. Here shall be upright living and generous dealing; the house shall be faithfully guarded from father to son; good men and women shall sit in the hall and dance to the sound of flutes and violins.

I have placed this room in the most secret part of the house and no one knows of it but the architect who built it and my oldest servant. But I have sealed the architect's tongue with a solemn oath and a heavy fee; and my servant is true to me.

I have decorated the room with gilt and figured leather hangings and costly carpets from the East. I have had two great armchairs made in Milan, whose woodwork is carved into birds and animals which grin strangely in the dark, but cease to do so when the lights are lit.

Then I gave my servant a key of the room and told him to care for it faithfully. Every evening, when it grows dusk, he is to light the candles on the mantelpiece; and he is to do this even if he know that his master is travelling in distant lands. Every morning, he is to adjust the room with his own hands. None but himself is ever to cross the threshold.

For this room shall be for me and my wife and for none other in the world. Therefore I placed it in the most secluded part of the house, far from the counting-house, where we work, from the passages, along which our servants go, and from the drawing-room, where we receive our guests, ay, even from our marriage-bed, where she sleeps by my side.

It shall be the temple of our marriage, hallowed by our love, which is greater than anything that we know. Here we will pray to Him Who gave us to each other. Here we will talk gladly and earnestly, every evening when our hearts impel us to. And, when we come to die, our son shall bring his wife here and they shall do as we did.

This evening, which is the first in my new house, I brought my wife in here and told her my wish. She listened to my words in love and gladness and I have written down in this document how it all happened and we have set our names to it in witness for those who come after us.

Finn read their names and the names of those who had taken possession of the room after the builder and his wife. Last of all stood Cordt's name and Fru Adelheid's, which were struck out again.

Then he put the document back in its place and locked it up andlooked round the room.

The old room stood again as it used to stand, built high over the square, long and deep and silent, like a spot where there is no life.

The balcony was white with snow and the sparrows hopped in the snow. Inside, behind the colored panes, stood many red fowers and longed for the sun. The dust had been removed from the fgured-leather hangings, which shone with a new brightness. The oriental carpet spread over the foor like a lord returning from exile and once more taking possession of his estates.

And all the old glories had found their places again and stood as lawfully and restfully as though it had never been otherwise. The spinet was there and the jar with the man writhing through thorns and the celestial globe whose stars shone and ran: all the furniture which the room's different owners had set there in the course of time, each after his own taste and heart.

Before the freplace stood the two great, strange armchairs.

Finn felt as if he were in a cathedral where every flag was a tombstone over a famous man. His senses drank the odor of the bygone times, his fancy peopled the room with the men and women who had sat there and exchanged strong and gentle words, while the house lay sleeping around them.

With it all, he became lost in thought of those who had sat there last and after whom no others were to come, those two who had given him the life which he knew not what to do with.

He saw them before him in the love and struggle of their youth. He heard their voices in the room, he saw Fru Adelheid's red mouth and Cordt's steady eyes. He saw Cordt bring his wife into the room, which was the soul of the house and its tradition and its secretchamber, and show her the strange things which his ancestors had put there.

He saw him on the day when he stood alone by the freplace…in the empty room…and struck out his own name and Fru Adelheid's from the document and went away and left the door open behind him…

He saw all this as it had happened. But they were not his father and mother. They were two attractive people of whom he had read in a book and grown fond, as a man loves art, palely and with no self-seeking in his desire.

Finn drew one of the big chairs over to the window and sat down and sat there for long.

He was sitting there when Fru Adelheid came.

She stood in the doorway, in her white gown, with her white hair, and nodded to him. Then she turned her face round to the room and looked at it.

And then that happened which was only the shadow of a dream that vanished then and there: everything came to life in the room.

The spinet sang, the queer faces on the old chairs raised themselves on their long necks; there was a whispering and a muttering in every corner…

Fru Adelheid shrank back against the door. She did not see Finn, did not remember that he was there.

But Finn saw her.

He rose from his chair and his eyes beamed:

“You light up the room, mother,”he said,“and the room lights up you.”

He took her hand and kissed it and, with her hand in his, FruAdelheid went through the old room, which had been too narrow for her youthful desires.

The fairy-tale was over and the dread. But the glow still lay over her figure and made her look wonderfully pretty. Her cheeks were as pink as a girl's; her step was light, her eyes moist and shy. She laughed softly and gladly, while she looked at the old things and talked about them and touched them.

She told the story of the woman who used to sing when she was sad and who had brought the old spinet there; and her hands shook as she struck a chord and the slender, beautiful notes sounded through the room. Of the spinning-wheel, which had whirred merrily every evening for many a good year and which stood as it was, with thread upon the spindle. Of the celestial globe, which had been the toy of the man whose intellect was obscured. Of the doll with the vacant face, which stood there in memory of the lady who dreaded the deep silence of the room and never entered it but once; but her son, who loved her, had hidden the doll in the curtain. Of Fru Lykke, whose portrait had hung where the light stain was, but hung there no longer, because her marriage had been dissolved.

Of the jar with the man writhing through thorns, which she herself had brought as her gift, she said nothing. She passed her hand over its bright surface and was silent.

Finn's eyes clung to her.

Never had he seen his beautiful mother so beautiful. He did not know that look, or that smile on her mouth, or that clear ring in her voice.

At times, he added something to what she was telling and spoke with such profound intelligence that she was quite surprised andfrightened. Now he guessed her words before she uttered them. Then he knew something which she had never suspected.

Secretly, her fear increased as to what Cordt could have told him.

But Finn was lost in his delight.

And, fascinated by her beauty and the strange things he had seen and heard and the deep silence of the room, he forgot that the seal of the old room was broken and wished to play the game as vividly as possible.

He drew the second of the two big chairs across to the window and made her sit down and sat himself beside her:

“Now you are not my mother,”he said.“You are my young bride. I have brought you into the sanctuary to-day and now I will initiate you into the mysteries.”

Fru Adelheid turned very pale and Finn took her hand penitently:

“Have I hurt you, mother?”

She shook her head and forced herself to smile.

Then he walked into the room again and rejoiced at all this and talked about it. But she remained sitting with knitted brow.

She was heavy at heart, because it seemed to her, all at once, that she was not his mother, as they sat talking here in the secret chamber of the house. The old days came in their great might; and their strong memories and impressive words drowned the bells which had rung her into another world.

It was the echo here, in the old room, of Cordt's words and of his love…of the strong faith and great happiness of the race which had sprouted in the good mould of tradition and produced flowerafter fower in the times that passed.

Fru Adelheid thought—for a moment—that it would have been well had things happened as Cordt wished.

But, at the same instant, she was seized by a thought that suddenly made her rebellious and young, as when she was here last, many years ago.

She thrust her chair back hard and looked with sparkling eyes round the room where everything and every memory was hostile to her.

She looked at Finn, who was standing by the celestial globe and trying to set it going, but could not, because the spring was rusty and refused to work.

She wondered, when the time came for Finn to take a wife…would he try to revive the tradition and bring her here and sit down with her in the old chairs?

Then Finn's son and his son after him would read her name, which was written on the yellow document and struck out again. She would be like one of those who were branded in that family…Legends would grow about her love of going out and her hunt after happiness which did not exist….

“Come and help me, mother,”said Finn.

She went over and pressed hard on the spring and the clockwork hummed.

“See how you let loose the magic,”he said.

He went on talking, delighted with the stars, which lit up and ran.

“Sit down here by me, Finn.”

She waited till he came and a little longer, as though she couldnot find the words she wanted, and did not look at him while she spoke:

“Finn,”she said and put her hand on his shoulder and drew it away again immediately.“Finn…once…ever so many years ago, I was alone, one evening, in the old room. I had often been here before, you know…with father. And I was under the power of the old room and never happy. I was young, Finn, and it went so terribly hard with my longing and my gladness. I could not understand that and could not mitigate it or get over it. For father belonged to the room and it was his and all the queer things in it and they were all against me. Every time I came to the door, my heart stopped beating…. And once I was inside…it was…it was as if my own words were taken from my tongue and others put in their place for me to speak…beautiful words and good words, Finn, but not mine. But then, when I took courage and said what I wanted to say, it sounded as if I was defying the old room and father and God himself. And then . . .”

Fru Adelheid felt that she was on the point of betraying something great and fne that had been laid in her hands. She looked round as if she were afraid that there was some one in the room or that the room itself would rise up against her in its venerable might.

But there was no one and it was silent.

Then she turned her face to Finn and looked at him and said, gaily:

“But that evening, Finn, I broke the spell of the old room. I tore the veil from the Holy of Holies and saw that there was nothing behind it. For the frst time, I breathed freely in my own home.”

Fru Adelheid did not tell how, at the same moment, she hadbeen overcome by terror and fled from the room. But she did not gain what she thought by her lie. For Finn looked at her sorrowfully and said:

“How could you do that, mother? How could you fnd it in your heart?”

“Are you also under the spell?”she asked.

There was in her tone a scorn which was stronger than she intended and which frightened herself. But Finn simply paid no attention to it:

“The old room no longer exists,”he said.“It is nothing more than an image, a monument…my fancy, which father humored me in.”

She turned her face away and listened.

“But had I lived in the days of the old room,”he said,“then it would certainly have captured me and held me captive.”

“Yes…you have been talking to father,”she said, softly.

“Yes.”

Then he lay down before her, with his cheek on her hand, as he so often did:

“Yes,”he repeated.“And…mother…I love you. You are so pretty. But we will not talk about the old room…ever. For I think it is the most wonderful…and the most beautiful and the strongest thing I know of.…But it hurts me that I am not wholly your son…or father's either, that I might devote myself to one of you in sharing your strongest feelings. And I cannot talk to father about it…neither can we two, can we?”

Fru Adelheid did not answer him, but stroked his hair with her hand. Neither of them spoke and it was quite silent in the room.

In the silence she became herself again. The many moulded years came to their own again and the bells rang monotonously and ever more strongly from out of the noise of the world, which had drowned them.

She marvelled at the excitement into which the old room had thrown her. Quenched was the love which had made her its mistress and quenched the red desire which made it too narrow. She thought of Cordt, who had fought, she considered, for what was not worth fighting for. Sorrowfully she looked at her tall, silent boy, whose weary thoughts kept pace so well with her own.

She crossed her hands in her lap and the light faded in her eyes. The glow of the old room withdrew from her face, her words became restful as her thoughts.

Finn looked at her, but did not see this. For him, too, the fairy-tale was over. He was sitting in his chair again with bent head and his hands open on his knees.

And, without their doing anything or thinking of it, they came in their usual way to talk together. It was not any interchange of thoughts and still less a contest of opinions. They said nearly the same thing and, wherever the thoughts of the one roamed, he found the other's. Often their words were solemn, but never powerful. Often the one was silent and agreed with the other. Many times they sat long without saying anything and thought they had told each other everything.

“Look,”said Finn, pointing out of the window.“How hideous!”

A hearse came trotting across the square.

He moved in his chair and said:

“A hearse should always drive at a foot's pace, solemnly andceremoniously…always…as though they were only driving the horses to water. And soldiers should always hold themselves stiff and starched, keeping step and time, even when they are taking their shoes to the cobbler's. Then it would all be easier.”

He was silent for a while. Then he slowly turned his face to her:

“I was talking about it to father the other day,”he said.“I happened to say something of the kind.”

She looked at him in surprise.

“I don't know how it came about. But he laughed and said I ought to write an article about it or form a society for preserving the correct pace of hearses.”

Fru Adelheid smiled and laid her hands in her lap and looked at them.

“Then he suddenly became serious and came up to me and laid his hands on my shoulders:‘Hearses ought to drive fast,’ he said,‘gallop…at a rousing pace. Away with the dead, Finn! Let life grow green and blossom !’”

“Father is so masterful,”said Fru Adelheid.

Finn nodded.

Then they began to talk about Cordt. They often did so. And they were always eager to find good words to praise him in. But under the words there lay the consciousness, like a secret understanding between them, that he was made of a coarser clay than they.

They never said this; but they felt a sort of patronizing pity for him, such as one feels for a person who runs and runs, when it is good to sit still.

But, when they talked together, Fru Adelheid knew that deepin Finn's soul there lay a secret yearning towards just that masterful side in his father which frightened him.

It was so weak, only a pale refection of her own young love, a distant echo of the voice which had stated Cordt's case in her own heart when he was fghting to win her.

But it was enough to hurt her. She thought she only had her son for a time. She traced a certain disdain in the intimacy to which he admitted her. She thought there was something in him which was greater than what he gave her and which was Cordt's or would become so.

And she realized that the fght for Finn would become harder than that which broke the seal on the door of the old room.

Finn was absorbed in what had flled his mind, the whole day, with light and color. He was thinking now of his mother's visit to the room on the evening when she had broken the spell:

“I simply cannot understand how you could have the heart,”he said.

She knew at once what he meant, but said nothing.

“There ought to be some law, like that in the fairy-story, where he who lifted the veil had to die,”he said.“And there ought to be veils upon veils…veils upon veils…Can you bear to look at the sun, mother? Women ought to go in a veil and never…never raise it, except when the occasion was so great that everything grew great.…And one ought not to see the people who play…”

Fru Adelheid half raised herself in her chair.

She wanted to tell him that, on that evening, she was punished for her presumption with the greatest terror which she had ever experienced in her life. But she could not. Then she said, quitequietly and with her eyes looking out over the square:

“And suppose there were some one who could not…suppose the veil stifed one…”

Finn looked out into space like her:

“Veils upon veils.…Veils over the dead,”he said.

Fru Adelheid sighed and said nothing.

“Then one could live,”said Finn.

Chapter 14

From that day onward, Finn only left the old room when obliged.

The spring had opened the fountain before the house and he was happy at its rippling, which never began and never stopped. The red fowers were put out on the balcony: when the wind blew, their petals fluttered right over into the basin of the fountain and rocked upon the water. He followed their dance through the air and wondered if they would reach their goal.

His best time was in the evening, when the square shone with a thousand lights.

He loved the dying day.

He knew every light that went out, every sound as it stopped. And he liked the sound best when it stopped and the light when it went out. He thought that the people who moved down below, disguised in the darkness, were of another kind or better than those whom the sun shone upon. He had no more to do with them than with the others; but he liked them better.

Then, when night came and the rippling of the fountain sang louder and louder through the silence and cries sounded from down below, no one knowing what they were, and solitary steps were heard, that approached and retreated again, then he lit the candles on the mantelpiece and sat down in one of the old chairs, there where the owners of the house and their wives had sat when the house sleptand they had something to say to each other.

He looked round the room, where the things sang in every dark corner, and simply could not conceive that he had not known the old room before.

He was more at home here than anywhere else: here, where he was outside the world, which worried him, because it demanded that of him which he had not; here, where every spot and every object told how all had been said and done and accomplished in the old days, so that he had nothing else to do but listen wonderingly and rejoice at its marvellous beauty.

Then he fell a-dreaming and remained sitting till the lights went out.

“He does not sleep enough,”said Fru Adelheid, anxiously.

Cordt crossed the foor with the same thought in his mind. Then he stopped where she was sitting and looked at her:

“I wonder, is he ever awake, Adelheid?”he said.

By day, Finn generally sat at the window and stared out, idly and silently, with his hands open on his knees.

Often, when Cordt was crossing the square, he thought that he could see Finn's old face behind the window-panes. He would stop and nod and beckon to him.

But Finn never saw him. For he saw nothing positively.

And Cordt went on…in and out…constantly longing to see the strong air of the old room color his son's cheeks and rouse his will…constantly trusting that, sooner or later, this would happen.

He never went up there since the day when he and his old servant had arranged the room as it used to be.

And Finn was glad of this. He was so afraid lest that shouldhappen that a long time passed before he could suppress his terror when he heard any one coming. And, even when he had recovered his composure, he knew that it would happen sooner or later and that the day of its happening would be a gloomy one.

For he well understood the eternal loving question in Cordt's eyes and it hurt him and frightened him. He dreaded the craving in his affection, which was greater than a father's. It was like that of a sovereign for the heir who is to occupy the throne after him.

And Finn could not take the reins of empire in his slack hands or bear the pressure of the crown upon his head, which ached at the mere thought of it.

But Fru Adelheid often came; and they two were comfortable up there, in the old room.

She came with no craving; and, if she was doubtful and restless, as she often was, since Finn had moved up into the old room, then she would be quite silent when the door closed behind her.

Silent like Finn…and like the big chairs and the jar with the man writhing through thorns…silent like the spinning-wheel, which had whirred merrily every evening for many a good year and stood as it was with thread upon its spindle.

He looked at her and smiled and nodded when she spoke. He himself talked . . .for long at a time and then stopped, without its making any difference, and listened to the rippling of the fountain and the voices in the old room, which always talked to him and plainest when Fru Adelheid was with him.

He told her that, when she came, the room was no longer his own.

For then he felt like a stranger, a man of another period, who should suddenly find himself in an old ruined castle, full of marvellous dangers and adventures, and stand face to face with the last of those who had lived the castle's rich, wonderful life.

Once he spoke her name aloud just as she was entering at the door. It was dark in the room and his voice and fgure were so like Cordt's that she grew pale and frightened. But he did not see this and she forced a laugh and soon forgot it.

And, gradually, the wonderful solemnity of the old room retreated into the background, when they were both there, for they spent more and more of their time there and at last simply did not think they were together except there. But Finn was always able to summon it up when he wished.

They used to read together.

And that happened in this way, that one of them found a book, a treasure of silence and singing, which was the only sort that they felt equal to, and read it and gave it to the other, who then read it while they were together.

They found most of the books in foreign languages and it seemed as if there were no end of them. Also, the fact that the language was foreign made the book dearer to them, because it carried them farther afeld.

When they had read one of these books, they lived in it for a time…not in its action, among its characters, for there was no action and no characters, but in its music. They tuned their thoughts and words in its key.

Then they felt as if they had passed through some experience or as if they were travelling.

“The artist lives,”said Finn.“He makes the sky blue and grey for himself…for himself and for us all. He wipes everything outwith his hand and builds it up again…greater, ever greater. He is the master. He is God.”

One day, he asked Fru Adelheid to sing.

She had not sung for many years, except in church, and was surprised at his request:

“I have given up singing, Finn.”

He lay down before her and looked up smiling into her face:

“I can remember so well when you used to sing,”he said.“You often sang to me when I was a boy. But one occasion…one occasion I remember in particular. There were many visitors and I, of course, had long been in bed, but I was not asleep. For old Marie had promised to take me down to the dining-room when the people had got up from dinner and you were to sing. She told me that, when there was company and all the candles were lighted and you were prettiest and brightest, then you sang a thousand times more beautifully than usual.”

She took her eyes from his face and laid her head back in her chair.

“I kept awake till she came and it lasted long. But then I heard you and also saw you for a moment through the door.”

“And was it so nice?”

“I don't remember,”he said.“But I remember the many faces.…I should know them again if I saw them now, I think. And best of all I remember father's.”

Fru Adelheid rose:

“What shall I sing?”she asked.

He laughed with content, went to the spinet and opened it. Then he took up one of the pieces of music:

“Look what I have found,”he said.“This was sung by the onewho put the spinet here. Look, here is her name: she herself wrote both the words and the music.…See how pale the writing is…and how distinct.”

Fru Adelheid stood with the old, yellow sheet in her hand. She hummed the tune and struck the keys.

Then she sat down to the spinet and sang:

Day is passing, dearest maiden:
Ere thou knowest, comes the night;
Warning winds, with fragrance laden,
Bring cool air and colder light.
We must part: time hastens so!
Day is passing, dew is falling.
Hark! Thy mother's voice is calling:
Dearest maiden, I must go.

Part we must, dear maid, in sorrow!
Day is surely doomed to die.
Ah, but we shall find to-morrow
Countless joys we let go by,
Countless words we uttered not,
Hours we robbed of wasted chances,
Eyes we balked of mutual glances,
Countless kisses we forgot.

Happy smiles will haunt thee dreaming
On a couch of virgin white;
In my brain thy picture gleaming,
I shall hasten through the night.
Let the crimson sun depart!
Brighter sunshine in thy face is,
Sunshine of remembered places,
Love's own sunshine in thy heart.

She remained sitting a while with the old music-sheet in her hand. Then Finn said:

“She used to sing that. Do you know if she was happy, mother?”

“She was often sad,”said Fru Adelheid.“And, when she was sad, she sang.”

She put down the sheet and took up the first music-book that came to hand, but threw it aside, as though it had burnt her fngers.

It was the Lenore songs, which she had sung to Cordt.

She rose and went back to her place beside Finn. Then she sprang up and stood with her arms crossed on her breast and sat down again and stared with great eyes through the window:

“Finn…if I sang it to you…would you recognize the…the song you heard when Marie carried you down…?”

He woke from his dream and looked at her in surprise:

“The song…no…I should not. Why, do you remember it?”

“No,”said Fru Adelheid.

They long sat silent. Twilight fell and it grew dark in the room.

“Mother,”said Finn,“what are women like?”

She turned her face slowly towards him. He did not look at her. His eyes were far away and she realized that he had forgotten his question or did not know that he had put it.

Chapter 15

Fru Adelheid stood in her wraps at the window and looked out. The horses were stamping in the porch below; the footman stood by the carriage-door and waited.

They were going to the station to fetch Finn.

He had been abroad the whole summer.

This was the frst time he had been away alone and he had not enjoyed himself abroad. From Florence, Spain and Paris he had written to ask if he might not come home. But Cordt was resolved that he should remain abroad for the time agreed upon.

He wrote oftenest to Fru Adelheid…and stupidly and awkwardly, because he knew that his father would read the letters. Cordt noticed this, but said nothing. He hurried through the letters as though he were looking for something positive and put them down with a face as though he had not found it.

He always gave Fru Adelheid the letters he received, although she never asked for them.

Fru Adelheid looked impatiently at her watch. She sat down, closed her eyes and pressed her forehead against the pane.

She thought how empty the house had been during the summer.

Cordt had not said a word about the old room, but, from the day when Finn had moved up there, things had altered between him and her. Something had happened…something indefnite and nameless, but none the less fateful on that account.

And, while Finn was abroad, this had grown between them…without their doing anything to further or prevent it. Neither of them thought about it. Both led their own lives and drifted farther apart in their yearning for their quiet child. The day was long for them, their rooms were cold.

But inside her was a growing anxiety for Cordt, who became ever more silent and wore such a melancholy look in his eyes.

A door opened and she sprang up:

“We shall be late, Cordt.”

“Not at all,”he said, calmly.“You ordered the carriage too early.”

“Let us go, Cordt. We may just as well wait there as here.”

Cordt sat down with his hat on his knee and looked at her. She stood with bent head and buttoned her gloves.

“Sit down for a moment,”he said and pushed a chair towards her.

“Do you want to talk to me?”

“Sit down, Adelheid,”he said, impatiently.“Sit down for a moment.”

Fru Adelheid leant against the chair and remained standing.

“It is long since we talked together, Adelheid…many, many years. Do you know that?”

She shrugged her shoulders:

“Very likely,”she said and made her voice as frm as she could.“We have peace now, you see.”

Cordt nodded. He drummed with his fingers on his hat andlooked out of the window:

“Yes…yes, no doubt. We are old, Adelheid. As old as can be.”

“Is that what you wanted to say to me?”

“I am afraid for Finn,”said Cordt.“He will come home as pale as when he went away, a poor dreamer by the grace of God. To-morrow, he will be sitting up there and staring out at the life he dare not live.”

“Yes…why should he be up in the old room?”

“It was he who asked me,”said Cordt, calmly.“I could not deny him his inheritance. He has the right to know the ground he sprang from.”

“And what then? Do you think you can bring the dead days to life again?”

“No,”he said.“I don't think that. I don't want that.”

He was silent for a little. She did not take her eyes from his face. Then he said:

“Finn can build himself a new house, if he likes. Or he can refurnish his ancestral halls. And put in plate-glass windows and wide staircases and anything that suits him and his period. But he must know and be thankful that the walls are strong and the towers tall.”

Fru Adelheid pushed back the chair she was leaning against:

“There does not appear to be room for a mother in your arrangement,”she said.

Her voice trembled, her eyes were large and angry. But Cordt rose and looked as calm as before:

“You went out of it, Adelheid. You did not wish to be there.”

She made no reply. She understood that he did not mean toconsult her, to ask her for her help…did not even want it.

“Adelheid…now that Finn is coming…”

“Yes?…”

“I am afraid for him, Adelheid. And I would ask you to be on your guard and do him no harm. I believe that sometimes you smother his poor, dejected spirit. The peace which you have gained may be good in itself and good for you…but he is young, you must remember. He is only at the start of life, he has no need for peace and resignation. What is a boon to you is death to him, perhaps…”

She took a step forward and raised her face close up to his:

“Now it has come to this, Cordt, that you think I am your enemy for Finn's sake.”

“You may become so,”he said.

“You will drive me to it, Cordt.”

He took her hand and held it tight when she tried to draw it away:

“No,”he said.“No, Adelheid. I only want to warn you.”

Chapter 16

The balcony-door was standing open, because they had forgotten to close it. But the weather was mild and there was hardly any wind. Now and again, a yellow leaf fell somewhere or other from the baluster. It began to grow dusk.

Fru Adelheid sat with her head in her hands and stared out before her.

Cordt's words kept ringing in her ears. She did not think either that Finn was as he used to be. He was restless, could not sit still, talked more than usual:

“Wherever I went, I found the fountain outside,”he said.“It followed me throughout my journey. There was not a rushing noise so strong but the fountain sounded through it nor a night so still but it came rippling and sang me home again to the old room.…I wonder, did one of the owners of this house set it up?”he asked.

“I don't think so.”

“Yes,”said Finn.“That must be it. I am sure of it. Perhaps it was the one who built the house. You see, it forms part and parcel of the old room…it sums it all up. If there was nothing else but the fountain, it would all be here just the same. I must ask father.”

She shivered with cold and Finn shut the door:

“We are chilly people,”he said.“Both of us. We are not like father. He laughed at me yesterday when I came down to his roomto say good-morning and wanted to shut the window.‘Don't, Finn,’ he said.‘The autumn air is bracing and healthy, it makes one young again…sit in the draught and don't be afraid, old man that you are!’”

“Yes, father is strong.”

Finn looked at her stealthily.

He had soon understood that his parents had drifted apart while he was abroad; and he suffered in consequence. He was as kind and affectionate to his mother as ever; but his thoughts were always harking back to Cordt, whatever they might be talking of:

“Father is so sad,”he said.

“I haven't noticed it.”

She colored after saying this. But Finn was not looking at her, scarcely heard her reply:

“It was strange, mother…out there, on my journey, ever so many times I had a feeling that I came upon father. Wherever I went, I would suddenly hear his voice…then he would be close to me, I walked with him, regulated my step by his and talked to him.”

He laid his head back in his chair and closed his eyes:

“Often it was as if he had been where I came and prepared everything for me, so that I saw him in every corner. Sometimes I felt that I must put off my departure until he came.”

“And did he come?”

“Always. Wasn't that strange?”

“Yes.”

Fru Adelheid thought the sound of his voice was different from ordinary. He did not look at her, as he was used to do…his thoughts were not with her.

“Where were you and father to-day?”she asked.

“We went out into the woods…a long way out. Father was silent, but not so bored as at home. It was so lovely out there…and so strange. One could hardly see a thing…for the leaves falling.”

“Yes,”said Fru Adelheid.

Then she bent over him to look into his face, which had grown thinner and paler during the time that he was away:

“Finn,”she said,“was I not with you…out there…when you were travelling?”

Finn smiled and nodded his head:

“You came in your letters,”he said.“That father never did. But you were mostly here at home, where I was longing to be.”

She thought it was strange that he did not take her hand when he said that.

And, suddenly, she became conscious that she was sitting in terror lest he should slip away from her.

What had she to hold him with, if anything seized him that was stronger than their quiet life in these hours…what had she, if he went…?

It seemed to her as though Cordt stood in the room and beckoned him out into the yellow woods, where the air was so bracing and good. And Finn leapt up with a joyful cry…they went away…and never looked back.…

She felt that Cordt was stronger than she and hated him for it. She sought for a weapon to defend herself. She wished that Finn, who loved her, would lie down before her, as he so often used to do, with his cheek against her hand. And she knew that he was not thinking of it.

She felt so wretched and so lonely that she grew frightened and called upon her old longing for the red happiness…if only it would come and take her, so that she might have something to set against him who had everything.…

“Sing to me, mother,”said Finn.

“Yes,”she said.

She crossed the room with a stronger step than usual. Her cheek was red and her eyes glowed. She took hold of the instrument with frm hands when she opened it. Finn noticed this and looked at her in surprise; but it was not light enough for him to make out her face.

Lovs't thou the peasant in his cosy cottage-nook ?
Thou shalt share bed and board with him, eating and sleeping;
Thou shalt tranquilly brew and merrily cook;
Dusty wheel, rusty needle thy care shall not brook;
Thou shalt bless sun and rain in God's keeping.
But she that loves none shall go weeping!

Lovs't thou the poet with harp all of gold?
Thou shalt list to his song o'er the loud strings sweeping;
Thou shalt meet him, where flowrets peep from the wold;
By thy smiles shall his going and coming be told,
His mind in thy joyfulness steeping.
But she that loves none shall go weeping!
Lovs't thou the lordling, who hunts in the grove?
Thou shalt sue to thy mother and fly from her keeping;
Thou shalt give him thy lips and give him thy love;
Thou shalt take, as he flings horse or hound from above,
Blows, fame and food flung to thee creeping.
But she that loves none shall go weeping!

Fru Adelheid remained sitting with bowed head.

The song had broken her pride. She trembled over all her body and great tears fell upon her hands. She had conjured up spirits which she could not lay; she felt more powerless and small than she had ever felt before.

She began to think of Finn and looked round in alarm. But he could not see her and she wept silently. She laid her forehead against the spinet…then her hand fell upon the keyboard and she started and rose from her seat.

“That was a strange song,”said Finn.

It was so still in the room that she could not bear it.

“I have not sung it for many years,”she said.“In the old days, I used to sing it often.”

“What was father like when you met him?”asked Finn.

She stood with her back to him and turned the pages of the music with trembling hands.

“Was he as handsome as now?”

“Yes…no.…I don't know if he was handsome.”

Finn listened.

“He was…he was charming.”

“That he was…that he was,”he said and clapped his hands like a child who is delighted with a story.“And then he was so masterful…was he not?…So that one was bound to follow him?”

“Yes,”said Fru Adelheid.

“Father was a king,”said Finn.

Her heart throbbed, she listened with all her senses. She felt that Finn was somewhere close to her and accomplishing something that would destroy her. And she could not turn round, could not go to him and beg him to desist.

“I could wish I had a brother,”said Finn.

“Do you feel lonely?”

“No…no, it is not that. But then he should have the kingdom.”

Chapter 17

At that time, Finn made a friend whom he had not chosen or wanted for himself, but whom Cordt gave him in his anxiety, because he thought he could never get any one better.

His name was Hans and they had known each other since they were children. He was a year older than Finn, not quite so tall, but more powerfully developed, with bright hair and eyes and disposition.

His father was a little man who sat among the people in the counting-house, where his father had sat before him. He and his little wife had no luck in life save their son. But at times they trembled for his future, because his ideas were so pronounced and took so wide a range.

For, even as he was taller than his father, so he would not be content with his measure in anything.

Above all, he did not want to sit in the offce, but to go out in the world, big as it was. And, from the time when he was a little boy, he believed that it was bigger than they told him.

Now that he had grown up and become conscious of his need and his powers and could not get anywhere, he went fearlessly to the master of the house and told him how the matter stood.

Cordt liked him and wanted to keep him for his house, but soon saw that he had nothing that could tempt him. He asked him what hewould like to be; and it appeared that Hans wanted to be an engineer.

Cordt looked at him and thought that his glance could blast rocks.

Then he promised his assistance and remained sitting in deep thought, while Hans went down the stairs singing.

Time passed. He advanced along his road and both he and the others could see that he was fully keeping pace with his dreams. Cordt did not lose sight of him and was pleased when he called. But Fru Adelheid did not like him, because he talked so loud and had such a heavy tread.

One evening, Cordt stood in Hans' room and talked to him as he had never talked to any one:

“I am your father's employer,”he said,“and my father was your grandfather's. My son will never be yours. For you mean to make your own way and be your own master. You would have done that even if no one had lent you a helping hand. That is true. But then you would have become bitter, perhaps, and distrustful and narrow-minded in the use of your strength. From this I delivered you. To-day, I come to ask for a return.”

Hans had taken the hand which he put out to him and stood ill at ease, without understanding. And Cordt sat down wearily and sat long without speaking further.

At last, he woke from his thoughts and looked at the young man, who could not interpret his glance, but was moved by it:

“I do not wish that you were my son,”he said.“I have a son and he is a good lad and I love him. He has not your strength of character, but then he does not need it. His path was smoothed and shaded from the day when he was born and grew up. But he can giveyou many things which you have not.”

He listened to his own words, to the way in which they kept on shaping themselves into an apology for Finn, a prayer for forbearance towards him. He suffered at this; and Hans, who saw his distress, felt, without understanding, that something important and tragic was taking place in this great house, where he and his had earned their living.

“Will you try if you can be his friend?”

Hans was quite willing.

Cordt looked at him and gauged his strength. He looked round in the little low-ceilinged room which contained nothing but what served Hans in his work. He looked out of the window, where the roofs intersected one another, dirty and grey against the sky: smoke rose from hundreds of chimneys, the noise of the courtyard and the street filled the room, the window was broken and pasted up with paper.

Then he again turned his eyes to the man who sat amidst these mean surroundings and grew up strong. And Cordt knew that he was not standing here as his benefactor and his father's employer, who was opening his rich house to him. He stood here as one who could beg and nothing more.

“You know you used to play together as children,”he said.

And, when he had said that, he was overcome with emotion, because he remembered that Finn had never played. Hans thought the same thing, but could not fnd the words that should be spoken on this occasion and the silence became heavy and painful to both of them.

To say something at all costs, Hans asked if Finn was ill.

Then Cordt understood that Hans must long since have pronounced his judgment on the pale, silent heir of the house and that the judgment could not be good.

He rose, tired of seeking for guarded phrases. He laid his hands on Hans' shoulders and looked at him in such a way that Hans never forgot it:

“Do you be David,”he said.“Come to us with your harp. And come of your own accord and come when we send for you.”

Chapter 18

The frst thing was that Finn had his former room arranged so that he and Hans could be there when Hans came to see him.

There was nothing said about it. For it was taken as a matter of course that no stranger should set foot in the old room. But Cordt at once thought that his hope in Hans was shattered.

Sometimes Finn was glad when Hans was there.

They could never talk together.

Hans' thoughts were constantly at work on plans and diffculties, the least of which seemed quite unsurmountable to Finn, and he had not the remotest idea as to what passed in his friend's brain. He talked to all men alike and his words were all questions or answers or opinions.

So it was Hans who spoke and, wholly taken up with himself as he was, he seldom noticed that Finn fell a-dreaming.

When Finn could get him to set to work on some calculation or other, he himself sat delighted and watched Hans while he struggled with fgures and drawings.

He was amused at Hans' wrinkled forehead, his eager, impatient movements. And he waited expectantly, like one sitting on a race-ground, or wherever else men are engaged in contest, for the shout with which the engineer would fling aside the pencil when the problem was solved.

Then Finn's face beamed with delight. He was as pleased as if it had been himself that had gained the triumph and he had no notion what sort of triumph it was or what it was worth.

But sometimes, and more and more frequently, Hans was too active, too restless for him.

There were days on which Finn hid when his friend called. Often, Hans' mere presence in the room occasioned him real bodily pain. He could feel half unconscious under his powerful glance, his voice, which was so loud and jolly, his words, which all meant something.

Then he sat tortured and wretched, because it was not possible for him to ask the other to go. And it was only seldom that Hans perceived this. When it did happen, there was no end to his awkward distress; and then Finn was not content before he had succeeded in persuading him that he was quite wrong.

Then Finn submitted, in the same way in which a hopeless invalid submits to a new cure which prepares new sufferings for him and in which he does not himself believe. And, while he suffered, he thought incessantly of his father, who suffered more than he did and whom he could not help.

His best time was when they were out together.

They drove and rode; and then they were never agreed, for Finn wanted to ride slowly and drive fast and Hans wanted just the opposite. They were always eager to accommodate themselves to each other, but this came to pass only when it was Finn's wish that prevailed.

Finn did not like going out. But, once he had started, he was glad; and then he always wanted to have Hans with him. He was shyin a crowd and his friend's presence reassured him.

They generally walked in the streets, for Finn felt cold if he went outside the town. Then he took Hans' arm and kept step with him and was proud of him. He liked to hear his strong voice through the noise of the street, his quick step, the tap of his stick on the pavement.

Then Finn would sometimes begin to talk.

Mostly of his travels. And he could speak of these almost as he thought and as he spoke to his mother. It was as though the life and the noise that half drowned his words made him feel freer and safer.

And, although Hans cared but little for what Finn had seen and talked about, still there was a color and a gleam about his words that captivated him.

But, when it happened that the noise in the street was suddenly stilled, then Finn was silent and frightened. And, if, for a moment, they were separated in the crowd and Hans failed to catch a sentence and asked him to repeat it, or seized upon some phrase and asked for a further explanation and confrmation, then Finn was forthwith tired and his mood changed.

He often stopped when a piece of street-life caught his attention. He pointed it out to his friend and made it the subject of his talk. Then Hans would underline his words with some racy observation or other, which amused Finn, but afterwards annoyed him, because it spoilt the picture for him.

They never talked about women.

Finn was silent, because his thoughts were vague and modest. And Hans' experiences were not of such a nature that he cared to talk about them. Then, also, they both had an instinctive feeling thatthey had less in common on this subject than on any other and that they did not wish ever to cross each other's path.

On one occasion only was Finn his friend's guest in his home.

It was a regular feast in the little rooms, high up under the roof, and Finn was glad to be there.

He looked in delight at the two little old people who stood and sat with folded hands and little bows and nods and did not know how to show their respect and gratitude to the young master of the house. They took it for granted, as a settled thing, that Finn must be vexed because Hans had broken with tradition and gone his own way and they made endless covert excuses for it.

And through the excuses rang their pride in the strong son whom they handled as cautiously as though he would fall to pieces if they took frm hold of him…their joyous dread of the greatness that awaited him.

Finn understood them and was touched by them. He sang his friend's praises and prophesied a preposterous success for him and was happy to read the gladness in the little parents' eyes.

And, while he was deep in conversation with them and amused at Hans, who was utterly confused that his friend should see the adoration of which he was the object, the picture of his own parents suddenly rose before his thoughts like great black silhouettes against the light background.

He stopped talking and then they all became silent and it was not pleasant in the room.

Afterwards, he stood with Hans and looked through the open window.

His eyes roamed over the hundreds of roofs. The sun shoneon the slates and the red tiles and lit up the telephone-wires. Little garret-windows stuck out on every side…with chintz curtains, with wall-fowers and geraniums and pelargoniums and yellow birds in white cages.

In one place there hung an elegantly-painted wooden box with ferns, which were quite brown, but stood proud and stiff, and a little fr-tree in the middle. In another, the curtain futtered right out into the air and waved and fapped like a fag. Here, two sparrows hopped about in the gutter…there, a caged bird was singing, shrilly and sweetly.

“How charming this is!”he said.

Hans did not exactly think so.

But, at that moment, Finn set eyes on a window a little to one side and so near that he felt as if he could reach across to it.

The window was open. There were fowers in it and there was a bird which hopped from perch to perch in its cage, silently and unceasingly. Behind the fowers sat a young girl sewing. He could see the back of her and a bit of her chin and hear the stitching of the sewing-machine:

“Look,”he said, in an undertone.

Hans came up and at once looked away again:

“That's Marie,”he said.“She's a seam-stress.”

There was nothing wrong either in the words or in the tone in which they were uttered. But he said it so loud and so carelessly that it hurt Finn. The girl opposite looked up and smiled.

Then something like a cloud passed over the whole picture, with the fowers and the bird and the sunny roofs. Finn sighed and came away from the window.

And, when they sat together at supper and had fnished eating, suddenly there fell upon him an insuppressible melancholy.

He looked from one to the other and read in their faces that they were subduing their gladness on his account. He imagined what it was like when the three were alone, busy and cheerful in their work and in their faith in one another.

And behind their kind words and smiles he felt the pity for their quiet guest. But he thought of this only as pity for Cordt and of himself as one who suffered blame.

Then he hurriedly took his leave.

Chapter 19

Hans and Finn were driving in the woods, when a little stray dog ran under the wheel and was badly hurt.

They both jumped out of the carriage. Hans knelt on the ground and took the gasping dog in his arms:

“Give me your pocket-handkerchief,”he said.

Not receiving it at once, he looked up, impatiently.

Finn did not stir.

He stood leaning over the dog and looking into its glazed eyes with a great, deep, strange glance. He was not thinking whether it was an animal or a human being, whether it could be saved or whether he himself could do anything.…

“Finn!”

He did not stir. He was staring into the great face of death. The door of the dark house was fung open and he stared and stared into the darkness. His soul was flled with a devout awe. He felt nothing, saw nothing, but life expiring before his eyes.

Hans looked at him speechlessly, terrifed at the expression in his face, which he did not know how to interpret, and grew more and more agitated.

“Give me your pocket-handkerchief, Finn.”

Finn started. He looked up and handed him the handkerchief:

“I didn't think of it,”he said.

Hans did not reply. In a little while, the dog was dead and he fung it in among the trees in such a way that Finn could have struck him.

They got into the carriage and drove on in silence. Finn thought of nothing but what he had seen and did not suspect his friend's agitation. Then, suddenly, he told the coachman to pull up:

“You mustn't mind, Hans,”he said.“I am going to get out.…I can go home by myself.…I want to be alone for a little.”

Hans jumped out of the carriage and walked away without saying good-bye. Finn took no notice. He let the coachman shut the door, shrank into a corner and drove home.

Fru Adelheid came to him in the old room and could not make him speak of what lay on his mind. She smiled to him and took his hand and sang for him.

But Finn sat silent and absent.

Some time after, the friends were walking, one evening, through the streets and along the canal, where the boats lay in a row and, on the other side, an old castle stood, with broken windows and charming green roofs.

“Let us sit here for a bit,”said Finn.

They sat on the quay. The water fowed black and angry beneath them. The boats rocked and bumped and swayed. Hans drummed with his cane against the embankment-wall:

“Is it like this in Venice?”he asked.

“No,”said Finn.“It's fner there. Because one's strange to it.”

Hans laughed gaily and Finn said nothing more and looked down into the water.

Then they suddenly heard a shout.

They both sprang up and ran and, when they had come some distance, they saw a child on the point of drowning:

“Here, Finn…help me.…”

Hans scrambled down into one of the boats and was fumbling with the oars. But Finn ran on and jumped into the water, where the child was, without a moment's refection.

He could not swim and Hans had frst to save him. Then, with the greatest difficulty, he rescued the child. They went home to Cordt's house and, when the frst fright was over and it became clear that Finn had suffered no harm, they all sat in the living-room and talked about it.

Fru Adelheid held Finn's hand between her own and patted it and pressed it. Cordt walked up and down in great emotion.

“How could you take it into your head?”said Hans.“You know you can't swim.”

“I never gave it a thought,”said Finn, quietly.

Cordt stopped in front of his son and nodded to him. Fru Adelheid kissed him on the forehead and her eyes beamed.

Hans looked at them, crimson with anger.

He thought of how Finn might have been drowned, or the child, or both of them. Then he remembered the scene in the woods, with the dying dog. He could not understand these people's train of thought and he despised it. He looked at none of them and, with an effort, forced his voice to be calm, as he said:

“One has no right to behave like that. It is stupid.”

“Yes,”said Finn.

But Cordt put his hand on the engineer's shoulder and lookedat him in such a way that Hans suddenly remembered his own little faint-hearted father:

“Yes,”said Cordt,“it is stupid that Finn shouldn't know how to swim.”

Then it was decided that Cordt's son should learn to swim.

Chapter 20

Fru Adelheid sat, book in hand, without reading.

It was late. Finn had been with her and had said good-night and Cordt was not at home. It was silent in the house and silent outside.

She had a feeling as though she were alone in the world.

Fru Adelheid was not happy.

The peace which the good grey years had brought had departed from the house. She could not see her way anywhere: not with Finn, not when she was alone, least of all when Cordt was in the room.

She did not feel safe even at church. It would happen to her that she left church heavier in mind than when she entered. It also happened that she simply dared not go in, but turned back, when the organ pealed to her in the porch.

She sat and stared, with her white hands folded in her lap. She wanted to try if she could think the thing out to the end. But she had tried before, with ever-decreasing success.

First, there was the going back to the old room.

This was the beginning and she could not but think that it was the whole matter, for, in truth, she had never got over it. She could not defend herself against the memories that came crowding one upon the other. Her blood grew hot, her eyes moist, without her knowing why.

She suffered from a constant terror which she could neitherexplain nor shake off. Now it was Finn, whose pale face frightened her. Now it was Cordt, who was silent and ever more silent and brooded over his thoughts.

Then she was overcome as by a despairing remorse and she could not see how she had offended. Then she went in a secret dread of revenge and she knew of no one who meant her any harm.

There were days on which every step she took gave a dull and threatening echo of the old days. She felt as though she were living in a house whose walls were full of secret recesses with old documents which would upset everything that existed, if they came to light…she felt as though she were walking over mysterious vaults that concealed the traces of mysterious crimes.

Wearily, Fru Adelheid leant her head upon her hand and let her hand fall again. She half rose in her chair and hid her face in the roses that stood on the table before her. She took up the book and put it down at once.

Then Cordt came.

He nodded to her, went to the farther side of the room and sat down with a book.

She looked at him timidly. She heard him turn the pages and wondered what book it was. She asked him. He answered, without looking up, and the silence increased twofold.

Fru Adelheid sighed and rose to go to bed:

“Good-night, Cordt.”

He closed the book and tossed it on the table. She stopped and looked at him. Then he asked:

“Has Hans been here to-day?”

She sat down in her chair again. He had got up and was pacingthe room. She waited and listened to his footsteps.

Then she could bear it no longer:

“Cordt!”

He stopped and looked at her.

“Cordt…Finn will die, if Hans is always with him.”

“Yes,”he said, softly and sorrowfully.“Finn will die and you will die and I shall die. But Hans will live.”

“What are you trying to do with him, Cordt?”

“Have you forgotten what I want?”

He looked at her and his eyes hurt her.

“I wonder if your wish is also mine, Cordt,”she asked.

“No.”

He said that calmly, without anger, but also without hesitation.

Then she leapt up:

“Your wish was never mine…never! You have been able to persuade me and frighten me and force me.…I never meant it, Cordt, never…even when I agreed.”

“Let the dead days be, Adelheid.”

“And now…Cordt.…Now I am farther away from you…now you understand me less than ever…there is something in me now that is a thousand times stronger than what parted us then.”

Cordt looked at her with a tempest in his strong eyes:

“So there is in me, Adelheid.”

He stood before her, drawn up to his full height. She thought he seemed taller than usual and his face looked strangely young.

“There is Finn,”he said.

Fru Adelheid sat in her chair, because she could not stand.

“You speak as if he were your son and not mine,”she said.

She did not take her eyes from his face. She could not get rid of the thought that he looked so young. His hair had not a sign of grey, his walk was easy and erect as in the old days, his eyes glowed with the same strength and the same confdence.

She bent forward and stared and sought. Surely she must be able to find the wounds which sorrow had given him, the marks which age had brought.

Cordt did not look at her. He stood with his hands folded about his neck and with strangely distant eyes:

“You have said it, Adelheid…it is as you say…there is something now that is a thousand times greater than what parted us then. We mortals always think, when misfortunes come, that no more will come now…that it must be over now. And so there is no difference between the child with its lost doll and the man with his dead love…none except time, which comes and goes, comes and goes, puts out a light and kindles a pyre and puts out the pyre also.”

He dropped his arms and stood silent for a while:

“Adelheid…”

He said no more. He looked round the room and at her, as though he were waking from his thoughts. Then he went to the window and looked across the square, where the lights were being put out.

Fru Adelheid stared with great fxed eyes at where he stood.

She had not seen him during many years…where had she been all those years…what had she been doing?

Then she had seen him again, distantly and dimly at frst, like the memory of a fght, a pain, on the day when she stood once more in the old room. He had come closer…the time he warned her aboutFinn. And, little by little, he had approached her through Finn…through his fears and his love, through his every word, constantly closer and more effectively.

She clutched the arms of the chair so frmly that her knuckles turned white.

Now it had come…now the doors of the mysterious cellars grated on their rusty hinges and the crime stood revealed…now the secret recesses in the walls were opened and the old documents bore witness to the right.…

Now there was no longer anything between her and him and there was nothing outside him and her. He stood beside her…she could reach him with her hands. She had no son and no God. His words swept over her like a storm, his eyes were bent upon her.…

She wanted to get up and run away, but could not. A sort of dizziness came over her and the ground retreated under her feet.

There were voices which told her that it was surely a very old and forgotten story…a legend preserved in the archives of the house for the entertainment and instruction of future times, which would possibly judge differently from the one who had set the legend down.

There were others, mocking and exultant voices, which whispered to her that it was all imagination and nothing else…that Finn belonged to her and not to him, that all his confdence and all his strength would break like glass against that pale, quiet boy, who loved his mother.

There were hymns and psalms and organ-pealing and impressive words about sin and forgiveness and Christ's heavenly glory. The cool air of the church-vault passed over her burningforehead…all the bells rang, as though for a soul in need.

She heard it all and it vanished like a sound in the air.

And all the voices were merged before her confused thoughts.

It turned into an evening in the old days…an evening of lights and gaiety. She saw the people of that time…she heard her own voice.…

Then, suddenly, it was quenched in the great silence of the old room.

The candles were burning on the mantelpiece.…She sat and stared into the red hearth. Now Cordt spoke . . .Cordt in the old days:

“I will stake life and happiness to win you. I will talk to you and importune you and conquer you. I will take you in my arms and close my door to you and run after you and forgive you. And, if I do not win you, I shall cast you off.”

She sprang up and clasped her head in her two hands:

“Cordt…Cordt…”

He turned round and looked into her white face.

She raised her face to him and sought and stared after her portrait in his eyes…only a thought from the old days…a memory…

It was not there. For him there was nothing in the world except that which was his happiness and his fear and his struggle…now as in the old days…

And it was no longer she.

“Adelheid…are you ill?”

“No…no…”

She laughed aloud. Cordt took her hands and led her to a chair.She let him do as he would and continued to look up in his face.

Then she suddenly thrust him from her.

She smiled and shook her head at her folly. She rose and walked round the room. She said she was quite well, told him to go away…just to go away.

And Cordt went.

She stared at the door, which closed after him, as though she had seen him for the last time. Then she turned round and looked into a mirror which showed her whole fgure.

Slowly she walked up to the mirror, sat down before it, with her head in her hands, and stared into her own face.

The clock struck one and two from the church-steeples and she did not hear. Then some one shouted down in the square. She rose, took a candle and left the room.

She went through the long passages and up the stairs, softly and carefully, as if she were a thief. She listened at Cordt's door and at Finn's. Then she stood outside the old room. She listened…there was no sound. She opened the door ajar and saw that it was dark.

She went in quickly and walked straight up to the secret recess in the wall. She opened it and took the yellow document in her trembling hands.

Then she stared at Cordt's name and her own, which were written down last and struck out again.

Chapter 21

Finn stood at the window in Cordt's room, with his head leaning against the frame, and looked down into the yard, where the porter's children were playing.

He had come, as usual, to say good-morning and Cordt had told him to wait while he fnished a letter. The letter had been sealed for some time, but Finn had not noticed it. He was watching the game down below and bending forward to see better.

Then the children were called in. He laid his head against the window-frame again and looked up at the grey sky. He thought of Hans, who had left for Paris that morning and was to remain abroad for two years.

Cordt sat silent. From where he was, he could see Finn's profle: the forehead, which was so white, the eyelids, which lifted themselves so heavily, the mouth, which was so tired and so weak.

“Finn!”

Finn started and turned round.

“Did you see Hans off?”

“Yes.”

Finn sat down by the window where he stood, with bent head and his hands upon his knees. He wound the cord of the blind round his fngers and unwound it again.

“I wonder if you will miss Hans?”

“Oh…yes.”

“I shall,”said Cordt.“Hans represents the new order at its fnest…the hero in modern poetry…the engineer, you know, whom they can never put on the stage without making him insipid…because he never acts a part. He is strong and has the courage to employ his powers. To us he often seems lacking in refnement and he fnds it diffcult to grant us our due. He has no ancestors…he is the ancestor…he founds a dynasty.”

“Yes,”said Finn.

They sat silent for a while.

There was no doubt in Cordt. He knew what he wanted and wanted it. He did not seek for kind words, but strong words. Finn knew this too. He sat like a culprit awaiting sentence and was thankful for every minute that passed.

Then they looked up into each other's eyes.

They measured each other's strength. And Finn was strong in his hopelessness, even as Cordt was strong in the hope which he could not let go, because he had nothing else to fall back upon.

“Do you know that you are a born artist, Finn?”

Finn smiled sadly and shook his head.

“You are,”said Cordt.“There is no doubt about it. When you were travelling abroad…there was simply nothing in your letters but delight at the pictures you saw. Your journey was one long progress through a royal gallery. At sea, in the street, on the mountains…everywhere you caught life and hung it on your wall and sat down to look at it.”

“Did I?”

“Had you not been born with a silver spoon in your mouth, youwould have been lost beyond redeeming. You would have become a painter…no…an author.”

“Would that be so bad?”

“What use is literature to us modern people?”said Cordt.“Where does it lead us? How does it form our lives? If the old poets had lived nowadays, they would certainly have been merchants, or electricians, or arctic navigators.…Just look round you, Finn…the books we read, the pictures we look at, the plays they perform: isn't it all like an orchestra that plays for an hour while people walk about the grounds? Tired people, who like to hear a bit of music before they go to bed. The band plays its tune and gets its pay and its applause and we are interested in seeing that the performance is well and properly given.…But…the poet, Finn…A solitary horn sounds over the hills. We drop the plough and listen and look up, because the notes seem to us so rare and so powerful and we have never heard them before and know them so well. Then our eyes glisten. And the sorrow that bent our back and the gladness that held us erect and the hope we had…all of that suddenly acquires color and light. And we go whither the horn calls us…over the hills…to new green felds where it is better living.”

“Father . . .”

Finn raised his head, but then could not fnd the phrase for what he wanted to say.

“Don't you think that the poet must be a man…a man like the others, with courage in his breast and a sword at his thigh? Then he goes forth and sings them to battle and wedding, to dance and death. He is a part of the business, foremost in the crowd.”

“The poets also sat in the ladies' chambers and sang,”said Finn.Cordt nodded:

“They did that also,”he said.“But the poets we now have do nothing else. There will always be fddlers as long as there are idle women and women with two husbands and wars and kings. As long as the stars wander so far through the sky and the children cannot catch the bird that flies in the bush.…But never mind that, Finn. Never mind that. Just look at those who sit in the orchestra today.…Would you sit among them? They are sick people singing about their sickness. One is sick with love and one with lewdness and one with drink. One chants his faith on vellum, another sells his doubts in sixpenny editions. The feeble will of the one quavers in silly verses…the other intoxicates his pale fancy with blood and horrors drawn from the olden times. Do you think that a free man would of his own accord select his place among those artists?”

Finn looked up with his quiet eyes:

“Who is a free man, father?…Are you?”

Cordt put his hands on Finn's shoulders and bent over him and looked at him:

“You are, Finn.…You are a free man…if you wish to be.”

“Father…”

Finn put out his hands like a child asking for something. But Cordt looked at him inexorably. And so strong and radiant was his glance, that Finn tried to escape it, but could not; tried to speak, but was silent.

Then Cordt walked across the room, up and down, with great, calm strides, and spoke and was silent and never for a moment released his son from his stern grasp.

His words seized Finn and lifted him up where things weregreat and beautiful and bitterly cold, he thought; then let him fall again, till he relapsed into his own dark corner; and seized him anew and carried him aloft.

But, when Cordt ceased, it was to Finn as though he heard a flourish of trumpets from the clouds proclaiming that other words were now coming, greater still and austerer, more loving, ever heavier to bear.

“You are right, Finn.…I am not a free man, I never was. I am bound up in the tradition that built my house and bore my race and, when I could not support the tradition, things broke for me. But that did not make me free.…Those were heavy days, Finn. I could not understand it, you see, and I fought to the end. I was young and strong and I was in love. You are fond of the old room…you can hear the legends up there singing their powerful, melancholy song.…Remember, Finn, I am one of those on whom the legend is laid. I have lived in the secrecy of the old room.…I have stood, in my calm, proud right…up there, where the room stood, unseen by any one except the master of the house and his wife…always remote and locked and hidden in its time-honored might…always open to him who owned it.…I left it like a beaten man. But I could not retire into a corner and mourn, for I had you, Finn. You were only a little child then, so I could not know how your paths would go. I knew only one thing, that you would never sit with your wife up there, where people became so small when they sat down in the big chairs and where it was so pleasant and so safe. I was the last. With me, the tradition of the old room was fnished.…Then I had to try if I could find my way in the world which I did not understand. I had to go through all that which I disliked so desperately and which had killedmy happiness. For myself, I had nothing to gain: I was a bound man and a wounded. But I had you, Finn.…And I had to know if they were building properly and honestly somewhere behind all the dancing and firting and singing which I saw before my eyes. Or if it was no different from what my eyes saw and if I should not be doing best to carry my child out into the mountains and let the wild beasts tear it to pieces.…I was alone in this. Your mother went to live in an old house beside the old house where her happiness could not grow. There she found peace. But I needed no refuge. Where I was, I was at home: I only wanted to see the place where you and your children should flourish.…I did not spare myself, Finn. I sought honestly, south and north, east and west. I took their books…the light ones burst like soap-bubbles in my hands and the powerful ones my thoughts had to struggle to understand. Not one of their green visions but has been with me in my room, not one of their bright swords but has flashed before my eyes.…I did not allow myself to be blinded by my own bitterness, or tricked by catchwords, or frightened by abuse. I went on as long as I could see the way…and longer, Finn. I peered out into the farthest, where those who thought as I did saw nothing but horror and insanity…. And Finn…I don't know.…Perhaps it was your mother's God that helped me…perhaps it was my ancestor, who himself had sailed into harbor and raised our house on new ground for many a good, long day. Perhaps it was your little hand, which lay so trustingly in mine, when you used to come to me in those anxious, lonely days and say good-morning and good-night.…I don't know. I daresay it was my love for you that lifted me above myself. I climbed as high up the mountains as a mortal can climb. It all lay under my feet like a cloud…longingand happiness and daily bread and daily trouble. I could not see the valley in which my house was built. But out of the cloud, over the mountain, I saw the road where we hustle and strive, generation after generation, ever forward towards the goal which we cannot see, but which is there, because the road is there.…And I saw land…the promised land of you and your children…from the mountain where I stood. A land I did not know…a land strange to my eyes…people with other habits and other beliefs, with a different form of love and a different code of honor.…I saw it through the storm that fung the door of the old room wide open.…That was a strange time, Finn…the strongest in my life and the happiest.”

Cordt stood at the window with his arms crossed over his chest. He looked at his son and smiled sadly. Finn sat still, with his head thrown back in his chair and his eyes closed.

“Then I equipped you for the journey, Finn.…I did not show you this way or that, for I was a bound man and could not go with you. I gave you books and masters, who opened all the gates of the world to you. I let you look into the mist where you wanted to ride. I feared nothing, because I wanted nothing for myself and because I had seen through the mist.…You grew up and I saw that you grew good and clever. Then I sat down and waited and longed for the day when I should wave to you from the balcony of my old house, when you marched forth to conquer your new land.…I was right to wait for the day.…Ah.…I have seen them, the poor devils, hungry and wounded, rush blindfold towards the new, which they did not know, because it could not possibly be worse than the old. I have heard them call for new laws because they had violated the old…they were driven from their huts and sat on the deck of the emigrant-shipwith their bundle and their uncertain hope for a better fate in the new world.…But you.…You had done no wrong and had nothing to revenge. Free as a king's son, you rode over the bridge with your retinue and rode through the world and planted your banner wherever you chose to dwell. Born of your mother's longing for excitement…in your father's house, whose walls are as thick as the walls of a castle…with the strong air of the old room in your lungs and without its yoke upon your neck…a rich and spotless nobleman, taking his place of his own free will in the ranks of the revolution.”

He was silent. His steps sounded heavily through the stillness:

“Are you with me, Finn?”

“Yes, father.”

“Come.”

Finn rose. Cordt put his arm over his shoulder and they paced the room together.

“I had so many dreams, Finn. And I gained such confidence, because my own happiness was shattered and I had you. I had become an old man, but my mind was not blunted. I had suffered shipwreck, but I was not afraid of the sea. I believed in life…in God, if you like.”

They did not walk well together and Cordt removed his arm. Finn sat down in his chair again and listened. Cordt went on walking:

“Then came the days which you know…the days of the present.…You grew up into the quiet man you are. Your eyes looked heavily upon life, you shrank back timidly when you saw that there was fre and smoke on earth.…You kept your scutcheon untarnished, but that is easily done, when one doesn't fight. Youwere never in places where one does not wish to be seen…that is true. But you never went outside your door, Finn…never. There was no fire in your blood, no desire in your thoughts. You were tired, Finn…merely tired.…I grew frightened for you…. As the years passed, you had become more to me than a son. You were not only flesh of my flesh and bone of my bone…you were a link in the human chain that goes on through the ages, ever onward. Your hand was in mine, but your life was more precious than mine. For you had to carry a greater burden and to carry it into new ways.…Remember, Finn, I had been on the mountain and seen through the mist. It was more than the question of an inheritance, more than family pride and family loyalty. You and I were allied in a great cause. And I sat with the map before me and followed the course of the battle…like an old soldier, who can no longer sally forth himself, but who has his son and his colors and his emperor under fre.…Remember how I had arrived at where I was. Remember what I had lost, what I had let go, how completely I had sacrifced myself for you. I had you, Finn…had I anything else ?…When I, then, became frightened for you, I plunged into my wonderful treasure and endowed you lavishly. I told you the legend of the old house and thought it would call you to arms, like the blast of the bugle over the camp. I revealed your father's and your mother's fate to you, that you might see how people fight for happiness. I sent you out into the world, where life is bigger and stronger than at home, so that life might make you into a man.…But never…never did I put any constraint upon you. Never did I usurp the place of Providence…. And you turned over the pages of the picture-book and came home paler than before and wearier. The old room was merely a charmingpoem to you, that sang you into deeper dreams. Up there…where the strong men of our race met their wives, when the sun went down upon the business of the day, and talked gladly and earnestly when their hearts impelled them to…there you sit, alone, all day long, with your slack hands.”

Then he laid his hands firmly on Finn's shoulders. And Finn looked up with moist eyes and quivering mouth.

“To-day, Finn, I have given you your inheritance. From to-day, I look upon you as of age. You were such that one could not use coercion with you…and, in fact, there was none that wanted to use it. Nor could one be angry with you…you were the same…it was the same…always. To-day, that is past. Go out and buy yourself a house and take a wife and have children by her. And remember that, if there were some in the family that fell, there was none that finched.”

“Father…I understand you…but I cannot do what you want.”

Cordt took a step back and tossed his thick hair from his forehead:

“You pale people understand everything, because no faith blinds your eyes: you are so kind and clever, you think. You judge leniently, you do not judge at all, you know that the truth is nowhere and everywhere. You justify every silly thought you have entertained…you sit for all time and contemplate your navel…and then you let the murderer go and the thief escape. God help you poor wretches! The stupidest, the most ignorant dervish is cleverer and kinder than you!”

Finn wanted to say something, but Cordt made a preventive gesture with his hand:

“A man must not understand everything. He must choose and judge and reject. If he doesn't do that, there is no happiness in the world and no loyalty and no peace. And, if he cannot hate, he cannot love either.”

He went to the window and looked out. And, as he stood there, Finn came up to him and seized his hand and looked at him pleadingly:

“I can't do what you want,”he said.

But Cordt withdrew his hand and moved away from him:

“You have no right to say that to me, Finn. I won't listen to it. For what I want is only that you should live. Take the inheritance which I have given you and use it as you can. One day, you shall be called upon to answer for your son, as I to-day for you.”

Finn smiled sadly:

“I shall never have a son,”he said, softly.

Cordt did not hear what he said. He was struggling with a memory…passed his hand over his face and stared before him. He saw Fru Adelheid…that evening in the old room, when she had said what Finn was saying now…the same hopeless, impotent words:“I cannot do what you want.”

He sat down and fell back in his chair.

All the despair of the old days came over him like a tremendous weariness. He was struggling against what was stronger than himself. He had nothing to set against that eternal, hopeless,“I cannot do what you want.”

Then he sprang up and stood in front of Finn with blazing eyes:“If it's your mother who paralyzes your will, then fy from her, hate her, thrust her from you…”

“Father…father…”

“Hate her, I say. She was smitten with the pestilence from her youth. She understood everything…like you. To her nothing was small or great, nothing near or far. Her will was gone, like yours. She knew where the glory lay, if she could reach it, but she could not. She hearkened to the times and the times made her their own. She was always sick…sick unto death.”

He crossed the room and said nothing more.

They were both of them very pale and both longed to be alone. They had nothing more to say to each other.

And Finn was not angry on his mother's account. He thought only of the one thing, that he could not do what Cordt wanted and could not appease his sorrow…could not even tell him that he loved him. And then he longed to sit still…in the old room…with his mother, who was so pretty and whom he had never offended:

“Are you angry with me, father?”

Cordt looked at him long and intently.Then he said:

“Yes.”

But, when Finn was gone, he sat with his face buried in his hands and wept.

Chapter 22

Cordt entered, dressed to go out, and hurriedly crossed the room.

Fru Adelheid sat writing. She looked up, as he came in, and went on writing.

“Where is Finn?”

“Upstairs, I suppose…in his room,”she answered, without looking at him.

He stood at the window for a moment. Then he fung himself into a chair and got up again and stood by the table at which she was sitting:

“Have you been with him to-day?”

“No.”

She closed her blotting-book and turned her chair so that her face was in shadow. Then she said:

“Finn is too much alone.”

“Yes.”

He nodded and said yes again; then stood with his head bowed deep in thought.

“It is so quiet here,”said Fru Adelheid.“You are not happy and Finn notices it. And Hans is away.…”

“Yes…yes…”

She crossed her arms over her breast and sat silent and lookedat the tip of her foot.

“Adelheid…”

Cordt drew himself erect:

“We will fll the house with gayety,”he said.“We will go and pay visits tomorrow morning…you and Finn and I…to old friends and new. We will have young and cheerful people here and pretty women and clever men…lights and music.”

She looked up at him. He smiled and put his hand on her shoulder.

“Yes,”she said.

Cordt talked about it a little and then went out hurriedly.

Fru Adelheid remained sitting long. The room grew dark. The lamps before the gateway were lit and their fickering gleams danced on the ceiling. The fire in the hearth smouldered under the ashes. Where she sat, no light fell; her white dress shone faintly through the gloom.

She thought of Cordt's smile…he had said that to her much as though he were asking one of the people in the offce to take pains in a diffcult matter.

She thought of Finn, who looked at her with such strange eyes, as though the relations between him and his mother had changed and he could not understand it.

She thought of herself. She felt like a tree in autumn, when the leaves fall… a tree that had always thought itself green and beautiful until now, when it saw its glory futter before the wind.

And, day after day and every hour of the day, she rebuilt it all as it might have been.

She built up the temple of the old room again and locked thedoor with seven seals. She put time back and sat with her little boy in her lap and resented old Marie's undressing him and singing him to sleep. She put time forward and celebrated the day when Finn should lead his wife into the secret chamber of the house and tell her all about it, in all its beauty and solemnity, and write his name and hers on the yellow document.

Fru Adelheid smiled sadly.

She thought she was like the man who had put the celestial globe up there in the old room…the man whose intellect was obscured and who sat and played with the stars until he died.

But her thoughts always went the same way, while the darkness fell ever closer about Cordt's house.

She wondered, would it be any use now, if the house were flled with lights and gayety? Or would the darkness lurk in every gloomy corner and spring forth when the feast was over and for ever hide the three who moved about the house, each his own way, anxiously and alone?

She did not know. But she always thought of it. And there was nothing tempestuous in her hope and in her fear and in her regret.

Fru Adelheid was calm now, always.

Chapter 23

Then the stately house on the square was lit up with gayety.

The horses trampled in the gateway and the servants ran up and down the carpeted stairs. The great drawing-rooms streamed with lights and fowers and music and the foor was flled with dancers.

It was a wealth and splendor even greater than in the old days, for now the master of the house was a more lavish host than he had ever been before. He could never have things fne enough, luxurious enough. He saw to everything, was everywhere and moved among his guests so that they could see that he delighted in them.

The entertainments at Cordt's house became legendary. And all that were rich and beautiful and noble and intelligent came when he invited them and came gratefully and were glad to stay.

The men gathered close about the lady of the house, who was charming in her white gown, with her white hair.

Those who had paid her their homage in the old days raised their grey heads when she passed them and followed her tall fgure with a gleam of their youthful fre in their eyes. And those who were now young wondered when they heard the old ones tell that she was once a thousand times prettier.

Or not prettier, perhaps. But such that every man on whom her eyes fell was, from that moment, hers and that every glance she vouchsafed was remembered for all time.

Now she was more remote in her smiles. Her glance was deeper, but it was as though it did not see. Her red mouth no longer promised happiness as it used to. Any one would think it a happiness to win her. But no one would believe it possible.

And, while they saw her thus in the light of their youth, they wondered what could have happened in the years that had passed and why the house had so long been closed and why it had now so suddenly opened its doors wide to the world which holds revel daily.

But their thoughts never grew to the shadow of a slander.

They asked her to sing. And, as she sat at the piano and looked through the room with her great, strange eyes, the old friends of the house remembered the glowing songs of her youth, which had set their blood afame as she exulted and wept in them with desire and love.

But now, when she sang, the young ones listened, enraptured with her voice, which was so bright and so clear and so wonderfully still:

The wildest water on earth to-day
(God grant me His grace consoling!)
Flows deep and dreary through gorges grey,
But whither and whence they alone can say
Who first set its wild waves rolling.

For no ship ever its tideway knew,
Its marge bore never a blossom.
And never a bird from the beaches flew,
And never a mirrored star it drew
From Heav'n to its own black bosom.

It wells from eyes that are glazed with pain
(God shield me in all disaster!)
When a man has rent like a rag in twain
His own life's bliss, by his own hand slain,
Being never his fortune's master.

There was a brief silence when she ceased. Then they crowded round her in admiration and with endless requests for more.

Fru Adelheid rose. She talked and smiled and thanked them. But her glance wandered far beyond all these people, who meant nothing to her, to Cordt, who stood at the far end of the room and was talking to some one and did not see her and had not heard her.

But Finn had heard her. And Finn had seen her great, humble, plaintive look.

He did not take his eyes off her and strange thoughts hurried through his head. He now understood what had happened in this house. He knew why Fru Adelheid had come to him so seldom, lately, in the old room. Why she had sat so silent, steeped in distant thoughts…why her glance had been so uncertain and so timid, her words so wavering, her hand so slack in his.

And he felt that the last bond was broken that bound him to mankind.

He had lost his mother, now that he was pushing hardest towards her. When she came to him now, it was Cordt she looked for. Were he to go to her now and lie down before her with his cheek on her hand, as he had so often done, she would lift him up and bidhim go out into the world and live.

He had a feeling as though he had been betrayed, but, at the same time, he wept with her in his heart. He looked at his father and thought how much more of a man he was than she suspected in her poor, tardy repentance. He looked at his mother and felt a curious loving contempt for her…such as men feel for a woman who comes to them and begs for something a thousand times less important than what she once possessed and despised.

Then he had to go into the crowd of people, who offered him their smiles and asked for his.

And so strong was the feeling of loneliness in him that he mingled readily with the guests of the house and was more cheerful than usual and more talkative.

He was as pleased to move about these bright rooms as elsewhere, because he was no longer at home anywhere. He might just as well exchange a few words with these smartly-dressed ladies and gentlemen, since he had to talk and since he could no longer tell any one what was passing within him and since no one could tell him what he wanted to hear.

The women crowded round him as the men did round Fru Adelheid. They wound a circle of white arms and bright eyes round the young heir of the house, who was so pale and so handsome and such that women longed for that which he did not show. They met him with charming, fattering words and smiled upon him and he did not hear the words and broke through the circle without a trouble and without a sigh.

The men offered him their friendship and he shook their hands and talked to them and went away and forgot their faces. Cordtfound him in every corner, where he had hidden for a moment without intending to or thinking about it, and carried him smilingly and teasingly and jestingly into the throng. And he smiled to his father and went with him and remained always alone.

He saw himself and only himself. He seized upon every thought that arose in him and discussed it as if it had been thought by another. He contemplated every mood that welled up in his soul as if he had read it in a book.

He climbed high up the peaks upon which men cannot live…the peaks whence they topple down one day or where they perish in the bright frost. For there is no sound up there and no air, no day and no paths. Only light and always light.

But, when it happened that Cordt's glance fell upon him, without his knowing it, the loneliness was suddenly extinguished in his soul.

Then he knew who he was and where he was and the pain of life gnawed into his soul. For he constantly read the eternal, hopeless, fond question in his father's eyes. He realized what he had forgotten, that the house was making holiday for his sake and his sake alone. Every strain that sounded, every rose that blushed, every pretty woman who moved across the foor: they were all his father's servants, who came to him with message after message that life's banquet was served if he would but take his seat at the board and drain its golden cup.

Then he thought sadly of his tranquil, beautiful mother, who had gone from him, out into life, which did not touch him. How good it would have been if they could sit together now and talk and be silent, while the fountain rippled in the square and the queerthings in the old room whispered their strange and mighty legend!

It would have been good for him. And good for her, he thought. And best of all, perhaps, for Cordt, who did not see her.

His thoughts gathered in love for Cordt, who was struggling to the death in his hopeless fght. He felt as though his father were a hero in the wars and wished that he were his meanest page to buckle on his armor for him and bathe his wounds and sit beside him with his lute, when he would sleep.

But the rout ran its course and it was late before the gate closed behind the last carriage.

It fell heavily and harshly as though it were striking angrily at the guests' heels. It grated its hinges long and shook its bolts as though it thought of never opening again, but of shutting out the world for ever from that old house, in which no light could drive away the increasing gloom, no joyous trumpets drown the hoarse voices that threatened in the corners.

Then they sat together for a while longer, they three who dwelt in the house, and talked with empty words and empty eyes.

Fru Adelheid it was who frst ceased, because her thoughts were the strongest. And Finn it was who said the most…as though to expiate the fault that oppressed him.

But it was Cordt who was bitterest in his care, while indifferent words passed between those who stood as close together as it was possible for mortals to stand and who feared the silence and who had nothing more to say to each other.

Then Cordt said good-night and Finn. But Fru Adelheid told the servants to leave her for a little and the candles burnt where the rout had been.

Restlessly she wandered about the room and again thought of the days that were gone and could never return. And she readily surrendered herself to her fancies, for there was in her now but one hope and one faith and one repentance.

She fancied that one of the long evenings was over in which gay acquaintances flled her rich house and Cordt and she exchanged glances which only they understood.

She had been to the nursery and leant over her little boy, who was sleeping with red cheeks. Now she would take the reddest fower there was and then go up the secret stair…up to where the old room stood, in its wonderful glory.

There he sat and waited for her.

She saw him as she entered…he raised his face to her and nodded and then lapsed again into his heavy thoughts. And she stood silent at the window, where the red fowers blushed before her feet and the square lay below her in the darkness of the night and the fountain sang its refrain, which never begins and never stops.

Then she rose and crossed the room. She heard his voice when he talked to her, as he so often talked…ever the same judgment upon the dance that passed over the world, the same mighty song in praise of great marriage, the same passionate, loving prayer that she would only see it while there was yet time and let those dance who had nothing better to do and take the proud place which he offered her by his side…in the old chair, in which people became so small and so strong, because they sat with their feet on an altar that was raised in faith and built up of faith and fenced in with faith throughout the changing times.

Then, when he had said that and sat by the chimney, where thefre glowed and the candles shed their rays sparingly in the corners of the old room…she would stand for a little at the window, while all was silent in the room, and look at him, who was the man in her life and had never ceased to be so. And then she would go up to him…slowly and quietly, because she honored the ground she trod on…kneel down where he sat and raise to him the eyes whose beauty he had loved, whose glance he had sought in such great hope and such great fear.

Then she would tell him exactly how it was…how strong it was and how silent:

“Cordt…you strong, you irresistible man…I love you as you would be loved. I thank you, because you talked to me and never grew weary. Because you always besought me. Because you waited for me and trusted that the day would come when the silence of the old room should turn to gladsome song in my soul and all the other sounds in the world like a distant buzz in the woods. Now I am here…Cordt…you strong, you irresistible man. Now I am yours, as I was before, and I am yours in the old room. There is nothing threatening or gloomy now in the strange things up here from the vanished days. I can sing to the old spinet so that no strings snap and no memories are mortally startled, for I sing only of you and of my boy and of my happiness. I can cherish the thread upon great-grandmother's spinning-wheel because I have woven the cloth of happiness in my own room. I can lovingly hide the wax doll in the folds of the curtain, because I have lived to see the day when I went gladly and readily to the secret chamber of the house and sat there long and was contented…But the jar with the naked man writhing through thorns: I set that up here when I was not yet what I am.It shall stand here in memory of the evil time that pulled at Fru Adelheid's soul and lured her desires with sounds from the square outside.…And our little boy, who sleeps with red cheeks, shall grow to man's estate and come up here one day, when you and I are dead, and sit with his wife in the chairs in which we sat. Then he shall know that his mother was tempted, it is true, but not destroyed.”

Fru Adelheid sat in her corner and dreamt in the silent, empty rooms.

Her white gown spread over the foor about her feet. Her eyes shone.

But high up, on the balcony of the old room, stood Finn and stared into the night that stretched round about him like a waveless sea.

It was silent. He did not think, did not dream. His soul mingled with the darkness, which was not evil and not good…only silent.

He was like a dead man who had been put on guard on the brink of the tower and who still stood there, staring with glazed eyes. The fountain rippled…it was as though the water rose over the edge of the basin and would rise and rise until it reached the dead man up there and washed him away.

Then a man came across the square.

He walked and sang, until he set eyes upon the man who stood up there, high and dark and motionless. Then he stopped and looked at him and shouted something.

And the man on the balcony answered with a shout. And the man below was seized with fear and ran away and vanished in the darkness.

Chapter 24

Cordt looked into the room where Fru Adelheid sat:

“Where is Finn?”

“I think he's in the old room.”

Cordt closed the door and walked quickly down the passage. She was sitting by the window and saw him in the square below, where he stood and looked up at the house. Then he walked away, in such a manner that she could see that he had no object for his walk.

The servant came and lit the candles. Fru Adelheid sat down by the freplace with her hands in her lap and listened for a sound in the quiet house.

Soon after, Cordt came home.

She heard his voice in the passage. Then he went into his own room…now he was outside again. She understood that he was on his way to Finn; but the next moment he came in to where she was sitting and sat down at a distance from her:

“Have you been up to him to-day, Adelheid?”

“No.”

Cordt moved restlessly in his chair, rose to go and sat down again. Fru Adelheid struggled with herself not to go over to him and take his hand and talk to him. Then he said:

“He has been so odd, lately. Brighter than usual, but more absent, nevertheless. He is not shamming, but still he is not himself.”Cordt went on talking about it, without looking at her and not so much in order to tell it to her as because he could not keep silent. She saw this exactly and turned away her face and cried quietly. Then he asked:

“Haven't you noticed it?”

“I think he is much as usual.”

Cordt rose and crossed the room. He stood for a time by the chimney, where she sat, and stared into the fire. She looked up at him with bright, moist eyes. Then he went over and sat where he had been sitting before and it was silent in the room.

“I wonder, oughtn't you to go up to him, Adelheid?”

He could not hear her reply and looked across at her. She had stood up and was coming towards him. He saw that she was very pale and that she was crying, but did not think about it and forgot it again at once.

Then she sat by him…so close that her white gown lay over his feet. She crossed her hands in her lap and parted them again and did not look at him while she spoke:

“Cordt…”she said.

And, when she had said that, she began to tremble and pressed her hands together.

“Yes?”

“You ought to go up to him, Cordt.”

He was silent for a moment. Then he bent closer to her and lowered his voice, as though there were some one in the room who could hear what he was saying and must not:

“I dare not. I have frightened him. He starts when he sees me…he stands outside my door and collects his courage when he comesto me to say good-morning. I will go quite away from him for a little while…go for a journey, I think, until he becomes more tranquil.”

She looked at him and pictured him roaming round the world so that Finn might recover his tranquillity. She saw him strolling in distant towns, where life fowed on around him, alone, knowing no peace, ever thinking of his son…longing for the day when he could come home, dreading how he would fnd him then.

Fru Adelheid slipped from her chair and lay on the foor before him, with her cheek against his hand and her eyes streaming with tears.

Cordt did not see. He stared into the room across her head, with the strained, racked look which he now always wore when he was alone:

“He does not like our parties, Adelheid,”he said, meditatively.“We only did him harm.”

“Yes.”

“But, if you would go up to him, Adelheid…very quietly…and sit with him a little, so that he could not give way to his thoughts. Or help him, so that his thoughts could find utterance. You two always got on well together, you know, and he was glad to see you whenever you came.”

“He is no longer glad to see me, Cordt.”

He looked at her in surprise and encountered her moist glance.

“If I went up now, Cordt…I could not sit with Finn as I used to. For I am no longer the same.”

“Ah, well!”was all he said.

He spoke calmly and indifferently, as though he had had no particular faith in his remedy and must look round for somethingelse.

“Cordt!…”

It was a scream.

He started. And, as if he had now first seen that she was kneeling before him, he pushed back his chair and rose to his feet.

He crossed the room and then came back and stood and looked at her with a sense of dislike that increased every minute. She crept to the chair from which he had risen and laid her head on it. She closed her eyes before his glance and wept silently and without stopping.

“You…?”he said slowly.

She received the blow which the word gave her without breathing a sound. Once she opened her eyes and immediately closed them again. Pale and still she lay before his feet.

Then his eyes blazed with anger and scorn:

“What a number of years have passed since we two frst met, Fru Adelheid…what a number of miserable years!”

“Yes,”she said and raised her head for a moment and laid it on the chair again.

“You went away…in search of your red happiness. You were not content with your husband, whom you loved and who loved you…you must have all men on their knees before your beauty…you must needs see the desire in their eyes and their unchaste hands cramped because they dared not lay them upon Cordt's wife.”

“Yes,”she said.

“Well, did you fnd the lover who bound your will to his foot? And did he spurn you when he had seen to the depths of your charming eyes? Or did you leave him of your own accord…and gofarther out into the world…in search of that which was greater still and redder?”

“I had no lover,”she said, in a low voice.

He tossed back the hair from his forehead and clenched his fsts:

“No,”he said.“You did not. That is your disgrace and your judgment.”

“Cordt…Cordt…suppose I had had…”

“Yes…if you had had a lover and were here to-day, then I should take your hand and lead you to our son and say to him,‘Here is your mother, who has been unhappy. She loved your father and her love died when the man came who was more to her than he. She has not known a really happy day in all these years, because her fate was too strong for her. Now she has come to ask for your affection and needs it.’”

He crossed the room and then came and stood by her again:

“Get up, Adelheid.”

She rose from the foor and sat down in her chair again, with her white hands crossed in her lap, silently and quietly. He looked at her and it was as though her humble obedience added to his anger:

“Where did you go on the day when you broke the bonds of your marriage, because the air in the old room was too pure for you and too strong? Where have you been since?”

“I went to God.”

Cordt laughed:

“Show me your God.”

He bent over and looked her in the face:

“I don't believe in your God,”he said.

She did not take her eyes from his and stretched out her trembling hands to him and her red mouth quivered with weeping:

“Then I don't believe in Him either, Cordt.”

He turned away from her. Quietly she bowed her head, her tears fell upon her hands, she listened and moaned under the blows which she had received and longed for more.

But Cordt sat at the window and looked out where the rain came pouring down and the fame of the lamps fickered in the wind. His anger was over. He could not remember what they had been talking of. His thoughts were where they always were and all the rest was nothing.

Then he suddenly stood by her again and struck his hand on his temples and looked at her with fear in his eyes:

“Adelheid…do you think Finn won't come to us at all to-night?”

She understood that it was too late…irremediably, hopelessly too late. She would never be able to tell him what was burning in her soul. He would never know that she did not come, because she was weary and because she was afraid, but that she had honestly wiped out the bad years of her life and stood again as he would have had her the time…the time he wanted to have her thus.

“He will come and say good-night,”she said calmly.

Fru Adelheid raised her folded hands to her mouth.

Things could not remain thus for ever. But she could wait. She could go barefoot over the stones, if only once she reached a place in his house where she could stay. There must be a road somewhere that led to him.

And the evening sped on.

She sat beside him again and held his hand in hers, happy that he allowed her to keep it. She wanted to push his hair off his forehead, where the wrinkles lay so sharply marked, but did not. She wanted to put her hands on his tired eyes, but dared not.

They talked of Finn and she talked softly and soothingly to him as to a child, happy to be going the way he wanted. She found such gentle words and such impressive ones…she found her smile again and looked at him and met his smile, which came stealing to his face like a sun-gleam and vanished again at once.

He heard but little of what she said. But the sound of her voice did him good. He heard it and the rain, which beat against the panes, and it grew warm and peaceful around him.

His fears, which had aroused and spied and driven his every thought and turned and weighed his every doubt, slumbered in this quiet hour. He sat there like an old man who has suffered so much that his faculties have been blunted to pain and who takes his solace as it comes and is thankful.

He looked at her as he used to look at his mother when he was young and unhappy. He thought of her as of a young girl who knew the old man so little and owed him nothing, but went to his chair and laid her roses in his hand, so that things might be a little pleasanter for him.

And once he moved uneasily in his chair and looked at her quite differently and said:

“Adelheid…why have I no child but him?”

He said that very quietly and, a little after, he said it again. He said it to himself and not to her. She saw this and wept, because sheknew he did not perceive it.

And the evening sped on.

They sat quietly and she was silent and talked again of their son up there in the old room. Then she said:

“Cordt, let us go up to him!”

“Both of us?”

She listened anxiously whether he would say any more…whether he would reflect who she was and thrust her from him in anger, as he had done before.

But he sat silent and looked at the red glow in the freplace.

Then she rose and put out her hands to him:

“Come…Cordt…let us go. We will sit with him a little and talk to him, quietly and cheerfully, till the shadows disappear. Then we will come down here again and they will return, when he is alone. But we will go up every day and fght with them for him and win him.”

He rose heavily and took her hand.

Fru Adelheid led him through the room like a child. They went through the long passage and up the secret stairs…She was always a little in front of him. Her eyes shone with happiness. The bells rang out in her soul and she held Cordt's hand so fast as though she would never let it go.

They came to the door of the old room and knocked and listened. She looked at him and bent over his hand and kissed it with streaming tears.

Then she opened the door briskly and went in with head uplifted and drew him after her.

Over by the window sat Cordt's son, in one of the big chairs. He had shot himself.

THE END.

译后记

十四行诗滥觞于十三世纪的意大利，最初采用这种诗体写诗的是西西里的宫廷诗人，后来流传到佛罗伦萨，在彼特拉克的笔下获得完美的表现，后人因此称意大利十四行诗为“彼特拉克体”。彼特拉克喜欢将这种诗写成两部分：前八行用来陈述问题，或表现某种情感的张力；后六行对问题做出解答，或消解前述的张力。前八行的押韵格式是abba abba，后六行是cde cde，也可以是cdc cdc，或cde dce。

十四行诗于十六世纪初从欧洲大陆传入英国，最初采用这种诗体写诗的英国诗人是托马斯·怀亚特（1503—1542）和亨利·霍华德（1517？—1547）。后来，莎士比亚写出一百五十四首十四行诗，将这一诗体的诗歌创作推向一个艺术的新高峰。他的十四行诗由三个四行体和一个对句组成，押韵格式为abab cdcd efef gg。内容上，前十二行用来陈述事物，最后的对句是结语，具有点题的作用。莎士比亚的十四行诗具备高超的语言艺术，后人称之为“莎士比亚体”。

负责印行莎士比亚十四行诗的出版商是托马斯·索普。他的本子即现在所谓的“第一四开本”，印行时莎士比亚自己显然没有校阅过，因为里面印刷的错误很多。卷首也没有诗人自己写的题献，取而代之的是出版商写的一句含义模糊的献词。献词中的“T. T.”是托马斯·索普（Thomas Thorpe）的起首字母，这已为莎士比亚研究者所认同。但“W. H. 先生”是谁，一直没有定论。有人说“W. H.”是南安普顿伯爵亨利·赖奥思利（Henry Wriothesley）名字的缩写颠倒。此人即接受作者题献《维纳斯与阿多尼斯》和《鲁克丽丝受辱记》的那个人，他是莎士比亚的庇护人，从情理上说是讲得过去的。但赖奥思利的身份是伯爵，何以称为“先生”（Mr.）？他的名字的缩写为什么不是“H. W.”，而是“W. H.”？于是有人怀疑这“W. H.”是莎士比亚的另一位庇护人彭布罗克伯爵威廉·赫伯特（William Herbert）。莎士比亚于1589年至1592年间写的戏剧就是由“彭布罗克剧团”演出的，而他的第一对开本所题献的也正是此人。但同样令人迷惑的是“先生”这个不相称的称呼。因此，有人干脆认为这“W. H.”就是莎士比亚本人（William Himself）。此外还有说“W. H.”是“T. T.”的一位助手，有说是莎士比亚的外甥或同事，等等，不一而足。

对“W. H.”做一些必要的考证并非没有意义，因为大多数研究者认为，莎士比亚的一百五十四首十四行诗可分为前后两部分：前面一百二十六首是写给诗人的一位少年朋友的；后面部分写给一位黑肤女郎。如果确定了“W. H.”的身份，就等于确定了这位朋友的身份，这对理解十四行诗的思想内容是有好处的。

另一位诗中人物黑肤女郎的情况与“W. H.”的情况差不多，她的身份也一样是个谜。根据诗人的描述，我们只知道她皮肤黝黑，性情放荡，但具有极大的魅力。她是诗人的情人，同时又与诗人的朋友有染。这位女性是实有其人，还是作者的虚构？种种迹象表明，前者的可能性很大，诗人至少是有感而发。如果可以肯定“W. H.”是彭布罗克伯爵，那么，这个女子可能是伯爵的情妇玛丽·菲顿（Mary Fitton）。她十七岁那年（1595）来到伦敦宫中，第二年奉女王命成为宫女。此人与彭布罗克的恋情曾在宫中闹得沸沸扬扬，彭布罗克还因此触怒了女王而被下狱。首先提出黑肤女郎即玛丽·菲顿的是莎学研究专家托马斯·泰勒（Thomas Tyler），附和这一主张的有弗兰克·哈里斯（Frank Harris）和剧作家萧伯纳等人。萧伯纳还为此写过一个剧本《十四行诗中的黑肤女郎》。

除了诗人的朋友和黑肤女郎，十四行诗中还提到了诗人的几位竞争对手（参见第七十六至第八十六首）。他们也写诗颂扬诗人的朋友，企图取代诗人在他心目中的地位。早期的一种看法认为这几位竞争对手是固定的一位诗人，后来的看法倾向于若干不同的诗人。候选人中包括本·琼生、多恩、甘平、马洛、斯宾塞等人。至于具体确定哪一首针对哪一位，没有人说得准。

尽管上述几个人物的原型是模糊的，学界始终没有统一的认识，但有一点可以肯定：莎士比亚的十四行诗比他的戏剧更具个人色彩。形式上是抒情诗，但这里所抒之“情”是作者自己的“情”，不像戏剧创作中一言一行都为剧中人物设计。因此，要了解莎士比亚的思想观点和人生态度，这些十四行诗无疑更有参考价值。

从表面上看，十四行诗描写的主题是友谊和爱情。具体地说，前面一百二十六首主要写友谊，余下二十八首写爱情。但这只是外部的情节构架，实际上，在这一表层下面，还有一个贯穿全诗的真正的主题，即“真善美”。

诗人并没有故弄玄虚为读者设置障碍，他甚至还担心别人不明白他的意思，干脆自己点破天机：

“真善美”，就是我全部的主题，
“真善美”，由此写出不同的诗，
我的创造力就运用在这里，
三者合一，描出风景的瑰奇。
　　真善美，通常都是各自为政，
　　我这里，三者同体，共存共生。（第一百〇五首）

这个“真善美”的主题具体表现在诗篇里常常是以礼赞朋友的美来实现的，这“美”的内涵已从单纯的美扩大到“真善美”三者的统一。诗人把他的朋友称为“我的太阳”（第三十三首）、“君主”（第五十七首），并时时祈求他充当自己的“缪斯”：

我常常召唤你做我的缪斯，
在我的诗里得到你的惠顾，
别的文人也从我获得启示，
受你的庇护发表他的诗赋。（第七十八首）

一个具体的人物形象在此已被概念化为一个理想、一个目标，供诗人向往和追求，只是在表现这种思想感情时，诗人又从抽象的、无形的概念返回具体的、有形的物象：

我是否可把你与夏天媲美？
你比夏天更可爱亦更温和：（第十八首）

又：

当一切画技用来描绘海伦，
那张脸又是你，着希腊衣装。（第五十三首）

少年男子的美超过了风光明媚的夏天，甚至可比希腊美女海伦，这“美”超凡脱俗，显然不能就事论事认为诗人只是夸张地形容了朋友的形体美。这里的“美”更多地在于精神的层面，伦理和道德的层面。

如果说诗人的朋友代表了“真善美”，那么，黑肤女郎则代表着它的反面：现实生活中不真不善不美的一个典型。她“不守婚约”（第一百五十二首），此为不真；“对你的新欢表示新的厌弃”（第一百五十二首），此为不善；皮肤黝黑，“缺点太多”（第一百四十一首），此为不美。诗人从自己的情感经历创造出这个性情放荡的女性形象，是以爱情为幌子深化真善美的主题，不同的是前面是正面的歌颂，后面是反衬。

这样一位具有许多缺陷的女子，一个“坏精灵”（第一百四十四首），诗人为什么还要神魂颠倒地爱上她呢？诗人自己也知道这种爱是一种“罪”（第一百四十二首），为什么仍自甘堕落，深陷其中而不能自拔？这是因为性爱的力量不可抗拒。在人文主义者的思想观念里，爱情具有伟大的力量，青年男女追求爱情的幸福是天经地义的事。莎士比亚大胆地披露自己的“隐私”，拿看似不道德的爱情经历说事，为的是弘扬有悖于传统的新的伦理观和爱情观，这正表现了他作为一位人文主义鼓吹者的非凡的魄力与勇气！

莎士比亚从没有写过专题性的文艺理论文章，但在十四行诗中却表达了一些很有价值的文艺观点，这也值得我们注意。他认为人的生命是有限的，而艺术是永恒的；诗歌能战胜死神，与时间同在：

但你永恒的夏天永不沉沦，
你拥有的美决不与你分开。
死神不能夸你身陷其阴影，
永恒的诗行使你与时同在。
　　只要人在呼吸，眼睛看得清，
　　这诗便活着，并赋予你生命。（第十八首）

莎士比亚认为诗要写得真实，应该写出“你就是你”，诗人应照抄“你身上的文句”（第八十四首）。在他看来，自然的美胜过艺术的美，但自然的美会消亡，补救的办法是生育繁衍，让美在子嗣身上得到继承（第十一首），或者用诗来装饰，在诗中实现永恒（第五十五首）。这些观点构成了莎士比亚的文学观。

陈才宇
于杭州寓所

潜　　逃

孔祥立　译

我一向确信，一旦一个女人下定决心要嫁给一个男人，那么使这个男人幸免于难的唯一方法，就是立刻逃之夭夭。但事情总有例外。我曾有一个朋友，眼瞅着这一不可避免的厄运朝他逼近，于是，他从一个港口登上了客轮一走了之（行囊里仅带了一把牙刷，他十分清楚自身面临的危险和这次紧急行动的必要性）。他花了整整一年的时间在世界各地游荡。当他认为自己已经安然无事时（女人是善变的，他说，十二个月的光阴足以让那个女人把他忘个干净），他返回了最初离开的那个港口，而他在码头上看到的第一个向他欣然招手的人，却还是那个他躲避、逃离一年之久的娇小女人。在此类情况下还能够抽身摆脱的，我仅认识一人，他叫罗杰·查林。跟露丝·巴罗陷入爱河时，罗杰已不再年轻，因而有了足够的经验让自己谨慎行事，但露丝有一种与生俱来的让男人乖乖就范的天赋（抑或称作素质？）。正是靠着这一点，她将罗杰拥有的常识、审慎，还有世俗智慧统统降服，他整个人如同九柱戏[1]中的一排木柱一样，噼里啪啦地倒下了——这种天赋就是让人心生怜悯。当过两次寡妇的巴罗夫人，有着一双黑漆漆的美目。我从未见过如此令人动容的眼睛，似乎每时每刻都有泪水要夺眶而出；这双眼睛让人觉得，这个世界对她来说，有着无法承受之重——你能感受到这一点。噢，可怜的人儿，她的不幸遭遇是任何人都无法忍受的。假如你像罗杰·查林一样，是个身强体壮又家财万贯的家伙，那你几乎无可避免地会对自己说：我一定要帮助一下这个孤独无依的小女人，让她远离那些人生的苦难。噢，如果能将这双楚楚动人的大眼睛里的忧伤拂去，那该是多么美妙的事情啊！我从罗杰那里得知，每个人都对巴罗夫人非常恶劣。她显然是那种诸事不顺的倒霉人儿中的一员。如果她结婚，丈夫会打她；如果她聘用经纪人，经纪人会骗她；如果她雇用一个厨师，这厨师会让她酗酒。她所珍爱的那些人，一个个都离她而去了。

当罗杰跟我说，他终于劝服了她同意跟自己结婚时，我祝他快乐。

“我希望你们能成为好朋友，”他说，“她有点儿怕你，你知道——她认为你这个人太冷淡。”

“真没想到，我不明白她怎么会这样想。”

“你真的喜欢她，是吧？”

“很喜欢。”

“她有段时间过得非常艰难，可怜人儿。我极其为她感到难过。”

“是的。”我说。

我的回答不能比这更简短了。我知道她很愚蠢，我认为她诡计多端，我坚信她是个冷酷无情的人。

第一次跟她见面时，我们一起打了桥牌。她是我的搭档，但两次动用王牌干掉了我最好的牌。打牌过程中，我表现得像个天使，但我不得不承认，如果有人眼睛里溢满了泪水，那个人只能是我，而不是她。那晚结束时，她输给我一大笔钱，她说会寄支票给我，但根本没寄。我只能想，下次见面时，带着可怜巴巴的表情的不是她，是我。

罗杰把她介绍给他的朋友，送她漂亮的珠宝，带她到这里、那里——没有不去的地儿。他们宣布婚礼将在不久后举行。罗杰感到非常快乐，他是在做一件好事，同时也是他喜欢的事。罗杰一直满足于独自一人，这时却热衷于与露丝在一起，确实非比寻常。

但突然间，他就不再爱她了，原因不得而知。不大可能是他厌倦了她的说话方式，因为她根本就不同人交流，或许只是——她那悲惨的表情已经不再能触动他的心弦。他的眼睛睁开了，他又重新成为曾经那个精明之人。他心里跟明镜似的，露丝·巴罗是下定决心要嫁给他了，但他庄严赌誓：没有任何东西能诱使他跟露丝·巴罗结婚。不过他的处境有些窘迫。现在，他重新恢复了自己的判断力，清楚地看到过去交往的是一个什么样的女人；他也明白，如果他请她主动放手的话，她一定会用她动人的方式去无限拔高所受到的情感伤害。再说，对一个男人来说，抛弃一个女人总是让人尴尬的，人们会倾向于认为他的行为有失检点。

罗杰决定保守自己的秘密。无论在言辞上还是姿态上，他都不让自己表露出对露丝·巴罗有任何的情感变化。他仍然留意着她所有的心愿，带她到饭店吃饭，陪她出去玩耍，送她鲜花，他依然讨人喜欢、魅力十足。他们决定，一旦找到适合他们的房子就立马结婚。之前他住的是单人套房，而她住的是带有家具的出租房，他们决定找一处合意的住宅。代理商寄给罗杰一些看房券，他带着露丝看了几套房子，但找到十分满意的房子很难。罗杰向更多的代理商提出了申请。他们看了一座又一座房子，看得甚是仔细，从地下室里的酒窖，到房顶下面的阁楼。有的房子太大，有的又太小了；有的离闹市太远，有的又太近了；有的过于昂贵，有的需要太多的修补；有的通气不佳，而有的室内风速过大；有的光线过暗，有的则一点儿遮蔽都没有。罗杰总能找到一处毛病，让房子不宜购买。他当然很难取悦，他怎么能忍心让他亲爱的露丝住在一套不完美的房子里呢？完美的房子是需要找的。找房是个累人的活儿，又让人烦心。不久，露丝开始焦躁起来。罗杰请她耐心些——在某个地方肯定有一套房子正是他们所渴望的，只需要再坚持一下，就一定能找到。他们找了几百套房子，爬了几千段楼梯，看过了难以尽数的厨房。露丝精疲力竭，不止一次动了肝火。

“如果你不能尽快找到房子，”她说，“我会再考虑我的想法的。哎呀，你老是这样，我们多少年也结不了婚。”

“不要说这样的话，”他回答，“我求你再耐心些。我刚刚收到一批全新的房源，都是最近刚认识的代理商提供的。他们手里至少有六十套房子。”

两人又开始了新一轮的求购，看的房子越来越多。他们已经找了两年啦！露丝的话越来越少，不时流露出轻蔑，她凄楚美丽的眼睛增添了一种愠怒的神色。人类的忍耐是有限度的，巴罗夫人有着天使般的耐心，但最终还是忍无可忍了。

“你到底想不想跟我结婚？”她问他。

她的话语里有一种异乎寻常的强硬，但这对他丝毫没有影响，他的回答仍然温文尔雅。

“我当然想啊。我们一找到房子就结婚。顺便告诉你，我刚听说有个房子，很适合我们。”

“我感觉不舒服，再也不想看什么房子了。”

“可怜的宝贝儿，恐怕是你太累了。”

露丝·巴罗病倒在床。她不愿再看到罗杰，罗杰倒是乐意前去她的住所看她，并给她带去鲜花。他像往常一样勤勉有加、殷勤备至。他每天给她写信，告诉她刚听说的房子。一星期过去了，罗杰收到了下面的信：

罗杰：

我认为你并没有真心爱我。我遇到了一个人，他愿意照顾我，我今天就同他结婚。

露丝

他派专人给她带去了回信。

露丝：

你的来信让我心碎，我永远都不能从这个打击中走出来，不过，你的幸福当然是我要首先考虑的。我给你寄去七张看房券，都是今天早上邮来的。我敢肯定，你一定能从中找到最适合你的房子。

罗杰

[1]　九柱戏，也称“保龄球”“地滚球”，起源于德国，是一种在木板球道上用球滚击木瓶的室内体育运动，流行于欧、美、大洋洲和亚洲一些国家。

教堂司事

叶雷　译

那天下午，位于内维尔广场的圣彼得教堂刚结束了一场洗礼仪式，艾伯特·爱德华·福尔曼仍然身披司事长袍。长袍已经半旧，他倒是有一件新的，但专门留在葬礼或婚礼（社会名流常常选择在内维尔广场的圣彼得教堂举办这些仪式）上穿。他把那件新长袍叠得方正笔挺，仿佛它不是羊驼毛织物，而是一件传了千秋万代的青铜器。他春风得意地披着这件长袍，因为它光荣地象征着他的职位。一旦脱下它（回家前他不得不这么做），他总有点儿张皇失措，仿佛衣不蔽体。他为这件长袍劳神费心，亲手把它熨烫得平整顺滑。在这个教堂做司事的十六年间，他有过一件又一件这样的长袍，但穿坏时总也舍不得扔掉，而是全部拿牛皮纸整整齐齐地包好，放在卧房衣橱最底下的抽屉里。

司事默默地埋首工作，换掉了大理石圣水盘上的描漆木盖，拿走了一张专门为一位年迈体衰的老太太搬来的椅子。只需等牧师从更衣室出来，他进去打扫干净便能回家了。片刻之后，他看见牧师从圣坛前走过，对祭台微微屈了一下膝，沿耳堂走了过来。但他仍旧穿着法衣。

“他在那里磨蹭什么呢？”司事喃喃自语道，“难道他不知道我着急回家喝下午茶吗？”

这位新到任的牧师才四十出头，面色红润，干劲冲天。对于前任牧师，艾伯特·爱德华依然念兹在兹。那位老派的牧师，做起布道来总是从容不迫，清亮的声音宛如珍珠落玉盘，还频繁与身份高贵的教区居民共同外出用膳。他喜欢让教堂里的事物井然有序，但从不苛求，不像这个新任牧师，每件事都事必躬亲。不过，艾伯特·爱德华深谙隐忍之道。圣彼得教堂坐落于上等街区，教区居民高贵优雅，而新任牧师来自伦敦东区[1]，自然不能指望他立刻从这些贵族身上学会谨慎而得体的行事风度。

“瞧他那风风火火的轻浮样子！”艾伯特·爱德华说，“不过假以时日，他总会成熟起来的。”

牧师走下耳堂，走到不用抬高音量就能让司事听清楚的地方便停下脚步。教堂是肃穆神圣之地，不容许高声说话。

“福尔曼，你能到更衣室来一下吗？我有事情跟你说。”

“我现在就过去，先生。”

牧师等他走近，他们便一道穿过了教堂。

“我觉得这次洗礼仪式十分成功，先生。您一抱起婴儿，他就不哭了，真是厉害。”

“确实经常如此，我也注意到了，”牧师说，露出一丝微笑，“毕竟我处理这种场面也是个老手了。”

牧师一直为此暗暗自豪着。他知道把婴儿抱起来的窍门，知道怎样立刻止住婴儿啼哭。那些目睹披着白色法袍的牧师将抱在他臂弯中的婴儿安抚下来的母亲和保姆常常对他赞不绝口，对此，牧师也并非毫无意识。司事知道牧师喜欢听到别人夸赏他这一项天才的技能。

牧师把艾伯特·爱德华领进更衣室。艾伯特·爱德华发现里面坐着两位教会委员，小小地吃了一惊。他没看见他们进去。他们和蔼可亲地向他点头示意。

“午安，阁下。午安，先生。”他逐一问候两位教会委员。

两位教会委员可谓年高德劭。艾伯特当了多久司事，他们几乎就当了多久教会委员。此刻，他们正坐在一张端庄典雅的大餐桌旁，那是前任牧师许多年前从意大利带回来的。新牧师在两人之间的空椅子上坐下。艾伯特·爱德华隔着桌子面朝他们站着，微微有些不安，心下疑惑发生了什么事。他还记得有一次琴师闯了祸，他们是如何不惜一切代价把事情掩盖了起来。内维尔广场的圣彼得教堂是如此尊贵，绝对不能卷入丑闻。牧师的脸红彤彤的，温和的表情里，透着一丝尘埃落定后的安详，但两位教会委员的表情却略显不安。

“牧师刚才肯定一直对他们纠缠不休来着，肯定，”司事暗暗想道，“他诱使他们做出违心的事情。就是这样，我敢保证。”

但艾伯特·爱德华那张棱角分明的脸并没有出卖这些想法。他生就贵族般的容貌，此刻恭恭敬敬站在那里，不卑不亢。在觅得这份神职工作之前，他一直是名男仆，但他只在钟鸣鼎食之家当差，他的态度举止是无可挑剔的。最开始的时候，他在一个巨贾之家做杂役，一步步从四等男仆升为一等男仆。后来，他在一位高贵的寡妇家中当了一年男管家，家中大小事务一概任他处置。圣彼得教堂的职位空缺出来时，他正在一位退休大使的家里管事，手下有两个人。他高大瘦削，不苟言笑，威严持重，即使看起来不像一位公爵，至少也像一名专门扮演公爵角色的老派演员。他有心机，有魄力，有自信。雇主都对他称赏不已。

牧师爽快干脆地开了口。

“福尔曼，我们要跟你说一件非常尴尬的事情。你已经在这里工作了很多年，我想爵爷阁下和会长阁下与我意见一致，认为你在任期间出色地履行了职责，获得了众人的认可。”

两位教会委员点点头。

“但前几天我忽然发现了一个很严重的问题，我觉得自己有义务告知教会委员们。你竟然不识字，这实在是太令我惊讶了。”

司事面不改色。

“前任牧师也知晓这一情况，先生，”他回应道，“他说这无关痛痒。他总说这个世界上的教育实在多得令他难以承受。”

“我从未听说过如此惊人之事，”会长喊起来，“按您的意思，您在这里足足当了十六年司事，却未能学会读书写字？”

“我十二岁就出来当差了，先生。最初那户人家的厨师试过教我，但我学得云里雾里。后来我忙于生计，一直没有时间念书。我从没感觉到有念书的必要。我常常想，现在的年轻人念书念得实在太多，他们本可以用这些时间做更有意义的事情。”

“可是，难道您不关心新闻吗？”另一位教会委员说，“难道您从未动过写信的念头吗？”

“亲爱的阁下，虽然我不识字，但我自有办法。况且近几年报纸上满是照片，我很清楚这个世界上发生着什么事。我的妻子很是识得几个字，如果我需要写信，她会帮助我。而且，我对赛马和彩票之类的事情也不感兴趣。”

两位教会委员不安地瞥了牧师一眼，便低头看向桌子。

“是这样，福尔曼，我已经和这两位委员详细讨论过此事，他们也认为这简直是天方夜谭。内维尔广场的圣彼得教堂大名鼎鼎，绝不能聘请一个不识字的司事。”

艾伯特·爱德华瘦黄的脸涨得通红。他窘迫地挪动着双脚，一言不发。

“请你理解我的苦衷，福尔曼，我丝毫没有埋怨你的意思。你非常称职，人品和能力都无可挑剔。但你这种可悲的无知很有可能给我们带来难以预料的灾难，我们无权铤而走险。小心驶得万年船，而且这也是原则问题。”

“为什么您不能尝试学习一下呢，福尔曼？”会长问道。

“不，先生，恐怕不行，已经太迟了。您也知道，我已经上年纪了。如果我年轻时都记不住那些字，现在就更记不住了。”

“我们也不是要赶你走，福尔曼，”牧师说，“但委员们和我已经达成共识。我们会给你三个月时间，如果到时你没有任何改观，恐怕就要请你另谋高就了。”

对这位新牧师，艾伯特·爱德华从未萌生过好感。当初他们把圣彼得教堂交至他手中，艾伯特便明言这将铸成大错。这个教区如此高贵，他与之格格不入。艾伯特稍稍站直了一些。他也算得上是才德兼备，他要维护自己的尊严。

“非常抱歉，先生，恐怕那对我已经没有什么意义了。我已经过了学习新事物的年纪。这么多年来，我不识字也过得很好。我不想说我有多么了不起，那样做没什么意思。但平心而论，我很感谢仁慈的上帝安排我如此过活，而我也可谓兢兢业业。即使我现在能学会读书写字，也不愿意浪费时间。”

“如果你固执己见，福尔曼，恐怕这里容不下你了。”

“好的，先生，我非常理解。等您找到新人来接替我的位置，我马上递交辞呈。”

当艾伯特·爱德华在牧师和两位教会委员身后关上大门的时候，他的举止一如既往地恭敬有礼。然而，他无论如何也无法继续装出一副若无其事的模样来捍卫自己的尊严。他的嘴唇不住地颤抖。他拖着沉沉的脚步走回更衣室，把司事长袍挂在属于他的钩子上。它见证过无数豪华的葬礼和华丽的婚礼，一场场都历历在目。他叹了一口气。他把更衣室收拾得井然有序、一尘不染，披上大衣，拿起帽子，穿过耳堂，锁上教堂大门，转过身去。他魂不守舍地横越广场，悲不自胜。他没有走向那条通往他家的路，即便家中正有一杯上好的浓茶在等着他，他转入了错误的路口。他沿街缓缓而行，一颗心沉沉地直往下坠，不知何以自处。他并不想回去给富贵人家当差，毕竟他已经自己当家做主这么多年了，因为不论牧师和教会委员如何信口雌黄，这些年一直都是他在运营内维尔广场的圣彼得教堂，他怎么能再回去受那样的委屈。他确实存了一大笔钱，但迟早会坐吃山空，而且生活成本逐年攀高。他竟也要为此等事情焦心劳思！圣彼得教堂的司事本应是终身职位，就如罗马教皇一般。他常常幻想自己死后第一个礼拜日的场景，牧师将在晚祷时充满赞赏之情地追思他，说：艾伯特·爱德华·福尔曼于漫长之任职期间恪尽职守，谦恭守礼，其嘉言懿行，堪为模范。他喟然长叹。艾伯特·爱德华不沾烟酒，但他不是个不懂变通的人。也就是说，晚饭时可以喝一杯啤酒，精疲力竭之时也会抽烟解乏。他想，此时此刻一根香烟可以平复他的心情，但他没带烟在身上，便环顾四周，想找到一间出售金箔牌香烟的店铺。视线范围之内没有，他继续往前走。那是一条长长的街道，街上开满各色店铺，却独独没有香烟店。

“真是奇怪了。”艾伯特·爱德华说。

他折回去，重新走了一趟。确实没有香烟店。他站定了，若有所思地前后打量这条街。

“我不可能是唯一一个走在这条街上，同时又想买一包香烟的人。”他说，“要是有人在这里开一间小香烟店，难道不是非常有利可图吗？一间卖香烟和糖果的小店。”

他灵光一闪。

“这是个好机会，”他说，“真是意外收获。”

他转身回家喝茶。

“艾伯特，你怎么一声不吭的？”他妻子说。

“我在想事情。”他说。

他反复彻底地把这件事考虑清楚之后，第二天又到那条街去，幸运地觅得一家心仪的小店铺。二十四小时后，他租下了它。一个月后，艾伯特·爱德华·福尔曼永远地离开内维尔广场的圣彼得教堂，开创了自己的事业，成为一名烟草商和报刊经销商。他妻子说，作为堂堂的教堂司事，此等行径简直是堕落无耻。但他回应说，人不得不跟上潮流，教堂已然不是从前的教堂，今后他要自食其力。香烟店大获成功，仅仅过了一年左右，他就发现自己可以开一间分店，聘一位经理来打理。他另觅没有香烟店的长街，正巧碰上一家店铺招租，便租下来，备足货。分店也获利丰厚。于是他想，他既然能开一家分店，为什么不干脆多开几家，便开始在伦敦四处走动，每发现一条既没有香烟店又有店铺招租的长街，就把店铺租下来。十年间，他开了不下十间分店，日进斗金。他每周一去各间分店巡视一番，收取每周的进款，把它们存入银行。

一天早上，他正要把一大捆钞票和一大包沉沉的银币存入银行，司库说经理想见他。他被引进一间办公室，经理忙上前跟他握手。

“福尔曼先生，我想跟您谈谈您在我们银行的存款。请问您知道具体数目吗？”

“确切的数字说不上来，先生，但我知道大概有多少。”

“不计您今天的存款，目前共有三万英镑出头。把这样一笔巨款存在银行不太上算，我建议您拿去投资。”

“我不想冒险，先生。我知道把它们存在银行很安全。”

“您完全可以放心。我们会给您列出一份保证收益的金边债券名单。收益率比存在我们银行要高得多。”

福尔曼先生那张贵族般的脸上露出困惑的表情。“我从未接触过股票债券之类的，这要麻烦您全权处理了。”他说。

经理微笑道：“我们会竭尽所能。下次您只要来签署委托书即可。”

“这倒不难，”艾伯特犹疑地说，“但我怎么知道您让我签的是什么？”

“我想您应该会先看看委托书的内容。”经理说，语气中隐隐地透出一丝尖刻。

福尔曼先生向经理微微一笑，打消他的疑虑。

“先生，事实上，我不识字。我知道这听起来很奇怪，但事实就是这样，我是个文盲。我只会写自己的名字，而且是为了做生意才学会的。”

经理惊讶得从椅子上跳了起来。

“我这辈子从未听说过如此不可思议的事情。”

“就是这样，先生。我一直没机会学识字，等到有机会，出于某个原因，我却不愿意学了。我有点儿倔。”

经理盯着他，仿佛他是一只史前怪兽。

“您是说，您不识字，却把生意做得这么大，还积攒起一笔三万英镑的财富？天啊，要是您识字，现在该从事多么了不起的事业啊！”

“我还真知道答案，先生。”福尔曼先生说，他那一如既往的高贵的脸上挂着一丝微笑，“那样的话，我现在会在内维尔广场的圣彼得教堂任职司事。”

[1]　伦敦东区为贫民区。

芒特拉戈勋爵

叶雷　译

奥德林大夫看看桌上的钟：五点四十分。他的病人竟然迟到了，真是令人惊讶，因为芒特拉戈勋爵向来为自己的守时而自豪。芒特拉戈勋爵好为人师，不论说点儿什么，总是煞有介事的，说出来的话一律带着格言的意味。他说惯了什么准时是对智者的赞美，对蠢材的谴责。芒特拉戈勋爵原来约的是五点半。

奥德林大夫长得乏善可陈，又高又瘦，削肩膀，有点儿驼背，灰白的头发稀稀落落，蜡黄色的长脸上爬满了皱纹。他不到五十岁，看起来却要老得多。一双淡蓝色的大眼睛总是昏昏欲睡，你要是跟他待上一会儿，就会发现这双眼睛几乎一动不动，只是一直死死地盯住你的脸，但尽管它们如此空洞无物，也不会令人难受。它们几乎从不闪烁，永不泄露他思想上的蛛丝马迹，而且无论他说什么，它们都我行我素地一成不变。要是你仔细观察他，就会惊讶地发现他连眨眼的次数都比常人少得多。他的手相当大，手指又细又长。这双手柔软却坚定，冰冷却干爽。假如不专门仔细看，你永远说不清楚奥德林大夫穿的是什么。他总是穿深色的衣裳，戴黑领带，这种穿着越发显得他那皱巴巴的黄脸没有血色，那空洞的双眼死滞无神。他总是一副病恹恹的样子。

奥德林大夫是一个心理治疗师。他误打误撞地入了行，每次给人看病都提心吊胆的。大战爆发时，他刚取得行医资格，正在各家医院实习。他主动申请为国效力，不久被派往法国。正是在那个时候，他发现了自己罕见的天赋。他用他那双冰凉而坚定的双手轻抚病人，就能减轻他们的痛苦。他和病人谈话，也常常能帮助备受失眠之苦的人顿生睡意。他说话很慢，他的音色普通之极，他不论说什么都是一样的语气，但却轻柔悦耳，使人平静。他告诉病人他们必须休息，无须担心，必须睡觉，接着睡意便会侵入他们筋疲力尽的骨头，就像在人满为患的长凳上挤出一个位置一般，安宁会把他们的焦虑挤走，睡意会降临到他们疲倦的眼睑上，仿佛绵绵春雨落在新土上一般。奥德林大夫发现，他用低沉单调的声音和病人说话，用空洞无神的眼睛凝视病人，或者用修长坚定的手指轻抚他们的额头，就可以舒缓病人的不安情绪，浇灭令病人坐卧难安的心火，并驱散日夜折磨他们的恐惧。有时他的治疗效果堪称神奇。有一个人在轰炸中被埋进土里，成了哑巴，他成功帮助这个人重新开口说话；另一个人因飞机失事不幸瘫痪，在他的帮助下，病人的四肢恢复了知觉。他无法理解自己的力量，并对这一转变秉持怀疑态度，尽管人们都说，遇到这种情况首先要自信，但他永远做不到。只是，就连最疑神疑鬼的目击者都认为他的行为有神奇的疗效，他只好承认自己有某种神秘的能力，说不清道不明，使他做出连自己也无法解释的事情来。战争结束后，他去维也纳进修，又去了苏黎世，最后在伦敦安顿下来，凭借这些莫名其妙得来的技巧行医糊口。不觉已经过了十五年，他在业内名声大震，关于他的奇闻逸事在坊间盛传。尽管他收费不菲，病人却多得看不过来。奥德林大夫自知取得了不少非凡的成就。他挽救过许多濒临自杀的人，治好了许多精神病患者，帮助生不如死的人摆脱痛苦，彻底扭转了不幸的婚姻。他消灭了丑恶的本性，把很多人从怨恨中释放了出来，让病人的精神恢复了健康。然而，尽管成果卓著，内心深处他一直怀疑自己不过是个江湖医生。

运用连自己都不能理解的力量行医，在他是一件违心之事。他是个诚实的人，连他自己都不相信自己，却叫病人相信他，这实在有违他的诚信。他已经家财万贯，不需要再工作了，而且工作也令他筋疲力尽，他已经无数次萌生过退意。他熟读弗洛伊德和荣格[1]以及其他心理学家的著作，但一直心怀不满，他确信他们所有的理论都是故弄玄虚，尽管治疗效果出人意料的好。十五年间，病人前赴后继地来到他在温坡街[2]上的昏暗房间，他还有什么丑恶的人性没有见识过？人们告诉他不可告人的秘密，有时迫不及待，有时羞羞答答，有时欲言又止，有时怒不可遏，他早就安之若素了，再没有什么能使他惊讶激动了。他现在知道了，人都是骗子，爱慕虚荣，他所知道的关于他们的事远比这些糟糕多了，但他也知道自己没有权利去评判或者声讨他们。只是，年复一年，随着这些可怕的秘密不断地传入他的耳朵，他的脸色变得越来越灰暗，皱纹也越来越深，本就空洞的双眼也越来越疲倦。他几乎忘记了怎么笑，除非偶尔为了放松去读小说的时候。那些作者真的会认为笔下的男男女女是真实的吗？如果他们知道了真实的人要复杂得多，复杂到难以想象的程度，他们灵魂中的各种元素将会如何你死我活地争斗，而这些将他们折磨得生不如死的斗争又是多么的阴暗和丑恶啊！

已经五点四十五分了。奥德林大夫诊治过许多病人，但在他的记忆中，没有哪个病人比芒特拉戈勋爵更奇怪。首先，这个病人的身份非常特殊。芒特拉戈勋爵能力过人，出身高贵，不到四十岁就被任命为外交大臣，他如今任职三年，已经制定出高明的政策，令人叹服，成为保守党中公认的最佳政治家。可惜他的父亲是贵族，一旦去世，他就不能继续在下议院中占有席位，这也使他失去了竞逐首相的资格。不过，即便是在民主时代的英国，首相也不可能来自上议院，只要保守党可以连续执政，芒特拉戈勋爵就能稳坐外交大臣之位，长久地掌控祖国的外交政策。

芒特拉戈勋爵有许多优点。他聪明勤奋，广为游历，能娴熟地驾驭好几门语言。从青少年时期开始，他就专门从事外交事务，切实了解其他国家的政治和经济情况。他敏锐果敢，擅长在公共场所和国会演讲，头脑清晰，一丝不苟，还时常妙语连珠。他是一个才华横溢的辩手，他巧辩的天赋为人称道。他生得一表人才，高大英俊。虽然头秃得厉害了些，也多少有点儿胖，却令他看上去更加稳重老成，这反而成了优势。年轻的时候，他也算是个运动员，参加过牛津的划艇赛，也是英格兰众所周知的优秀射击手。二十四岁时娶了一位十八岁的妻子，岳父是位公爵，岳母是某位美国富豪的继承人。这位既富有又高贵的夫人给他生了两个儿子。两人已经分居多年，但为了保全面子，在公众场合总是出双入对，况且双方都没有外遇，别人也没法说他们闲话。芒特拉戈勋爵实在是太过雄心勃勃，太过勤奋，加之太过爱国，一心扑在事业上，简直不可能受到声色犬马的诱惑。总的来说，他有很多过人之处，因此备受爱戴，功成名就。不幸的是，他的缺点也很显著。

他势利得出奇。如果这个爵位是他父亲挣来的，他这么势利倒实属正常。假如一个律师、制造商或者酿酒师获封为贵族，他的儿子过分地珍重自己的身份地位完全无可厚非。但芒特拉戈勋爵父亲的伯爵爵位是查理二世[3]授予的，他们祖上受封男爵更可远溯至玫瑰战争[4]时期。三百年来，该爵位的继承者不断和英国最显贵的家族联姻。但芒特拉戈勋爵却像暴发户喜欢炫耀家财一般，从不放过任何机会向别人炫耀自己的身份地位。他的举止雍容高贵，但只有对他认为与自己平起平坐的人如此。在社会地位不如他的人面前，他冷漠粗暴。下人被他呼来喝去，秘书也动辄受辱，在他连任的政府部门任职的下属官员对他又怕又恨。他傲慢得吓人。他不得不与形形色色的人接触，他知道他们中的大部分人都不及他聪明，他也从不在他们面前掩饰这一事实。人性的缺陷总是令他不耐烦。他觉得对别人指手画脚是他天生的权利，如果有人请他听取意见，或者要求他解释为何做此决定，无异于引火烧身。他自私到无法形容。别人替他做事，他总觉得理所应当，因为他身居高位，并且才华出众，但他从未想过自己也应该为别人做事。他树敌众多，但没有一个是他瞧得起的，在他眼里没有人值得他费心帮助或者怜悯同情。没有人愿意和他做朋友。长官不信任他，因为他们怀疑他不忠；党内其他成员也不喜欢他，因为他目中无人，横行霸道。然而他太卓尔不群，太爱国，太聪明，把外交事务打理得太出色，他们不得不忍受他的种种不如意之处。他们之所以还忍得下去，也是因为他有时十分招人喜欢。遇到他认为与自己平等的人或是想要结交的人时，陪同外国权贵或名媛淑女时，他会变得欢快、机智和温文尔雅，举手投足间都带着切斯特菲尔德勋爵[5]的影子。他会讲精彩的故事，他能够表现得自然而然，通情达理，甚至知识渊博。你会惊讶于他的无所不知，情趣高雅，和非同凡响。你会觉得他是世界上最好的同伴，你会忘了他昨天才侮辱过你，并且很可能明天又要对你视而不见。

芒特拉戈勋爵差点儿与奥德林大夫失之交臂。有个秘书打电话给奥德林大夫，说他的爵爷想向他咨询，劳烦他第二天早上十点钟到官邸走一趟。奥德林大夫说他去不了，但很乐意与爵爷预约后天五点钟在咨询室见面。秘书记下来，过了一会儿回复说芒特拉戈勋爵坚持在自家官邸会见奥德林大夫，随便大夫收多少钱。奥德林大夫说他只在自己的咨询室会见病人，并表示抱歉，如果芒特拉戈勋爵不准备来见他，他恐怕不能替爵爷排忧解难。一刻钟后，一封便笺送到他手里，说爵爷将于明天五点钟过来，而不是后天。

芒特拉戈勋爵按时赴约，但他没有进门，而是站在门边不可一世地上下打量奥德林大夫。奥德林大夫认为，爵爷肯定已经怒火中烧。他盯着爵爷不说话。这个肥胖沉重的男人像个小巨人，头发开始发灰，向后平梳着，把眉毛衬得很高贵。圆鼓鼓的脸配上端正突出的五官，加之一副桀骜不驯的表情，乍一看倒也有几分十八世纪波旁王室成员的神气。

“看来见你比见首相还难啊，奥德林大夫。我可是个日理万机的人。”

“你不坐下吗？”大夫说。

他面不改色，仿佛芒特拉戈勋爵的话只是耳旁风。奥德林大夫坐在桌子旁的椅子上，芒特拉戈勋爵仍然站着，本来就阴霾满布的眉头蹙得更深了。

“我想我应该告诉你我是外交大臣。”爵爷严厉地说。

“你不坐下吗？”大夫重复道。

芒特拉戈勋爵晃了晃身子，仿佛要立刻转身大步流星地走出咨询室，但他显然仔细想了想这是否是他的本意，于是便坐下了。奥德林大夫展开一本巨大的笔记本，拿起笔，头也不抬地写起来。

“年龄？”

“四十二。”

“结婚了吗？”

“结了。”

“结婚多久了？”

“十八年。”

“有孩子了吗？”

“有两个儿子。”

芒特拉戈勋爵一边粗声粗气地回答问题，奥德林大夫一边把答案记下来，然后他斜靠在椅背上看着爵爷。他没有说话，只是用空洞呆滞的眼睛严肃地看着病人。

“你来找我所为何事？”他终于问道。

“我听说过你。我知道你给嘉纽女士看过病，她说效果还不错。”

奥德林大夫没有回答，依然死死地盯着对方的脸。但这双眼睛毫无表情，仿佛根本看不见爵爷。

“我可不是什么神医。”他终于说，没有一丝笑容，但眼底闪过淡淡的笑意，“就算我做了什么神奇的事情，伦敦皇家内科医学院也不会给我颁发证书。”

芒特拉戈勋爵忍不住笑了一声。看来那缓解了他的敌意，他的口气柔软了些。

“你可是名声在外，看得出来人们很信任你。”

“你来找我所为何事？”

现在轮到芒特拉戈勋爵不说话了，一副难以启齿的模样。奥德林大夫等待着。最后芒特拉戈勋爵终于鼓足勇气开了口。

“我健康得不得了。几天前，我让我的私人医生帮我做了次体检，就是奥古斯塔斯·菲茨赫伯特爵士，你肯定听说过他。他说我像三十岁的年轻人一样壮实。我对国家可谓鞠躬尽瘁，但乐此不疲，工作对我而言是一种享受。我不怎么抽烟，喝酒也很节制，经常运动，生活规律。我健康极了，一点儿毛病也没有。我想你现在肯定会把我看成恶作剧的蠢小孩。”

奥德林大夫知道自己必须帮助他。

“我不知道可以为你做什么，但我会尽力而为。你有感到痛苦不堪吗？”

芒特拉戈勋爵蹙起眉头。

“我可是个举足轻重的人物，我奉命做出的决定不仅直接影响国家利益，还关系到世界和平。我的判断必须公平，我的头脑必须保持清醒，这绝对必要。我严于律己，坚决不让任何可能引致烦恼的事情影响到我的工作表现。”

奥德林大夫一直盯着他，看出不少问题。在他的病人虚浮的架子和傲慢的自负背后，潜藏着无法驱散的焦虑。

“我之所以请你上门，是因为这么多年的经验告诉我，相比熟悉的环境，人在肮脏的咨询室里更容易向医生推心置腹。”

“这里确实够脏的。”芒特拉戈勋爵刻薄地说，然后停了下来。这个人向来充满自信，思维敏捷，雷厉风行，这一刻他却忐忑不安，张皇失措。他勉强挤出笑容，好让医生认为自己毫不紧张，但他的眼睛却出卖了他烦乱的心情。当他再度开口时，表现出一种不自然的诚实。

“为了这么微不足道的事情来麻烦你，我真有点儿不好意思。恐怕你只会说我是个笨蛋，简直是在浪费你的时间。”

“再微不足道的事情也可能很重要，可能是深度神经错乱的表现。别担心浪费我的时间。”

奥德林先生的声音低沉严肃，平缓的语调有一种奇异的抚慰作用。芒特拉戈勋爵终于下定决心把心里话说出来。

“是这样的，我近来一直在做一些很无聊的梦。我也知道拿它们当回事真的很蠢，但——好吧，事实上，恐怕正是它们把我折磨得心神不宁。”

“可以描述一下吗？”

芒特拉戈勋爵不好意思地笑了，他试着笑得轻松一些，却越发显得苦涩。

“它们简直愚蠢至极，我实在有些难以启齿。”

“没关系。”

“好吧。第一个梦是从大概一个月之前开始的。我梦见自己去康纳马拉大宅参加宴会。那是一个官方宴会，国王和王后将应邀驾临，我当然要盛装出席，我佩戴着勋带和星形勋章。我走进衣帽间，让仆人帮我脱掉大衣。有个小个子男人也在那里，他叫欧文·格里菲思，是威尔士的小议员。实话告诉你，我见到他非常惊讶。他地位低微，我自言自语地说，‘真是的，莉迪亚·康纳马拉也太离谱了，说不定下次连乞丐也会请过来。’我想他一定在非常好奇地望着我，但我没有理他。事实上，我装作没看见他，径直走上楼梯。我猜你从来没去过那里吧？”

“没有。”

“这就对了，那不是你会去的地方。那座房子俗不可耐，但有一条非常漂亮的大理石楼梯，康纳马拉夫妇在楼梯上面接待客人。我和康纳马拉夫人握手时，她惊讶地看着我，忍不住咯咯地笑起来。我没有太在意，她总是很蠢，没有教养，举止风度比起她那受封于查理二世的祖先好不了多少。我不得不承认，康纳马拉大宅的会客室还算体面。我一直往里走，向很多人点头示意，和他们握手，后来看见德国大使和一个奥地利大公[6]相谈甚欢。我正好有事找大公，便上前伸出手。大公一看见我就捧腹大笑起来。他竟敢公然侮辱我，我严厉地上下扫视他，但他笑得更加厉害。我正准备反唇相讥时，会客室突然肃静下来，我想一定是国王和王后驾到了。我转身背向大公，朝前走去，然后，突然之间，我发现自己没穿长裤，露着丝织内裤，还有猩红色的吊带袜！难怪康纳马拉夫人窃笑，也难怪大公狂笑！我无法告诉你那一刻究竟意味着什么。简直丢脸丢到家了。我惊醒了，一身冷汗。噢，你不知道当我发现它仅仅是梦时有多欣慰。”

“这个梦也算不上很离奇。”奥德林大夫说。

“我也是这样想。但第二天发生了一件奇怪的事。我走在下议院的走廊里，那个格里菲思慢条斯理地从我身边经过。他故意看看我的腿，又直直看着我的脸，我敢肯定他在那里挤眉弄眼。尽管很荒唐，但我突然觉得，前一天晚上，他确实在我的梦里，看到我在人前出洋相，并在一旁窃喜。不过我也知道那是不可能的，那只是梦罢了。我冷冷地斜了他一眼，他便继续往前走了，但笑得摇头晃脑的。”

芒特拉戈勋爵从口袋里掏出手帕擦干手心。现在他不再挣扎着要掩饰自己内心的不安，奥德林大夫的眼睛一刻也没有离开他。

“把另一个梦告诉我。”

“第二晚的梦更荒诞了。我梦见自己在下议院里参加一场关于外交事务的辩论，这场辩论不仅备受全国上下关注，甚至堪称举世瞩目。政府决定调整一项与帝国命运息息相关的政策，那可是个历史性的场合。下议院当然是座无虚席，所有的大使都在场，连过道也被挤得水泄不通。我当晚负责发表一篇重要的演讲，讲稿准备得非常仔细。像我这样的人自然有许多敌人，不少人对我年纪轻轻便身居高位心怀怨妒，要知道很多聪明绝顶的人在我这个岁数能当个小官员就已经心满意足了。我决心不仅要让这次演讲流芳百世，同时还要通过它来使那些诋毁我的人无话可说。想到自己所说的一字一句都牵动着世界的命脉，实在是激动不已。我站起身。如果你在下议院开过会，就知道在辩论的时候议员们会不断地交头接耳，沙沙地查阅文件，把报告翻来翻去，然而我一开口，全场立刻安静下来。我忽然看到那个面目可憎的威尔士议员格里菲思就坐在对面一张长凳上向我吐舌头。不知道你有没有听过一首粗俗的舞厅流行曲，叫作《双人自行车》，很多年前曾红极一时。为了向格里菲思表示我有多么瞧不起他，我开始唱这首歌。第一段唱得非常好，面向讲台的听众们惊讶得一时语塞，唱完后，他们高喊‘继续！继续！’我举手示意他们安静下来，接着唱第二段。所有人一声不吭地听我唱下去，我察觉到自己越唱越难听，感到很气恼，我的男中音可是十分优美动人的。我决心要挽回面子，但当我唱第三段的时候，有人开始笑，笑声一发不可收拾，各国大使，贵宾席上的权贵，女宾席上的贵妇，记者，全部笑得前俯后仰，笑声响彻云霄，有人笑得歪到一旁，有人在座位上打滚。每个人都笑个不停，除了坐在我身后的前座议员席上的大臣们。他们被空前的狂乱吓得目瞪口呆，感到难以置信，坐在那里一动不动。我扫了他们一眼，突然意识到自己闯了大祸。我让自己成了全世界的笑柄，我痛苦地意识到这下想不辞职都不行了。我惊醒了，知道这只是一个梦。”

讲述这个梦的时候，芒特拉戈勋爵完全顾不上保持优雅的举止风度。等到终于说完，他已脸如死灰，浑身乱颤。但他努力振作起来，勉强用颤抖的嘴唇笑道：

“这个梦真是太天马行空了，连我都忍俊不禁。我没再多想。第二天下午，当我走进下议院时自觉状态良好。那天下午的辩论很无趣，但我必须在场，于是我就翻起一些需要我审阅的文件来。忘记是因为什么事情了，我偶然抬起头来，发现格里菲思正在发言。他的威尔士口音真是难听，外表也邋里邋遢，令人反感。我简直无法想象他能说出值得我花时间去听的话，便打算低头继续看文件，他却忽然引用了两句《双人自行车》里的歌词。我忍不住斜了他一眼，他正盯着我，嘲讽地笑着。我微微耸耸肩。一个地位低微的威尔士小议员竟敢那样看着我，真是不知天高地厚。他引用了那首歌的歌词，那首我在梦里唱了一整晚的歌，难道仅仅是一个巧合吗？真是奇怪。我又继续开始看文件，但坦白说，我根本无法集中精神。我感到有些蹊跷。欧文·格里菲思闯入了我的第一个梦，在康纳马拉大宅的那个，过后给了我一个非常强烈的印象，他肯定看到了我的窘相。他刚才引用那两句歌词真的只是一个巧合吗？我不禁问自己，他是否也梦见了我的梦？不过当然这纯属异想天开，我决心不再大惊小怪。”

两人都不说话。奥德林大夫看着芒特拉戈勋爵，芒特拉戈勋爵也看着奥德林大夫。

“其他人的梦总是非常无聊。我太太偶尔做一个梦，第二天就非要告诉我她梦见了什么不可，还要把每一个细节都认认真真地描述出来，真是烦死人。”

奥德林大夫微微一笑。

“你做的梦还挺有趣的。”

“我再告诉你几天后我做的一个梦吧。我梦见自己走进莱姆豪斯区[7]的一间小酒吧。我从未去过莱姆豪斯区，而且入读牛津大学之后就再也没有去过酒吧，但我看着我走进的那条街和那间酒吧就像我是正身处家中一般。我走进一个房间，我不知道他们是否称它为沙龙吧或是私人吧，那儿有一个火炉和一张大大的皮面扶手椅，另一边则摆着一张小沙发，吧台占了一整面墙，望出去就是公共区。临门是一张圆形大理石桌面的桌子，旁边放着两张扶手椅。那是周六晚上，酒吧里人山人海。灯大亮着，但许多人在抽烟，熏得我眼睛疼。我打扮得像个流氓，戴着帽子，脖子上围着丝巾。我觉得那里的人都喝醉了，有趣得很。留声机正播着唱片，也可能是无线电的声音，我也分不清楚。火炉前有两个女人在跳着古怪的舞，她们身边围了一小群人，笑着，欢呼着，唱着歌。我起身过去凑热闹，有人冲我说，‘来杯酒吧，比尔！’桌子上放着装满黑色液体的玻璃杯，我知道它叫作棕色艾尔酒。他递给我一杯，我不想惹人怀疑就喝了下去。正在跳舞的其中一个女人撇下同伴，从我手里夺过杯子。‘你这是想怎么着？’她说，‘你喝的是我的酒。’‘啊，真对不起，’我说，‘这位先生叫我喝，我还以为是他请客呢。’‘好吧，伙计，’她说，‘没关系。来和我跳支舞吧！’我还来不及拒绝，她已经一把拉住我跳起舞来。然后我发现自己坐在了扶手椅上，她就坐在我大腿上，我们喝着同一杯啤酒。我必须说，对我来说夫妻生活从来不是什么要紧的事情。我之所以这么早结婚，是身份与地位所需，同时也是为了一次性彻底解决性的问题。我决心要有两个儿子，达成任务后就把男女之事抛开了。我忙得不可开交，哪里有时间想这类事，况且我又是个公众人物，传出桃色新闻无异于自毁前程。政治家最有价值的资本就是与女人毫无瓜葛。对于那些事业被女人搞得一塌糊涂的男人，我最不耐烦了，我鄙视他们。我大腿上的女人喝得醉醺醺的，既不漂亮也不年轻，事实上，她只是个黑乎乎的老妓女。她令我恶心之极，但当她把嘴凑上来亲我时，尽管她满嘴酒臭，一口烂牙，尽管我也恨自己不争气，但我想要她——不顾一切地想要她。突然我听到一个声音，‘那就对了，老友，好好享受吧。’我抬起头来，是欧文·格里菲思。我差点儿跳了起来，但那个可怕的女人压着我。‘别理他，’她说，‘他总是闲得慌。’‘别磨蹭了，’他说，‘茉儿可好了，她不会让你白花钱的。’在那种荒唐的情境下碰到他已经够糟糕的了，他居然还叫我‘老友’。我把那个女人推开，站起来凶恶地面向着他。‘我不认识你，也不想认识你。’我说。‘我可认识你。’他说，‘茉儿，你可要看紧了，他经常赖账，别让他跑了。’旁边的桌子上有一瓶酒，我二话不说，抓起瓶脖子，用尽全身力气从他头上敲下去，一下子把自己惊醒了。”

“那样的梦也不是不可理解，”奥德林大夫说，“只是复仇的天性在品德高尚的人身上闪现出来罢了。”

“这个梦本身不值一提，太荒唐了，关键是第二天发生的事情。我急于查点儿资料，便走进议会图书馆，找到那本书翻起来。我随便找了个座位坐下，没想到格里菲思就坐在我旁边。另一个工党议员走进来，踱到他身旁。‘你好，欧文，’那个工党议员对他说，‘你气色不太好。’‘我头疼得厉害，’他回答说，‘就跟被酒瓶子砸到脑袋似的。’”

这会儿，芒特拉戈勋爵痛苦得面如死灰。

“那一刻，我确信之前被我抛弃的想法并不荒谬。格里菲思和我做着一样的梦，并且与我一样记得清清楚楚。”

“那可能也只是个巧合。”

“他那句话不是对朋友说的，而是故意说给我听的。他看着我，一脸怨毒。”

“为什么这个人总是出现在你的梦中？你对此有什么想法吗？”

“毫无头绪。”

奥德林大夫的目光从未从病人脸上移开，他看出来爵爷撒谎了。他用铅笔在吸墨纸上胡乱画了一两根曲线。要让病人坦白往往需要花费很长时间，纵然他们也知道如果不说实话，大夫就无法提供帮助。

“你刚刚向我描述的这些梦是三周多前做的。那之后你还做过吗？”

“每晚都做。”

“每晚都能梦见格里菲思？”

“是的。”

大夫在吸墨纸上画了更多的线条。这间小屋死一般的寂静，沉闷得令人发慌，光线昏暗，他希望这种氛围能让芒特拉戈勋爵变得敏感起来。芒特拉戈勋爵一甩身靠在椅背上，别过头去，躲开了对方严肃的目光。

“奥德林大夫，请你一定帮帮我。我已经撑不下去了，再这样下去我一定会发疯。我不敢上床睡觉，已经熬了好几晚。我坐着读书，困了就披上大衣出去走，直到精疲力竭。但我不得不睡觉，我有这么多事情要处理，我必须时刻处于最佳状态，充分调动各方面的能力。我需要休息，但越睡越累。我一睡着就开始做梦，总是梦见他，那个下流的无赖，对我露齿而笑，他讥讽我，鄙视我。我受不了这种虐待。真的，大夫，我不是梦里的那个我，用这些梦来判断我的为人是不公正的。不管你问谁，他都会说我是正直诚实的正派人，在公在私我都光明磊落，没有人可以对我的人品横加指责。我一心只是想为国效力，保住祖国的荣耀地位。我有钱，有地位，我不像地位低微的人那样，如此容易就向诱惑屈服，我也不需要别人说我清正廉洁。但我可以发誓，荣誉也好，特权也好，私利也好，没有什么能让我做出对不起这个职位的事情。我牺牲了一切才换来今天的成就，我要的是名垂千古，这个愿望马上要实现了，我却开始畏缩。我并不是梦里那个卑鄙、懦弱、下流的生物，那个可怕的无赖看到的都是假象。我告诉你的那三个梦简直不值一提，但我在梦里的所作所为是如此野蛮，如此恐怖，如此可耻，就算死我也不想说出来。但他全都看见了，他记得一清二楚。我简直不能面对他那嘲讽和厌恶的目光，我甚至不敢跟他说话，我知道他只会把我的话当成骗人的鬼话。他亲眼看见我做出了任何有自尊的人都不会做的事。不论谁做了这样的事，都会众叛亲离，锒铛入狱。他还听到我说的下流话，在他眼中，我不知所谓、令人作呕。他鄙视我，而且马上就要把我的丑态公之于众。真的，如果你不帮我想想办法，我只能自杀，或者杀死他。”

“换作是我就不会杀他，”奥德林大夫淡淡地说，依然是舒缓的声音，“在这个国家，杀害同胞可是滔天大罪。”

“你是说我要为此偿命？我不会因此而上绞刑台的。谁会知道我是凶手？那个梦让我知道应该怎么做。真的，我用酒瓶砸他的头后，他第二天头疼欲裂，看不清楚东西，那是他自己说的。那表明他在睡梦中的遭遇会影响到醒来后的他。下次我不用酒瓶砸他。等下次做梦的时候，我要拿着一把刀，或者在口袋里装一支枪，我一定能做到的，因为我一心要杀死他！我要抓住机会，像刺死一头猪一样刺死他，像射死一条狗一样射死他。我要射穿他的心脏，摆脱他那惨无人道的虐待。”

也许有人会觉得芒特拉戈勋爵疯了。然而，奥德林大夫行医这么多年，专职医治生了病的人类灵魂，他知道被我们称作正常与失常的人之间可能并没有那么明显的区别。他知道，有很多人在我们眼中正常健康，安分守己，不存非分之想，不仅能把自己照顾得妥妥帖帖，还能惠及旁人。但当你获得他们的信任，撕掉他们在世人面前戴着的面具后，却常常会发现他们不仅反常得变态，还有许多奇怪的念头，难填的欲壑，从这些方面来看，他们完全可以被称为精神病人。不要幻想把这些人全部关进疯人院，世界上根本没有那么多疯人院。无论如何，即使一个人做了奇怪的梦，并因此而变得神经兮兮，也未必就可以被诊断为患有精神病。这个病例很特殊，但也只不过是比奥德林大夫的其他病人严重一些而已。然而，奥德林大夫很有点儿怀疑，他惯用的有效治疗方法能不能治好这位爵爷的病。

“你有没有咨询过我的同行？”他问。

“只有奥古斯塔斯爵士。我只是告诉他我在经受噩梦的折磨。他说我操劳过度，建议我去旅游散心。简直胡闹！国际形势紧张得很，我哪里离得开外交部？我知道外交部少了我可不行，况且我要是在这个关键时刻犯错，前途就毁了。他给我开镇静药，我吃了毫无效果，他又给我开补药，我吃了更难受。要他有什么用！”

“为什么总是这个人不断地在你梦中出现？你能想出点儿什么理由来吗？”

“这个问题你已经问过我，我也已经回答过了。”

他说得倒也不错，但奥德林大夫对他的回答并不满意。

“刚刚你提到了虐待。欧文·格里菲思为什么要虐待你？”

“我不知道。”

芒特拉戈勋爵躲开了奥德林大夫的目光。奥德林大夫非常肯定他没有说真话。

“你伤害过他吗？”

“从未。”

芒特拉戈勋爵一动不动，但奥德林大夫有一种奇怪的感觉，觉得他仿佛缩成了一团。眼前这个男人，高大威武，桀骜不驯，好像问他这样的问题无疑是一种傲慢无礼的行为。但在这个外表之下，某些东西隐约泄露出他内心的慌乱和恐惧，让人想起落入陷阱的野兽。奥德林大夫探过身去，用严厉的目光强迫芒特拉戈勋爵与自己对视。

“你肯定？”

“当然肯定。看来你没有弄清楚，我和他是两个世界的人。对此我也懒得解释，但我必须提醒你，我贵为外交大臣，而格里菲思只不过是一个无足挂齿的工党议员，我和他风马牛不相及。他出身低微，而我总是出入于上流场所，基本见不到他。我的政治地位也比他高出太多，根本不可同日而语。”

“如果你不肯坦诚相告，我就无能为力。”

芒特拉戈勋爵扬起眉毛，声音粗哑地说：

“我不习惯别人质疑我的话，奥德林大夫。如果你要这样做，继续留在这里打扰你只是在浪费我的时间。请你告诉我的秘书治疗费用是多少，他会给你寄支票。”

如果只看奥德林大夫脸上的表情，你一定会以为他没有听到芒特拉戈勋爵的话。他继续定定地看着爵爷的眼睛，用严肃而低沉的声音说：“你有做过什么可能令他视为伤害的事情吗？”

芒特拉戈勋爵犹疑了。他的目光转向别处，然后就好像奥德林大夫的目光中隐藏着一种他无法抵挡的压迫性的力量，他只好又把目光转了回来。他闷闷不乐地回答道：“都怪他是个肮脏下流的小无赖。”

“你刚刚就是这么描述他的。”

芒特拉戈勋爵叹了一口气，他被打败了。奥德林大夫知道这声叹息表明他终于要坦白了。奥德林大夫不再逼他，低下头开始在吸墨纸上胡乱画几何图案。沉默持续了好几分钟。

“我说，我什么都跟你说，只要对治疗有帮助。我之前没有提到这件事，是因为我认为它太微不足道了，说出来也没有用。在上一次选举中，格里菲思赢得了一个席位，一上任就兴风作浪，惹人讨厌。他父亲是个矿主，他自己年轻时也在矿上工作，后来成为公立小学的校长，还当过记者。他属于那种似懂非懂、骄傲自负的知识分子，学识不纯，观点片面，制定出来的计划简直是异想天开，他是义务教育产生的怪胎。他骨瘦如柴，面无血色，一副食不果腹的样子，穿得也总是邋里邋遢。尽管现在的议员都不怎么在意自己的衣着，但他穿成这样简直有损议会的尊严。他仿佛还为自己的寒酸相感到光荣，衣领从来不洗干净，领带打得歪歪扭扭，整个人看起来好像一个月没洗澡，双手肮脏不堪。工党有几个前座议员[8]还算有点儿本事，其余的都是无能之辈。在盲人的国度里，独眼人就是国王，因为格里菲思巧舌如簧，对什么都懂得点儿皮毛，一有机会工党的秘书就把他推出去发言。看来他也自以为是个外交专家，不断向我提出愚蠢无聊的问题。坦白说，我决定好好教训他一回，他完全是自作自受。从一开始我就讨厌他说话的方式，带着哭腔，满嘴浓重的口音，粗俗不堪。他总是摆出一副扭扭捏捏的样子，让我尤为恼火。他讲话十分腼腆，迟疑不决，好像叫他说话是在折磨他，但他的内心又仿佛充满热情，不吐不快，常常说出些令人哭笑不得的话来。我不得不说，他偶尔也能慷慨激昂地雄辩一番，对工党议员稀里糊涂的思想影响甚深。他们被他的诚恳真挚打动，但在我看来，他那种多愁善感简直令人作呕。装作多愁善感是政治辩论中的惯用伎俩，每个国家都以自身利益为重，同时又倾向于在外交目标中涂抹上利他的色彩。如果政治家能用花言巧语来说服选民，说自己为了保护国家利益而进行的艰难谈判同时也有利于促进人类的整体幸福，倒也无可指责，但像格里菲思这样的人错就错在把这些花言巧语当了真。他是狂热分子，讨厌的狂热分子。他叫自己理想主义者，张口就是那些学界喋喋不休了许多年的废话，什么不抵抗主义，人类的兄弟之情，简直是垃圾。糟糕的是，他不仅在工党内产生了影响，甚至动摇了我们保守党内一些愚不可及的糊涂成员。有传言说，如果工党上台，格里菲思很可能会身居要职，甚至有人建议由他出任外交大臣。这当然有点儿荒谬，但也不是绝对不可能。一天，格里菲思挑起了一场关于外交事务的辩论，我乘机煽风点火，让大家都参与进来。他说了足足一个小时，我认为这是毁掉他的天赐良机，感谢上帝，先生，我真的把他毁掉了。我痛批他的发言，指出他论证错误，无知无识，我把他贬得一文不值。在下议院中，最要命的武器就是嘲笑，我对他极尽讥讽之能事。我那天状态很好，下议院里的笑声惊天动地，他们笑得越开心，我就越兴奋，越发地滔滔不绝，反对党的成员默默地坐着，垂头丧气，但其中几个成员后来也忍不住笑出了声。被对手讥笑倒还可以忍受，但连同僚也讥笑自己，让他情何以堪。我把格里菲思侮辱得无地自容，我想再没有人能做到这种程度。他坐下，缩成一团，脸色煞白。过了一会儿，他用双手遮住脸。我说完坐下的时候，他已经没有翻身的可能了。我彻底摧毁了他的名声，就算工党上台，他也没有希望任职外交大臣，就如看门的警察一样没有机会。后来，我听说他的父亲，那个老矿主，带着他母亲和许多支持他的选民专门从威尔士北上为他打气，准备为他期望中的胜利喝彩，结果却看到他输得一败涂地。他以极为微弱的优势当选，这样一个打击很容易导致他失去议会的席位，但那不关我的事。”

“要是我说你毁了他的事业，算不算言过其实？”奥德林大夫问。

“我觉得你不会那样说。”

“你给他造成了非常严重的伤害。”

“那是他自找的。”

“你有为此感到过内疚吗？”

“要是我知道他父母也在场，也许会给他一个台阶下。”

奥德林大夫的话已经说完了，开始用他认为有效的方法为病人治疗。他试图通过心理暗示来帮助病人在清醒的时候忘记梦中景象，并试图帮助病人进入深沉的无梦睡眠，但他发现芒特拉戈勋爵的抗性实在无懈可击。过了一个小时，他请病人回去。后来爵爷又来过五六回，但疗效甚微。可怕的梦境继续每晚折磨着这个可怜的人，病人的身体状态每况愈下，他变得面目全非，暴躁到无法自控。芒特拉戈勋爵对于治疗的无效十分不满，但他依然按时求诊，因为与大夫见面不仅是唯一一线生机，而且大夫也是唯一一个可以听他畅所欲言的人，把烦恼说出来总算是一种释放。最终，奥德林大夫得出结论，只有一个办法可以让他得到解脱，但他太了解他了，依他的性子，绝对不肯这样做。芒特拉戈勋爵已经处于崩溃的边缘，如果要救他，一定要诱使他放下天生的骄傲和顽固的自负，尽管这对他而言是个很大的挑战。不能再拖了。大夫一直使用心理暗示的方式进行治疗，效果越来越明显。最后，他终于变得睡意蒙眬。大夫的声音低沉、柔软、单调，舒缓着他备受折磨的神经。大夫不断重复相同的话，芒特拉戈勋爵非常安静地躺着，闭着眼，呼吸规律，四肢放松。然后奥德林大夫继续用那种安静的语气把准备好的话说了出来。

“你要去找欧文·格里菲思，说你为给他造成如此巨大的伤害感到非常抱歉。你跟他说你要运用手中的权力，不惜一切地弥补这个伤害。”

这些话好像鞭子一样抽向芒特拉戈勋爵的脸，他一下子醒了，跳起来。他的眼睛燃烧着熊熊怒火，他失去理智一般随口谩骂大夫，骂出了许多连他自己都没听过的污言秽语。他诋毁大夫，诅咒大夫，奥德林大夫什么难听的话没有听过？他甚至还听过优雅高贵的太太骂粗口，但此刻也对他的话大为震惊。

“要我向那个下贱的威尔士人道歉？我还不如去自杀。”

“我相信那是唯一让你恢复正常的办法。”

爵爷还没有到精神失常的地步，竟然如此失控，这种情况在奥德林大夫的病人中也不多见。爵爷的脸红得像烧熟了一般，双眼暴突，嘴角的白沫清晰可见。奥德林大夫冷静地看着他，等待这场风暴自行平息。目前来看，连日来的紧张状态已让芒特拉戈勋爵日渐憔悴，他已经精疲力竭了。

“坐下。”大夫厉声说。

芒特拉戈勋爵蜷缩到椅子里。

“天啊，我快不行了。让我缓一分钟，然后我就走。”

他们一声不吭，寂静持续了大约五分钟。芒特拉戈勋爵是一个粗野横蛮的恶霸，但也是一位绅士。当他恢复镇定时，便主动打破了沉默。

“我恐怕刚才太过失礼了，对你说了那样的话，对此我感到十分羞愧。即使你拒绝继续帮我治疗，我也不会怪你。但我希望你不要放弃我，我觉得这几次治疗确实对我有帮助，我想你是我的唯一机会。”

“别再想你说过的话了，没关系的。”

“但只有一件事你不能要求我做，那就是叫我去向格里菲思道歉。”

“我在你身上费了不少心思。我不想假装已经很理解你，但我想只有按我的建议去做，你才能获得解脱。我认为，我们每个人都不仅仅拥有一个自我，而是有很多个。你的其中一个自我站了出来，抗议你对格里菲思造成的伤害，在你的脑海中变成了格里菲思的形象，代他惩罚你的恶行。如果我是牧师，就会说是你的良心变成了他的样子，呵斥你痛改前非，劝喻你诚心赎罪。”

“我并没有感到良心不安。我确实毁了他的前途，但那不是我的错。这么做跟踩死花园里的一条蛞蝓没什么区别，没什么值得后悔的。”

芒特拉戈勋爵说完这句话就离开了。奥德林大夫一边等着他来，一边把笔记从头到尾翻了一遍，思考着在各种常规疗法都已经失效之后，该如何说服他接受这个唯一可行的办法。大夫看了一眼钟，六点。芒特拉戈勋爵竟然没有来。大夫知道他原本打算来的，因为秘书早上打电话来说他会在老时间前去拜访。肯定有什么紧急事务把他给耽误了。这么一想，大夫又醒悟到另一个问题：芒特拉戈勋爵已经非常不适合继续坚持工作，他的状态也不适合处理重要的国家事务。大夫想，也许应该联系某个当权人物、首相或者外交部常务秘书，告诉他们芒特拉戈勋爵的精神状态非常不稳定，继续把国家要务交由他处理是很危险的。那相当棘手，很可能招致不必要的麻烦，费力不讨好。他耸耸肩。

“反正，”他想，“在过去二十五年间，政治家已经把世界弄得如此乌烟瘴气，也许不管他们是正常人还是疯子，结果都是一样的吧。”

他拉响铃。

“如果芒特拉戈勋爵来了，请告诉他我六点一刻还有预约，恐怕不能见他。”

“好的，先生。”

“晚报送来了吗？”

“我去看看。”

过了一会儿，仆人把晚报拿进来。一个巨大的标题横在头版上：外交大臣不幸辞世。

“天啊！”奥德林大夫大喊。

这一次，他再也无法保持镇静。他大吃一惊，心中充满恐惧，但一点儿也不觉得意外。他多次想到过芒特拉戈勋爵很有可能看不开，所以这次肯定是自杀，他毫不怀疑。报上说事发时芒特拉戈勋爵在地铁站等车，站在站台的边缘，火车进站时，有人看到他掉下铁轨，可能是突发昏厥。报道又说，芒特拉戈勋爵已经连续好几周超负荷工作，然而外国局势需要他密切注视，他只好坚守工作岗位。现代的杰出政治人物总是备受压力摧残，芒特拉戈勋爵是又一位受害者。还有一篇小短文赞颂已故的芒特拉戈勋爵才华横溢、勤奋努力、高瞻远瞩，接着是外交大臣后继者的各种猜测。奥德林大夫全部都读了。他从来没有喜欢过芒特拉戈勋爵，这个惨案之所以令他情绪激动，主要是因为他觉得自己没能帮上忙。

也许他应该和芒特拉戈勋爵的私人医生联系一下。他很泄气。他总是尽心尽力地治疗病人，一旦失败了，就会非常受挫，对那套赖以为生的江湖医术产生极端的反感。他的对手是各种黑暗神秘的力量，超出了人类头脑的理解范围。他像蒙着眼睛摸索道路的人，不知道会走去哪里。他无精打采地翻着报纸，突然吓了一大跳，差点儿又大喊出来。某个栏目底部有一篇小报道：国会议员猝然离世。欧文·格里菲思先生，某党成员，当天下午在舰队街[9]突发疾病，被送到查令十字医院时已经去世了。他的死看来是由自然原因引致的，但稍后会验尸。奥德林大夫几乎无法相信自己的眼睛。难道前一天晚上芒特拉戈勋爵终于在梦中如愿发现自己手持武器，刀或枪，并杀死了折磨他的人？跟上次用酒瓶砸欧文，令欧文次日头痛欲裂一样，这桩梦中的谋杀案是否也在次日产生了效果？又或者，更为神秘和可怕的是，当芒特拉戈勋爵自杀以求解脱，那个备受他残酷虐待的敌人，怨恨难平，也放弃了自己终将结束的生命，追逐他去到另一个时空，继续折磨他？实在是太离奇了。当然，把这两件事看成一次离奇的巧合更加合乎常理。奥德林大夫摇响铃。

“请告诉米尔顿太太，恐怕今晚我不能见她了，我有点儿不舒服。”

此言不虚。他浑身颤抖，好像得了疟疾一样，一种超自然的触感瞬间流过全身，他仿佛窥见了一个荒凉狰狞的空间。灵魂的黑夜吞噬了他，他感到了难以名状的、奇怪而原始的恐惧。

[1]　弗洛伊德和荣格均为著名精神分析学家。

[2]　位于伦敦市中心，是医疗机构密集之地。

[3]　查理二世（1661—1685年在位），苏格兰、英格兰和爱尔兰的国王，深受民众爱戴。

[4]　发生于十五世纪中后期。

[5]　英国著名的政治家和文学家。

[6]　奥地利王子的称呼。

[7]　位于伦敦东部的贫民区。

[8]　下议院开会时，地位较高的议员坐前排，被称为“前座议员”。

[9]　英国几家重要报馆所在街道，过去是英国新闻业之中心地。

密　　函

叶雷　译

烈日炙烤着外面的码头。摩托车、卡车、公共汽车、私家车、出租车川流不息地从拥挤的道路上驶过，每个司机都在按喇叭。人力车沿着它们轻巧的路线在人群中穿梭，气喘吁吁的车夫们，声嘶力竭地相互吆喝着。苦力们背着沉重的大包裹，侧着身子，踉踉跄跄地碎步快走着，向路人大声嚷嚷，要他们让路。路边有许多小贩在叫卖各色货物。新加坡是诸多民族交汇之处，在这里能看到肤色各异的人：棕黑色的泰米尔人，黄色的中国佬，赭石色的马来人，亚美尼亚人，犹太人，孟加拉人，他们粗声向对方问好。但里普利、乔伊斯和内勒律师事务所里却清新舒适。它躲在烁玉流金、沙尘滚滚、人声鼎沸的大街后面，独享一方幽静阴凉。乔伊斯先生坐在他个人办公室里的桌子边，一台电扇迎面朝他吹着强风。他斜靠在椅背上，双肘抵着扶手，十指轻巧地尖尖相对。他面朝一个长长的架子，上面是如断烂朝报一般成堆的《判例汇编》，此刻他正看着它们出神。一个橱柜上面放着漆过的方形铁盒，铁盒上用油漆写着各个委托人的姓名。

有人敲门。

“进来。”

一名衣装整洁的华人助理开门进来。

“克罗斯比先生已到，先生。”

他的英语标准流利，每个单词的发音都精确无误，乔伊斯先生总是惊讶于他无边无际的词汇量。王智生是广东人，曾在格雷律师学院[1]修习法律。他意欲在里普利、乔伊斯和内勒律师事务所实习几年，以备将来自立门户。他勤奋，有礼，品行端正。

“请带他进来。”乔伊斯先生道。

他站起来和访客握手，请访客就座。在此过程中，一片光在他身上掠过，然而他的脸仍然藏在阴影中。他生来就是一个沉默的男人。此时，他凝视着罗伯特·克罗斯比，久久不置一词。克罗斯比轩昂魁伟，身高超过六英尺，肩膀宽阔，肌肉结实。他是一位橡胶园主，常常要在种植园里四处走动，每天工作结束后还去打网球放松，锻炼出一身钢筋铁骨。他被晒得乌黑，一双巨手毛茸茸的，一双巨脚穿着又笨又沉的靴子。乔伊斯先生不禁想，他的铁拳真的能够一下打死一个脆弱的泰米尔人。但他碧青的眼睛是温和的，柔软的目光里充满信任。他生得粗枝大叶，却有一张坦率而真诚的脸，但此刻这张脸枯槁憔悴，正笼罩在悲伤的阴霾里。

“看来你这几晚都没怎么合眼。”乔伊斯先生道。

“没错。”

乔伊斯先生注意到克罗斯比先生放在桌上的一顶破双檐帽，又把目光移到他的卡其色短裤上，他发红的大腿长着浓密的毛，网球衫的领子敞开着，没戴领带，卡其色夹克脏兮兮的，袖口捋了起来。他这副模样，仿佛刚刚去橡胶树林流浪了一番。乔伊斯先生不禁双眉微蹙。

“请你振作起来。你必须保持镇静。”

“噢，我好着呢。”

“今天去见你太太了吗？”

“还没，我打算下午去。他们竟然把她抓了起来，真是丧尽天良！”

“他们没有选择。”乔伊斯先生用他特有的柔和嗓音说道。

“我以为他们会让我保释她。”

“这可是一件大案子。”

“得了吧！任何一个正派女人遇到那种情况都会反抗，只是没几个有那份勇气罢了。世上再也没有比莱斯莉更善良的人了，她连一只苍蝇都不忍心拍死。为什么要这样对她！这些人真过分！我和她结婚十二年了，难道还不知道她是什么人？上天作证，要是让我抓到那个男人，一定会拧断他的脖子，毫不犹豫地将他杀死！换做是您，您也一定会这么做。”

“我亲爱的朋友，大家都支持你，没有人会替哈蒙德说话。我们会帮她洗脱嫌疑。我想，陪审团或法官都打算等到下定决心判她无罪之后才开庭。”

“有什么好等的，”克罗斯比狂躁地说，“一开始就不应该把她抓起来。这个可怜的女孩儿已经受够了苦，他们居然还要让她经历审判的折磨，真是没良心！我回到新加坡后，不论男女，人人都说莱斯莉这样做天经地义。把她抓起来关这么久真是没道理。”

“法律就是法律。毕竟，她承认自己杀人了。真是太不幸了，我对你们深表同情。”

“我才不在乎呢。”克罗斯比打断他道。

“问题是，这桩罪案已经发生。现在是文明社会，审判在所难免。”

“杀死一个穷凶极恶的歹徒也算是谋杀吗？她射死他，跟射死一条疯狗有什么区别？”

乔伊斯先生重新斜靠在椅子上，再次将十指指尖合拢，形状看上去就像一个屋顶的框架一般，他沉默了一阵子。

“我是你的法律顾问，”他终于开口道，声音沉着冷静，一双棕色的眼睛冷冷地盯着他的诉讼委托人，“如果我不向你明言一个困扰我的细节，就是疏于职守。假如你的妻子只是向哈蒙德开了一枪，我们便胜券在握。问题是，她一共开了六枪。”

“她解释过了，很简单！在那种情形下，不论是谁都会那样做。”

“当然，”乔伊斯先生说，“我也认为这个解释合情合理，但我不想自欺欺人。换位思考总是好的。我不否认，即使我是王室检察官，也要将此视为最大疑点。”

“我亲爱的朋友，没必要做那种蠢事。”

乔伊斯先生目光锐利地瞥了罗伯特·克罗斯比一眼，他优美的嘴唇上掠过一丝微笑。克罗斯比是个良友，但着实不怎么聪明。

“也许是我多心了，”律师道，“我只是觉得这个细节值得一提。事情已经接近尾声，等这一切画上句号，我建议你和妻子离开此地，找个地方旅游一番，彻底忘掉这个噩梦。尽管无罪判决已差不多是板上钉钉之事，但谋杀案的审判总是一场折磨，事后你们需要休息。”

克罗斯比终于笑了。他一笑，仿佛换了一张脸，先前的粗笨一扫而空，你只能看见他灵魂深处的美好。

“我想我比莱斯莉更需要休息。她一直很坚强。感谢上帝吧，您的委托人是一个多么勇敢的弱女子。”

“是的，她的自制力真是太惊人了。”律师说，“她如此坚强，真是出乎我的意料。”

他是她的法律顾问，在克罗斯比太太被捕之后，两人自然需要频繁会面。尽管狱中的一切尽可能地为她安排得舒适妥帖，她毕竟是入狱了，等候指控她谋杀的审判，重压之下精神崩溃也是顺理成章之事，然而她却安之若素。她读了很多书，用一切机会舒展筋骨。当局特许她在狱中绣枕边，作为她借以消磨漫长岁月的一个小爱好。她端庄整洁地出现在乔伊斯先生面前，身上的连衣裙清凉素雅，头发梳得纹丝不乱，指甲修剪得漂漂亮亮。她谈笑自如，甚至不忘对目前的尴尬处境揶揄几句。谈到这个悲剧，她竟有些漫不经心，乔伊斯先生不禁想，多亏她的知书识礼，才让她避免了在此等逆境中失言。他从未意识到她也有幽默感，为此小小地吃了一惊。

他认识她很多年了，但不常见面。来新加坡时，她一般都会过来与他们夫妇共进晚宴，有几次还去了他们的海边别墅共度周末。他的妻子跟她在橡胶园里住过两个礼拜，见过杰弗里·哈蒙德几面。两对夫妇虽谈不上是密友，但也相处得相当愉快。因此，灾难发生后，罗伯特·克罗斯比马上赶到新加坡来，请求乔伊斯先生亲自为他不幸的妻子辩护。

从他第一次见到她起，她向他叙述的事情经过就从未变过，即便是在细枝末节上。悲剧发生后的几个小时，她就冷静沉着地叙述了一遍，和现在所说的一模一样。她的叙述连贯清晰，声音沉着冷静，只是在描述其中几个细节时，她稍稍有些不安，双颊泛红。她简直不可能招致此等横祸。这个三十一二岁的女人，弱不禁风，中等身段，要说她漂亮，倒不如说是优雅动人。她瘦骨嶙峋，手腕和脚踝精致纤巧，白皙的皮肤覆在手骨上，粗蓝的静脉清晰可见。一张没有血色的脸，略有点儿灰黄，嘴唇则是苍白的。她的眼睛平淡无奇，但她有许多淡棕色的头发，天然地微卷着，若稍微做一下美发，一定会漂亮得惊人，但克罗斯比太太绝不会让她的头发受那些设备摆布。她安静地喜悦着，不事张扬。她的言谈举止高贵迷人，但由于内敛自重，她在社交圈里过于默默无闻。这种情况完全无可指责，因为橡胶园主的妻子总是孤独地生活在深闺之中。可是，当她在自己家中与可靠的熟人相处时，会展现出一种静谧的魔力。乔伊斯太太和她住了两周，回家后告诉她丈夫说，莱斯莉是一位异常甜美可亲的女主人。乔伊斯太太说，她有许多外人意想不到的好处，若深入了解她，一定会惊叹她是多么的博览群书，又是多么的风流灵巧。

她是世间最不可能犯谋杀罪的女人。

乔伊斯先生费尽唇舌，总算让罗伯特·克罗斯比安下心来。他把克罗斯比送走，办公室里又只剩下他一人了，他随手翻起案情摘要来。但那只是机械性的动作，这份摘要他早已倒背如流。这件案子轰动一时，从新加坡到槟榔屿[2]，在整个半岛的俱乐部里和餐桌上，人们都在津津有味地谈论它。事实上克罗斯比太太陈述的案情相当简单。案发当晚她先生去新加坡出差，她独自一人在家。她自己到八点三刻才吃晚饭，饭后坐在客厅绣枕边。通往游廊的门开着，屋子里一个人也没有，仆人们都已返回屋后的住处休息。花园的碎石小路上忽然传来脚步声，把她吓得够戗。那是靴子的声音，来者一定是一位白人男士而非当地人，当地人总是把汽车直接开进来。她也不知道谁会那么晚来打扰她。那人拾阶而上，穿过游廊，在客厅门口停下脚步。她坐在一盏昏灯旁，而他站在黑暗中，她一时间没认出他是谁。

“我能进来吗？”他说。

她听不出是谁。

“是谁？”她问。

她原本戴着眼镜，说话时把它摘掉了。

“杰夫[3]·哈蒙德。”

“快请进。来喝点儿东西。”

她站起身，热情地同他握手。见到他多少有点儿惊讶，尽管他也算是邻居，但近来她和罗伯特不常与他见面，而她已经好几周没看见他了。他也有一个橡胶园，距离克罗斯比夫妇的橡胶园八英里。都这么晚了，也不知道他来找他们有什么要紧的事。

“罗伯特不在，”她说，“他去新加坡过夜了。”

也许他认为有必要解释一下自己的来访，便说：“真是抱歉。我今晚寂寞得难受，所以出来散散心，顺便来问候一下你们。”

“你是怎么来的？我没听到汽车的声音。”

“怕你们睡了，我把它停在下面的马路边。”

这个解释合情合理。庄园主每天要给工人们点名，只好起早贪黑，吃完晚饭就差不多要去睡觉了。警察第二天也确实在距离克罗斯比家四分之一英里处找到了哈蒙德的汽车。

罗伯特不在，客厅里没准备威士忌和苏打水。男仆很可能已经睡着了，莱斯莉没有叫他，亲自去端过来。客人自己混了一杯酒，点着烟斗。

杰夫·哈蒙德在这片殖民地人缘很广。他已年近四十，从小便出来闯荡。战争爆发后，他参加了第一批志愿军，战功卓著。两年后，他膝部受伤，被迫退役，带着优异服务勋章和十字勋章回到马来联邦。他是此地最好的台球手之一，过去也曾舞姿翩翩，网球也打得不错。虽然他无法再跳舞，膝盖受伤僵化后网球也大为退步，他却懂得如何让大家都喜欢他。他高大英俊，长着摄人心魄的碧眼和乌润浓密的鬈发。那些久惯老诚的人说他唯一的缺点就是太爱寻花问柳。等他终于招来杀身之祸，这些人赶忙摇头晃脑地宣称他们早料到他会毁在女人手里。

他开始和莱斯莉闲聊一些本地事务，新加坡近期要举办的赛事，橡胶的价格，还有他差点儿打死一只最近在附近出没的老虎。她急于按期绣完一条枕边，赶在母亲生日前寄回家，于是重新戴上眼镜，把椅子挪到摆着枕头的小桌旁边。

“你真该把这副牛角边眼镜换掉，”他说，“你为什么要把自己的花容月貌掩藏起来？”

这句话吓了她一跳。他之前从未用过这么奇怪的腔调跟她说话。她想最好不要在这个话题上纠缠不休。

“我可从来不觉得自己是个美人，如果你觉得这副眼镜不好看，我可以告诉你，我并不在意自己在你眼中的形象。”

“可我觉得你美艳绝伦。”

“你嘴可真甜，”她反讽道，“但你说出这样的话，我只会认为你头脑不正常。”

他咯咯地笑了。他站起来，在她身旁的椅子上坐下。

“那你总不能矢口否认你这双手精致玲珑得举世无双吧？”他说。

他作势要抓起她的一只手，她轻轻打了他一下。

“放尊重点儿。坐回去，好好说话，否则我就要请你打道回府。”

他一动不动。

“你难道不知道我已经对你爱得不能自拔了吗？”他说。

她仍然是一副凛然不可侵犯的模样。

“我不知道。我甚至都懒得相信这是真的。即使确实如此，我也不想你说出来。”

她真惊讶他竟如此口不择言。他们相识七年，他从未对她有过任何越轨之举。他退役后，常常与克罗斯比夫妇见面，有一次他生病了，罗伯特还自己开车将他接到了他们的小屋。他在克罗斯比家住了两周，但由于志趣相异，始终没有与他们成为好友。近两三年来，他们几乎不与他来往。他偶尔过来打网球，他们也偶尔在某个种植园主举办的派对上见到他，但更多的时候，他们整月整月地看不见他。

他又倒了一杯威士忌掺苏打水。莱斯莉不知道他之前喝没喝酒。他今天有些古怪，她心生疑虑。看着他毫不见外的样子，她柳眉紧蹙。

“如果我是你，就会少喝一点儿。”她说，依然客客气气的。

他自己干了一杯，把杯子放下。

“你以为我是因为喝醉了，才这么口无遮拦吗？”他唐突地发问。

“难道不是吗？”

“哼，当然不是。我对你一见倾心。我一直忍着没说，但我实在忍不下去了。我爱你，我爱你，我爱你。”

她站起来，小心翼翼地把枕头放到一旁。

“晚安。”她说。

“我不会走的。”

她终于发怒了。

“你这个大笨蛋，难道你不知道我对罗伯特是死心塌地的吗？即使我不爱罗伯特，也绝对不会爱上你。”

“管他呢，反正罗伯特不在家。”

“如果你不赶快滚出去，我就要叫男仆来把你扔出去了。”

“他们听不到。”

她怒不可遏，迈开脚步，像是要走到游廊去叫人，在那里仆人一定能听见她的叫声。但他抓住她的手臂。

“放开我！”她狂吼道。

“不可能，你逃不掉的。”

她大叫“来人，来人啊”，但他迅速捂住她的嘴。等她回过神来，意识到他的企图时，他已经将她紧紧抱住，如暴雨一般疯狂地亲吻她。她绝望地挣扎着，躲开他滚烫的双唇。

“快停下！”她喊道，“放开我，你这个禽兽！”

接下来的事情她却记不清楚了。之前他说的话，她记得丝毫不差，但从那刻起，他的话仿佛要穿过一层恐惧和害怕的迷雾才能进入她的耳朵。他似乎在恳求她做见不得人的事情。他失去了自制力，变得狂热残暴，像一个铁钳，紧紧地把她夹在怀里。在这个强壮而又孔武有力的男人面前，她是那样的无助，她的手臂被夹在身体两边无法动弹。她的挣扎都是徒劳，她感觉自己变得越来越虚弱，她担心自己随时都可能昏过去。他灼热的呼吸喷在她脸上，恶心至极。他亲吻她的嘴，她的眼睛，她的双颊，她的头发，他的臂力让她几欲窒息。她被举离地面。她奋力踢他，但他只会将她抱得更紧。他抱着她走动起来，不再说话，但他一定脸色苍白，双眼燃烧着欲火。他要把她抱进卧房。他变回原始的野蛮人，急不可耐地跑起来，却撞到一张挡住去路的桌子。膝盖僵硬的他腿脚本来就不灵便，加上抱着女人，一下子摔倒了。她抓住机会挣脱开来，跑到沙发后面。他闪电般站起来冲向她。桌上有一支左轮手枪。她不是一个神经兮兮的人，但罗伯特那天晚上不在家，她打算睡觉时把枪拿进卧房以防不测，因此它碰巧在那里。她已经被吓得丧失了理智，不知道自己在做什么，只是听到一声枪响。她看见哈蒙德踉跄几步，喊了一声，还说了几句话，但她没听清。他跌跌撞撞地逃出房间到游廊上，她已经因为恐惧和愤怒发了狂，追着他出去，是的，就是那样，她肯定是追着他出去了，尽管她对此毫无印象。她下意识地一边扣动扳机，一边追了出去，一枪又一枪，直到六颗子弹都射光了。哈蒙德倒在游廊的地板上，缩成一个血堆。

仆人们被枪声惊醒，慌慌张张地冲上来时，看见她站在哈蒙德身边，手中仍然攥着枪，哈蒙德已经断了气。她一言不发地看了他们一眼，他们战战兢兢地站拢成一团。她松开手，让手枪落到地板上，默默转身走进客厅，并在他们的目光中走进卧房，把门锁上。他们被吓得魂飞魄散，不敢碰尸体，只是望着它，眼中充满恐惧，惊慌失措地交头接耳。仆役长是一名华人，服侍克罗斯比夫妇多年，头脑比较清醒。他勉强打起精神来，寻思如何打破僵局。罗伯特骑摩托车去新加坡，汽车还留在车库里。仆役长知道必须马上把这一意外事故通知给助理地区警长，便叫司机把车开来，一边拾起枪放进口袋。助理地区警长名叫威瑟斯，住在离此地最近的城市市郊，大约三十五英里远。一个半小时后，他们到达他家，所有人都已就寝，他们不得不把仆役叫起来。过了一会儿，威瑟斯现身，仆役长告诉他来访因由，把枪交给他作证。警长进房穿衣，并叫人把车开来，迅速上路。他跟随他们驶过荒凉的道路，到达克罗斯比家时，天刚破晓。警长跑上走廊的台阶，看到哈蒙德的尸体便立刻停下。尸体仍在原地。他摸摸尸体的脸，已经是冷的。

“夫人在哪里？”他问男仆。

仆役长指指卧房，威瑟斯上前去敲门。没有应答。他再敲。

“克罗斯比太太！”他喊道。

“是谁？”

“威瑟斯。”

又过了一会儿，锁开了，门慢慢打开。莱斯莉出现在他跟前。她一夜未眠，身上仍然是晚餐时穿的宽松女袍。她站着，无声地看着警官。

“您的仆役长请我来的，”他说，“哈蒙德——您做了什么？”

“他要非礼我，我向他开枪了。”

“天啊。您最好出来，详细地告诉我事情的经过。”

“现在不行。我做不到。您必须给我点儿时间。请把我丈夫叫回来。”

威瑟斯少不更事，不懂得如何处理这种意料之外的紧急局面。罗伯特回家后，莱斯莉才肯开口，她告诉两人事发经过。此后她把这个故事重复了无数遍，但每遍都与最初的陈述毫无二致。

开枪的细节一直困扰着乔伊斯先生。作为她的律师，他无论如何想不明白她为什么要开六枪，而不是仅开一枪。尸检发现有四枪是近身射击，这难免引人怀疑，哈蒙德倒下后，她还站在旁边冲他打光了子弹。她承认自己一直清晰无误的记忆到这里就中断了，大脑变得一片空白。那表明她陷入了出离的愤怒之中，但这样一位娴静从容的女士怎么可能陷入出离的愤怒之中？乔伊斯先生与她相识多年，一直感觉她是一个麻木无情的人，而且在悲剧发生后的这几周里，她自始至终展现出惊人的镇静。

乔伊斯先生耸耸肩。

“事实也许是，”他想道，“在最值得尊敬的女人身上，潜藏着多么可怕的野性，这是一个永恒的谜。”

有人敲门。

“请进。”

那位华人助理走进来，鬼鬼祟祟地把身后的门轻轻关上，面色凝重地走到乔伊斯先生跟前。

“很抱歉打搅您，先生，我想私下与您沟通几句。”他说。

这位助理说起话来总是字斟句酌，把乔伊斯先生都逗笑了。

“别这么客气，智生。”他回答道。

“先生，我急于向您汇报之事，是机密的，对案情的影响甚是微妙。”

“请讲。”

乔伊斯先生撞上助理精明的目光。王智生的穿着打扮可谓一如既往地入时，时髦的皮鞋油光锃亮，丝质短袜色彩艳丽，黑领带，珠光宝气的领带夹，左手无名指上一只明晃晃的钻戒，整洁的白色外衣口袋里突出来一根金自来水笔和一根金铅笔。他戴着金腕表，鼻梁上架一副透明的夹鼻眼镜。他轻轻咳嗽了一声。

“此事与克罗斯比一案有关。”

“请往下说。”

“我了解到一个情况，先生，它推翻了我此前对此案的看法。”

“什么情况？”

“先生，我听说被告写了一封信给这场悲剧中不幸的受害者。”

“这有什么值得惊讶的。他们认识了整整七年，克罗斯比太太写信给哈蒙德先生的机会多的是。”

乔伊斯先生很清楚这个助理有多么聪明，他这么说，是在故意装糊涂。

“当然如此，先生。克罗斯比太太无疑需要频繁地和死者通信，例如邀请他共进晚宴，或是提议一起打网球赛。听到这封信时，这也是我的第一反应。然而，这封信是在哈蒙德先生去世当天写的。”

乔伊斯先生连眼睛也没有眨一下。他继续看着王智生，微笑着，表现出淡淡的兴趣，和王智生交谈时，他一般都是这副表情。

“你从哪儿听来的？”

“我朋友那里，先生。”

乔伊斯先生深知没必要追问下去。

“您应该还记得，先生，克罗斯比太太陈述道，事发前她已经有好几周没与死者联系。”

“那封信在你手上吗？”

“没有，先生。”

“信上写了什么？”

“我朋友给了我一份誊抄本。请您过目，先生。”

“好的。”

王智生从贴身暗袋里掏出一个胀鼓鼓的钱夹，里面装满各色纸片、新加坡币和烟卡。他迅速从这堆乱纸中抽出半张便条纸，放在乔伊斯先生前面。该信内容如下：

罗今晚不回家，我一定要见你。我等你，十一点。我什么都顾不上了，你要敢不来，后果自负。切记把车停在外面。——莱

笔迹很流利，是这个华人在外国学校接受教导的成果之一。如此凶险的话，根本不像是用这么平平无奇的字体写出来的。

“你为什么会认为这张字条是克罗斯比太太写的？”

“我的信息来源非常可靠，”王智生回答道，“而且很容易证明其真实性。毫无疑问，克罗斯比太太能够马上告诉您她是否写过这张便条。”

乔伊斯先生一直盯着这个助理那张毕恭毕敬的脸，此刻他疑心这张脸上有没有恶作剧的蛛丝马迹。

“克罗斯比太太居然写了这样一封信，简直不可思议。”乔伊斯先生说。

“如果您持这种态度，先生，这件事情到此为止。我朋友向我透露此信息，仅仅是因为他考虑到我是您的助理。在和副检察官沟通之前，你可能会想知道这封信的存在。”

“原件在哪里？”乔伊斯先生厉声问道。

王智生不动声色，仿佛他并未从此问题中察觉出乔伊斯先生态度的转变。

“先生，您一定没有忘记，哈蒙德先生死后，人们发现他和一个中国女人纠缠不清。现在信在她手中。”

这是把哈蒙德先生推向风口浪尖的诸多丑闻之一。大家都知道了他曾和一个中国女人同居数月。

两人陷入了沉默。实际上，话已经说完了，两人的心思都瞒不过对方。

“谢谢你，智生。我会仔细考虑此事。”

“您客气了，先生。您希望我就此事和我朋友沟通一下吗？”

“你最好和他保持联络。”乔伊斯先生板着脸说。

“好的，先生。”

助理一声不响地退出房间，再次从容地把门关上，留下乔伊斯先生在办公室里苦苦思索。他盯着誊抄本上平平无奇的整洁笔迹，隐隐生疑。他感到不妙，努力想把这种怀疑从脑子里驱除出去。莱斯莉肯定可以第一时间给出一个简单直接的解释，但是，天啊，他需要这个解释！他站起身，把信放进口袋，拿起遮阳帽。他出去的时候，王智生正坐在办公桌前埋头写文件。

“我出去一会儿，智生。”他说。

“乔治·里德先生约好十二点来访，先生，我该如何向他解释？”

乔伊斯先生微微一笑。

“你可以说你也不知道我在哪里。”

他要去的是监狱，他知道王智生对此心知肚明。尽管事发地点在荷兰村[4]，审判也定在当地举行，由于在监狱中拘留一个白人女士有着诸多不便，克罗斯比太太被关押在新加坡。

她被带进等候室，向他伸出优雅消瘦的手，粲然一笑。她和往常一样，穿戴简单朴素，一头浓密的淡棕色头发梳理得一丝不苟。

“真没想到今天早上能看见您。”她彬彬有礼地说。

恍惚之间，乔伊斯先生仿佛坐在她的家中，她好像正要叫男仆去给他把苦杜松子酒端来。

“你还好吗？”他问。

“好得不得了，谢谢您。”她的双眸闪过一丝喜悦的光芒，“这真是静养的好地方。”

看守离开了，房间里只剩下他们两人。

“请坐。”莱斯莉道。

他拿过一张椅子来坐下。他不知该如何开口。她一副若无其事的模样，他简直无法向她提起信的事情。尽管她谈不上漂亮，却很有些楚楚动人。不像社交场上那些装腔作势的女士，她因知书识礼而显得落落大方、雍容娴雅。她的社交圈子和生活环境简单纯粹，加上她弱如蒲柳，更显温柔娴静，看上去与任何粗野之事无涉。

“我真希望罗伯特下午来看我，”她说，声音自然动听（听她讲话可谓一大快事，她的声音和口音能够忠实地传达出这个阶级特有的气质），“可怜的孩子，真是难为他了。谢天谢地，再过几天就全部结束了。”

“离审判只有五天了。”

“我知道。每天早上醒来时，我就对自己说，‘又少了一天’。”她说着不禁笑了起来，“就像从前上学那会儿，快要放假的时候一样。”

“顺便问一句，我想事发之前你有好几周不曾和哈蒙德联系过，是不是？”

“我很肯定没有。我们最后一次见面还是在麦法伦斯网球赛上。我没怎么跟他说话。那里有两块场地，我们碰巧不在一起。”

“你也没有给他写信？”

“没有。”

“你确定？”

“确定。”她回答，淡淡一笑，“我给他写信，也不过是请他过来吃饭，或是打网球。我有好几个月没做这两件事了。”

“你曾经一度与他过从甚密，为什么突然对他如此冷淡？”

克罗斯比太太耸耸她瘦削的肩膀。

“也许是厌倦了吧。我们总有点儿话不投机。当然，他生病的时候，罗伯特和我曾竭尽所能帮他渡过难关，但最近这一两年，他非常健康，也从不寂寞。他忙于奔赴各种社交场合，看上去没必要再给他添麻烦了。”

“你确定就只是这样？”

克罗斯比太太犹疑了一会儿。

“不妨告诉您另一个原因。我们听说他和一个中国女人同居，罗伯特不愿意让他弄脏我们的屋子。我还亲眼见过那个女人。”

乔伊斯先生坐在一张直背扶手椅上，手托下巴，直直盯着莱斯莉。她说这句话的时候，他仿佛看见一道粗钝的红光闪过她黑色的双瞳，十分恐怖。乔伊斯先生挪了挪椅子，他又把十根手指尖尖相对。他谨慎地缓缓说道：

“我想，我有必要告诉你，有人发现了一封你亲自写给杰夫·哈蒙德的信。”

他密切地注视着她。她无动于衷，但过了一段时间才做出回应。

“过去我常常给他写便条，请他帮各种忙。要是我知道他去新加坡，就托他带点儿东西。”

“这封信是邀请他来见你，因为罗伯特要去新加坡。”

“那不可能，我从没写过那样的信。”

“你最好自己看看这张便条。”

他把便条从口袋里拿出来递给她。她扫了一眼，冷笑着把便条还给他。

“这可不是我的笔迹。”

“我知道，听说这只是一字不差的誊抄本。”

她现在认真地读起便条来，浑身上下发生了可怕的变化：和颜悦色的脸变得惨绿，看上去狰狞恐怖；身上的肉仿佛一下子掉得精光，皮肤紧紧绷在骨头上；嘴唇往后缩，露出牙齿，仿佛在做鬼脸。她用暴突出来的眼睛盯着乔伊斯先生，他眼前的人变成了一具语无伦次的骷髅。

“这是什么意思？”她轻声道。

她嘴唇太干了，只能嘶嘶地哑声说话，像鬼一样。

“应该由我来问你。”他回答。

“我没有写它。我发誓我没有写它。”

“话不能乱讲。如果原件是你的笔迹，否认也是徒劳的。”

“那是伪造的。”

“要证明它是伪造的很难，但要证明它是真的易如反掌。”

她清瘦的身子打了一个寒战，额头渗出大粒的汗珠来。她从包里掏出一张手帕擦干手心，又看了信一眼，斜着眼睛望着乔伊斯先生。

“上面没有日期。如果我真的写了这封信，却又把它忘得一干二净，那可能是很多年前写的。给我一点儿时间，我会尝试回忆起当时的情景来。”

“这点我注意到了。如果检察官拿到这封信，一定会仔细盘查仆人，很快便能知道有没有人在哈蒙德遇难当天给他送去一封信。”

克罗斯比太太把双手绞在一起，已经坐不稳了，他以为她会晕过去。

“我向您发誓，我没写那封信。”

乔伊斯先生沉默不语。他把目光从她扭曲的脸上移开，低下头去，陷入沉思。

“如果你是这种态度，我们就没有必要再谈下去。”他终于打破沉默，慢慢地说，“如果手握这封信的人认为应该把它交到检察官手中，你必须有所准备。”

他已经清晰地暗示自己的话已经说完了，但坐着不动，没有要离开的意思。他在等。在他，仿佛已经等了好几个世纪。他没有抬头看莱斯莉，但他知道她也坐着不动。房间里一片死寂。最后还是他打破了僵局。

“如果你要对我说的话已经说完了，我就回办公室去了。”

“看到这封信的人会怎么想？”她问他。

“认为你故意撒谎了。”乔伊斯先生直截了当地说。

“我什么时候撒谎了？”

“你信誓旦旦地说，你和哈蒙德已经有好几个月没有联系过。”

“这件事整个地对我打击太大了。那晚发生的一切太可怕，简直是一场噩梦。我忘记了某个细节也是正常的。”

“他遇害当晚去找你，完全是因为你歇斯底里地要见他。你把如此重要的事情忘掉了，却能如数家珍地讲出与哈蒙德交谈的每一个细节，这多少有点儿说不过去。”

“我并未忘记此事，只是事发后不敢提起它。要是我承认他是应邀赴约，你们就不会相信我的口供。是的，我是很傻，但我当时已经魂不守舍，随口说出好久没和哈蒙德联系的话来，想改口也来不及了。”

莱斯莉已经恢复镇定。乔伊斯先生向她投去赞赏的目光，她坦荡荡地与他对视。她恬静温柔，很容易消释他人的怀疑。

“既然如此，检察官会要求你解释为什么趁罗伯特不回家过夜时叫哈蒙德来见你。”

她直直地盯着律师。他总以为那是一双普通的眼睛，但他错了，他突然发现它们很迷人。此刻，这双眼睛隐隐地闪烁着泪光，清亮生辉。她的声音有点儿哽咽。

“我正准备给罗伯特一个惊喜。他下个月生日，我知道他想要一支新手枪。您也知道，我对这些东西一窍不通。我想找杰夫商量，请他帮我订购一支。”

“看来你是记不清这封信的措辞了吧，要不要再看一眼？”

“不，我不想再看它。”她立刻说道。

“你觉得，一位女士会因为咨询买枪的事情而给一位生疏的朋友写这样的信吗？”

“那确实有些小题大做。但我就是这么有口无心，我不得不承认那很蠢。”她微微一笑，“毕竟，杰夫·哈蒙德不能算是生疏的朋友，他生病的时候我像母亲一样无微不至地照料过他。我趁罗伯特不在家的时候请他过来，是因为罗伯特不许他上门。”

乔伊斯先生坐乏了，站起来在房间里走了几圈，思考接下来应该说什么。他斜倚在刚才坐过的椅子上，缓慢而艰难地道：

“克罗斯比太太，我希望非常严肃地与你谈谈。这个案子进展得相当顺利，唯独有一点令我困惑不已，我了解到，在哈蒙德倒地后，你至少还瞄准他开了四枪。很难想象一位像你这么瘦弱的女士，生性温柔，知书达理，一向沉着冷静，受惊后竟会彻底丧失理智。当然，这种情况也不是完全没有可能发生。尽管杰弗里·哈蒙德备受欢迎，声誉良好，我已经下定决心要证实你对他的指控，还你清白。他死后，人们发现他和一个中国女人同居，这个不光彩的事实已经使他身败名裂，情况对我们极为有利。我无论如何也要抓住他这个污点，所有德高望重的人都会因此对他嗤之以鼻。今天早上，我向你丈夫保证你将被判无罪释放，这并不是在安慰他。我相信陪审团的倾向相当明显。”

他们四目相对。克罗斯比太太仍然一动不动，十分古怪。她像一只被毒蛇蛊惑住的小鸟，动弹不得。他继续不紧不慢地说道：

“但这封信的出现完全改变了局面。我是你的辩护律师，将代表你出庭。我必须相信你的口供，并据此为你辩护。私底下我可能相信你的口供，也可能怀疑它。辩护律师的职责是说服法庭，现有证据不足以引致有罪判决，至于我个人是否认为你有罪，那是无关紧要的。”

莱斯莉的眼中闪过一丝笑意，他吃了一惊。他的自尊心受到了伤害，语气冷淡下来，继续说道：

“你不会否认哈蒙德是因为你那封十万火急的信才去找你的吧？我就是说你气急败坏地邀请他过来，也不过分。”

克罗斯比太太迟疑着，仿佛在思索。

“他们可以证实那封信是由你的仆人送去他家，并且连他骑自行车去也知道。

“你不要低估人们的智商。尽管他们现在相信你的话，但是这封信会使他们生疑。我不想与你分享我看到这封信时的心情，我只希望你能想想如何洗脱自己的死罪嫌疑。”

克罗斯比太太惊叫一声，跳起来，害怕得面如死灰。

“难道你认为他们会判我绞刑？”

“假如他们裁定你杀害哈蒙德的行为并非正当防卫，陪审团有责任做出有罪判决，罪名是谋杀。法官必须依法判你死刑。”

“但他们有什么证据？”她喘着气道。

“我不知道。但你心里有数。你大可不必向我坦白。只是，假如他们起了疑心，针对你展开调查，假如他们盘问当地人——你觉得他们会发现什么？”

她突然崩溃倒地，他根本来不及扶住她。她晕了过去。他急得团团转，想找来一杯水。房间里没有水，他又不想惊动看守，便帮她平躺在地，在她身边蹲下来，等她苏醒。她醒来时，双眼充满恐惧，把他吓得六神无主。

“躺着别动，”他说，“一会儿就好。”

“请不要让他们绞死我。”她有气无力地说。

她发狂一般大哭起来，他连忙低声安慰她。

“看在上帝的分儿上，请你振作起来。”他说。

“给我一点儿时间。”

她实在是胆色过人。他看着她竭尽全力控制住情绪，迅速镇静了下来。

“请扶我起来。”

他把手递给她，拉她起身，搀她坐到椅子上。她精疲力竭地坐下。

“请让我冷静几分钟。”她说。

“好的。”

等到她终于开口说话，却是语出惊人。她轻轻叹了一口气。

“恐怕我把事情弄到了不可收拾的地步。”她说。

他没有回答，两人再度陷入沉默。

“难道我们无法取得那封信吗？”她终于说道。

“如果信的持有者不打算卖掉它，我就不会知道它的存在。”

“它在谁手里？”

“在和哈蒙德同居的中国女人手里。”

莱斯莉的脸红一阵白一阵的。

“她肯定想趁机敲诈一笔。”

“我想她很清楚这封信的价值，看来要花一笔巨款。”

“难道您要见死不救吗？”

“这件证物对我们如此不利，你以为她会那么容易就交给我们吗？那无异于贿赂证人。你没有权利要求我以身试法。”

“那他们会怎么对我？”

“依法宣判。”

她的脸色死一般苍白，浑身一阵颤抖。

“请您为我做主。当然我无权请求您铤而走险。”

乔伊斯先生没想到她一向自控得法的声音呜咽起来是如此令人于心不忍。她茫然无措地望着他，假使他拒绝伸出援手，也许终生无法释怀。毕竟，逝者已矣，可怜的哈蒙德不可能起死回生了。他很想知道那封信的玄机，仅凭它就判定哈蒙德并非因为把她逼得走投无路才招致杀身之祸，显然有失公正。他在远东混迹已久，职业操守也许远不如二十年前高尚。他望着地板，做了一个决定。他知道这样做不对，因此羞于启齿，暗暗怨恨着莱斯莉。他甚至开始憎恶自己的声音。

“我不太清楚你丈夫的财产情况。”

她飞红了脸，瞥他一眼。

“他持有许多锡矿股份以及几个橡胶园的少量股份。我想他能筹到钱。”

“我必须告诉他这笔钱的去处。”

她沉默了一会儿，仿佛在思索。

“他还深爱着我。他会不惜一切代价救我。您要给他看那封信吗？”

乔伊斯先生皱皱眉头。她立刻察觉到了，继续说道：

“罗伯特是您的老朋友。我不是在求您为我效劳，我是在求您解救一个单纯善良的人。他从未伤害过您，我想您也一定不忍心看见他受罪。”

乔伊斯先生没有回应她的话，站起来要走。克罗斯比太太像往常一样自然优雅地伸出手。受到这场突如其来的惊吓，她看起来有点儿黯然憔悴，但依旧强打精神，祝他一切顺利。

“谢谢您帮我处理这么棘手的事情，我的感激之情无以言表。”

乔伊斯先生回到办公室，也没有心思工作，只闷坐着胡思乱想，脑海里闪过各种奇怪的画面。他有点儿不寒而栗。最后，他如愿听到那阵鬼鬼祟祟的敲门声。王智生推门进来。

“我正要出去吃午饭，先生。”他道。

“去吧。”

“请问在我出去之前您有什么事情吩咐吗，先生？”

“暂时没有。里德先生有没有重新预约？”

“重新预约过了，先生。他下午三点钟过来。”

“很好。”

王智生转身走到门口，把细长的手指放在门把手上。仿佛突然想起有话未说，又反身回来。

“请问您有什么话要对我的朋友说吗，先生？我很乐意代为转达。”

尽管王智生的英文说得如此漂亮，仍然有一个音永远发不准，把朋友说成“甭友”。

“什么朋友？”

“您大概还记得克罗斯比太太写过一封信给已故的哈蒙德先生吧。”

“啊，我还真忘了。我与克罗斯比太太谈过这件事，她否认写过那样的信。那明显是伪造的。”

乔伊斯先生把誊抄本从口袋里拿出来，递给王智生。王智生没有伸手去接。

“既然如此，先生，我想不会有人反对我的‘甭友’把信呈交副检察官。”

“不会。但我不知道那样做对你的朋友有什么好处。”

“我的‘甭友’，先生，一向将维护正义视为己责。”

“我绝不会阻止任何人履行自己的责任，智生。”

律师和华人助理四目相对。他们都面无表情，但对彼此的想法都心知肚明。

“您当然不会，先生，”王智生说，“但根据我对此案的研究，我认为这样一封信对我们的委托人极为不利。”

“我一向很欣赏你敏锐的法律意识，智生。”

“先生，我发现，如果我可以说服我的‘甭友’诱使这位中国女人把信交给我们，事情就简单多了。”

乔伊斯先生漫不经心地在吸墨纸上画人脸。

“我猜你的朋友是个商人。他会开出什么条件？”

“信在那位中国女人手里，他只是这个女人的亲戚。这个女人是个糊涂的人，若不是我‘甭友’告诉她，她也不知道那封信的价值。”

“你朋友怎么说？”

“他说这封信值一万叻币[5]，先生。”

“天啊！你居然认为克罗斯比太太拿得出一万叻币！你听好了，那封信是伪造的。”

说这话的时候，他抬起头暴怒地看着王智生。助理不为所动，站在桌子的另一旁，彬彬有礼，怡然自若，毕恭毕敬。

“克罗斯比先生持有勿洞橡胶园八分之一的股份和南河橡胶园六分之一的股份。如果他肯拿这些股份作抵押，我有一个‘甭友’可以借钱给他。”

“你认识的人真不少，智生。”

“没错，先生。”

“你可以让他们趁早死心。这封信很好解释，依我看，克罗斯比先生最多出五千叻币。”

“那位中国女人并不想把这封信卖掉，先生。我的‘甭友’费尽唇舌才说服了她，一万叻币是底线。”

乔伊斯先生死死地盯着王智生。助理恭顺地低头站着，毫无窘态。乔伊斯先生知道他是什么人。他想，王智生，你也太聪明了，你能从中渔利多少呢？

“一万叻币可不是笔小数目。”

“克罗斯比先生当然愿意出这笔钱，他不会眼睁睁看着自己的妻子被绞死。”

乔伊斯先生又沉默了。王智生还藏了什么话？他一口咬定这是底线，看来已经胸有成竹。不管谁是幕后主使，这个人肯定十分清楚这是罗伯特·克罗斯比刚好能拿得出来的一笔钱，绝对不会让步。

“那个中国女人现在在哪里？”乔伊斯先生问。

“我‘甭友’家，先生。”

“她愿意到这儿来吗？”

“我想最好还是您去找她，先生。今晚我可以为您带路，她会把信给您。她很糊涂，先生，看不懂支票。”

“我没打算给她支票。我会付现金。”

“假如您带的现金不足数，只会浪费您的宝贵时间。”

“不用你说。”

“我吃完午饭便去通知‘甭友’。”

“很好，请你今晚十点在俱乐部外面等我。”

“谢谢，先生。”王智生说。

王智生向乔伊斯先生微微鞠了一躬便出去了。乔伊斯先生也外出吃饭，在俱乐部如愿见到了罗伯特·克罗斯比。他坐在一张拥挤的桌子旁，乔伊斯先生找座位时顺道经过他，拍拍他的肩膀。

“在你走之前我想和你谈谈。”他说。

“我正好也找您呢，您吃完饭就叫我吧。”

对于这次谈话，乔伊斯先生已经心里有数。午饭后，他去打桥牌，等俱乐部里的人自然散去。他不想专门就此事与克罗斯比在办公室见面。克罗斯比走进棋牌室看他打牌，牌局结束后，众人各自去忙自己的事，棋牌室里只剩下他们两人。

“老朋友，我有一个坏消息要告诉你，”乔伊斯先生尽量让自己听起来平淡随意，“哈蒙德被杀当晚，似乎你的妻子给他送了一封信请他过来。”

“怎么可能！”克罗斯比喊道，“她一直说自己根本不与哈蒙德联系。据我所知她已经有好几个月没见过他了。”

“但她确实写了那封信。这封信目前在和哈蒙德同居的中国女人手里。你的妻子想托哈蒙德帮她买一份礼物给你庆祝生日。那个悲剧令她情绪失控，完全忘记了此事，否认联系过哈蒙德，如今她也没有勇气承认错误了。这当然很不幸，但也实属自然。”

克罗斯比没有说话。他那张又大又红的脸露出困惑的神情，乔伊斯先生马上放下心来，却又觉得不耐烦。他太蠢了，乔伊斯先生讨厌在蠢人身上浪费时间。但想到事发以来他受到的种种折磨，律师忽然对他生出无限的同情。克罗斯比太太以丈夫的名义请求帮助，恰恰戳中了律师心中最柔软的地方。

“很明显，如果这封信被送到检察官手里，无疑会节外生枝。你的妻子说了谎话，检察官会要求她解释这个谎言。如果哈蒙德没有不请自来，不是一个不速之客，而是应邀上门，事情就没有那么简单。陪审团的立场很容易因此动摇。”

乔伊斯先生犹豫了。他必须执行自己的决定。如果有时间开玩笑，他一定会嘲讽自己，因为他突然想到，他马上要为了眼前这个人作奸犯科，这个人对问题的严重性却还懵然不知。但即使克罗斯比细思之，也很可能只会以为这是乔伊斯先生的例行公事。

“我亲爱的罗伯特，你不仅是我的委托人，还是我的朋友。我想我们必须拿到那封信，但那要花很多钱，否则我情愿瞒住你。”

“要花多少钱？”

“一万叻币。”

“那也太多了吧。现在时世艰难，诸事不顺，这简直是要我倾家荡产。”

“你能立刻筹齐这笔钱吗？”

“差不多吧。要是我拿锡矿和两个庄园的股份作抵押，老查理·梅多斯会借给我的。”

“那你愿意吗？”

“我不得不这么做吗？”

“如果你希望你的妻子被判无罪释放的话。”

克罗斯比涨红了脸，龇牙咧嘴的一脸怪相。

“但……”他不知道说什么好，脸色已经发紫了，“但我不懂。她可以解释。您不是要告诉我，他们会判她有罪吧？他们怎么可以因为她杀掉这个人人喊打的歹徒而绞死她呢？”

“他们当然不会绞死她，可能只会裁定她误杀，判两三年有期徒刑。”

克罗斯比跳起来，万分惊恐之下，他红扑扑的脸变得狰狞可怖。

“三年。”

刹那间，迟钝的他仿佛想起了某件事情。一道闪电突然划破黑暗，尽管接下来的黑暗依然如前一般深邃，某段回忆却被短暂地照亮了。乔伊斯先生看见克罗斯比那双因久经历练而长满老茧的红色巨手在颤抖。

“她想给我买什么礼物？”

“她说想送你一支新的手枪。”

克罗斯比的巨脸再度涨得通红。

“这笔钱什么时候要？”

此时他的声音有点儿奇怪，仿佛喉咙被一双隐形的手死死掐着。

“今晚十点。麻烦你六点左右带着钱来我办公室。”

“那女人会来找你吗？”

“不，我去找她。”

“我会带上钱，到时跟您一起去。”

乔伊斯先生用锋利的目光看着他。

“你觉得有这个必要吗？我认为你最好把这件事交给我全权处理。”

“那是我的钱吧？我要去。”

乔伊斯先生耸耸肩。他们起身握手，乔伊斯先生盯着他，仿佛对他很感兴趣似的。

十点钟，他们在空荡荡的俱乐部见面。

“准备好了？”乔伊斯先生问。

“是的，我把钱放口袋里了。”

“那走吧。”

他们走下楼梯。乔伊斯先生的车在静悄悄的广场上等着他们。他们走向汽车时，王智生从一座房子的阴影中大步走出，坐到司机旁边指路。他们驶过欧洲酒店和水手之家[6]，开上维多利亚街。街上的中国商店仍未打烊，流浪汉在街上四处游荡，黄包车、汽车和马车匆忙来去。车突然停了，王智生转过来。

“我想我们最好是在这里下车走过去，先生。”他说。

他们下了车，他负责引路，另外两人隔着几步的距离跟在后面。过了一会儿，他请他们停步。

“请您在这里等一下，先生。我进去知会我‘甭友’一声。”

他走进一间临街的商店，有几个华人站在柜台后面。总有一些奇怪的商店，里面什么商品也看不见，不知道做的是什么生意，这间就是其中之一。他们看见他和一个矮胖的男人说话。那男人穿着唐装，胸前挂一条巨大的金项链，迅速向外面扫了一眼，交给王智生一把钥匙，王智生走出来，向在一旁等待的两人点头示意，溜进商店的侧门。他们跟着他来到一条楼梯下面。

“请等一会儿，我点根火柴。”他说，多么机灵，“请上楼。”

他在他们前面举着一根日本火柴，但几乎没有用，他们摸索着跟在他后面一步步走上二楼。他打开一扇门，进房点亮煤油灯。

“请进。”他说。

房间很小，四方形，有一扇窗户，家具只有两张铺着席子的中式床。角落放着一个大箱子，锁非常精致，箱子上有一个破旧的托盘，摆着鸦片烟枪和一盏灯。一股微微辛辣的鸦片烟味弥漫着。两人坐下来，王智生给他们递烟。过了一会儿，刚才站在柜台后面的那个矮胖华人进来了，他用娴熟的英文向他们问好，在他的同胞身旁坐下。

“那位女士马上来。”王智生说。

商店的伙计把茶端上来，矮胖的华人请他们用茶，克罗斯比拒绝了。两位华人悄声交谈，克罗斯比和乔伊斯先生沉默不语。过了很久，外面传来人声，有人低声叫唤，那个矮胖的华人走到门边，开门说了几句话，请一个女人进来。乔伊斯先生仔细端详她。哈蒙德过世后，她艳名远播，乔伊斯先生现在总算能一睹其真容了。她略微有些发福，年纪也偏大，大脸盘，一副漠然的神气，粉光脂艳，眉毛描成细长的黑线，有一种悍然的魔力。她穿着淡蓝上衣和白裙，打扮得不中不西的，但踩着一双小巧的中式丝面织锦拖鞋。她戴着沉沉的金项链、金手镯、金耳环，乌黑的发髻上插着金簪子。她缓缓步入，昂然自信，但步伐有点儿沉滞。她在王智生旁边的床上坐下，他对她说了几句话，她点点头，淡淡地斜了两位白人男士一眼。

“她带着信吧？”乔伊斯先生问。

“是的，先生。”

克罗斯比一言不发，掏出一卷五百元的钞票，数出两百张递给王智生。

“你数数看对不对。”

助理点了一遍，把钱递给那位矮胖的华人。

“没问题，先生。”

那矮胖的华人又数了一次，把钱放进口袋。他又向女人说话，她从怀里摸出一封信递给王智生，王智生看了一眼。

“就是这封信，先生。”他说。他正要把信交给乔伊斯先生，克罗斯比一手抢了过去。

“给我看看。”他说。

乔伊斯先生看着他把信读完，向他伸出手。

“还是交给我来保管吧。”

克罗斯比小心地把它折起来，放进口袋。

“不，我要自己留着，这封信可真够贵的。”

乔伊斯先生没有坚持。三个华人旁观着这场小型纷争，但他们的表情过于冷漠，看不出他们的感想。也许他们根本就没有感想。乔伊斯先生站起来。

“今晚还有什么吩咐吗，先生？”王智生说。

“没有了。”他知道助理想留下来分赃，便转向克罗斯比，“好了吗？”

克罗斯比没有回答，直接站起身。那矮胖的华人走到门边给他们开门。王智生找到一小截蜡烛点着，为他们照路，和同伴一起把他们送到街上。那女人留下来，安静地坐在床上抽烟。两位华人在街上与他们道别，回身上楼。

“你想怎样处理这封信？”乔伊斯先生问。

“留着它。”

他们回到车上，乔伊斯先生想送朋友一程，但克罗斯比摇摇头。

“我想走走。”他犹豫了一会儿，迈开沉重的步子，“哈蒙德被杀那晚，我之所以去新加坡，其中一件事是找熟人买支新枪，他正好要出手。晚安。”

黑夜迅速吞噬了他。

乔伊斯先生对审判结果的判断非常准确。开庭时，陪审团已经决定无论如何也要宣判克罗斯比太太无罪。她亲自作证，清晰简洁地陈述了案情。副检察官面软心慈，显出一副他仅仅是在公事公办的样子，随便问了几个例行的问题，结案陈词基本上是被告的辩护词。陪审团花了不到五分钟就做出了众望所归的判决，挤满法庭的人群沸腾了，雷鸣般的掌声不绝于耳。法官祝贺克罗斯比太太重获自由。

没有人比乔伊斯太太对哈蒙德的兽行更为义愤填膺。她对朋友总是赤诚相见，早就说好等审判结束后把克罗斯比夫妇接到自己家中小住一阵，等一切安排妥当后再离开。她跟所有人一样认定克罗斯比太太会被判无罪，当然不能让可怜的、亲爱的、勇敢的莱斯莉直接返回惨案现场。审讯十二点半结束，他们到达乔伊斯家时，丰盛的午餐和上等的鸡尾酒已经待客多时。乔伊斯太太特意准备了在马来亚联合邦久负盛名的天价鸡尾酒，祝莱斯莉早日恢复健康。她是一位活泼健谈的主妇，此刻更是兴高采烈。也幸好她是这样没眼色，不然就没人说话了。不过也没什么好怀疑的，她的丈夫向来抱定“沉默是金”的态度，而另外两人久经折磨，自然已是筋疲力尽。用餐期间只有她独自欢欣鼓舞地说个不停，直到仆役端来咖啡。

“好了，孩子们，”她兴冲冲地说，“你们快去休息一下，用过下午茶我带你们一起去海边兜风。”

乔伊斯先生今天是破例回家吃午饭，饭后自然要回事务所去。

“恐怕我要失陪了，乔伊斯太太，”克罗斯比说，“我必须马上赶回橡胶园。”

“今天就走？”她喊道。

“是的，今天就走。我很久没回去了，有些急事要处理。很感谢您照顾莱斯莉，我们会再作打算的。”

乔伊斯太太想劝他留下来，乔伊斯先生拦住她。

“如果他已经决定了，就随他去吧。天下无不散之筵席。”

她听出了弦外之音，斜了他一眼，不再说话。一阵沉默过后，克罗斯比开口了。

“请您原谅。我现在就动身，好在天黑前赶到。”他站起身，“你能来送送我吗，莱斯莉？”

“当然了。”

他们一起走出餐厅。

“他也太不懂得体贴人了，”乔伊斯太太说，“他难道不知道莱斯莉现在离不开他？”

“如果他能留下来，就一定不会走。相信我。”

“好吧，那我去看看莱斯莉的房间收拾好没有。她绝对需要好好休息，然后好好玩几天。”

乔伊斯太太走出房间，乔伊斯重新坐下。过了一会儿，他听到克罗斯比发动摩托车引擎，车轮轧过花园的碎石小路，骨碌碌地响。他起身走到会客室，克罗斯比太太站在会客室中央，茫然若失，手执一封摊开的信。就是那封密函。他进来的时候，她看了他一眼，脸色死一般的苍白。

“他知道了。”她喃喃道。

乔伊斯先生走到她跟前，把信拿到自己手里，划燃一根火柴，点着那张纸。她看着它一寸一寸地烧掉。火快烧到他手上时，他把它丢到瓷砖地面上，两人看着那张纸卷起来，变黑。他把它踩成灰。

“他知道什么了？”

她久久地凝视着他，双眸带着奇怪的表情。鄙夷还是绝望？乔伊斯先生说不上来。

“他知道了杰夫是我的情人。”

乔伊斯先生惊讶得呆若木鸡。

“我和他在一起很久了。他刚退伍不久我们就开始了。我们知道怎样小心都不为过，我假装讨厌他，罗伯特在的时候他也几乎不上我家来。我常常开车出去与他幽会，每周两三次，罗伯特去新加坡时，他就等仆人就寝之后来找我。我们一直都很好，如胶似漆，心有灵犀。然而最近，大概一年前吧，他开始变得跟从前不一样，我不知道是怎么回事。我无法相信他不再爱我了。他总是说我多心，但我真的受不了了，不断地和他吵架，有时候我想他是厌恶我了。啊，那真是无以言说的痛苦，我伤心得死去活来。我知道他要抛弃我，但我怎么愿意放手！多么痛苦！多么痛苦！我爱他，我把一切毫无保留地交给了他，失去他我活不下去。后来我听说他和一个中国女人同居。我不能相信这是真的，我怎么能够！但终于有一天，我看见了她，亲眼看见她戴着金镯子和金项链在村子里闲逛，那个又老又胖的中国女人！她比我还要老！简直是作孽！那个村里的人都知道她是杰夫的情人。我在她身边经过，她看着我，我知道她知道我也是杰夫的情人。我写信把杰夫叫来，告诉他我必须见他，您也读过那封信。我真是疯了，不知道自己在做什么。我不在乎后果如何，我已经足足十天没见他，那对我来说就像一辈子。最后一次分别时，他把我拥入怀里，吻我，叫我放心，但他头也不回地从我的怀里走进她的怀里。”

她一直在激动地低声说话，说到这里停住了，拧着双手。

“那封可恶的信。我们总是很注意，每次我给他写信，他看完后都会撕碎，怎么想到他偏留下了那一封？他来了，我告诉他我知道那个中国女人的事，但他矢口否认，说那只是流言蜚语。我气得发狂，不知道自己说了些什么。啊，他那个时候是多么面目可憎！我抓他，挠他，我要把他撕得粉碎。我什么都说了，只为了伤害他的自尊心。我侮辱了他，可能还扇了他耳光，他终于生气了。他说我令他感到恶心，他再也不想见到我。他说我把他烦得要命，然后承认了自己与那个中国女人的关系。他说他们两个认识多年，早在战前就已经认识了，只有这个女人才是他的全部，其余的不过是些闲花野草。他说他很高兴，我终于知道了这件事，不会再缠住他。接下来发生了什么，我也不知道。我疯了，我控制不住自己。我抓起枪，扣动了扳机。他大喊一声，我看见他中枪了。他踉跄了几步，逃到游廊上去，我紧跟着他，又开了一枪，他倒下了，我站在他旁边不断扣动扳机，直到枪咔咔作响，我才反应过来子弹已经打光了。”

她终于说完了，气喘吁吁。那张脸不再是人脸，野蛮、愤怒和痛苦把它毁掉了。这位娴静高贵的女士竟然会生出如此邪恶的情感，简直无法想象。她的样子把乔伊斯先生吓得连忙后撤了几步。他看见的不是一张脸，而是一个口齿不清的鬼面具。突然从另一间房间传来一个响亮、亲切又欢快的声音。是乔伊斯太太。

“亲爱的莱斯莉，快来快来，房间准备好了，你肯定困得睁不开眼睛了吧。”

克罗斯比太太的面容慢慢舒缓下来。那些激烈的情绪消失了，仿佛用手抚平一张被揉皱了的纸一样，这张脸重新变得平静淡雅。她的脸色略微有些苍白，双唇却露出甜美可亲的微笑。她又变回那位知书识礼、雍容华贵的太太。

“这就来，亲爱的多萝西。给您添了这么多麻烦，还真是过意不去呢。”

[1]　英国四大律师学院之一，历史悠久。

[2]　即槟城，位于马来亚西北部。

[3]　杰弗里之昵称。

[4]　位于马来半岛西部的霹雳州。

[5]　英国殖民时期流通于马来亚与新加坡的货币。

[6]　专为水手提供住宿的旅店，收费低廉。

晚会之前

孔祥立　译

斯金纳夫人做事向来守时。现在她已穿戴完毕——身上这件黑色绸料衣服，既与她的年龄相符，又适合为她的女婿服丧，现在她戴上了她的丝绒帽。不过她不太确定戴上它是否合适，因为装饰帽子的白鹭羽毛定会引来一些她将在晚会上碰到的朋友的刻薄劝告。当然，为了这些羽毛而杀掉那些漂亮的白鸟儿，并且是在交配季节，这种事确实令人扼腕。不过，这些羽毛实在是太漂亮、太时尚了，傻子才会拒绝它们，再说，如果她真这样做，肯定会伤害到她女婿的感情，他一路从婆罗洲把它们带来，只希望能讨她欢心。凯思林曾十分厌恶这些羽毛，发生那件事后，她一定希望自己当时没有那样表现。不过，凯思林本就从未真心喜欢过哈罗德。斯金纳夫人站在梳妆台前，将丝绒帽戴在头上，并用一枚有着硕大黑玉圆头的饰针将帽子固定，不管怎样，这是她仅有的一顶漂亮帽子。要是有谁跟她谈起那些鸟儿，她已想好怎么回答了。

“我知道这很不好，”她可以说，“我做梦都不会想买这些东西，但它们是我可怜的女婿上次回家休假时给我带来的。”

那样就能够解释她为何会拥有它们，并为使用它们找到了借口。大家都是善良之人嘛。斯金纳夫人从抽屉里拿出一块干净的手帕，然后在上面喷了点儿古龙水[1]。她从来不用香水，她认为香水太黏稠了，但古龙水却让人神清气爽。现在她已经差不多准备好了。她的目光越过梳妆镜，朝窗外望去。卡农·海伍德为花园晚会挑选了个好日子。天气暖融融的，天空一片蔚蓝，树木尚未褪去春日里的鲜绿。当看见她的小外孙女琼正在房子后面的带状花园里忙着为自己的花坛耙土时，斯金纳夫人不由得笑了。她希望琼的脸色不要那么苍白，让她在热带待那么久，真是个错误，而且就她那个年龄段来讲，她显得太过沉闷了，你从来看不到她跑来跑去，她总是静静地玩自己发明的游戏，或是给花园浇水。斯金纳夫人轻轻拍了拍裙子的前摆，拿起手套，下了楼。

凯思林正坐在靠窗的书桌前，忙着做手里的清单。她是女子高尔夫球俱乐部的名誉秘书长，每当有赛事举办时都有一大堆事情等着她去做。但她已经准备好参加晚会了。

“你最终还是穿了套衫。”斯金纳夫人说。

吃午餐时，她们讨论过凯思林是穿套衫还是黑色雪纺衫的问题。套衫是黑白相间的，凯思林觉得它更时尚一些，但实在不太适合用来服丧，不过米莉森特支持她穿。

“干吗要让我们看上去都像刚参加完葬礼回来似的？”她说，“哈罗德已经死了八个月了。”

在斯金纳夫人看来，说这样的话未免太过绝情。自打从婆罗洲回来后，米莉森特就显得很奇怪。

“你们不会现在就要停戴黑纱了吧，亲爱的？”她问。

米莉森特没有直接回答。

“人们现在穿丧服跟以前不一样了。”她说。而后她稍稍停顿了一下，当她再次开口时，语气让斯金纳夫人觉得非常怪异。显然，凯思林也注意到了这点，因为她也正用奇怪的目光盯着她的姐姐。“我敢肯定，哈罗德也不希望我永远为他穿着丧服。”

“我早穿好了，因为我有些话想跟米莉森特说。”凯思林就母亲的言论做出回答。

“哦？”

凯思林没有解释。不过，她把清单放到一边，皱着眉头重读了一位女士的来信。那位女士在信中投诉俱乐部委员会极不公平地把她应得的让棍数[2]从二十四减到了十八；作为女子高尔夫球俱乐部的名誉秘书长，必须具备相当的智慧。斯金纳夫人开始戴她的新手套。遮阳帘使房间变得凉爽幽暗，她看了一眼那个涂着鲜艳油漆的巨大木制犀鸟——那是哈罗德留给她的，以保佑她一生平安。在她看来，这只犀鸟有些古怪、粗野，但哈罗德很是看重它。这个东西有一定的宗教意义，卡农·海伍德也对它印象极深。沙发上面的墙上，挂着些马来武器，她记不得它们叫什么名字了。茶几上，到处放着一些银器和铜器，都是哈罗德在不同时期送给他们的。她从前一直很喜欢哈罗德，她的眼睛不由自主地开始搜寻起他的那张照片来。照片以前是放在钢琴上的，与她两个女儿、外孙女、姐姐以及外甥的照片放在一起。

“哎呀，凯思林，哈罗德的照片哪里去了？”她问。

凯思林转过头来，照片不见了。

“有人把它拿走了。”凯思林说。

惊讶之余，斯金纳夫人又感到疑惑不解，她起身走到钢琴旁。照片重新整理过了，这样照片之间就没有空隙了。

“或许是米莉森特把它放到自己房间里了。”她说。

“我应该注意到的。再说，米莉森特已经有好几张哈罗德的照片了。她将它们都锁起来了。”

斯金纳夫人觉得奇怪，女儿的房间里竟然没有哈罗德的照片。事实上，有一次她曾提到过这件事，但米莉森特没有回答。自打从婆罗洲回来后，米莉森特就异常沉默，斯金纳夫人本来十分想要安慰一下她的，但看她这个样子，也就不了了之了。米莉森特似乎不愿意谈起自己的巨大不幸。人们表达悲伤的方式千差万别，她丈夫说，最有效的做法就是不要管她。一想到丈夫，斯金纳夫人的心思又回到了即将参加的晚会上。

“你们的父亲问我，是否觉得他应戴个高顶礼帽。”她说，“我说，我觉得为了稳妥起见，还是戴上为好。”

这将是一场盛大的晚宴。他们会吃上博迪糖果店制作的草莓和香草味的冰淇淋。不过，海伍德一家也会提供自制的冰镇咖啡。每个人都会出席。他们已被邀请前去拜见香港主教——他正和卡农一家在一起，他是卡农的老同学，将做关于中国传教活动的演讲。斯金纳夫人的女儿曾在东方待过八年，而她的女婿原先就是婆罗洲某个地区的驻扎官员，所以她对此很感兴趣。当然，跟那些与殖民地之类的事情毫无瓜葛的人相比，这场演讲对她来说有着更多的意义。

“只有英国人才知道的东西他们懂什么呢？”斯金纳先生这样说过。

正在这时，他走进了房间。他是名律师，他父亲以前也是律师，他在林肯营田[3]有自己的办公室。他每天早上前去伦敦，晚上回来。这次他能够陪着妻子和女儿们去参加卡农家的花园晚会，是因为卡农非常巧妙地把晚会时间定在了周六。斯金纳先生身着燕尾服和黑白相间的裤子，看起来神采奕奕。他不是特别讲究穿着，但穿戴非常整洁，看起来像是一名受人尊重的家庭律师，事实也是如此。他的公司从不接手那些不能完全摆上台面的事务。假如一个遇到麻烦的客户找到他，但涉及的事务不那么光彩，他的脸色就会变得非常严峻。

“我觉得，我们是不大乐意接这种案子的，”他说，“你最好到别处问问。”

他抽出便笺，快速写下了一个名字和地址，然后把纸撕下来交给客户。

“假如我是你的话，我想我会去见这些人。只要你提到我的名字，我相信他们一定会竭诚为您服务。”

斯金纳先生脸上的胡子刮得非常干净，他秃顶严重，苍白的薄唇紧紧地抿着，但一双蓝眼睛却尽显羞怯。他的面颊看不到血色，脸上布满皱纹。

“你穿上新裤子了。”斯金纳夫人说。

“我觉得这个场合挺合适的，”他回答，“我在想，我是不是应该在翻领上别枝花呀。”

“我反正不会那样做，爸爸，”凯思林说，“我认为那个样子不好看。”

“很多人都会戴的。”斯金纳夫人说道。

“只有办事员那类人才会戴，”凯思林说，“海伍德一家宴请了所有人，你知道的。再说，我们还在服丧啊。”

“不知道主教演讲后会不会要求捐款。”斯金纳说。

“我觉得应该不会。”斯金纳夫人回答。

“我觉得这样做的话就太差劲了。”凯思林发表看法道。

“还是以防万一为好，”斯金纳先生说，“到时候，我就代表全家捐款了，不知道十个先令够不够，还是我必须捐一英镑啊。”

“假如你要捐款，我想你应该捐一英镑，爸爸。”凯思林说。

“到时我会视情况而定的。我不能比别人给得少，但另一方面，也没有理由多给。”

凯思林把她的文件放进写字台的抽屉里，然后站起身。她看了看腕表。

“米莉森特准备好了吗？”斯金纳夫人问。

“还有的是时间。我们约的是四点，我认为我们四点半之前不用到的。我告诉了戴维斯，让他四点十五左右把车开过来。”

通常都是凯思林开车，但像今天这样的重大场合，园丁戴维斯就会穿上制服充当司机。这样当车开到门口时，也会更加体面一些。并且凯思林穿上了新套衫，自然是不太想开车的。看到母亲正一根手指一根手指地费力戴着手套，她想到自己也需要戴上。她闻了闻手套，看是否还有肥皂的气味残留在上面。还好，味很淡，她想不会有人注意。

门终于打开了，米莉森特走了进来。她戴着寡妇用的黑纱。斯金纳夫人一直没能适应它们，但她当然知道米莉森特必须整整一年都戴着它们。很遗憾，黑纱并不适合她，它只适合一些人。她曾试戴过一次米莉森特的帽子，还有配套的白带子、长面纱，她自觉看上去很不错。她当然希望亲爱的阿尔弗雷德比自己活得更长久，但如果他不能，她将永远为他戴着黑纱。维多利亚女王的黑纱就从未摘下过。但米莉森特不一样，她要年轻得多，她只有三十六岁——三十六岁就做寡妇真是太不幸了，而且她再婚的可能性并不大。凯思林现在还不大可能结婚，虽然她已经三十五岁了。上次米莉森特和哈罗德回来时，她曾提议让凯思林去跟他们一起住，哈罗德倒是非常愿意，但米莉森特却说不能这样。斯金纳夫人不知道为什么不能，那原本能给凯思林一个机会。当然，他们并不是想摆脱她，但女孩子终究是要嫁人的，问题是，他们在国内所熟知的男人都已经结婚了。米莉森特解释说，是因为天气太糟糕了。的确，她的肤色变得很差，现在已经没人认为米莉森特是两姐妹中更漂亮的那一个了。随着年龄的增长，凯思林长得越发精致，当然也有人说她太瘦，但现在她剪短了头发，再加上不管刮风下雨坚持打高尔夫球，她的脸颊已经逐渐红润了起来，斯金纳夫人认为她现在很漂亮，但没人能够这样说可怜的米莉森特。她的身材整个走了形，本来个子就不高，现在又发起福来，看上去一副矮胖粗壮的样子。她实在太胖了，斯金纳夫人认为这是由于热带的高温让她无法进行锻炼。她的皮肤灰黄，像泥土一样，而那一双蓝眼睛，曾经是她脸上最好看的地方，如今也变得黯淡无光了。

“她应该处理一下她的脖子，”斯金纳夫人心想，“她现在的双下巴太可怕了！”

她曾跟丈夫提起过一两次，他说米莉森特也不年轻了，话是没错，但她也不能破罐子破摔呀。斯金纳夫人决定跟她的女儿好好谈谈，但她当然必须尊重女儿的不幸，她可以等一年结束后再说。她很高兴能够找到这个理由推迟跟女儿的谈话，一想到这件事她就有点儿紧张。因为米莉森特肯定是变了，她脸上的阴郁让她的母亲感到陌生。斯金纳夫人总是喜欢不过脑子就把心中所想大声讲出来，但当你说话时（只是随便说说，你知道），米莉森特总是不予搭理，这让人感到尴尬，因为你根本不知道她有没有在听。有时候，斯金纳夫人会因此恼羞成怒，但为了不冲米莉森特发火，她不得不提醒自己可怜的哈罗德才刚刚死了八个月。

寡妇正默不作声地向前走，阳光透过窗户照进来，打在了她那张肥厚的脸庞上，而凯思林是背光站着的，她已经注视了她姐姐好一会儿了。

“米莉森特，我想跟你说件事，”她说，“今天早上我跟格拉迪斯·海伍德一起打高尔夫球了。”

“你打败她了？”米莉森特问。

格拉迪斯·海伍德是卡农家唯一未嫁的女儿。

“她跟我说了一件与你有关的事，我认为你应该要知道。”

米莉森特的目光从她妹妹身上转移开，投向了正在花园里浇花的小女孩。

“你有告诉安妮把琼放在厨房的茶端给她吗，妈妈？”她问。

“已经告诉她了，仆人喝茶时她就会喝。”凯思林冷冷地看着她。

“主教回家路上在新加坡待了两三天，”凯思林继续说道，“他很喜欢旅行，去过婆罗洲。他认识很多你认识的人。”

“他很有兴致见见你，亲爱的，”斯金纳夫人说，“他认识可怜的哈罗德吗？”

“是的，他在瓜拉索洛见过他，对他印象深刻。他说当他听到他的死讯时，非常震惊。”

米莉森特坐下来，开始戴她那双黑色的手套。让斯金纳夫人感到奇怪的是，听到这些话后，她居然一言不发。

“哦，米莉森特，”她说，“哈罗德的照片不见了，是你拿了吗？”

“是的，我把它拿走了。”

“我就想着应该是你拿走的。”

米莉森特再次陷入了沉默，这真是一个气死人的臭毛病。

凯思林稍稍转了下身，以便能正对着她的姐姐。

“米莉森特，你为什么跟我们说哈罗德死于热病？”

寡妇纹丝不动，她直直地看着凯思林，土黄色的皮肤因为泛红而暗淡下来。她没有回答。

“你这话什么意思，凯思林？”斯金纳夫人惊讶地问。

“主教说，哈罗德是自杀的。”

斯金纳夫人惊讶地大叫起来，但她丈夫伸了伸手，示意她不要激动。

“是真的吗，米莉森特？”

“是真的。”

“那你为何不告诉我们？”

米莉森特停顿了片刻，她用手指漫不经心地拨弄着一个放在身侧桌子上的文莱铜器。那也是一份来自哈罗德的礼物。

“我觉得让琼以为她的父亲死于热病会更好些。我不想让她知道任何有关这件事的情况。”

“你让我们陷入了一种极度尴尬的境况，”凯思林微微皱了皱眉头，“格拉迪斯·海伍德说，她觉得我很不厚道，因为我没告诉她真相。我很难让她相信我对这件事一无所知。她说她父亲也很不高兴，他说我们认识这么多年了，想想还是他给你们主持的婚礼，大家关系如此融洽，他认为我们应该相信他。无论如何，即使我们不想告诉他真相，那也不应该骗他。”

“我得说，在这点上我跟他观点一致。”斯金纳先生不悦道。

“当然，我告诉格拉迪斯，这也不怨我们。我们只是把你的话转告给他们了。”

“但愿没有因此耽误你们的那场高尔夫球赛。”米莉森特说。

“说真的，亲爱的，我认为你这种说法太不恰当了。”她的父亲大声说道。

他从椅子上站起来，走到空空的壁炉边。出于习惯，他把燕尾分开了站在壁炉前。

“这是我的私事，”米莉森特答道，“如果我不想说出去，我不知道有什么理由非说不可。”

“如果连你的母亲你都不告诉，你对她还有什么感情可言？”斯金纳夫人道。

米莉森特耸了耸肩。

“你早该知道这种事迟早会曝光的。”凯思林说。

“我怎么可能知道？我没料到那两个喜欢传播流言蜚语的老神父除了议论我之外竟然无事可谈。”

“当时主教提到他去过婆罗洲，海伍德一家自然而然就会问他认不认识哈罗德了。”

“这些都不是重点，”斯金纳先生说，“我觉得你理应把真实的情况告诉我们，那样我们才能决定怎样做最好。作为一名律师，我可以告诉你，如果你想掩盖真相，从长远看只能让事情变得更糟。”

“可怜的哈罗德，”斯金纳夫人说着，泪水缓缓地从她涂满脂粉的脸颊上滑落，“真是太可怕了！他一直都是我的好女婿。到底是什么原因让他做出这种可怕的事？”

“是气候。”

“我想你最好把全部的真实情况都告诉我们，米莉森特。”父亲说。

“凯思林会跟你们说的。”

凯思林犹豫了。她要说的的确太可怕了，这种让人恐惧的事情似乎不应该发生在他们这样的家庭。

“主教说他是割喉自杀的。”

斯金纳夫人的呼吸变得急促起来，冲动之下她走到了丧失亲人的女儿身边。她想把她搂进怀里。

“我可怜的孩子。”她呜咽道。

但米莉森特缩了回去。

“不要来烦我，妈妈。我真的受不了这种搂搂抱抱。”

“你也真是的，米莉森特。”斯金纳先生皱了皱眉，说道。

他一直觉得她的举止不太像话。

斯金纳夫人小心翼翼地用手帕擦了擦眼，摇头叹气地坐回到椅子上。凯思林玩弄着脖子上的长项链。

“让一个朋友来告诉我姐夫死亡的细节，还有比这更荒唐的事吗？这件事让我们看起来像傻瓜一样。主教非常希望见见你，米莉森特。他想告诉你他对你有多么同情。”她停顿了一下，但米莉森特没有开口，“他说米莉森特带着琼出去了，当她回来时，发现可怜的哈罗德已经死在了床上。”

“那打击一定很大。”斯金纳先生说。

斯金纳夫人又开始哭了，凯思林轻轻地把手放在她肩上。

“别哭了，妈妈，”她说，“你的眼睛会哭红的，那会让人笑话的。”

他们都沉默下来。斯金纳夫人擦干了眼泪，努力控制住了自己。在这一刻，她的羽绒帽上还戴着可怜的哈罗德送给她的白鹭羽毛，这让她觉得非常奇怪。

“我还有话要告诉你。”凯思林说道。

米莉森特再次不慌不忙地看向她的妹妹，她的目光很沉着，但充满了警惕，神情像极了一个人在等待着一种响声，唯恐错过似的。

“我不想说任何伤害你的话，亲爱的，”凯思林继续说道，“但是还有些事情，我觉得你应该要知道。主教说，哈罗德喝醉了酒。”

“哦，亲爱的，太可怕了！”斯金纳夫人叫道，“这话说得太令人震惊了！是格拉迪斯·海伍德告诉你的吗？你怎么回答的？”

“我说那完全是胡说八道。”

“这都是掩盖真相造成的。”斯金纳先生气愤道，“事情总是如此。你越是想保守秘密，各种流言就越是会满天飞，那些往往要比真相糟糕得多。”

“在新加坡时，有人告诉主教，哈罗德是在震颤性谵妄发作时自杀的。我想，为了我们全家考虑，你应该否认这件事，米莉森特。”

“如此议论一个已经去世的人，真是件可怕的事，”斯金纳夫人说，“等琼长大了，对她来说这将是件十分糟糕的事！”

“不过这个说法有什么依据吗，米莉森特？”她父亲问，“哈罗德一向很节制的。”

“这个嘛。”寡妇回答。

“他喝酒吗？”

“简直就是暴饮，像鱼一样。”

这个回答如此出人意料，讥讽的语气如此强烈，让三个人都吓了一跳。

“米莉森特，你怎么可以这样说自己已经去世的丈夫？”她母亲大声叫道，两只整齐的戴着手套的手紧攥着，“我真的无法理解你。自从回来以后，你就一直很怪异。我根本无法相信，我的女儿，竟然会这样对待自己丈夫的死。”

“先别说这个了，孩子他妈。”斯金纳先生说，“这事儿我们可以以后再细说。”

他走到窗前，望着那个洒满阳光的小花园，然后又走回房间。他从口袋里掏出夹鼻眼镜，尽管没有戴上的打算，但还是用手帕擦了擦。米莉森特看了父亲一眼，眼神里尽是愤世嫉俗的嘲讽。斯金纳先生十分气恼，他已经完成了一周的工作，在下周一早晨之前，他都是个自由人。尽管他跟妻子说，这个花园晚会真是个麻烦事，他宁愿在自家的花园里静静地喝会儿茶，但他还是很期待这场晚会的。他对中国的传教活动不怎么在意，但倒是颇有兴致跟主教见上一面。唉，现在却发生了这档子事！他真不愿让自己牵扯到这类事情中。再说，突如其来地被人告知女婿是个酒鬼，还自杀了，这太叫人不快了！米莉森特若有所思地按压着白色的袖口，以使它变得平滑一些。她的冷淡神情激怒了他，但他没跟她说话，而是转向了小女儿。

“你怎么不坐下，凯思林？房间里有的是椅子。”

凯思林拉过一把椅子，一声不吭地坐了下来。斯金纳先生走到米莉森特面前，面对着她。

“我当然明白你为什么跟我们说哈罗德死于热病。我认为这个做法是错误的，因为这类事情根本掩盖不住。我不知道主教告诉海伍德一家的情况跟事实有多大出入，但是如果你愿意听从我的劝告的话，你就应该将一切尽可能详细地告诉我们，然后我们再看看该如何处理。既然现在卡农·海伍德和格拉迪斯已经知道了这个事情，我们也就别指望能够就此打住了。在这种地方，这样的事必定会传出去。不管怎样，如果我们了解了真相，处理起来就会方便很多。”

斯金纳夫人和凯思林觉得他把话说得够清楚了，便等着米莉森特的回答。米莉森特面无表情地听父亲讲完，脸上突然出现的那道红晕消失了，脸色又变得像往常一样苍白、灰黄。

“我觉得如果我把真相告诉你们，你们可能会不大乐意听。”

“你必须知道，你完全可以相信我们是同情和理解你的。”凯思林郑重说道。

米莉森特扫了她一眼，紧闭的嘴角上闪过了一丝微笑。她缓缓地看向他们三个。斯金纳夫人心里有些不安：她看着他们，就像看着服装公司的人体模特一样，她仿佛生活在另一个不同的世界里，跟他们毫无瓜葛。

“你们知道，我跟哈罗德结婚时，我并不爱他。”她若有所思地说道。

斯金纳夫人正要发出惊叫，她的丈夫迅速做出一个手势，制止了她——这个手势微乎其微，但多年来的婚姻生活，已经赋予了这个手势举足轻重的意义。米莉森特继续说了下去，声音非常平缓，几乎没有任何语气变化。

“我当时二十七岁了，似乎也没有其他人愿意娶我。他那时四十四岁，看起来还要更老一些，但他有一份非常不错的工作，不是吗？我不可能有更好的机会了。”

斯金纳夫人又差点儿哭出来，但她想起来还有场晚会等着她。

“我现在算是明白你为什么要把他的照片拿走了。”她悲痛地说道。

“不要说话，妈妈。”凯思林大叫道。

照片是哈罗德跟米莉森特订婚时拍的，哈罗德照得非常不错。斯金纳夫人一直觉得他是个很好的人。他体格健壮，身材高大，或许有点儿太胖了，但他保养得很好，风度非凡。他那时已显露出秃顶的迹象，不过现在的男人秃顶都很早，他说那些遮阳帽、太阳帽之类的东西，都对头发非常不好。他有一撮小黑胡子，面庞被太阳晒成了深褐色。当然，他脸上最好的地方是他的眼睛——棕色的大眼睛，跟琼的一模一样。他谈笑风生，凯思林说他那是夸夸其谈，但斯金纳夫人并不这么认为，她觉得一个男人说点儿大话没什么大不了。尤其是当她发现——她很快就发现了——他被米莉森特迷住时，她便开始非常喜欢他。他对斯金纳夫人殷勤备至，他给她讲他住的那个地方的情形，讲他杀死的大猎物，她似乎真的听得兴致盎然。凯思林说他自我感觉过于良好，但斯金纳夫人她们那代人完全接受这种男人应该自负一点儿的观念。米莉森特很快也看出了苗头，尽管她没跟母亲提及，但她的母亲知道，如果哈罗德向她求婚的话，她会答应的。

哈罗德跟一些已经在婆罗洲待了三十年的人住在一起，他们都对这个国家赞不绝口。一个女人住到那里应该也会感到舒适的。当然，孩子们到了七岁还是要回到国内的，但斯金纳夫人认为没必要非得那样。她请哈罗德到家里来吃饭，告诉他他们总喜欢在家里喝茶。他当时似乎也正闲得没事可做，当他对老朋友的拜访结束之时，她告诉他，如果他能前来跟他们一起住上两周，他们将非常高兴。正是在这两周即将结束之时，哈罗德和米莉森特订了婚。他们举行了一个非常漂亮的婚礼，然后前往威尼斯度了蜜月。蜜月结束后，两人才坐船去东方。每当轮船停靠到不同的港口时，米莉森特都会给家里写信。她看起来非常快乐。

“在瓜拉索洛，人们对我非常好。”她说。瓜拉索洛是塞姆布鲁州的中心城市。“我们跟驻外代表住在一起，每个人都邀请我们去吃饭。有一两次，我听说有人请哈罗德去喝酒，但是他拒绝了。他说他已经翻开了人生的新篇章，他现在是已婚人士了。我不知道为什么他们都笑了。格雷夫人，就是驻外代表的妻子，她告诉我说，哈罗德结婚了他们都很高兴，她说驻扎地的单身汉们都太孤独了。当我们离开瓜拉索洛时，格雷夫人跟我们告别的方式很是古怪，让我备感惊讶，就好像她郑重其事地把哈罗德交由我来照管了。”

三个人都一声不响地听她说着。凯思林一直没有把视线从她姐姐那张冷漠的脸上移开，而斯金纳先生则直直地盯着他身前的那些马来武器——克力士短剑[4]和帕兰刀[5]，它们就悬挂在他妻子所坐的沙发之上的墙面上。

“直到一年半后我又回到瓜拉索洛时，我才明白他们的举止为何如此怪异。”米莉森特的喉咙里发出一种细微的奇怪声音，就像是一种嘲笑的回声，“我还知道了许多之前我并不知道的事情。哈罗德那时是为了结婚才回英国的，至于跟谁结婚他倒不是很在意。你们还记得我们当时是多么兴师动众地接待他吗，妈妈？其实根本没必要那么麻烦的。”

“我不懂你是什么意思，米莉森特。”斯金纳夫人说道，语气不无刻薄，因为这种含沙射影式的讽刺让她感到不悦，“我看他是真的为你着迷。”

米莉森特耸了耸她那肥厚的肩膀。

“他是个十足的酒鬼，以前每晚都是抱着一瓶威士忌入睡，到第二天早上酒瓶就干了。政务司司长告诉他，如果他再不戒酒，他就得辞职了，他说他再给他一次机会。他可以让他请假回国，他还建议他结婚，这样他回来后就有人照料了。哈罗德跟我结婚，是因为他需要一个监护人。他们在瓜拉索洛打赌，看我能让他保持多长时间的清醒。”

“但是他爱你呀。”斯金纳夫人打断了她的话，“你不知道，他过去都是怎样跟我谈论你的。就在你刚刚所说的那段时间里，你回瓜拉索洛生孩子了，他给我写了一封感人肺腑的信，全是关于你的。”

米莉森特又看了一眼她的母亲，她灰黄的皮肤暗淡了下来，放在膝盖上的双手微微颤抖起来。她想起了婚后头几个月的日子。官方的汽艇将他们送到河口，他们在那里的小木屋里度过了一个夜晚。哈罗德开玩笑说，这是他们的海滨豪宅。第二天，他们坐着一艘普拉胡帆船沿河逆流而上。由于受以前所读小说的影响，她以为婆罗洲的河流都是漆黑一片，异常凶险的，但事实上那儿的天空是蔚蓝的，上面还点缀着几朵小小的白云，红树林和尼帕林里的绿草被流水冲洗过后，在阳光下闪闪发光；河的两侧是成片的没有任何小道的灌木丛，远处的天空映衬出一座座蜿蜒起伏的山峦的轮廓。清晨的清新空气令人身心愉悦。她就像来到了一片友好富庶的土地，拥有了无边的自由。他们的目光在河岸上搜寻着，看是否有猴子蹲伏在枝叶缠绕的树丛中。一次，哈罗德指着一块像是木头的东西，告诉她那是一条鳄鱼。戴着遮阳帽，穿着帆布裤子的代表助理，正站在浮动码头上迎接他们，十二个年轻士兵齐刷刷地向他们列队致意。他们向她介绍了代表助理，他的名字叫辛普森。

“啊，先生，”他对哈罗德说，“看到你回来，我真是太高兴了。你不在的晚上简直太冷清了！”

驻外代表的平房，就坐落在一座低矮的山头上，周围是一片花园，园里各式各样的鲜艳花朵竞相开放。平房有点儿破旧了，家具稀稀拉拉的没有几件，但屋子很是凉爽，而且很宽敞。

“村庄就在那下面。”哈罗德说道，并用手指了指。

她的视线跟随着他的手势移动。这时，一阵锣响从那片椰子林中传来，在她心里激起了一丝奇异的感觉。

尽管她每天都没什么事可做，但这样的日子过得相当轻松。黎明时分，一个男仆会给他们端来茶水。然后，他们会到游廊漫步，呼吸清晨芳香的空气（哈罗德穿着汗衫和纱笼[6]；米莉森特穿着睡衣），直到更衣去吃早饭。饭毕，哈罗德会到自己的办公室去，她会花一两个小时来学习马来语。午饭后，当她午休时，他又会回到办公室去。下午，他们会喝上杯茶，这样就能精神焕发了，然后出去散步，或者在九洞球场上打打高尔夫——球场是哈罗德将平房下面的一片丛林清除后，整出一块平地修建的。晚上六点，辛普森先生会过来跟他们喝上一杯。他们会一直聊到晚些时候的用餐时间。有时，哈罗德和辛普森先生也会下下象棋。香雾缭绕的夜晚最是迷人。萤火虫把游廊下的灌木丛变成了闪烁着冷光的、颤巍巍的灯塔，繁花盛开的树木在空气中散发着香甜的气味。晚饭后，两人会读读六周前从伦敦寄来的报纸，然后很快便上床休息。米莉森特很享受作为已婚妇女的生活，她有一套属于自己的房子，她也很满意穿着纱笼的当地仆人，他们赤着脚在平房里四处走动，十分安静但也非常友好。驻扎官员妻子的身份让她觉得自己很重要，她为此感到快乐。哈罗德说着流利的当地语言，发号施令的样子和身上透出的威严都让她印象深刻。她偶尔会到法庭去听他审理案件。他职责繁多，能力出众，让她肃然起敬。辛普森先生告诉她，哈罗德对本地居民的了解不亚于这个国家的任何人，坚定、机智和良好的幽默感在他身上融合一气，这些特质用以对付那些胆小怕事、报复心强、天性多疑的本地民族，很是受用。米莉森特开始对她的丈夫心生某种崇拜之感。

在他们结婚近一年时，有两名英国博物学家在回国途中来到他们这里，跟他们一块儿住了几天。他们带着总督亲笔书写的推荐信，言辞恳切，哈罗德说很荣幸能为他们效劳。他们的到来给他们的生活带来了令人愉快的变化。米莉森特邀请辛普森先生前来吃饭（他住在“要塞”，只有周日晚上才能跟他们共进晚餐）。晚饭后，男人们坐下来打桥牌，米莉森特很快便离开他们，上床睡觉了。但他们太吵了，导致她很长时间都无法入睡。不知什么时候，哈罗德晃晃悠悠地进了房间，她被惊醒了，但没有说话。他决定洗个澡再睡，洗浴间就在他们房间的楼下。他走下楼梯时显然滑了一跤，因为她听到了一声巨响，接着他便开始咒骂。随后，他剧烈地呕吐起来，她听到他接二连三地往自己身上浇了数桶水。过了一会儿，他回来了，这次走得非常小心。他爬上楼梯，悄悄地溜上了床。米莉森特假装睡着了，心中泛起一阵厌恶之感：哈罗德喝醉了。她决定第二天早上再谈这件事，博物学家会怎么看他呢？但第二天一早，他又恢复了以往的体面尊贵，这让她下不了决心提及那个话题。八点，哈罗德和她同两位客人一起，坐下来吃早餐。哈罗德打量了一下餐桌。

“麦片粥，”他说，“米莉森特，客人们的早饭应该来点儿伍斯特沙司，我觉得别的他们可能不想吃。至于我嘛，来点儿威士忌苏打，就心满意足了。”

博物学家们笑了，但一脸羞愧的表情。

“你丈夫太可怕了。”其中一人说。

“你们初来乍到，如果我头天晚上就让你们头脑清醒地上床睡觉，那我真是没有尽到殷勤待客的职责。”哈罗德以他圆熟而郑重的说话方式说道。

米莉森特不悦地笑了笑，不由得松了一口气，看来客人们跟丈夫一样喝醉了。第二天晚上，她跟他们在一起，没有离开，聚会在一个合适的时间结束了。当客人们重新踏上了旅程时，她感到开心。他们的生活又恢复了平静。几个月后，哈罗德去视察他的管辖区，回来时染上了疟疾。这种疾病她以前听说的多了，但还是第一次亲眼见到。病愈后，哈罗德身体变得非常虚弱，但她并未觉得奇怪。不过她发现他的举止变得有些古怪。从办公室回来，他总是瞪大眼睛盯着她。他站在游廊上，就英国的政治形势，喋喋不休地发表长篇大论时，身体总是微微摇晃着，但仍保持着那份高贵。有时说着说着思路就断了，这时他会用淘气的眼神看着她，但他天生的庄重让她对这种淘气心生不安，他说：

“真是把人折腾得够呛啊，这讨人厌的疟疾。啊，老婆，你不知道，一个男人要成为帝国的建造者，将承担多少压力。”

她觉得辛普森先生开始显得有些焦虑，有一两次当他们独处时，似乎有什么话已到了他的嘴边，但由于羞怯，他最终没有说出口。这种感觉越来越强烈，已经让她紧张了起来。一天晚上，哈罗德不知何故待在办公室的时间比平时更久了些，还没回来。于是，她揪住了他。

“你究竟有什么话要跟我说，辛普森先生？”她突然大叫道。

他顿时红了脸，一副犹豫不定的样子。

“没什么要说的。你怎么会认为我有什么特别的话要跟你说？”

辛普森先生是个二十四岁的年轻人，人很瘦弱，本来有一头好看的鬈发，但他却煞费苦心地用发蜡弄平了它们。他腰部肿胀，留有蚊子叮咬过的伤疤。米莉森特直直地盯着他。

“如果这事与哈罗德有关，你难道不认为坦白跟我讲会更好些吗？”

现在他的脸变得更红了。他坐在藤条椅上不安地推诿着，她则一再坚持。

“恐怕你会觉得这事糟糕极了，”他终于开了口，“在背后说上司坏话的我真是糟糕极了。疟疾很可怕，人一旦得过一回，整个人都会变得不堪一击。”

他又变得犹犹豫豫，嘴角向下耷拉着，似乎快要哭出来了。在米莉森特眼中，他看起来就像个小男孩。

“我会守口如瓶的，”她微笑着说，竭力掩饰住自己的担忧，“告诉我吧。”

“我觉得很遗憾，你丈夫在办公室留有一瓶威士忌。这样他就常常能比平时多喝上几口。”

辛普森先生因为激动嗓音变得沙哑，米莉森特顿时感觉到一股冷意传遍了全身，但她控制住了自己，因为她知道，如果想让这个年轻人说出一切，她就不能把他吓住。他不愿说，她就给他施压，哄骗他，勾起他的责任感，最后，她哭了起来。于是，他向她全盘托出了，他说在过去的两周里，哈罗德多多少少都处于醉酒状态，当地人都在谈论这事。他们说，很快他就将变得像婚前一样糟糕了。那时的他终日酗酒成性。关于当时的细节，虽然她已经想尽一切办法，但辛普森先生还是绝口不提。

“你认为他现在正在喝酒吗？”她问。

“我不知道。”

米莉森特突然感到了强烈的羞辱和愤怒。法院就设在“要塞”，之所以叫这个名字，是因为它是枪支弹药的存放地。它就坐落在平房对面的花园里。太阳就快落下去了，她无须戴帽。她站起来向那边走去。她看到哈罗德正坐在一个大厅后面的办公室里——这是他处理司法案件的地方——前面放着一瓶威士忌。他抽着烟，正在跟三四个马来人交谈。他们就站在他的面前，满脸谄媚地听他讲话，同时还带着轻蔑的微笑。而他则满脸通红。

当地人一下子都走了。

“我来看看你在做什么。”她说。

因为他一直都以礼待她，所以他站了起来，但趔趄了一下。他感觉自己无法站稳，但仍尽力使自己的行为显得庄重一些。

“坐吧，亲爱的，坐吧。工作太多了，我实在是抽不开身。”

她气愤地看着他。

“你喝醉了。”她说。

他凝视着她，眼睛微微凸起，肥大的脸上渐渐浮现出一副傲慢的神情。

“我根本不明白你的意思。”他说。

她本来准备好了一大串愤怒的劝告，但突然间她就号啕大哭起来。然后，她坐到椅子上，双手捂住了脸。哈罗德看了她一会儿，泪水也顺着他的脸颊汩汩流了下来。他张开双臂来到她面前，扑通一声沉重地跪在地上，啜泣着将她搂入怀中。

“原谅我，原谅我吧，”他说，“我向你保证，这种事再也不会发生了。都怪那该死的疟疾！”

“真是太丢脸了！”她悲叹道。

他像个孩子般哭泣着。这个高大、尊贵的男人所表现出的自卑有些让人动容。不久，米莉森特抬起头来，他正用恳求、悔恨的目光看着她。

“你能向我发誓再也不沾酒了吗？”

“我发誓，我发誓。我痛恨它。”

正是那个时候，她告诉了他，她有身孕了。他陷入狂喜之中。

“这正是我唯一想要的，我会因此成为一个真正的人。”

他们回到了平房。哈罗德洗了个澡，稍睡了会儿。晚饭后，他们心平气和地谈了很久。他承认，在他们结婚前，他一直时不时地饮酒过量——在偏远的驻扎地很容易养成这种恶习。米莉森特提出的每一个要求他都同意了。在米莉森特前去瓜拉索洛分娩前的那几个月，哈罗德扮演了一个优秀丈夫的角色，温柔体贴，充满自豪，深情款款，无可挑剔。一艘汽艇前来接米莉森特，她将离开哈罗德六周时间。他诚心诚意地承诺，在她不在的日子里，绝对滴酒不沾。他把手放在她肩上。

“我从不食言，”他庄重地说道，“即使没有这个承诺，你想你在遭那么大的罪，我还能增加你的痛苦吗？”

琼出生了。米莉森特住在驻外代表家里。驻外代表的妻子是个和善的中年女子，待她非常友好。在两人单独相处的漫长时间里，她们几乎无事可做，只有通过聊天来打发时间。也正是在这段时间里，她渐渐透悉了丈夫过去的酗酒史。对她来说最难接受的事实是，当时哈罗德被告知要保住自己位置的唯一条件就是带回一个妻子，这让她气愤、怨恨不已。当她意识到他过去是一个不可救药的酒鬼时，她隐隐感到不安。她惊恐地想到，在她不在家的这段时间里，他不可能抵御住酒瘾的。她带着孩子和保姆回了家。她在河口待了一个晚上，让一名信使坐上轻舟去通知丈夫。汽艇到达后，她焦虑地扫视了一下码头，看到哈罗德和辛普森先生正站在那里，年轻的士兵整齐地列队站着。她的心沉重异常，因为她看到哈罗德的身子在轻微地摇晃着，像是一个正站在行驶的船上，努力保持着平衡的人。她知道他又醉了。

这不是一次令人愉快的回家。她几乎忘记了母亲、父亲和妹妹正静静地听着。现在她终于清醒过来，意识到了他们的存在。她说的那些似乎太遥远了。

“那时我知道我痛恨他，”她说，“我都想杀死他。”

“哦，米莉森特，不要那样说，”她母亲叫道，“别忘了，他人已经死了，可怜的人哪！”

米莉森特看了看母亲，片刻后，愤怒使她那张漠然的脸阴沉下来。斯金纳先生不安地走动着。

“继续说。”凯思林道。

“当他发现我已了解到了一切后，他反而释然了。三个月后，他的震颤性谵妄又发作了一次。”

“那你怎么不离开他？”凯思林问。

“那样做有什么好处？要是那样做，两周之内他就会被解雇。谁来养我和琼？我必须留下来。当他清醒时，我没什么抱怨的。他根本不爱我，但他喜欢我；我跟他结婚也不是因为我爱他，只是因为我需要结婚了。我尽了最大努力不让他沾酒，还设法让格雷先生下令禁止从瓜拉索洛运威士忌过来，但他能从中国人手里买到。我监视着他就像猫监视老鼠一样。但他太狡猾了，不久又发作了一次。对于工作他开始玩忽职守，我担心会遭到投诉。我们离开瓜拉索洛两天，以便进行治疗，但我想这时有了些风言风语，因为格雷先生给我发来一封私人告诫信。我给哈罗德看了，他怒骂、咆哮起来，但我看出他有些害怕。在接下来的两三个月里，他没有再喝醉，不过随之又旧病复发了。这样反反复复，直到我们离开那里。

“在我们到这里停留之前，我苦苦恳求他小心，我不想让你们任何人知道我嫁给了一个什么样的男人。在英国停留期间，他的表现一切正常，在我们乘船离开前，我又警告了他。他越来越喜欢琼，并为她感到自豪，琼也对他很依恋，她喜欢他更甚于喜欢我。我问他是不是想让孩子长大后，知道他是个醉鬼，我终于找到了控制他的方法。这个想法让他感到害怕。我告诉他，我不允许这件事情再次发生了，倘若他让琼看到他喝醉了，我马上带她走。你们知道吗？当我说这话时，他的脸一下子变得惨白。那天晚上，我跪下来感谢上帝，因为我找到了拯救自己丈夫的办法。”

“他说如果我支持他，他将再试一次，我们决定一起战斗。他做出了艰辛的努力，当他觉得‘必须’得喝点儿的时候，他就来找我。你们知道，他这个人往往喜欢炫耀，但在我面前，他非常谦和，像个孩子一样，他需要依靠我。或许结婚时他不爱我，但这个时候，他是爱我的，也爱琼。过去我恨他，因为那份耻辱，因为他喝醉了酒还故作尊贵威严，让人憎恶，但现在我内心里面产生了一种奇特的情感——它不是爱，而是一种奇异而羞涩的柔情。他不只是我的丈夫了，他还像个孩子，在那些漫长而艰难的日子里，被我揣在心里。他为我感到骄傲，我也感到自豪。他说话时的长篇大论不再让我心烦，而他一本正经的说话方式让我觉得滑稽而迷人。最后我们胜利了——有两年的时间，他再没喝过一滴酒，而且酒瘾一点儿都没了，他甚至能对此开开玩笑。

“辛普森先生那时已经走了，我们又有了一个年轻人，叫弗朗西斯。

“‘我是个改造好的酒鬼，弗朗西斯。’哈罗德有一次跟他说，‘如果不是因为我的妻子，我早就被开除了。我有个全世界最好的妻子，弗朗西斯。’

“你们不知道听到他说那样的话，对我来说意味着什么。我觉得我过去经历的一切都是值得的，我感到如此快乐。”

她沉默下来——她想起了那条宽阔、浑浊的黄色河流，在它的两岸她生活了如此之久。那些白鹭，羽毛洁白，在悠悠夕阳中闪烁着光泽，沿着溪流成群地飞下来，那样低、那样迅速，飞着飞着便散开了。它们像是雪白的音符激起的涟漪，甜美、纯粹，如春天一般，被一只无形的手演奏着，又如无形的竖琴上弹出的琴音。它们在绿色的河堤之间飞旋，裹着傍晚时的暗影，像知足的头脑里快乐的思绪。

“这时琼病倒了，有三个星期我们都处于焦虑之中。比瓜拉索洛更近的地方没有一名医生，我们只好将就着让本地的一名药剂师进行诊治。等她痊愈后，我带她去了河口，以便能让她呼吸些新鲜的海滨空气。我们在那里待了一周。自从生孩子以后，这还是我第一次和哈罗德分别。那里有一个渔村，房子都建在木桩之上，离我们并不远，但几乎没人过来打扰我们。我非常思念哈罗德，柔情充溢了整个心胸，我突然明白，我是爱他的。当普拉胡帆船来接我们回去时，我是如此开心，因为我要去把这件事告诉他，我想这对他有着重要的意义。我没法告诉你们那时我有多快乐。在我们坐船逆流而上时，船长告诉我，弗朗西斯先生去内地抓捕一个弑夫的女人去了，他已经走了几天。

“让我感到惊讶的是，哈罗德没有在码头接我。他一向对这类事情非常在意，他过去常说夫妻之间应该相敬如宾，我想不出有什么事让他不能前来。我爬上了平房所在的小山丘。女仆在后面抱着琼。平房里异常安静。周围似乎也没有仆人，我不明白是怎么回事。我想是不是哈罗德没料到我会回来这么早，所以出去了。我上了楼梯，琼感到口渴，女仆带她到仆人的住处找些饮料。哈罗德不在起居室，我大声喊他，也没有回答。我感到失望，因为我希望能在那里看到他。我走进卧室，原来哈罗德根本没有出去，他正躺在床上睡觉。我觉得很有意思，因为他总是假装他下午从不睡觉的，他说白人不需要这个习惯。我轻轻地走到床边，我想我可以跟他开个玩笑。我掀起蚊帐，看到他仰面躺着，除了一条纱笼之外什么也没穿，一个空的威士忌酒瓶就放在他的身侧，他喝醉了。

“他又开始喝了，我多年来的努力付诸东流，我的梦想被击了个粉碎，希望不复存在了，我变得怒不可遏。”

米莉森特的脸又一次变成了深红色，她紧紧抓住椅子的扶手。

“我抓住他的肩膀，用尽全力晃动他。‘你这畜生，’我叫道，‘你这个畜生！’我太生气了，我不知道自己做了什么，说了什么，我一直在晃他。你们不知道那一刻他看起来是多么令人憎恶——一个肥胖的大个子，半裸着身子，他已经几天没刮脸了，脸色青紫浮肿。他的呼吸非常沉重，我冲他大声叫喊，但他根本没有反应。我想把他拖下床来，但他太重了，躺在那里像块木头一样。‘睁开眼！’我尖叫道。我又开始晃他，我恨他，我比任何时候都恨他，因为一周来，我真心地爱着他，但他叫我失望了，叫我失望了。我想告诉他他是个多么肮脏的禽兽，但无论如何都不管用。‘你睁开眼睛！’我大喊道。我决心要让他看着我。”

寡妇舔了舔她那干燥的嘴唇。她的呼吸似乎加快了，而后忽然陷入沉默。

“如果他处于那种状态，我想最好的方式是让他继续睡觉。”凯思林说道。

“床侧的墙上有一把帕兰刀。你们知道，哈罗德对古董有多么喜欢。”

“什么是帕兰刀？”斯金纳夫人问。

“别犯傻了，孩子他妈，”她的丈夫暴躁地回答道，“你身后的墙上就有一把。”

他指了指那把马来刀，但不知为何，他的目光在刀上不知不觉地停留了一会儿。斯金纳夫人猛地缩回到沙发的一角，有点儿紧张地摆了个手势，仿佛有条蛇蜷缩在身边。

“突然，哈罗德的脖子喷出一股血来，脖子上有一道很长很深的血淋淋的伤口。”

“米莉森特，”凯思林一下子跳了起来，差点儿向她扑过去，“你到底什么意思？”

斯金纳夫人目瞪口呆地盯着她。

“墙上的帕兰刀没有了，正在床上放着。哈罗德睁开了眼睛——那双眼睛跟琼的眼睛一模一样。”

“我不明白，”斯金纳夫人说道，“如果他的状态跟你说的一样，他怎么会自杀呢？”

凯思林抓住姐姐的胳膊，愤怒地摇晃着。

“米莉森特，看在上帝的分儿上，你说说是怎么回事。”

米莉森特挣脱开了。

“帕兰刀本来是挂在墙上的，我告诉过你们。我不知道发生了什么事，到处是血，哈罗德睁开了眼睛，但气若游丝，一句话也说不出，只是微微有些喘气。”

斯金纳先生终于开口了。

“你这个可怜的人，这是谋杀呀。”

米莉森特脸红一块，白一块，带着轻蔑和愤恨看了父亲一眼，他坐回到椅子上。斯金纳夫人喊叫起来。

“米莉森特，不是你干的，是吧？”

米莉森特接下来的表现让他们血管里的血液一下子变得冰冷。她咯咯笑起来。

“我不知道谁干的。”她说。

“我的上帝啊。”斯金纳先生嘟囔说。

凯思林直挺挺地站着，两只手放在胸口，似乎心脏的剧烈跳动已让她无法承受。

“后来怎么样了？”她问。

“我尖叫起来，冲到窗前，把窗子猛地打开，喊女仆过来。她抱着琼穿过院子跑过来了。‘不要抱琼过来，’我叫道，‘不要让她进来。’她叫来厨师，让他抱着孩子。我大声叫她赶紧，她到了后，我把哈罗德指给她看。‘先生自杀了！’我叫道。她尖叫了一声，跑出了房间。

“没人愿意靠近，他们都吓傻了。我给弗朗西斯先生写了封信，告诉他发生的一切，让他赶紧过来。”

“你是怎么告诉他所发生的事情的？”

“我跟他说，我刚从河口回来就发现哈罗德受伤了，脖子划开了。你们知道，在热带地区人死后必须尽快掩埋起来。我买了口中国棺材，士兵们在‘要塞’后面挖了个坟墓。当弗朗西斯先生到了后，哈罗德已经埋了两天了。他还很年轻，我想叫他干什么都可以。我告诉他我看到哈罗德手里有一把帕兰刀，他毫无疑问是在震颤性谵妄发作时自杀的。我给他看了那个空酒瓶。仆人们说，自打我离家去海边以来他就一直在酗酒。在瓜拉索洛我跟他们说了同样的话。每个人对我都很好，政府给我发了一笔抚恤金。”

短时间里没有人说话。最后，斯金纳先生回过神来。

“我从事的是法律职业，我是律师，我有一定的责任，我们过去的执业经历一直极受尊重。不过，你现在把我置入了一个非常糟糕的境地。”

他绞尽脑汁地搜寻着措辞，但在支离破碎的思绪中，那些话语似乎在跟他玩捉迷藏。米莉森特轻蔑地看了他一眼。

“你要怎么样？”

“这是谋杀，的确如此。你认为我能纵容这件事情吗？”

“别胡说了，爸爸，”凯思林厉声说道，“你想让你的亲生女儿栽进去吗？”

“你把我置入了一个非常糟糕的境地。”他重复道。

米莉森特又耸了耸肩。

“你们非要让我说出真相。我自己已经忍受得够久了，是时候轮到你们来忍受了。”

就在这时，女仆打开了门。

“戴维斯把车开过来了，先生。”她说。

凯思林心里有话要说，女仆退了出去。

“我们最好出发吧。”米莉森特说。

“我现在不能去参加晚会了，”斯金纳夫人害怕地嚷道，“我感到极其不安，我们该怎么面对海伍德一家？主教还希望同你结识呢。”

米莉森特冷漠地做了个手势，眼睛里依然带着讥讽的神色。

“我们必须去，妈妈，”凯思林说，“如果不去那就显得可笑了。”她满脸愠怒地转向米莉森特，“哦，我觉得整件事简直太荒唐，太有失体统了。”

斯金纳夫人无助地看了看丈夫。他走过去抓住她的手，帮助她从沙发上站了起来。

“恐怕必须得去，孩子他妈。”他说。

“我丝绒帽上的羽毛还是哈罗德亲自给我的。”她哀痛道。

他领着她走出了房间，凯思林紧紧跟在母亲身后，米莉森特走在最后面，隔了一两步。

“你们会习惯的。”她静静地说，“起初，这件事在我脑子里一直萦绕不去，不过现在有两三天我没想到它了，似乎并没有什么危险。”

他们都没有回答。四个人走出大厅，从前门出去了。三名女士坐在汽车后排，斯金纳先生坐在司机旁边。汽车没有自动启动装置，是一辆老款车。戴维斯来到引擎罩前，把车发动了起来。斯金纳先生转过身，焦躁地看着米莉森特。

“你根本不应该告诉我，”他说道，“我觉得你也太自私了。”

戴维斯坐上了驾驶座，他们开着车去参加卡农家的花园晚会了。

[1]　古龙水（Eau de Cologne），又译科隆水，一种原产于德国科隆的香水。

[2]　根据高尔夫球赛规则，击棍数较少者获胜。业余球员和正式球员比赛，业余球员可以将自己的击棍数减去让棍数，以其相减的差值与正式球员的击棍数相比，只要差值低于正式球员击棍数就算胜出。

[3]　英国伦敦最大的广场。

[4]　是自菲律宾至印度一带马来民族古代所用的剑。

[5]　一种马来人惯用的弯月形的大而重的短刀，具有典型的地域特点，在日常生活中，它过于笨重不便携带，但在野外生活中它独特的前倾重心十分适合劈砍大型树木。

[6]　马来群岛土著人穿的围裙。

雨

孔祥立　译

快到上床时间了，明天早上醒来就能看到陆地啦！麦克费尔医生点上烟斗，斜靠在船栏上，搜寻着夜空里的南十字星座。在前线待了两年，有个早该愈合的伤口迟迟没能痊愈，他很高兴能到阿皮亚安静地住上至少十二个月，并且在旅途中，他已经感觉好多了。因为有些乘客明天将在帕果帕果下船，他们今晚刚刚举行了一场小型舞会，自动演奏钢琴尖厉的音符至今还在他的耳畔萦绕，但甲板上终于安静了下来。不远处，他看到他的妻子正坐在一把长椅上跟戴维森夫妇聊天，便溜达到了她那儿去。他在灯下落座，摘掉帽子——你能看到，他有着一头赤红色的头发，头顶秃了一块；长满雀斑的红皮肤倒也与赤发交相辉映。他年已四十，瘦骨嶙峋，脸颊干瘪瘪的，为人处世一丝不苟，颇有点儿学究味；他操着一口苏格兰口音，嗓门很小，说起话来很是文静。

戴维森夫妇是传教士，麦克费尔夫妇跟他们产生了一种同舟共济的情谊，这倒不是因为他们趣味多相投，顶多只能算是相似。他们主要的联系便是都看不惯那些没日没夜地在吸烟室打扑克、玩桥牌、酗酒的人。麦克费尔夫人一想到她和她的丈夫是戴维森夫妇在船上唯一乐于交往的人，就有点儿受宠若惊，甚至连医生自己——他虽然很腼腆，但并不蠢——也模糊地觉得这是对自己的恭维，而这不过是因为他长着一颗喜欢争强好辩的头脑，他觉得晚上在船舱里跟人发发牢骚也未尝不可。

“戴维森夫人说，要是没有我们，她真不知道这次旅行要怎么熬过来。”麦克费尔夫人一边说着，一边娴熟地梳理着自己的假发，“她说在这条船上也就我们两个她还愿意认识。”

“我并不觉得传教士是多大的人物啊，居然如此装腔作势。”

“不是装腔作势，我非常明白她的意思。让戴维森夫妇跟吸烟室那些粗人混在一起，这的确很不好。”

“他们的宗教创始者可没这么排外。”麦克费尔医生笑着说。

“我跟你说过多少遍了，不要拿宗教开玩笑。”他妻子说道，“我不喜欢你这种性格，亚历克，你从来看不到别人的长处。”

他用黯淡的蓝眼睛斜瞥了她一眼，没有回话。多年来的婚姻生活使他学会了一点：将最后一句话留给他的妻子更有利于和谐共处。他赶在她之前脱掉了衣服，爬到了上铺，然后躺下来读点儿书，便可以睡觉了。

第二天早上，当他来到甲板上时，船已经快靠岸了。他用渴望的目光注视着岸上的一切。那是一片细长的银色沙滩，紧紧挨着一片草木茂盛的山冈。椰子树蓊蓊郁郁，几乎延伸到了水边。树丛中你可以看见萨摩亚人居住的草屋和随处可见的小型教堂，散发着亮闪闪的白光。戴维森夫人走过来站在了他身边。她身着一袭黑衣，脖子上戴着一条金项链，上面挂着个小小的十字架。她是个身材矮小的女人，枯燥的褐色头发梳理得一丝不乱，不起眼的夹鼻眼镜后面是一双突起的蓝眼睛。她的脸蛋长长的，就像绵羊的脸一样，但并不给人愚蠢之感，相反会让人觉得极为机警。她动作敏捷，如鸟儿一样。而她身上最惹人注意的地方便是她的嗓音，高亢，刺耳，一点儿也不婉转；当尖厉单调的嗓音传入你的耳中时，就像无情喧嚣的风钻一般，让你的神经不胜其烦。

“这里看起来一定和你家那边很像。”麦克费尔医生说道，脸上带着一种不自然的浅笑。

“我们那里都是低平的岛屿——你知道的，跟这里的不同。那里都是珊瑚岛，这里全是火山岛，还得再花上十天才能到我们那里。”

“在这些地方，简直就像在家里邻近的街道上一样。”麦克费尔医生戏谑道。

“哦，这样说未免有点儿太夸张了，不过在南太平洋，人们对于远近的理解不同。照这样来看，你的说法也没错。”

麦克费尔医生淡淡地叹了口气。

“我很高兴我们没在这儿驻扎，”她继续说道，“他们说在这个地方极难开展工作。出入的轮船让居民们没法安生，而且这里还有一座军港，这对当地人来说可不是什么好事。在我们那个区，根本不存在像这样的困难需要我们去应对。当然也有一两个商人，但我们注意对他们严加管教，要是他们不服从管教，我们就会想方设法地让他们在那里待不下去，他们也就只能心甘情愿地离开了。”

她固了固鼻梁上的眼镜，冷冷地凝视着这片绿色的岛屿。

“对于传教士而言，要想在这里布道几乎就是一个无望的工作。我对上帝感激不尽，至少我们是幸免于难了。”

戴维森所在的教区包括北萨摩亚的一群岛屿，各岛屿之间相隔遥远，所以他不得不经常乘独木舟去远方的岛屿，这种时候，他妻子就留在总教区处理布道事务。一想到她布道时的精明强干，麦克费尔医生就不由得心头一沉。当谈起当地土著人的堕落时，她慷慨陈词，滔滔不绝，令人战栗，任何东西都不能让她消声；她的感觉敏锐得超乎寻常。早在他们初识时，她便跟他说过：

“要知道，当我们最初上岛时，他们的婚俗真是让人触目惊心，我没法跟你描述，不过我可以告诉你妻子，她会转述给你的。”

接下来，他便看到他妻子和戴维森夫人的帆布躺椅紧紧地靠在一起，她们认真交谈了差不多两小时。当他为了活动一下身体，来来回回从她们身边路过好几次时，他曾听到戴维森夫人激动的低语声，宛如远处山涧的流水，他还看到妻子大张的嘴，苍白的脸，她似乎正享受着一种令人惊异的体验。晚上在他们自己的船舱里，她压低音量，把听来的话完完整整地向他复述了一遍。

“看吧，我怎么跟你说的？”第二天早上，戴维森夫人欢欣雀跃地喊道，“你可曾听过比那更恐怖的事吗？你懂得我为什么不能直接告诉你了吧？尽管你是名医生。”

戴维森夫人打量着他的脸，她显然热切渴望看到自己预期的效果。

“你能想象到我们初到那里时的心灰意冷吗？要是我告诉你，要在那里的村庄里找到一个好的单身女孩是根本不可能的事，你绝对无法相信。”

她极富技术性地运用了“好的”这个词语。

“戴维森先生和我讨论过这件事，我们决定从遏制跳舞着手。这帮土著人对跳舞可痴迷了。”

“我年轻时倒也不反对跳舞。”麦克费尔医生说道。

“昨天晚上我听到你邀请麦克费尔夫人陪你跳一圈时，我就差不多猜到了。我认为，如果一个男人只跟自己妻子跳舞，这不会产生任何真正的伤害——她不愿陪你跳，倒让我松了一口气。在这种情况下，我认为我们最好严于克己自持。”

“在什么情况下？”

戴维森夫人透过夹鼻眼镜快速地扫了他一眼，但并没有回答他的问题。

“不过在白人之间，情况就不太一样。”她继续说道，“但戴维森先生说，他不明白一个丈夫怎么能够袖手旁观，眼睁睁地看着自己的妻子向另一个男人投怀送抱。我得说我相当赞同他的说法，就我而言，自打结婚以来我就再没跳过一步舞。但当地人跳舞完全是另外一回事，跳舞不仅本身就不道德，而且显然会导致伤风败俗。不管怎样，感谢上帝，我们将它铲除掉了，八年来在我们的教区没有一个人跳舞，我认为这样说没错。”

现在他们来到了海港的入口处，麦克费尔夫人也加入了他们的谈话。船转了个急弯后便缓缓向前行进。这是一个为广大陆地所包围的海港，大得足足可以装下一支战舰舰队，海港四周矗立着高耸陡峭的绿色山丘。靠近入口，海风轻拂，这里坐落着为花园所环绕的总督府。星条旗无精打采地耷拉在旗杆上。他们驶过两三座排列整齐的平房和一个网球场，接着就来到了带仓库的码头前。戴维森夫人指了指停泊在离岸边两三百码处的一艘双桅帆船，它将把他们载往阿皮亚。岸边汇集着从岛屿的四面八方赶来的一群热切、喧嚣、欢天喜地的土著人，有些是来看稀奇的，有些则是来同前往悉尼的旅客交换东西的——他们带来了菠萝、大串的香蕉、树皮布衣服、贝壳项链、鲨鱼牙齿、卡瓦碗，还有战船模型。穿戴整齐、胡子刮得干干净净、神情率真的美国船员们，夹在人群中闲逛，旁边还有一小群政府官员。在行李上岸的空闲时间里，麦克费尔夫妇和戴维森夫人观望着这片人群。麦克费尔医生注意到这里的绝大多数孩子和年轻人似乎都患上了雅司病，一种类似慢性溃疡的难看的褥疮；另外他自从医以来第一次见到了象皮病，这使得他那双专业的眼睛闪闪发光——该病患者要么长着一只巨大而笨重的手臂，要么拖着一条严重变形的腿蹒跚前行。无论男女，腰间都系着拉瓦拉瓦[1]。

“这种服装太不像话了，”戴维森夫人说道，“戴维森先生认为法律应该禁止如此穿着。除了腰间裹着一条红棉布之外，身上几乎一丝不挂，你怎么能够指望这样的人讲道德？”

“就气候而言，这样的穿着再合适不过了。”医生揩了揩头上的汗水说道。

现在他们已经上了岸，尽管还是大清早，但那股热劲儿已经压得人喘不过气来。由于被群山包围，没有一丝凉风可以吹进帕果帕果。

“在我们那些岛上，”戴维森夫人用她刺耳的音调继续说道，“我们已经几乎将拉瓦拉瓦全部消灭了。有几个老人还在穿，但也就那么多了。女人们全都穿上了长罩衣[2]，男人们则穿长裤和汗衫。我们刚在那里驻扎时，戴维森在一次报告中讲到，这些岛上的居民不可能彻底成为基督教徒，除非让每个十岁以上的男孩都穿上裤子。”

但是戴维森夫人用她那鸟似的眼睛轻快地扫了几眼港口上空飘浮着的厚重乌云。几滴雨落了下来。

“我们最好避避雨。”她说。

于是他们随着人群拥进了一个波纹铁皮盖的大棚子，瓢泼大雨顿时倾盆而下。他们在那里站了些时候，随后戴维森先生过来加入了他们。整个旅途中，他对麦克费尔夫妇一直彬彬有礼，不过他不像他妻子那样善于交际，所以他大部分时间都用来读书了。他是个沉默寡言，有点儿阴沉的人，你会觉得，他的亲和完全是基督教义强加给他的一份职责。他天性矜持，甚至可以说是孤僻。他那副相貌也是独一无二的。他的身材高削，长长的四肢松松垮垮地连接在躯体上，脸颊凹陷，颧骨却高得古怪；你会惊讶地发现，虽然他面色惨白，但嘴唇却特别丰满性感。他留着长长的头发。他那双乌黑的眼睛，深陷在眼窝里，又大又悲凉；他的手指又粗又长，显得手掌非常好看，给他平添了几分力量之感。不过，他身上最引人注目的地方在于他总是给人一种强抑怒火的感觉。这一点实在让人印象深刻，甚至有些隐隐不安。他不是一个能够深交的男人。

他现在给大伙带来了坏消息：在卡纳卡人[3]中爆发的一种严重且经常致人死命的麻疹病已经传播到了这座岛上，他们即将搭乘的双桅帆船的船员中已经发现了一例病患。患者已被送上岸，目前正在医院的防疫禁区，但有电报从阿皮亚发来说，直到确保没有其他船员被感染为止，这条帆船不得进入港口。

“这意味着我们必须在这里驻留至少十天。”

“可我急需抵达阿皮亚呀！”麦克费尔医生说道。

“那没用。如果船上没有人再感染，双桅帆船可以恢复航行，但也只能承载白人旅客，而当地人将在未来三个月全部禁行。”

“这里有宾馆吗？”麦克费尔夫人问。

戴维森低声笑了笑。

“没有。”

“那我们怎么办？”

“我一直在跟总督交涉。沿海有个商人在出租房屋，我的建议是，等雨停了，我们就到那儿去，看看该怎么办。别指望会多舒服，如果我们能有张床可以睡觉，不用风餐露宿就该谢天谢地了。”

但雨丝毫没有停止的迹象，最后他们只好撑着雨伞、披上雨衣出发了。岛上没有城镇，只有一群办公楼，一两间商店，在街道后面的椰树林和大蕉丛里有几座当地人的房子。他们要找的房子距码头大约五分钟的路程。这是一座两层木架构房屋，每层都带有宽阔的阳台，屋顶由波纹铁皮做成。房东霍恩是个混血儿，娶了个当地人，生了一群棕皮肤小孩。他在房子的一楼开了家商店，出售罐头食品和棉布。他领他们看的房间几乎没有任何家具，麦克费尔夫妇的房间除了一张破破烂烂的旧床，上面挂着皱巴巴的蚊帐，一把快要散架的椅子和脸盆架之外，再无其他。他们心灰意冷地四下打量了一下。瓢泼大雨哗哗地下个不停。

“不是真正需要的行李我就不打开了。”麦克费尔夫人说。

戴维森夫人一面打开旅行皮包，一面走了进来。她是个非常活泼的人，为人机敏，阴雨的环境丝毫没有影响到她。

“你要是听我劝告的话，现在就拿根针和线把蚊帐补一补，”她说，“否则，今晚你别想合眼。”

“蚊子有那么猖獗吗？”麦克费尔医生问。

“现在正是它们猖獗的季节。当你在阿皮亚被邀请到总督府参加晚会时，你就会看到女士们都拿到一个枕套用来将她们的——她们的下肢裹住。”

“我希望雨能停一会儿，”麦克费尔夫人说，“如果能出太阳的话，我就更有心思把这里弄舒服一些了。”

“哦，如果你要等那么一天，你可要等上好长一段时间。帕果帕果差不多是太平洋地区雨水最多的地方。你看，那些山丘，还有港湾，它们都很招雨水，并且不管怎么说，一年中的这个季节下雨也是正常的。”

戴维森夫人看了看麦克费尔，又看了看他妻子。两人不知所措地各自站在房间的一端，一副失魂落魄的样子。她噘了噘嘴，她知道她必须要帮他们一把了。像这种软弱的人真让她没耐心，但她忍不住要把一切都收拾得有条不紊，这已经成了她的天性。

“来，你把针和线给我，我帮你补蚊帐，你接着弄你的行李。一点钟吃午饭。麦克费尔医生，你最好到码头去看看你那些重行李有没有被放到干燥的地方，你知道当地人都是些什么人，他们很可能会把行李存放在一直漏雨的地方。”

医生再次穿上雨衣下了楼。霍恩先生正站在门口跟他们刚才乘坐的那艘船上的舵手和一个他在甲板上见过几次的二等舱乘客交谈。舵手是个个子小、身材干瘪的男人，全身污垢不堪。医生经过时，他冲他点了点头。

“治疗麻疹可不是什么好活儿，医生。”他说，“我知道你的住处已经安排妥当了。”

麦克费尔医生觉得他有些放肆，不过他是胆怯之人，一般不轻易动怒。

“是的，我们在楼上有了个房间。”

“汤普森小姐跟你同去阿皮亚，所以我把她带到这里来了。”

舵手用他的大拇指指了指站在他旁边的女子。她大约二十七岁的样子，体态丰满，长得虽然有些俗气，但还算漂亮。她身穿白色连衣裙，戴着一顶硕大的白帽子，穿着白棉长筒袜的胖乎乎的小腿从小山羊皮皮面的白色长靴子的顶端鼓出来。她逢迎地朝麦克费尔笑了笑。

“这小伙子想敲诈我，那么小的房间一天居然要一美元半！”她用嘶哑的声音说道。

“我跟你说，乔，她是我的一个朋友。”舵手说，“她最多就能付一美元，你必须得照她说的办。”

商人长得圆润，人也圆滑，他默默地微笑着。

“好吧，斯旺先生，既然你这样说，我想想该怎么办吧。我会跟我夫人说说，看看能不能打个折扣。”

“别跟我来那一套。”汤普森小姐说道，“我们现在就要搬进来，房间一天一美元，不能再多了。”

麦克费尔笑了笑，他很钦佩她这种厚颜无耻的砍价方式，他自己是那种人家要多少就给多少的人，他宁愿多付钱也不愿讨价还价。商人叹了口气。

“好吧，看在斯旺先生的分儿上，我认了。”

“这还差不多。”汤普森小姐道，“斯旺先生，进来喝杯烈酒吧，那个小旅行包你如果带过来了，里面有上好的黑麦威士忌。医生，你也一起来吧。”

“哦，我想我还是不去了，谢谢。”他回答道，“我得去看看我们的行李安置妥当了没。”

他走出门，踏进了雨中。雨正大片大片地从港口横扫进来，对岸全都模糊不清了。一路上他碰见了两三个只穿着拉瓦拉瓦、撑着把大伞的当地人，他们身姿优雅、优哉游哉地走在路上，躯干挺得笔直。当他从旁边经过时，他们都冲他微笑，并用一种奇怪的语言向他问好。

等他回来时已经临近午饭时间，他们的饭菜已经被放在了房东家的客厅里。设计这间客厅时就没打算用来住宿，只是为了装装体面，因此房间里散发着一股霉味，气氛阴郁。一套轧花长毛绒沙发整齐地绕墙而立，为了防苍蝇，天花板上贴着黄色薄纸，正中央悬挂着一盏镀金枝形吊灯。戴维森没有来。

“我知道他去拜访总督了。”戴维森夫人说，“我想总督留下他共进午餐了。”

一个当地小女孩端上来一盘油炸肉饼。过了一会儿，商人便走过来看了看他们要的饭菜是否已经上齐。

“我看到我们有了一位新房客，霍恩先生。”麦克费尔医生说道。

“她就租了一个房间，就这样。”商人回答，“她自己解决伙食。”

他奉承地看了看桌上的两位女士。

“我让她住在楼下，这样就不会碍事了，她不会给你们带来任何麻烦的。”

“她原先也在船上吗？”麦克费尔夫人问。

“是的，夫人，她在二等舱，去阿皮亚，有份出纳员的工作在等着她。”

“哦！”

商人离开后，麦克费尔说：“我想她一个人在房间里吃饭一定觉得很乏味。”

“如果她坐的是二等舱，我想她还是就在房间里吃吧。”戴维森夫人说，“真不知道她会是哪种人。”

“舵手带她来时，我正好在那里，她的名字叫汤普森。”

“该不会是昨天晚上跟舵手跳舞的那个女人吧？”戴维森夫人问。

“肯定是了。”麦克费尔夫人说，“当时我还想她是谁呢，我觉得她是个放荡的女人。”

“不是什么好货色。”戴维森夫人说。

他们开始谈论其他话题。午饭后，因为早上起得早，他们觉得有些倦意，便各自分开去午休了。醒来后，尽管天还是灰蒙蒙的，乌云低垂，但雨已经停了，于是他们沿着美国人修建的海湾公路散了会儿步。

当他们回来后，发现戴维森也刚刚进来。

“我们可能要在这里待上两周。”他气急败坏地说道，“我已经就此跟总督争论过了，但他说没有办法。”

“戴维森先生只是渴望赶紧回去工作。”他妻子焦虑地扫了他一眼说道。

“我们已经离开一年了，”他在阳台上来回踱着，“我的任务是管理当地的传教士们，我非常担心他们会放任自流。他们都是好人，我说这话绝不是在斥责他们，他们敬畏上帝，虔诚，是些真正的基督徒——他们对基督的信仰让我们国家许多所谓的基督徒脸红——但遗憾的是，他们干劲儿不足，他们可以抗争一两次，但不会一直抗争下去。如果你交给当地传教士一项任务，不管他看起来是多么叫人放心，但终有一天你会发现他悄悄地胡作非为起来。”

戴维森先生静静地站在那里。他身材高挑消瘦，苍白的脸上一双大眼闪烁着，是一个令人印象深刻的人物。他的诚挚从他热情的姿势和低沉清晰的嗓音中尽显出来。

“我想我有一大堆工作要做。我应当采取行动了，必须立即行动起来。如果树木已经腐烂，它就应被砍倒，然后投到火里去。”

吃完下午茶之后——那是他们一天中的最后一餐，已是傍晚。他们坐在阴冷的客厅里，女士们在忙着针线活儿，麦克费尔医生正用烟斗抽着烟，传教士则在向他们讲述自己在岛上的工作。

“我们刚到那里时，他们毫无罪恶感。”他说，“他们一个接一个地违反戒律，根本不知道这样做是有罪的。我想我工作中最困难的部分就是给那些当地人灌输罪恶感。”

麦克费尔夫妇已经知道，戴维森在遇到他妻子之前在所罗门群岛工作过五年。她之前在中国当传教士，两人相识于波士顿——当时他们都利用部分假期参加了一次传教士大会。婚后，他们被派到了这些岛屿上，工作至今。

在他们跟戴维森先生进行的所有谈话过程中，他身上有一种特质一直在熠熠闪光，那就是这个男人百折不挠的勇气。他是一名医学传教士，随时都有可能被叫到群岛中任何一个岛上去。雨季中的太平洋动辄狂风暴雨，这种天气连捕鲸船都觉得不是那么安全，不敢航行，但他却经常驾着一叶轻舟出海，所以危险性极高。碰到有人生病或遭遇事故，他从未犹豫过。他曾多次彻夜失联，戴维森夫人也不止一次以为他失踪了。

“有时我求他不要去了，”她说，“或者至少等到天气稳定下来再说，但他从来不听。他这个人很固执，一旦下定了决心，什么都不能使他动摇。”

“如果我自己都感到害怕，那我怎能要求当地人相信上帝呢？”戴维森大声说道，“我决不会害怕，决不。他们知道如果他们在苦难中召唤我，只要人力所及，我就必然会去。我是在为上帝尽责，你觉得他会抛弃我吗？风是遵照他的圣谕而吹拂，浪花亦是按照他的旨意而汹涌。”

麦克费尔医生是个胆小之人。他从未习惯战壕上方的枪林弹雨，在前线急救站做手术时，由于要拼命控制住颤抖的双手，大把的汗水从他的额间渗出，模糊了眼镜。他望着传教士，身子微微抖动了一下。

“我希望我能够说我从未畏惧过。”他说。

“我希望你可以说你信奉上帝。”另一人回应道。

但出于某种缘由，那个晚上，传教士的思绪回到了他和妻子初到岛上的那些日子。

“有时，戴维森夫人和我会相视而泣，泪水从脸颊上滚滚落下。我们夜以继日地工作，从未停止，但却似乎没有任何进展。那时要是没有她在身边，我真不知道该做些什么。当我心灰意冷时，当我几近绝望时，是她给了我勇气和希望。”

戴维森夫人低头注视着手中的针线活儿，瘦削的脸颊微微泛红，两只手微微颤抖了一下，没有开口——她没有把握该说些什么。

“没有人帮助我们。我们孤身在外，和自己的同胞相隔数千里，四周一片黑暗。当我筋疲力尽、心力交瘁时，她就将手中的工作搁置一旁，拿起《圣经》，为我诵读，直到平静降临到我的身上，如同睡意降临到孩童的眼皮上一样。最后，她合上书说，‘不管他们自己如何，我们都要拯救他们。’我对上帝的信仰又一次变坚定了，我回答道，‘是的，在上帝的帮助下，我要拯救他们，我必须拯救他们。’”

他走向餐桌，站在桌子前面，仿佛那是一张诵经台。

“你要知道，他们的天性是如此堕落，以至于他们几乎无法看清自己的邪恶。我们不得不从他们习以为常的行为中定义出什么是罪恶。我们不仅把通奸、说谎、偷窃定义为罪恶，还把裸露身体、跳舞、不去教堂也定义为罪恶。我还把女孩袒胸露乳、男子不穿裤子也定义为罪恶。”

“你怎么做到的？”麦克费尔医生不无诧异地问。

“我制定了罚款制度。显然要让人们意识到一个行为是有罪的唯一途径就是如果他们做出了这个行为，就要惩罚他们。如果他们不到教堂来，我就罚他们的款，如果他们跳舞，我也罚他们的款，如果他们穿着不当，我也要罚款。我有一张罚款表，违反任何一项都要罚钱或罚苦力。最后，我终于让他们明白了。”

“不过他们从不拒绝交钱吗？”

“他们怎么敢不交？”传教士道。

“试图站出来跟戴维森先生抗衡的，必定是个胆大包天的人。”他的妻子绷紧了嘴唇说道。

麦克费尔医生看着戴维森先生，眼睛里满是困惑。他听到的话让他感到惊讶，不过他不愿把自己的反对意见表达出来。

“切记，我最后的撒手锏就是将他们从教堂里开除。”

“他们在意吗？”

戴维森笑了笑，轻轻摩挲着他的手掌。

“那样他们就无法销售他们的干椰子肉了，当人们打了鱼，他们也分不到应有的一份，这就差不多意味着他们会被饿死。是的，他们非常在意。”

“给他讲讲弗雷德·奥尔森的事。”戴维森夫人补充道。

传教士兴奋地注视着麦克费尔医生。

“弗雷德·奥尔森是一个丹麦商人，他已经在岛上待了很多年了。他跟其他商人一样非常有钱。我们刚到岛上时，他不是很开心。你知道的，他在那儿想干什么就干什么。他想付什么给当地人来收购他们的干椰子肉就付什么，他会用货物和威士忌跟他们交换干椰子肉。他娶了一个当地人做妻子，但他明目张胆地背叛了她，另外他还是个酒鬼。我给了他机会来纠正自己的行为，但他根本不听，还嘲笑我。”

当说最后几个字的时候，戴维森的声音降得很低，然后他沉默了一两分钟，这种沉默让人心情沉重、不安。

“两年后，他就破产了，二十五年来的积蓄荡然无存。我搞得他倾家荡产了，最终他不得不来找我，像个乞丐一样，恳求我给他一笔回悉尼的路费。”

“我真希望你能看看他来见戴维森先生时的样子。”传教士的妻子说道，“他曾是一个帅气强壮的人，人长得肥硕，声音洪亮，不过现在他整个人都小了一半，全身颤巍巍的。他突然间就变成了一个老人。”

戴维森出神地凝视着外面的夜色。又下雨了。

一阵声音突然从楼下传来，戴维森转过身疑惑地望向妻子。这是留声机尖锐又喧嚣的声音，呼哧呼哧地响着音节交错的乐曲。

“那是什么？”他问。

戴维森夫人把夹鼻眼镜按了按，使之更稳固了些。

“二等舱的一名乘客也住在这里，我想声音是从她那里发出来的。”

他们沉默地听了一会儿，很快又听到了跳舞声。然后，音乐声停下了，他们听到了瓶塞的砰砰声和欢快的说话声。

“我猜她是在给船上的朋友举办告别会。”麦克费尔医生说，“船十二点出发，是吧？”

戴维森没有回答，但他看了看表。

“你准备好了吗？”他问妻子。

她站起身，折好了手里的针线活儿。

“是的，我想是这样。”她回答。

“现在上床有点儿太早了，是吗？”医生说。

“我们还有很多东西要读。”戴维森夫人解释道，“不管在哪里，晚上睡觉前我们都要读一章《圣经》，并根据注释做些研究，然后再彻底地讨论一番，这对心智来说是个再好不过的训练。”

两对夫妇互道了晚安。只剩下麦克费尔夫妇了，有两三分钟的时间两人都没说话。

“我想我还是去把扑克拿过来吧。”医生最后说。

麦克费尔夫人充满疑虑地看着他。跟戴维森夫妇的谈话让她有些不安，但她又不大乐意说她觉得他们最好还是别玩扑克的好，以防戴维森夫妇随时都可能过来。麦克费尔医生把扑克拿了过来，她看着他把牌洗好——虽然心里隐隐约约有些负罪感。楼下的狂欢声则从未消停。

第二天天气已经晴好，在帕果帕果滞留两周已成定局，麦克费尔夫妇决定随遇而安。他们步行到了码头，从行李箱中取了几本书。医生拜访了海军医院的外科主任医师，然后跟他一起查了病房。他们还在总督府留下了名片。路上他们还碰到了汤普森小姐。医生脱帽行礼，她大声欢快地回了他一句“早上好，医生！”，她的穿着与昨天相同，一袭白裙，白亮的高跟靴，她那胖乎乎的小腿从靴筒顶部鼓了出来，显得与周围的异国风情有些格格不入。

“我觉得她穿得太不得体了。”麦克费尔夫人说道，“在我看来，她真是太不堪入目了。”

当他们回到住处时，她正在阳台上跟商人深色皮肤的孩子们玩耍。

“去跟她说句话。”麦克费尔医生小声对妻子说，“她独自一人待在这儿，对她不理不睬有些不厚道。”

麦克费尔夫人有些迟疑，但她习惯了按照丈夫的要求去做。

“我想咱们都是这里的房客。”她走过去，有些傻里傻气地开口道。

“被困在这么个小镇，真是太糟糕了，是不是？”汤普森小姐回答道，“他们跟我说，我能在这里有间房住已经很幸运了。我不知道自己怎么会住在一个土著人家里，可有些人不得不这样做，真搞不懂他们为什么不在这里开家旅馆。”

她们又交流了几句。汤普森小姐是个大嗓门，说起话来喋喋不休，显然挺乐意闲聊的。不过麦克费尔夫人却不擅长闲聊，不一会儿她就说：

“哦，我想我们该上楼了。”

薄暮时分，当他们坐下来喝下午茶时，戴维森走进来说：

“我看到楼下那个女人那里坐着两三个水手。真不知道她是怎么跟他们混熟的。”

“她这种人不可能有多讲究。”戴维森夫人道。

度过了无所事事、漫无目的的一天后，他们都感到有些腻烦。

“要是天天如此地待上两周，我真不知道我们最后会是什么感觉。”麦克费尔医生说。

“我们只能把一天的时间分配给不同的活动。”传教士答道，“我要拿出几个钟头来学习，几个钟头来锻炼，无论是雨天还是晴天——在雨季里你根本没法注意天晴与否——另外，我还要用几个钟头来娱乐。”

麦克费尔医生疑虑地看了看他的伙伴，戴维森的计划让他感到了压力。这次他们吃的还是油炸肉饼，这似乎是厨师唯一会做的一道菜。然后楼下留声机的声音又响了起来。戴维森一听到这个声音就紧张了起来，但他什么也没说。接着，男人们的声音飘了上来。汤普森小姐的客人们唱起了一首著名歌曲，不一会儿他们便听到她那沙哑而高亢的嗓音也夹杂在其中，喊叫声、大笑声响成一片。楼上试图进行交谈的四个人，不由自主地停了下来，去听楼下酒杯的叮当声，以及拖拽椅子发出的刺耳的响声。显然，又来了许多人。汤普森小姐在举行一场晚会。

“真不知道她是怎么把他们招来的。”麦克费尔夫人突然打断了传教士和她丈夫正在进行的医学方面的谈话，说道。

这句话表明了她的思绪飘荡到了哪里，戴维森脸上的抽动也证明了尽管他嘴里谈论的是科学问题，但心思已经同麦克费尔夫人走向了一处。医生讲述着他在佛兰德斯前线的从医经历，戴维森甚感无趣，突然间，他大叫一声站了起来。

“怎么啦，阿尔弗雷德？”戴维森夫人问。

“一定没错！我竟然从未想到，她是从伊韦雷来的。”

“不可能。”

“她是在火鲁奴奴[4]上的船，这是明摆着的。她到这里来是做生意。这里！”

他带着满腔怒火说出最后两个字。

“伊韦雷是哪里？”麦克费尔夫人问。

他把忧郁的目光转向她，声音因恐惧而颤抖了。

“是火鲁奴奴的疫区，红灯区——人类文明的耻辱。”

伊韦雷地处火鲁奴奴的城市边缘。你自港口起穿过几条黑漆漆的小巷，走过一座摇摇晃晃的桥梁，就会来到一条坑坑洼洼、沟壑纵横的荒芜小道上，然后你的周围就会突然明亮起来。道路两旁设有停车区，还有花里胡哨、灯火通明的酒吧，每个里面都传来嘈杂的自动钢琴声，还有理发店和烟草店。空气中流淌着一股躁动的气息，让人感觉好像随处都可以寻欢作乐。这条道路将伊韦雷一分为二，你随便向左或向右拐进一条狭窄小巷都能发现自己身处这个区域之中。这里有成排的小房屋，整齐干净地涂着绿漆，房屋间的道路宽阔笔直，布置得像一座花园城市；不过，在这规整体面、洁净有序的外观之下，却给人以一种讽刺的恐怖印象，因为在寻欢逐爱上没有任何地方比这里更自成体系，有章可循。道路上路灯稀疏，如果没有从小房屋开着的窗户里透出的光亮，路上简直一片漆黑。男人们在此踟蹰，窥视着坐在窗前的女人们。她们有的在读书，有的在做针线活儿，大多时候都不会理会这些过客。这些过客同这些女人一样来自世界各国，他们中有美国人，港口船上的水手，炮艇士兵，喝得醉醺醺的酒鬼，还有驻扎在岛上的兵团里的士兵，黑人白人都有，还有三三两两结伴而行的日本人，还有夏威夷人、穿长袍的中国人，以及戴着滑稽帽子的菲律宾人。他们全都沉默不语，似乎被压抑住了。欲望是叫人伤心的东西。

“这是太平洋地区最骇人听闻的丑事。”戴维森言辞激烈地叫道，“传教士多年来一直在鼓动反对，最后当地报纸开始报道这件事，但警方拒绝介入。你知道他们的观点。他们说罪恶是不可避免的，因此最好的办法就是集中管理。而实际情况是，他们被收买了！被收买了！他们被酒吧主给收买了，被暴徒收买了，那些女人自己也给了他们好处。最终他们只能撤出了。”

“船在火鲁奴奴停泊时，我在当地报纸上读到过此事。”麦克费尔医生说。

“伊韦雷，连同它的邪恶和耻辱一起，就在我们到达的那一天被连根拔除了，所有人都受到了司法审判。不知道为何我没有立马看出那个女人是哪种货色。”

“你这么一说，”麦克费尔夫人说，“我倒想起来，我看到她是在起锚前的几分钟上的船。我记得我当时还想，她可真会卡时间。”

“她怎么敢到这里来！”戴维森愤怒地喊道，“我决不会姑息这件事。”

他大步向门口走去。

“你要去干什么？”麦克费尔问道。

“你认为我要干什么？我要去阻止这件事，我不能让这座房子变成，变成一个——”

他在寻求一个合适的字眼，以免冒犯了两位女士的耳朵。他的目光变得凌厉，苍白的脸色因情绪的爆发而更显苍白。

“听起来楼下那里好像有三四名男子，”医生说，“现在过去你不觉得有些莽撞吗？”

传教士鄙夷地看了他一眼，一句话没说便冲出了房门。

“如果你认为戴维森先生会因担忧个人安危而怯于履行自己的职责，那你对他就太不了解了。”戴维森夫人说道。

她高高的颧骨微微发红，双手交握着，焦急地坐在那里倾听楼下即将发生的一切。他们都在侧耳听着，先是听到戴维森嘎吱嘎吱冲下木楼梯的声音，接着他砰的一声摔开了门。歌声戛然而止，但留声机还继续播放着刺耳低俗的乐曲。他们听到了戴维森的说话声，接着是某个重物落地的声音，音乐停止了。他把留声机狠狠地摔到了地上。接着他们又听到戴维森的声音，但听不清在说什么，然后是汤普森小姐的声音，又大又尖，再然后便是嘈杂的喧闹声，就好像几个人同时声嘶力竭地叫喊着。戴维森夫人微微倒吸了一口气，把两只手攥得更紧了。麦克费尔医生犹豫地将目光从她身上扫向他的妻子。他不想到楼下去，但不知道她们是否希望他去。而后传来了一阵类似扭打的响声，现在声音更加清晰了。或许是戴维森被赶出了房间，门被重重地关上了。片刻的沉寂之后，他们又一次听到了戴维森上楼的声音。他回到了自己房间。

“我想我最好去看看他。”戴维森夫人说道。

她起身走出了房间。

“如果你需要我，尽管打电话。”麦克费尔夫人说。当戴维森夫人离开后，她又说：“我希望他没受伤。”

“他干吗要多管闲事呢？”麦克费尔医生道。

两人默默地坐了一两分钟，而后都大感吃惊，因为留声机又响起来了，挑衅一般，嘲弄的语调嘶哑地吼着一首下流歌曲的歌词。

第二天，戴维森夫人面色苍白，身形疲惫，她抱怨说头疼，整个人看上去苍老而委顿。她跟麦克费尔夫人说，传教士彻夜未眠，异常焦虑地度过了一个晚上后，凌晨五点就起床出了门。他被人泼了啤酒，衣服都弄脏了，散发着臭味。但当戴维森夫人谈及汤普森小姐时，她眼中涌现出了一股阴沉沉的怒火。

“她嘲弄了戴维森先生，总有一天她会为此感到懊悔的。”她说，“戴维森先生有一颗慈悲的心，陷入困境的人们去找他，无不得到安慰，但他嫉恶如仇。如果有谁激起了他正义的怒火，他将变得非常可怕。”

“哦，他会做什么呢？”麦克费尔夫人问。

“我不知道，不管怎样，这个世界上没有任何东西能够让我甘愿落入她那种境地。”

麦克费尔夫人不寒而栗，这个小个子女人举手投足之间流露出来的自信和得意着实令人惊讶。那天早上，她们一起出了门，肩并肩地走下了楼。汤普森小姐的门是开着的，她们看到她穿着一件破旧睡衣，正在用平底锅做饭。

“早上好！”她喊道，“戴维森先生今天早上好些了吗？”

她们昂着头默默地从她身边走过，就好像她不存在一般。然而当她发出一阵讽刺的大笑声时，她们的脸一下子红了，戴维森夫人猛地转过身。

“你竟然还敢跟我说话！”她厉声叫道，“如果你敢羞辱我，我就叫人把你从这里赶出去。”

“喂，是我邀请戴维森先生来我这儿的吗？”

“别理她。”麦克费尔夫人小声地匆匆说道。

她们继续往前走，直到听不到她说话了才停下来。

“她真是厚颜无耻，厚颜无耻！”戴维森夫人火冒三丈。

愤怒简直要让她窒息了。

回去路上，她们又碰到她正慢悠悠地迈着步子向港口走去。她一身盛装，她那插着俗艳花朵的大白帽子本身就是一种挑衅！从她们身边经过时，她欢快地冲着她们大声叫喊，当这两位女士对此报以冷目时，旁边站着的几个美国水手不由得咧嘴大笑起来。她们刚一进门，雨又落了下来。

“我想她的漂亮衣服可要完蛋喽！”戴维森夫人很是幸灾乐祸地说道。

她们的午餐吃到一半的时候，戴维森才回来。他全身都湿透了，但是不愿意换衣服，只是一声不吭地闷坐着，草草吃了一口饭后，便开始凝视着外面斜飘的雨水。当戴维森夫人告诉他她们两次碰到汤普森小姐的遭遇时，戴维森也没有回话，但他愈加紧蹙的眉头表明他已听到了。

“你不觉得我们应该让霍恩先生把她赶走吗？”戴维森夫人问道，“我们不能让她羞辱我们。”

“不过她好像没别的地方可去了。”麦克费尔说。

“她可以跟当地人一起住。”

“像这种天气，当地人的小屋住起来一定很不舒服。”

“我在那种小屋住过多年。”传教士说。

一个矮小的当地女孩端进来一盘炸香蕉——这是他们每天都要吃的甜点，戴维森转过身面向她。

“去问问汤普森小姐何时方便，我要见见她。”他说道。

女孩羞怯地点了点头，走了出去。

“你见她干什么，阿尔弗雷德？”他妻子问。

“见她是我的职责所在，在我给尽她一切机会之前，我是不会采取行动的。”

“你还不知道她是哪种人吗？她会羞辱你的。”

“让她羞辱我吧，让她对我吐口水好了，她跟所有人一样有着不腐不朽的灵魂，我要尽我所能拯救她。”

戴维森夫人耳朵里还回响着那个贱人的嘲笑声。

“她太过分了！”

“过分到无法接受上帝的慈爱吗？”戴维森的眼睛顿时明亮了，声音也变得温和起来，“绝非如此。恶人的罪孽可能比地狱还深，但耶稣基督的慈爱依然能够降临到他们身上。”

女孩带回了消息。

“汤普森小姐深感荣幸，她说只要不是‘营业’时间，她随时恭候戴维森牧师大驾光临。”

几个人听了之后都沉默着没说一句话，麦克费尔医生迅速收敛了浮现在嘴角上的笑意，他知道如果他觉得汤普森小姐的厚颜无耻很好玩的话，他妻子会生他的气的。

他们默默地吃完了午饭。饭后两位女士起身拿起了针线活儿，麦克费尔夫人开始织另外一条羊毛围巾——从战争爆发到现在她已经织了无数条。医生点上了烟斗，而戴维森却仍坐在椅子上，两眼空洞地注视着桌子。最后他站起身，一声不吭地走出了房间。他们听到他下了楼，又听到当他敲门后汤普森小姐那声挑衅的“进来”。他在那里待了有一个小时了。麦克费尔医生注视着外面的大雨，神经渐渐紧张起来。这里的雨水跟英国那飘飘洒洒落入大地的柔和雨水不同，它冷酷得让人有些害怕，你能从这些雨水里感受到大自然原始力量的恶劣性质。这里的雨水并不是倾盆而下，而是决堤似的，就像一股直接从天空迸发的洪水般，飞流直下，打在波形铁的房顶上，持续不断地啪啪作响，令人抓狂，好似雨水也有自己的愤怒一样。有时，你会感觉如果雨水再不停歇，你就忍不住要尖叫了，随之你又会突然变得软弱无力，仿佛你的骨头霎时间都松软了，这时你便会苦不堪言、绝望透顶。

传教士回来了，麦克费尔转过头看着他，两个女人也抬起了头。

“我已经仁至义尽了，我劝诫她悔罪自新。她是个邪恶的女人。”

他停顿了一下，麦克费尔医生看到他两眼黯淡，那张苍白的脸紧紧地绷着，神色严峻。

“现在我要拿起那条皮鞭了，那条主耶稣曾用来驱赶圣殿里的高利贷者和货币兑换商的皮鞭。”

他在房间里来回踱步，嘴唇紧紧抿着，黝黑的眉毛拧成了一团。

“即使她逃到天涯海角，我也不会放过她。”

他突然转过身，大步流星地走出了房间。他们听到他又下楼去了。

“他要干什么去？”麦克费尔夫人问。

“不知道。”戴维森夫人把夹鼻眼镜摘下来擦了擦，“他履行圣职时我从不过问。”

她轻轻地叹了口气。

“怎么啦？”

“他总把自己搞得筋疲力尽，从不知道放松自己。”

他的行为产生的第一个结果，麦克费尔医生是从租给他们房间的混血商人那儿得知的。医生从店铺门口经过时被他叫住，然后他走了出来，站在门廊边跟医生说话，肥胖的脸上忧虑重重。

“戴维森牧师责怪我把房间租给了汤普森小姐，”他说，“不过，我当时根本就不知道她是什么人。人们来问我是否能租给他们一间房，我所关心的只有他们是否付得起房租。而她提前预付了我一周的房租。”

麦克费尔医生不想承担什么责任。

“不管怎么说，房子是你的，你能让我们住进来，我们已经感激不尽。”

霍恩满腹疑虑地看着他，他还没把握麦克费尔在多大程度上站在传教士一边。

“传教士都是一伙儿的，”他吞吞吐吐地说，“如果他们要对付一个商人，那他可能就只有关门大吉，卷起铺盖走人。”

“他要你把她赶走吗？”

“没有。他说只要她规规矩矩的，就不会要求我那样做。他说为了公平起见，我保证她不会再接待客人，我刚去她那里告诉她了。”

“她什么反应？”

“她把我骂了一顿。”

房东的两条腿在破旧的帆布裤子里扭动着，他已经发现汤普森小姐是个难缠的主顾。

“唔，好吧，我猜她还是会走的。要是一个客人都没有，我想她是不会留在这里的。”

“她没地方可去。只有一家当地宾馆，而眼下当地人是不会接待她的，传教士们目前也不会惩罚她。”

麦克费尔医生望着外面哗哗的大雨。

“啊，别指望放晴了，没用的。”

晚上当他们坐在客厅里时，戴维森谈起了他刚上大学时的那些日子。当时由于没有生活来源，他只能靠在假期干些零活来完成学业。这时楼下静悄悄的，汤普森小姐正一个人待在自己的小房间里。突然留声机开始响起来，她打开它只是为了挑衅，为了掩饰她的孤独，但是那儿没人跟唱，只有机器发出的悲凉的调子，就像是有人在求救。戴维森并未理会，他的长篇轶事刚讲到一半，他面不改色地继续讲了下去。留声机继续响着，唱片放了一张又一张，看上去就好像夜晚的静寂让汤普森小姐惴惴不安。这个晚上闷热得让人透不过气来，麦克费尔夫妇上床后迟迟无法入眠。他们睁着眼并排躺着，听着蚊帐外面蚊子冷酷的嗡嗡声。

“什么声音？”麦克费尔夫人突然低声问。

他们听到一个人的说话声——是戴维森的声音——透过木制隔板传了过来。语调平稳，语气诚恳、坚定，他正在大声祈祷，为汤普森小姐的灵魂祈祷。

两三天过去了。现在当他们在路上碰到汤普森小姐时，她不再用嘲讽的口吻问候他们或冲他们微笑了，而是把头仰得高高的，涂脂抹粉的脸上看上去有些郁郁不乐，眉头紧锁，就好像完全没有看见他们一样。商人告诉麦克费尔，她曾试着到别处寻找住处，但没成功。每天晚上，她用留声机一张张地播放着唱片，现在看来那显然不过是强作欢颜罢了。唱片中的拉格泰姆音乐[5]带有一种令人崩溃、心碎的节奏，就像是一种绝望的舞步。礼拜天她又开始播放音乐时，戴维森请霍恩立即去阻止她，因为这天是安息日！唱片从留声机上拿掉了，整栋房子都安静下来，只有雨水打在铁皮屋顶上发出的连续不断的啪啪声。

“我觉得她有点儿抓狂了，”第二天商人对麦克费尔说，“她不知道戴维森先生究竟在干什么，这令她感到惶恐。”

那天早上，麦克费尔瞥了她一眼，他突然意识到她那倨傲的神情已经变了，脸上露出了一种走投无路的神情。混血商人朝他斜瞥了一眼。

“我想你也不知道戴维森先生究竟在做什么吧？”他大胆地问道。

“是的，我不知道。”

霍恩会问他这个问题真是不可思议，因为他自己也有这种想法，传教士正在暗自谋划着。他的感觉是，传教士正在精心地、有条不紊而又出其不意地在那个女人周围布网，等一切就绪就会突然把绳子收紧。

“他让我告诉她，”商人说，“如果，任何时候她想要见他，只需要发出邀请，他就会赴邀。”

“你告诉她后她怎么说？”

“她什么也没说，我也没等她回话。我只说了他要我传达的话后就走了。我想她可能要哭了。”

“我坚信，那种孤独让她心烦意乱。”医生说，“还有这场足以让任何人变得神经质的雨。”他暴躁地继续说道，“这个鬼地方的雨难道不停了吗？”

“雨季总是下个没完没了，今年的降水已经达到了三百英寸。你知道，这是港湾地形造成的，整个太平洋的降水好像都被吸引来了。”

“这该死的港湾地形！”医生道。

他挠了挠被蚊子叮咬的地方，觉得很想发泄一通。一旦雨过天晴、太阳出来，这个地方又会变得跟蒸笼一般，酷热潮湿，闷得让人喘不过气来，这时你就会产生一种奇怪的感觉，似乎万物生长都夹杂着一种野蛮的暴力。素以孩子般的快乐和单纯闻名的当地人在这个时候也会因为他们的文身和染发而看起来多了几分邪恶。当他们光着脚板啪嗒啪嗒地紧跟在你身后时，你会本能地转过身，你会觉得他们随时都有可能冲上来，将一把长匕首刺进你的肩胛骨之间。你摸不清他们那双间距很开的眼睛里潜藏着怎样的阴暗念头。他们有点儿像画在神庙墙壁上的古埃及人，散发着极其古老的恐怖气息。

传教士来了又走了。他很忙，但麦克费尔夫妇并不知道他在忙些什么。霍恩告诉医生他天天去见总督，有一次戴维森还提到了总督。

“他看起来好像已经下了很大的决心，”传教士说，“不过当涉及实质问题时，他又变得没了魄力。”

“我想那意味着他不会完全照着你的意思办。”医生开玩笑道。

传教士没有笑。

“我希望他做正确的事，这个是不需要人劝的。”

“不过，是非对错因人而异。”

“要是一个人的脚患上了坏疽病还犹豫着要不要截肢，你会对他有耐心吗？”

“坏疽倒是一种实质问题。”

“那么罪恶呢？”

戴维森在做什么没过多久就清楚了。四人刚刚吃过午饭，尚未各自去午睡——酷热的天气迫使两位女士和医生每天中午都要睡上一觉，戴维森无法容忍这种怠惰的习惯。门砰地开了，汤普森小姐走了进来，她四下里打量了一番房间，径直朝戴维森走过去。

“你这个下三烂，卑鄙小人！你跟总督说我什么了？”

她气急败坏，唾沫乱飞。在她停下来的片刻，传教士推过来一把椅子。

“不想坐一坐吗，汤普森小姐？我一直想再跟你谈谈。”

“你这个卑劣的杂种！”

她破口大骂起来，污言秽语，粗鄙不堪。戴维森始终用冷峻的眼神看着她。

“你爱怎么骂就怎么骂，我无所谓，汤普森小姐，”他说，“不过我必须得请你记住这里还有两位女士。”

她愤怒地抑制住了泪水，面部通红浮肿，就好像在抽泣。

“发生了什么？”麦克费尔医生问。

“有个家伙刚刚过来，他说我必须乘坐下一班船离开。”

传教士的眼神闪烁了一下，不过看上去仍面无表情。

“照目前的情况来看，你休想总督同意让你留在这儿。”

“都是你干的好事！”她扯着嗓门叫道，“你骗不了我，就是你干的。”

“我不想欺骗你，那是我力劝总督采取的唯一可行的举措，这是为了让他恪尽职守。”

“为什么你就不能放过我？我没做过什么伤害你的事。”

“你尽管放心，就算你做过，我也不会恨你。”

“你以为我愿意继续待在这个连城镇都算不上的破地方吗？我看上去那么不入流吗？”

“既然如此，我不明白你还有什么可抱怨的。”他回答。

她含糊不清地怒骂了一声，冲出了房门。房间里陷入了片刻的宁静。

“我很欣慰，总督最终还是采取了行动。”戴维森最后说，“他为人软弱，优柔寡断。他说不管怎样她只在这里停留两周；她去阿皮亚以后，就到了英国管辖区，就跟他没有任何关系了。”

传教士突然站起来，大步走到了房间的另一端。

“掌权者试图逃避责任的做法真是太可怕。按照他们的说法，似乎恶魔逃出了视野就不再是恶魔了一样。那个女人的存在就是件丑闻，即使驱赶到别的岛也于事无补，最后我只能直截了当地说出来了。”

戴维森双眉紧皱，他那结实的下巴向前伸着，看起来又凶狠又坚决。

“你这话是什么意思？”

“我们教区对华盛顿并非完全没有影响，我跟总督讲，如果有人投诉他在这里的管理方式，对他是没有好处的。”

“那她何时得走？”医生迟疑了一下，问道。

“从悉尼起航到圣弗朗西斯科的客轮预计下周二到达这里，她必须坐那艘船离开。”

那还有五天的时间。第二天，麦克费尔从医院回来——如果没有更合适的事情做，大多数上午他都在医院度过——正要上楼，混血商人叫住了他。

“不好意思，麦克费尔医生，汤普森小姐病了，你能去看看她吗？”

“当然可以。”

霍恩把他领进了汤普森的房间。她正百无聊赖地坐在椅子里，既没看书也没做针线，只是目不转睛地盯着前方。她依然穿着她的白裙子，戴着插满花的硕大帽子。麦克费尔还注意到，她脂粉之下的皮肤已变得蜡黄、暗沉，目光也变得呆滞。

“听说你病了，我很难过。”他说。

“呃，我实际上没病，这样说只是想见你一下，我必须乘坐一班前往圣弗朗西斯科的轮船离开这里了。”

她看了他一眼，他注意到她的眼神突然之间变得像是受到了惊吓一般，两只手痉挛似的一张一合。商人站在门口，听着他们说话。

“这我已经知道了。”医生说。

她微微叹了口气。

“我觉得我现在不大方便去圣弗朗西斯科。我昨天下午去找了总督，但没能见到他，只见到了秘书。他告诉我只能搭乘那班船，再没有别的船到那里了。我一定要见到总督，所以今天早上我就在他家房子外面等他，他一出来我就上前跟他说话。我承认他不愿理睬我，但我不会让他把我甩开。最后他说只要戴维森牧师同意，他就不会反对我在这里继续待到去悉尼的下一班船过来。”

她停下来焦虑地看着麦克费尔医生。

“我真不知道我能做什么。”他说。

“好吧，我想或许你不会介意帮我向他求求情。我向上帝发誓，如果他允许我留下来，我不会再干别的了，只要他满意，我就待在房间里不出门。不就是两周嘛。”

“我去跟他说说。”

“他不会同意的，”霍恩说，“他让你周二搬走，你最好还是接受吧。”

“告诉他我会在悉尼找到工作的，我的意思是，正经八百的工作。这个要求不过分吧。”

“我尽力而为。”

“请尽快告诉我结果，好吗？不管怎样，得不到消息我无法安心做任何事。”

这种差事医生可不大喜欢干。以他的性格，他会采取迂回战术来处理这件事。他把汤普森小姐跟他说的话告诉了妻子，然后让她跟戴维森夫人讲一讲。传教士的态度有些反复无常，让这个女孩在帕果帕果停留两周应该没什么问题，但对于这个策略产生的结果他没有把握。传教士直接来找他了。

“我夫人跟我说汤普森和你谈过了。”

由于如此直接地交涉，麦克费尔医生的内心生起一股羞涩男人被迫打开天窗说亮话时总会有的怨气，他感到自己的怒火正一点点升起，脸变得通红。

“我真不明白她去悉尼和去圣弗朗西斯科有什么不同，只要她保证在这里规规矩矩的就行了，现在这样强求她有些过头了。”

传教士用他一贯冷峻的眼神盯着他。

“那她为何不愿回圣弗朗西斯科呢？”

“我没问。”医生有些不耐烦地回答，“我认为一个人管好自己的事就行了。”

这或许不是一个很老练的回答。

“总督命令她乘坐离岛的第一班船离开，他只是履行了自己的职责，我不会干预的。她留在这里是个危险。”

“我觉得你太严厉了，专横过头了。”

两位女士有些惊讶地看着医生，但她们并不担心会吵起来，因为传教士已经笑得很温和了。

“我很遗憾你居然如此看待我，麦克费尔医生。相信我，我的心为那个不幸的女人感到悲痛，但我只能恪尽职守。”

医生没有回答，阴着脸朝窗外望去。这一次雨停了，已经可以看到港湾对岸的树丛里当地人村落中的小屋了。

“我想趁着雨停出去一下。”他说。

“不要因为我不能遂你心愿就怨恨我。”戴维森苦笑了一下说，“我非常尊敬你，医生，如果你觉得我这个人不好，我会很难过的。”

“我敢肯定你自以为很了不起，所以根本不会安之若素地接受我的建议。”他回击道。

“这点倒是没错。”戴维森轻声笑起来。

麦克费尔医生为自己无缘无故地蛮不讲理感到自责。当他下楼时，汤普森小姐正站在半开的门前等着他。

“好了，”她问，“你跟他说过了吗？”

“说了，很遗憾，他不愿意。”他回答说，因为觉得尴尬所以不敢去瞧她。

但当她倏地呜咽起来时，他飞快地瞄了她一眼。他看见她的脸因恐惧而变得苍白，这让他大感惊慌。忽然间他灵光一闪。

“但不要放弃希望，我觉得他们对待你的方式是可耻的，我会亲自去见总督。”

“现在吗？”

他点点头，她的脸上露出了喜色。

“呀！你真是好人。如果你帮我说话，我肯定总督会让我留下的。在这里我不会做任何不该做的事。”

麦克费尔医生不太清楚自己为何下定决心要向总督求助。汤普森小姐的事本来和他毫不相干，不过传教士激怒了他，他的脾气一直都是压抑着的。他在总督家里见到了总督本人。他是个魁梧英俊的人，做过水手，一把花白的牙刷似的胡须，穿着笔挺的白色斜纹布制服。

“我来见您是为了一个跟我们同住一起的女人，”他说，“她的名字叫汤普森。”

“我想关于她我已经听得够多了，麦克费尔医生。”总督笑眯眯地说，“我命令她下周二离开这里，我只能这样做。”

“我想请求您是否可以破一次例，让她待到从圣弗朗西斯科来的船抵达这里，这样她就可以乘船前往悉尼了。我保证她会行为良好的。”

总督保持着微笑，不过他眯起了眼睛，神情变得严肃起来。

“我很愿意帮你，麦克费尔医生，不过我既然已经下了命令，就必须得执行。”

医生尽可能合理地分析了整个情况，总督脸上的笑容已经完全消失了，他目光闪躲、闷不作声地听着。麦克费尔知道自己是在白费口舌。

“我很抱歉给任何一位女士造成不便，不过下周二她必须坐船离开，只能这样了。”

“不过这到底有什么要紧的呢？”

“对不起，医生，除了有关部门以外，我不希望被任何人要求解释我的行政行为。”

麦克费尔用犀利的目光看着他。他想起戴维森曾暗示他威胁过总督，而从总督的态度里，他读出了明显的尴尬。

“戴维森是个该死的好事者！”他怒道。

“不瞒你说，麦克费尔医生，我不能说我对戴维森先生有很高的评价，不过我必须得承认，他是出于自己的职责跟我指出，让汤普森小姐这种性情的女人留在这里是危险的，这里有很多士兵驻扎在当地人中。”

他站了起来，麦克费尔医生也不得不跟着起身。

“我得请你原谅，我还有个约会。请代我向麦克费尔夫人致意。”

医生垂头丧气地离开了。他知道汤普森小姐在等着他，他不想亲自告诉她事情没成，于是他直接从后门进了房子，然后蹑手蹑脚地上了楼梯，就像是有什么见不得人的事一样。

晚饭时他一言不发，局促不安，而传教士兴高采烈，眉飞色舞。麦克费尔医生感觉到，他的目光不时落在自己身上，带有一种胜利者的喜悦之情。他突然觉得戴维森已经知道他拜访总督一事，并且知道他没成功。不过他到底怎么得知的呢？这个人本领可真是深不可测。饭后他看到霍恩站在阳台上，就做出一副要跟他随便聊几句的样子，走了过去。

“她想知道你有没有见到总督。”房东低声道。

“见到了，不过他还是无动于衷，非常抱歉，我已经无能为力了。”

“我就知道他不会答应的。他们不敢和传教士对着干。”

“你们在谈什么呢？”戴维森友好地问道，过来加入了他们的谈话。

“我在说至少还得再过一星期你们才能去阿皮亚。”商人说。

霍恩离开后，两个人回到客厅，戴维森先生每顿饭后都会有一个小时的消遣时间。不久之后他们便听到了一阵怯怯的敲门声。

“进来！”戴维森夫人用她那尖锐的嗓音说道。

门没有被打开。她起身开了门，他们看到汤普森小姐站在门槛处。她的样子看起来变化极大，不再是那个在路上讥讽她们的招摇轻佻的女人，而变成了一个面容忧伤、担惊受怕的女人。她的头发一贯都会精心梳理一番，现在却乱糟糟地堆在脖颈上。她穿的室内拖鞋、短裙和衬衣全都破破烂烂、肮脏不堪。她站在门口，脸上泪迹斑斑，不敢进来。

“你想干什么？”戴维森夫人厉声问道。

“我可以跟戴维森先生谈谈吗？”她哽咽着说。

传教士站起来向她走去。

“进来吧，汤普森小姐。”他语气热忱地说，“有什么我能为你效劳的？”

她走进了房间。

“唉，我为前几天跟你说的话——为我所做的一切——感到抱歉，我想我当时有点儿喝多了，请原谅。”

“呃，这不算什么。我想我的心胸足够宽广，还是可以受得了几句难听的话的。”

她走到他跟前，完全是一副卑躬屈膝的样子。

“你把我打败了，我已经精疲力竭了。你不会让我去圣弗朗西斯科的吧？”

他的和蔼一下子消失了，声音突然变得尖锐而严厉。

“你为何不愿回到那里？”

她在他面前蜷缩着。

“我的亲友们都住在那儿，我不希望他们看到我这个样子，别的地方你让我去哪儿都行。”

“你为何不想回圣弗朗西斯科？”

“我已经告诉你了。”

他俯下身子，盯着她，两只炯炯有神的大眼睛似乎要将她的灵魂看穿。然后，他突然倒吸了一口气。

“监狱！”

她尖叫一声，跪在他脚下，紧紧抱住了他的腿。

“不要把我送回那里，我向上帝发誓我会做一个好女人，我会把一切都放弃掉。”

她开始喋喋不休地胡乱恳求起来，泪水哗哗地从涂着脂粉的脸颊上滚落。他弯下腰托起她的脸，逼着她看向自己。

“是不是因为那个地方，那个叫监狱的地方？”

“他们抓住我之前我就溜了。”她喘着气说，“如果警察逮住我，我将被判上三年。”

他松开了手，她一下子瘫在了地上，痛苦地呜咽着。麦克费尔医生站了起来。

“现在一切都不一样了，”他说，“既然你知道了这个情况，就更不能让她回去了。再给她一次机会，她想翻开新的一页。”

“我正是要给她一个前所未有的好机会。如果她感到悔恨，就让她接受惩罚吧。”

她误解了他的话，抬起头，呆滞的眼睛里闪现出一丝希望。

“你放过我了？”

“没有，周二你得坐船去圣弗朗西斯科。”

她发出了一声惊恐的呻吟，而后便是低弱嘶哑的尖叫声，听上去根本不像人发出的声音。她发疯般地把头撞向地面，麦克费尔医生跳起身，将她扶了起来。

“别这样，你没必要这么做。你最好还是回房间躺一会儿，我去给你拿点儿药。”

他帮助她站了起来，半拖半抱地将她送下了楼。他对戴维森夫人和自己的妻子没有设法帮忙的行为感到怒不可遏。混血商人正站在楼梯平台上，在他的帮助下，医生把汤普森小姐扶到床上躺着。她一直在呻吟，不断地哭喊，几乎神志不清了，他便给她打了一针。当再次上楼时，他觉得全身发热、筋疲力尽。

“我让她躺下了。”

两个女人和戴维森还坐在他离开时的位置上，打他走后，他们没有进行任何的活动和交流。

“我在等你，”戴维森用一种陌生、冷淡的声音说道，“我想让你们跟我一起为这个犯下错误的姐妹的灵魂祈祷。”

他从书架上取下《圣经》，然后在他们刚才吃晚饭的餐桌旁落座。桌子还未收拾，他把茶壶推到一边，开始用洪亮、深沉、有力的嗓音给他们诵读耶稣基督审判犯了通奸罪的女子的那一章。

“现在，跟我一起跪下来，让我们为我们亲爱的姐妹——莎蒂·汤普森的灵魂祈祷。”

他开始了滔滔不绝、激情洋溢的祷告，恳求上帝施恩于这个罪孽深重的女人。麦克费尔夫人和戴维森夫人也闭着眼睛跪了下来。医生即便甚感惊讶、尴尬和局促不安，但还是跪了下来。传教士的祈祷狂放而流畅，他自己都极受感动，讲着讲着便泪湿两颊。屋外，无情的雨水不住地下着，不止不歇，带着一种人类常有的强烈的恶意。

最后他停了下来，沉默片刻后说道：

“现在我们再重复一遍主祷文。”

重复完之后，他们都跟着他站了起来。戴维森夫人面容苍白而安宁，她感到舒适、平和，而麦克费尔夫妇却突然窘迫了，不知所措。

“我下去看看她怎么样了。”麦克费尔医生说。

当他敲了门之后，是霍恩给他开的门，汤普森小姐正坐在一把摇椅里，轻轻地抽泣着。

“你在那里做什么？”麦克费尔大声喊道，“我跟你说了要躺着。”

“我躺不下去，我想见戴维森先生。”

“可怜的孩子，你认为这有用吗？你根本无法动摇他。”

“他说过如果我请他来他就会来。”

麦克费尔给商人打了个手势。

“去把他叫来。”

商人上楼时他和汤普森一起默默地等待着。戴维森进来了。

“非常抱歉请你到这里来。”她面色忧郁地看着他说。

“我一直等着你来请我，我知道上帝会回应我的祈祷的。”

他们相互凝视了片刻，然后她就把目光移开了，说话时也一直没敢正眼瞧他。

“我一直是个坏女人，我想忏悔。”

“感谢上帝，感谢上帝，他听到我们的祷告了。”

他转向两位男士。

“让我单独跟她待会儿，告诉戴维森夫人我们的祈祷上帝已经答复了。”

他们走了出去，随手关上了门。

“哎呀！”商人叹息道。

那天晚上麦克费尔医生迟迟不能入睡，当他听到传教士走上楼来，他看了看表，已经夜里两点了，但传教士仍没有立即上床，因为他一直透过房间之间的木制隔板听着他大声祈祷，直至精疲力竭，酣然睡去。

第二天早上他再见到传教士时，他的样子让他很是惊异。他的脸色比平时显得更加苍白疲倦，不过眼睛里却闪烁着奇异的光芒，看上去似乎欣喜若狂。

“我想让你等会儿下去看看莎蒂，”他说，“我不敢说她的身体好些了，但她的精神——她的精神已经有所改观。”

医生感到恍惚不安。

“昨天你跟她待到很晚啊。”他说。

“是的，她受不了我离开她。”

“你看起来很高兴啊！”医生怒不可遏道。

戴维森的眼睛里洋溢着狂喜的光辉。

“我得到了莫大恩宠，昨天晚上，我有幸让一个迷失的灵魂回到了耶稣的怀抱。”

汤普森小姐依旧斜靠在摇椅上，床没有整理，房间乱成一团。她懒得梳妆打扮，只穿了一件脏兮兮的睡衣，头发胡乱地打了个结。虽然已经用湿毛巾草草擦过了，但她的脸整个儿都哭肿了，皱纹密布。人看起来死气沉沉。

医生进门时她有气无力地抬眼看了看，惊惧而伤心。

“戴维森先生在哪里？”她问。

“如果你想找他，他很快就到。”医生不悦道，“我来看看你怎么样了。”

“哦，我想我没事了，你不用担心了。”

“吃过东西了吗？”

“霍恩给我拿了些咖啡。”

她焦急地望着门口。

“你认为他会很快下来吗？我觉得有他在身边，好像感觉就没那么糟糕了。”

“你周二还走吗？”

“是的，他说我必须走。请让他马上过来，你帮不上忙，现在只有他能帮我。”

“那好吧。”医生说。

接下来的三天，传教士几乎把所有的时间都花在了莎蒂·汤普森那儿，只是吃饭时才跟他们在一起。麦克费尔医生注意到他几乎没怎么吃。

“他把自己弄得太疲惫了，”戴维森夫人心疼道，“如果他不注意的话，身体会垮掉的，但他就是不肯宽待自己。”

她的面色一片苍白，她跟麦克费尔说她昨晚一夜未眠。从汤普森小姐那里上楼后，戴维森一直在祈祷，直到筋疲力尽为止。但尽管如此他也没睡多久，一两个小时后他就起床穿上了衣服，然后沿着港湾散步去了。他做了些奇怪的梦。

“今天早上他跟我说，他梦到了内布拉斯加州的山丘。”戴维森夫人说。

“那是很奇怪。”麦克费尔医生应道。

他记得他曾在火车横穿美国时透过车窗见过那些山丘，它们就像巨大的鼹鼠窝，光滑圆润，兀立在平原之上。麦克费尔医生还记得让他为之一动的是它们活像女人的双峰。

戴维森的坐立不安甚至到了连他自己也忍无可忍的地步，但有一种妙不可言的兴奋让他重新振作了起来。他要将那个不幸的女人心底的隐蔽角落里残存的最后一丝罪恶连根拔起，他跟她一起读《圣经》，一起祈祷。

“太棒了！”有天晚餐时他跟他们讲，“真正的重生！她的灵魂曾如夜晚一般漆黑，但现在却变得跟新雪一样纯净洁白，相形之下我是如此卑微、如此怯懦。她对于自己所有的罪恶所做的忏悔是如此美丽，我简直连她外套的下摆都不配碰一下。”

“你还是决心把她送回圣弗朗西斯科吗？”医生问，“在美国监狱里待上三年，我本以为就这一点你应该会放过她。”

“啊，你还不明白吗？这是必需的。你以为我的心没有在为她流血吗？我爱她就像爱我的妻子和姐妹。她在监狱里的每一天，我都将与她一同承受她所遭遇的痛苦。”

“一派胡言！”医生不耐烦地叫嚷道。

“你不明白是因为你是盲目的。她犯了罪，就必须为此受苦。我知道她将遭受什么，她将忍饥挨饿，受尽折磨和羞辱。我希望她接受这种人类的惩罚，就当作向上帝进献。我希望她能愉快地接受这些，她拥有了一个我们少有的机会。上帝是非常怜悯、非常仁慈的。”

戴维森的声音兴奋得颤抖了起来，他几乎是口齿不清地将这番话从嘴唇间抖搂出来的。

“每天我都跟她一起祈祷，离开她后我依旧在祷告。我全身心地投入其中，这样上帝或许就能赐她以巨大的恩惠。我希望把渴望受罚的强烈愿望植入到她的心中，以至于最终，即便我放她离开，她都会拒绝。我想让她感受到，牢狱中的痛苦惩戒是她放在上帝脚下的感恩供品——是上帝把自己的生命献给了她。”

日子慢悠悠地过去了。整个房子的人皆因关注着楼下这个可怜的、备受折磨的女人，而生活在一种不自然的兴奋当中。她如同一个为血腥的邪神崇拜仪式准备的牺牲品。恐惧让她麻木，她已无法忍受戴维森离开她的视线。只有他在身边，她才有勇气，她对他的依赖已到了盲从的地步。她常常哭泣，并诵读《圣经》，进行祈祷。有时她会感到疲惫和厌倦，但她确实期待审判快快到来，因为那似乎是让她从正在遭受着的痛苦中解脱出来的一种直截了当的、实实在在的方法。她已经受够了现在主宰她身心的这种不清不楚的恐惧了。罪恶已经让她抛掉了所有的个人虚荣，她在房间里四下晃荡，头发蓬乱，衣冠不整，身上穿着那件俗艳的晨衣。她已经四天没脱睡衣了，长筒袜也没穿。屋子里杂乱无章，而室外雨水仍残忍地落个不停。你感到九天之上的水必定已经倾空，但大雨依然如注，直刷刷地重击在铁皮屋顶上，一遍又一遍，疯狂地周而复始。所有的一切都是湿漉漉、黏糊糊的，墙上和门口的皮靴都发霉了。一个个不眠夜里，蚊子愤怒地嗡嗡作响。

“雨哪怕停上一天也不至于这么糟糕。”麦克费尔医生说。

他们都在盼着星期二的到来，到时从悉尼来的前往圣弗朗西斯科的船就到了。压力令人窒息。就麦克费尔医生而言，也想早点儿摆脱那个不幸的女人，到时他的同情和怨气都随之烟消云散。既然不可避免那就接受好了，他感觉当船起航以后他的呼吸都会变得更加自由。莎蒂·汤普森将由总督办公室的一名职员护送上船，这个人星期一晚上来拜访了汤普森小姐，告诉她第二天上午十一点做好准备，当时戴维森正陪着她。

“我来看看一切是否准备妥当，我打算亲自陪着她上船。”

汤普森小姐没有开口。

当麦克费尔医生吹灭蜡烛小心地爬进蚊帐时，他松了口气。

“好了，感谢上帝，一切都结束了，明天这个时候她就离开了。”

“戴维森夫人也会开心的，她说‘他已经瘦得不成样子了’。”麦克费尔夫人说，“她也变成另外一个人。”

“谁？”

“莎蒂。我本来从未觉得这件事是可能的，但它的确使人变得谦逊。”

麦克费尔医生没有答话，他很快就睡着了。他疲乏不堪，睡得比平时都香。

第二天早上，他被一只放在他胳膊上的手弄醒了，便一下子坐了起来，随后看到霍恩正站在床边。霍恩把手指放在嘴边示意他不要大声说话，并做手势让医生跟他走。他平常穿破旧的帆布工作服，但今天赤着脚，仅系着当地人常穿的拉瓦拉瓦，突然有了一副野蛮人的样子。麦克费尔医生下床时看见他身上刺着密密的文身。霍恩又给他打了个手势，示意他到阳台上去。麦克费尔医生下了床跟着他走了出去。

“不要弄出声音，”他小声说道，“有人找你，穿上外套和鞋，快！”

麦克费尔医生的第一个念头是汤普森小姐发生了什么事情。

“怎么啦？需要带治疗仪器吗？”

“快，请快些！”

麦克费尔医生悄悄回到卧室，拿了一件雨衣披在睡衣上，又穿上一双橡胶底的鞋，然后他回到了商人那里，两人蹑手蹑脚地下了楼。通往大路的门开着，路上站着五六个当地人。

“怎么啦？”医生重复道。

“跟我来。”霍恩说。

他走出门，医生在后边跟着，当地人陆续跟在他们后面。他们穿过大路，来到海岸边。医生看到一群当地人正站在水边围着什么东西。他们快步走过去，约有几十码的距离。看到医生过来，当地人让开了一个小口，商人把他往前推了推。这时他看到，一个可怕的东西正一半泡在水里，一半露在岸上，是戴维森的尸体。麦克费尔医生弯下腰——他不是一遇到紧急情况便惊慌失措的人——把尸体翻了过来。喉咙从两耳之间整个切开了，右手还拿着作案工具——剃须刀。

“身体已经凉透了，”医生说，“他肯定已经死了有些时候了。”

“刚才一个年轻人在上班的路上看到他躺在那儿，就过来告诉了我。你认为他是自杀吗？”

“是的，得让人去报警。”

霍恩用当地话说了句什么，两个年轻人就离开了。

“在他们到来之前不要动他。”医生说。

“他们不能把他带到我的房子去，我不会让他进我的房子的。”

“你要按当局说的做，”医生厉声说道，“实际上，我想他们会把他运到停尸间。”

他们在原地等着。商人从他的拉瓦拉瓦折缝里掏出一盒香烟，然后递给了麦克费尔医生一支。他们一边抽着，一边凝视着尸体。麦克费尔医生想不明白。

“你觉得他为什么这样做？”霍恩问。

医生耸了耸肩。过了一会儿，一名海军军官带着当地警察拿着担架来了，很快又来了几名海军军官和一名海军医生。他们有条不紊地处理好了一切。

“他妻子怎么样了？”一名军官问。

“既然你们来了，我回房子再穿点儿衣服。我想，这件事会让她心碎的，在给他稍加修饰之前最好不要让她看到。”

“我想那样做是对的。”海军医生说。

当麦克费尔回去时，他看到他的妻子已经快穿戴好了。

“戴维森夫人很担心她丈夫的情况。”他一回来她就跟他讲，“他一整夜都没睡觉，她听到他在夜里两点离开了汤普森小姐的房间，然后出去了。如果从那一刻起他就一直在四处走动，那肯定会死掉的。”

麦克费尔医生告诉了她发生的情况，并让她委婉地把这个坏消息告诉戴维森夫人。

“不过他为何这样做呢？”她战栗着问。

“我不知道。”

“但我不能告诉她，我不能。”

“你必须去。”

她恐惧地看了他一眼，然后走了出去，他听到她进了戴维森夫人的房间。麦克费尔等了一会儿才重新振作起来，开始刮须、洗脸，然后穿好衣服，坐在床上等他妻子。她终于回来了。

“她想见他。”她说。

“他们把他送去停尸间了，我们最好陪她一起下去。她情况怎么样？”

“我想她是吓坏了，她没有哭，但全身颤抖得跟一片树叶一样。”

“我们最好马上过去。”

他们敲门后，戴维森夫人走了出来，她没有流泪，脸色苍白得厉害。在医生看来，这种镇静不大合乎情理。他们一言不发，沉默地向大路走去。到了停尸间，戴维森夫人说道：

“让我一个人进去看看他。”

他们都站在一边。一个当地人给她开了门，她进去后又关上了。他们坐下来等着。一两个白人走过来，小声地跟他们说了些话。麦克费尔医生再一次把他所知道的情况跟他们讲了一遍。最后门轻轻地打开了，戴维森夫人走了出来，众人陷入了沉默。

“我现在准备回去了。”她说。

她的声音冷酷而坚定，眼里的神色让麦克费尔医生感到困惑，她苍白的面容冷峻异常。他们慢慢地往回走，一句话都没说，最后他们走到了房子对面的拐弯处。戴维森夫人喘了口气，那一刻他们都停了下来。一个叫人难以置信的声音猛地传入他们耳中。那台沉默已久的留声机又开始播放了，放的是拉格泰姆音乐，声音又大又刺耳。

“那是什么声音？”麦克费尔夫人惊恐地叫起来。

“我们还是走吧。”戴维森夫人说。

他们走上台阶，进了大厅。汤普森小姐正站在她房间的门口跟一个水手聊天。她身上陡然出现了变化，不再是过去几天里那个畏缩的慵懒模样，她一身盛装，穿着白裙子和亮闪闪的白靴，套着长棉袜的一双胖乎乎的小腿从靴筒顶部挤出来；她的头发精心梳理过了，戴着那顶插着俗艳花朵的硕大帽子；脸上涂了脂粉，眉毛黑得扎眼，嘴唇是猩红的。她身子挺得笔直，俨然还是他们初识时的那个招摇女人。他们进来后，她突然爆发出一阵嘲弄的大笑。接着，当戴维森夫人不自觉地停下来时，她攒了一口唾沫吐了出来。戴维森夫人向后退了一下，两颊顿时变得通红，而后用手捂住脸赶紧离开了，她快步跑上了楼。麦克费尔医生怒不可遏，把这个女人推回了她自己的房间。

“你到底在搞什么鬼？”他叫嚷道，“把那个该死的机器关掉！”

他冲过去，把唱片扯了下来。她冲他怒道：

“啊，医生，你住手！你到我房间里来到底想干什么？”

“你什么意思？”他喊道，“你究竟什么意思？”

她镇定了下来，但她表情中的嘲讽和话语中的轻蔑与仇恨，没人能够描述。

“你们男人！都是污秽、肮脏的猪！你们都一样，全都一样！猪！猪！”

麦克费尔医生倒吸了一口气，他明白了。

[1]　萨摩亚及其他太平洋岛屿土著人穿的印花布短围裙。

[2]　英文原文为the Mother Hubbard，即Mother Hubbard Dress，是一种又长又宽的宽松长衫，长袖高领，意在遮住尽可能多的皮肤。这种服饰是由波利尼西亚传教士传入，以“文明化”那些他们眼中的半裸土著人。

[3]　即夏威夷人，美国的少数民族，分布在太平洋东北部夏威夷群岛。

[4]　即檀香山，美国夏威夷州的首府和港口城市。

[5]　拉格泰姆音乐，1890—1915年在美国流行的一种音乐。